<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0507"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05070001" /> Teodoro, being enamoured of Violante, daughter of Messer
 Amerigo, his lord, gets her with child, and is sentenced
 to the gallows; but while he is being scourged
 thither, he is recognized by his father, and being set
 at large, takes Violante to wife.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05070002" /> While they doubted whether the two lovers would be burned,
 the ladies were all fear and suspense; but when they heard of their
 deliverance, they all with one accord put on a cheerful countenance,
 praising God. The story ended, the queen ordained that the next
 should be told by Lauretta, who blithely thus began:</p></div3><p><milestone id="p05070003" />Fairest ladies, what time good King Guglielmo ruled Sicily there
 dwelt on the island a gentleman, Messer Amerigo Abate da Trapani
 by name, who was well provided, as with other temporal goods, so
 also with children.  <milestone id="p05070004" />For which cause being in need of servants, he
 took occasion of the appearance in Trapani waters of certain Genoese
 corsairs from the Levant, who, scouring the coast of Armenia,
 had captured not a few boys, to purchase of them some of these
 youngsters, supposing them to be Turks; among whom, albeit most
 shewed as mere shepherd boys, there was one, Teodoro by name,
 whose less rustic mien seemed to betoken gentle blood.  <milestone id="p05070005" />Who,
 though still treated as a slave, was suffered to grow up in the house
 with Messer Amerigo's children, and, nature getting the better of
 circumstance, bore himself with such grace and dignity that Messer
 Amerigo gladly gave him his freedom, and still deeming him to be
 a Turk, had him baptized and named Pietro, and made him his major-domo,
 and placed much trust in him.  <milestone id="p05070006" />Now among the other
 children that grew up in Messer Amerigo's house was his fair and
 <pb n="43" />dainty daughter, Violante; and, as her father was in no hurry to give
 her in marriage, it so befell that she became enamoured of Pietro;
 but, for all her love and the great conceit she had of his qualities
 and conduct, she nevertheless was too shamefast to discover her
 passion to him.  <milestone id="p05070007" />However, Love spared her the pains, for Pietro had
 cast many a furtive glance in her direction, and had grown so
 enamoured of her that 'twas never well with him except he saw her;
 but great was his fear lest any should detect his passion, for he
 deemed 'twould be the worse for him. The damsel, who was fain
 indeed of the sight of him, understood his case; and to encourage
 him dissembled not her exceeding great satisfaction.  <milestone id="p05070008" />On which
 footing they remained a great while, neither venturing to say aught
 to the other, much as both longed to do so.  <milestone id="p05070009" />But, while they both
 burned with a mutual flame, Fortune, as if their entanglement
 were of her preordaining, found means to banish the fear and
 hesitation that kept them tongue-tied.</p><p><milestone id="p05070010" />Messer Amerigo possessed, a mile or so from Trapani, a goodly
 estate, to which he was wont not seldom to resort with his daughter
 and other ladies by way of recreation;  <milestone id="p05070011" />and on one of these days,
 while there they tarried with Pietro, whom they had brought with
 them, suddenly, as will sometimes happen in summer, the sky became
 overcast with black clouds, insomuch that the lady and her companions,
 lest the storm should surprise them there, set out on their return
 to Trapani, making all the haste they might.  <milestone id="p05070012" />But Pietro and the
 girl being young, and sped perchance by Love no less than by fear of
 the storm, completely outstripped her mother and the other ladies;
 and when they were gotten so far ahead as to be well-nigh out of
 sight of the lady and all the rest, the thunder burst upon them peal
 upon peal, hard upon which came a fall of hail very thick and close,
 from which the lady sought shelter in the house of a husbandman.
  <milestone id="p05070013" />Pietro and the damsel, finding no more convenient refuge, betook
 them to an old, and all but ruinous, and now deserted, cottage, which,
 however, still had a bit of roof left, whereunder they both took their
 stand in such close quarters, owing to the exiguity of the shelter, that
 they perforce touched one another. Which contact was the occasion
 that they gathered somewhat more courage to disclose their love;
  <milestone id="p05070014" />and so it was that Pietro began on this wise: <q direct="unspecified">Now would to God
 that this hail might never cease, that so I might stay here for ever!</q>
 <pb n="44" /><milestone id="p05070015" /><q direct="unspecified">And well content were I,</q> returned the damsel. 
 <milestone id="p05070016" />And by and by
 their hands met, not without a tender pressure, and then they fell to
 embracing and so to kissing one another, while the hail continued.
 And not to dwell on every detail, the sky was not clear before they
 had known the last degree of love's felicity, and had taken thought
 how they might secretly enjoy one another in the future.  <milestone id="p05070017" />The
 cottage being close to the city gate, they hied them thither, as soon
 as the storm was overpast, and having there awaited the lady, returned
 home with her. Nor, using all discretion, did they fail thereafter to
 meet from time to time in secret, to their no small solace; and the
 affair went so far that the damsel conceived, whereby they were both
 not a little disconcerted; insomuch that the damsel employed many
 artifices to arrest the course of nature, but to no effect.  <milestone id="p05070018" />Wherefore
 Pietro, being in fear of his life, saw nothing for it but flight, and told
 her so. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">If thou leave me,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">I shall
 certainly kill myself.</q>  <milestone id="p05070019" />Much as he loved her, Pietro answered:
 <q direct="unspecified">Nay but, my lady, wherefore wouldst thou have me tarry here?
 Thy pregnancy will discover our offence: thou wilt be readily
 forgiven; but 'twill be my woeful lot to bear the penalty of thy sin
 and mine.</q> <milestone id="p05070020" /><q direct="unspecified">Pietro,</q> returned the damsel, <q direct="unspecified">too well will they wot
 of my offence, but be sure that, if thou confess not, none will ever
 wot of thine.</q>  <milestone id="p05070021" />Then quoth he: <q direct="unspecified">Since thou givest me this
 promise, I will stay; but mind thou keep it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05070022" />The damsel, who had done her best to keep her condition secret,
 saw at length by the increase of her bulk that 'twas impossible:
 wherefore one day most piteously bewailing herself, she made her
 avowal to her mother, and besought her to shield her from the
 consequences.  <milestone id="p05070023" />Distressed beyond measure, the lady chid her severely,
 and then asked her how it had come to pass. The damsel, to screen
 Pietro, invented a story by which she put another complexion on the
 affair. The lady believed her, and, that her fall might not be
 discovered, took her off to one of their estates;  <milestone id="p05070024" />where, the time of her
 delivery being come, and she, as women do in such a case, crying out
 for pain, it so befell that Messer Amerigo, whom the lady expected
 not, as indeed he was scarce ever wont, to come there, did so, having
 been out a hawking, and passing by the chamber where the damsel
 lay, marvelled to hear her cries, and forthwith entered, and asked what
 it meant.  <milestone id="p05070025" />On sight of whom the lady rose and sorrowfully gave him
 <pb n="45" />her daughter's version of what had befallen her. But he, less credulous
 than his wife, averred that it could not be true that she knew
 not by whom she was pregnant, and was minded to know the whole
 truth: let the damsel confess and she might regain his favour;
 otherwise she must expect no mercy and prepare for death.</p><p><milestone id="p05070026" />The lady did all she could to induce her husband to rest satisfied
 with what she had told him; but all to no purpose.  <milestone id="p05070027" />Mad with rage,
 he rushed, drawn sword in hand, to his daughter's bedside (she, pending
 the parley, having given birth to a boy) and cried out: <q direct="unspecified">Declare
 whose this infant is, or forthwith thou diest.</q>  <milestone id="p05070028" />Overcome by fear of
 death, the damsel broke her promise to Pietro, and made a clean
 breast of all that had passed between him and her. Whereat the
 knight, grown fell with rage, could scarce refrain from slaying her.
 However, having given vent to his wrath in such words as it
 dictated, he remounted his horse and rode to Trapani, and there
 before one Messer Currado, the King's lieutenant, laid information of
 the wrong done him by Pietro, in consequence whereof Pietro, who
 suspected nothing, was forthwith taken, and being put to the torture,
 confessed all.  <milestone id="p05070029" />Some days later the lieutenant sentenced him to be
 scourged through the city, and then hanged by the neck; and Messer
 Amerigo, being minded that one and the same hour should rid the
 earth of the two lovers and their son (for to have compassed Pietro's
 death was not enough to appease his wrath), mingled poison and wine
 in a goblet, and gave it to one of his servants with a drawn sword,
 saying: <milestone id="p05070030" /><q direct="unspecified">Get thee with this gear to Violante, and tell her from me
 to make instant choice of one of these two deaths, either the poison
 or the steel; else, I will have her burned, as she deserves, in view of
 all the citizens; which done, thou wilt take the boy that she bore a
 few days ago, and beat his brains out against the wall, and cast his
 body for a prey to the dogs.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05070031" />Hearing the remorseless doom thus passed by the angry father
 upon both his daughter and his grandson, the servant, prompt to do
 evil rather than good, hied him thence.</p><p><milestone id="p05070032" />Now, as Pietro in execution of his sentence was being scourged to
 the gallows by the serjeants, 'twas so ordered by the leaders of the band
 that he passed by an inn, where were three noblemen of Armenia,
 sent by the king of that country as ambassadors to Rome, to treat
 with the Pope of matters of the highest importance, touching a
 <pb n="46" />crusade that was to be; who, having there alighted to rest and recreate
 them for some days, had received not a few tokens of honour
 from the nobles of Trapani, and most of all from Messer Amerigo.
  <milestone id="p05070033" />Hearing the tramp of Pietro's escort, they came to a window to see
 what was toward;  <milestone id="p05070034" />and one of them, an aged man, and of great
 authority, Fineo by name, looking hard at Pietro, who was stripped
 from the waist up, and had his hands bound behind his back, espied
 on his breast a great spot of scarlet, not laid on by art, but wrought
 in the skin by operation of Nature, being such as the ladies here call
 a rose.  <milestone id="p05070035" />Which he no sooner saw, than he was reminded of a son
 that had been stolen from him by corsairs on the coast of Lazistan
 some fifteen years before, nor had he since been able to hear tidings
 of him;  <milestone id="p05070036" />and guessing the age of the poor wretch that was being
 scourged, he set it down as about what his son's would be, were
 he living, and, what with the mark and the age, he began to
 suspect that 'twas even his son, and bethought him that, if so, he
 would scarce as yet have forgotten his name or the speech of Armenia.
  <milestone id="p05070037" />Wherefore, as he was within earshot he called to him: <q direct="unspecified">Teodoro!</q>
  <milestone id="p05070038" />At the word Pietro raised his head: whereupon Fineo,
 speaking in Armenian, asked him: <q direct="unspecified">Whence and whose son art
 thou?</q>  <milestone id="p05070039" />The serjeants, that were leading him, paused in deference
 to the great man, and so Pietro answered: <q direct="unspecified">Of Armenia was I,
 son of one Fineo, brought hither by folk I wot not of, when I was
 but a little child.</q>  <milestone id="p05070040" />Then Fineo, witting that in very truth 'twas
 the boy that he had lost, came down with his companions, weeping;
 and, all the serjeants making way, he ran to him, and embraced him,
 and doffing a mantle of richest texture that he wore, he prayed the
 captain of the band to be pleased to tarry there until he should receive
 orders to go forward, and was answered by the captain that he would
 willingly so wait.</p><p><milestone id="p05070041" />Fineo already knew, for 'twas bruited everywhere, the cause for
 which Pietro was being led to the gallows; wherefore he straightway
 hied him with his companions and their retinue to Messer Currado,
 and said to him: <milestone id="p05070042" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir, this lad, whom you are sending to the
 gallows like a slave, is freeborn, and my son, and is ready to take to
 wife her whom, as 'tis said, he has deflowered; so please you, therefore,
 delay the execution until such time as it may be understood whether
 she be minded to have him for husband, lest, should she be so minded,
 <pb n="47" />you be found to have broken the law.</q>  <milestone id="p05070043" />Messer Currado marvelled
 to hear that Pietro was Fineo's son, and not without shame, albeit
 'twas not his but Fortune's fault, confessed that 'twas even as Fineo
 said: and having caused Pietro to be taken home with all speed, and
 Messer Amerigo to be brought before him, told him the whole
 matter.  <milestone id="p05070044" />Messer Amerigo, who supposed that by this time his
 daughter and grandson must be dead, was the saddest man in the world
 to think that 'twas by his deed, witting that, were the damsel still alive,
 all might very easily be set right: however, he sent post haste to his
 daughter's abode, revoking his orders, if they were not yet carried
 out.  <milestone id="p05070045" />The servant, whom he had earlier despatched, had laid the
 sword and poison before the damsel, and, for that she was in no hurry
 to make her choice, was giving her foul words, and endeavouring to
 constrain her thereto, when the messenger arrived; but on hearing
 the injunction laid upon him by his lord, he desisted, and went back,
 and told him how things stood.  <milestone id="p05070046" />Whereupon Messer Amerigo, much
 relieved, hied him to Fineo, and well-nigh weeping, and excusing
 himself for what had befallen, as best he knew how, craved his
 pardon, and professed himself well content to give Teodoro, so he
 were minded to have her, his daughter to wife.  <milestone id="p05070047" />Fineo readily
 accepted his excuses, and made answer: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis my will that my son
 espouse your daughter, and, so he will not, let thy sentence passed
 upon him be carried out.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05070048" />So Fineo and Messer Amerigo being agreed, while Teodoro still
 languished in fear of death, albeit he was glad at heart to have found
 his father, they questioned him of his will in regard of this matter.</p><p><milestone id="p05070049" />When he heard that, if he would, he might have Violante to
 wife, Teodoro's delight was such that he seemed to leap from hell
 to paradise, and said that, if 'twas agreeable to them all, he should
 deem it the greatest of favours.  <milestone id="p05070050" />So they sent to the damsel to learn
 her pleasure: who, having heard how it had fared, and was now like
 to fare, with Teodoro, albeit, saddest of women, she looked for
 nought but death, began at length to give some credence to their
 words, and to recover heart a little, and answered that, were she to
 follow the bent of her desire, nought that could happen would delight
 her more than to be Teodoro's wife; but nevertheless she would do
 as her father bade her.</p><p><milestone id="p05070051" />So, all agreeing, the damsel was espoused with all pomp and festal
 <pb n="48" />cheer, to the boundless delight of all the citizens, 
<milestone id="p05070052" />and was comforted,
 and nurtured her little boy, and in no long time waxed more beautiful
 than ever before; and, her confinement being ended, she presented
 herself before Fineo, who was then about to quit Rome on his
 homeward journey, and did him such reverence as is due to a father.
 Fineo, mighty well pleased to have so fair a daughter-in-law, caused
 celebrate her nuptials most bravely and gaily, and received, and did
 ever thereafter entreat, her as his daughter.</p><p><milestone id="p05070053" />And so he took her, not many days after the festivities were
 ended, with his son and little grandson, aboard a galley, and brought
 them to Lazistan, and there thenceforth the two lovers dwelt with
 him in easeful and lifelong peace.</p></div2>