<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0203"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02030001" />Three young men squander their substance and are
 reduced to poverty. Their nephew, returning home
 a desperate man, falls in with an abbot, in whom he
 discovers the daughter of the King of England. She
 marries him, and he retrieves the losses and reestablishes
 the fortune of his uncles.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02030002" />The ladies marvelled to hear the adventures of Rinaldo d'Asti,
	praised his devotion, and gave thanks to God and St. Julian for the
	succour lent him in his extreme need. Nor, though the verdict was
	hardly outspoken, was the lady deemed unwise to take the boon
	which God had sent her. <milestone id="p02030003" />So they tittered and talked of her night
	of delight, while Pampinea, being seated by Filostrato, and surmising
	that her turn would, as it did, come next, was lost in meditation on
	what she was to say. Roused from her reverie by the word of the
	queen, she put on a cheerful courage, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02030004" />Noble ladies, discourse as we may of Fortune's handiwork, much
	still remains to be said if we but scan events aright, nor need we
	marvel thereat, if we but duly consider that all matters, which we
	foolishly call our own, are in her hands, and therefore subject, at her
	inscrutable will, to every variety of chance and change without any
	order therein by us discernible. <milestone id="p02030005" />Which is indeed signally manifest
	everywhere and all day long; yet, as 'tis our queen's will that we
	speak thereof, perhaps 'twill not be unprofitable to you, if,
	notwithstanding
	it has been the theme of some of the foregoing stories, I add
	to them another, which, I believe, should give you pleasure.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02030006" />There was formerly in our city a knight, by name Messer
 Tedaldo, of the Lamberti, according to some, or, as others say, of the
 <pb n="80" />Agolanti
 family, perhaps for no better reason than that the occupation
 of his sons was similar to that which always was and is the
      occupation of the Agolanti. <milestone id="p02030007" />However, without professing to
 determine which of the two houses he belonged to, I say, that he
 was in his day a very wealthy knight, and had three sons, the eldest
 being by name Lamberto, the second Tedaldo, and the third
 Agolante. Fine, spirited young men were they all, though the
 eldest was not yet eighteen years old when their father, Messer
 Tedaldo, died very rich, leaving to them as his lawful heirs the
 whole of his property both movable and immovable. <milestone id="p02030008" />Finding
 themselves thus possessed of great wealth, both in money and in
 lands and chattels, they fell to spending without stint or restraint,
 indulging their every desire, maintaining a great establishment, and
 a large and well-filled stable, besides dogs and hawks, keeping ever
 open house, scattering largesses, jousting, and, not content with these
 and the like pastimes proper to their condition, indulging every
 appetite natural to their youth. <milestone id="p02030009" />They had not long followed this
 course of life before the cash left them by their father was exhausted;
 and, their rents not sufficing to defray their expenditure, they began
 to sell and pledge their property, and disposing of it by degrees, one
 item to-day and another to-morrow, they hardly perceived that they
 were approaching the verge of ruin, until poverty opened the eyes
 which wealth had fast sealed. <milestone id="p02030010" />So one day Lamberto called his
 brothers to him, reminded them of the position of wealth and
 dignity which had been theirs and their father's before them, and
 shewed them the poverty to which their extravagance had reduced
 them, and adjured them most earnestly that, before their destitution
 was yet further manifest, they should all three sell what little
 remained to them and depart thence; which accordingly they did.
 <milestone id="p02030011" />Without leave-taking, or any ceremony, they quitted Florence; nor
 did they rest until they had arrived in England and established
 themselves in a small house in London, where, by living with extreme
 parsimony and lending at exorbitant usances, they prospered so well
 that in the course of a few years they amassed a fortune; <milestone id="p02030012" />and so,
 one by one, they returned to Florence, purchased not a few of their
 former estates besides many others, and married. The management
 of their affairs in England where they continued their business of
 usurers, they left to a young nephew, Alessandro by name, while,
 <pb n="81" />heedless
 alike of the teaching of experience and of marital and
 parental duty, they all three launched out at Florence into more
 extravagant expenditure than before, and contracted debts on all
 hands and to large amounts. <milestone id="p02030013" />This expenditure they were enabled
 for some years to support by the remittances made by Alessandro,
 who, to his great profit, had lent money to the barons on the
 security of their castles and rents.</p><p><milestone id="p02030014" />While the three brothers thus continued to spend freely, and,
 when short of money, to borrow it, never doubting of help from
 England, it so happened that, to the surprise of everybody, there
 broke out in England a war between the King and his son, by which
 the whole island was divided into two camps; whereby Alessandro
 lost all his mortgages of the baronial castles and every other source of
 income whatsoever. <milestone id="p02030015" />However, in the daily expectation that peace
 would be concluded between the King and his son, Alessandro,
 hoping that in that event all would be restored to him, principal and
 interest, tarried in the island; and the three brothers at Florence in
 no degree retrenched their extravagant expenditure, but went on
 borrowing from day to day. <milestone id="p02030016" />Several years thus passed; and, their
 hopes being frustrated, the three brothers not only lost credit, but,
 being pressed for payment by their creditors, were suddenly arrested,
 and, their property proving deficient, were kept in prison for the
 balance, while their wives and little children went into the country
 parts, or elsewhere, wretchedly equipped, and with no other prospect
 than to pass the rest of their days in destitution. <milestone id="p02030017" />Alessandro, meanwhile,
 seeing that the peace, which he had for several years awaited
 in England, did not come, and deeming that he would hazard his
 life to no purpose by tarrying longer in the country, made up his
 mind to return to Italy. He travelled at first altogether alone; but
 it so chanced that he left Bruges at the same time with an abbot,
 habited in white, attended by a numerous retinue, and preceded by
 a goodly baggage-train. Behind the abbot rode two greybeard
 knights, kinsmen of the King, in whom Alessandro recognised
 acquaintances, and, making himself known to them, was readily
 received into their company. <milestone id="p02030018" />As thus they journeyed together,
 Alessandro softly asked them who the monks were that rode in front
 with so great a train, and whither they were bound. 
<milestone id="p02030019" /><q direct="unspecified">The foremost
 rider,</q> replied one of the knights, <q direct="unspecified">is a young kinsman of ours, the
 <pb n="82" />newly-elected
 abbot of one of the greatest abbeys of England; and
 as he is not of legal age for such a dignity, we are going with him to
 Rome to obtain the Holy Father's dispensation and his confirmation
 in the office; but this is not a matter for common talk.</q> 
<milestone id="p02030020" />Now the
 new abbot, as lords are wont to do when they travel, was sometimes
 in front, sometimes in rear of his train; and thus it happened that,
 as he passed, he set eyes on Alessandro, who was still quite young,
 and very shapely and well-favoured, and as courteous, gracious and
 debonair as e'er another. The abbot was marvellously taken with
 him at first sight, having never seen aught that pleased him so much,
 called him to his side, addressed him graciously, and asked him who
 he was, whence he came, and whither he was bound. <milestone id="p02030021" />Alessandro
 frankly told all about himself, and having thus answered the abbot's
 questions, placed himself at his service as far as his small ability
 might extend. <milestone id="p02030022" />The abbot was struck by his easy flow of apt speech,
 and observing his bearing more closely, he made up his mind that,
 albeit his occupation was base, he was nevertheless of gentle blood,
 which added no little to his interest in him; and being moved to
 compassion by his misfortunes, he gave him friendly consolation,
 bidding him be of good hope, that if he lived a worthy life, God
 would yet set him in a place no less or even more exalted than that
 whence Fortune had cast him down, and prayed him to be of his
 company as far as Tuscany, as both were going the same way.
 <milestone id="p02030023" />Alessandro thanked him for his words of comfort, and professed
 himself ready to obey his every command.</p><p><milestone id="p02030024" />So fared on the abbot, his mind full of new ideas begotten by the
 sight of Alessandro, until some days later they came to a town which
 was none too well provided with inns; and, as the abbot must needs
 put up there, Alessandro, who was well acquainted with one of the
 innkeepers, arranged that the abbot should alight at his house, and
 procured him the least discomfortable quarters which it could afford.
 He thus became for the nonce the abbot's seneschal, and being very
 expert for such office, managed excellently, quartering the retinue in
 divers parts of the town. So the abbot supped, and, the night being
 far spent, all went to bed except Alessandro, who then asked the host
 where he might find quarters for the night. 
<milestone id="p02030025" /><q direct="unspecified">In good sooth, I
 know not,</q> replied the host; <q direct="unspecified">thou seest that every place is occupied,
 and that I and my household must lie on the benches. How<pb n="83" />ever,
 in the abbot's chamber there are some corn-sacks. I can shew
 thee the way thither, and lay a bit of a bed upon them, and there, an
 it like thee, thou mayst pass the night very well.</q> <q direct="unspecified">How sayst
 thou?</q> 
<milestone id="p02030026" />said Alessandro; <q direct="unspecified">in the abbot's chamber, which thou
 knowest is small, so that there was not room for any of the monks
 to sleep there? Had I understood this when the curtains were
 drawn, I would have quartered his monks on the corn-sacks, and
 slept myself where the monks sleep.</q> 
<milestone id="p02030027" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis even so, however,</q>
 replied the host, <q direct="unspecified">and thou canst, if thou wilt, find excellent quarters
 there: the abbot sleeps, the curtains are close drawn; I will go
 in softly and lay a small bed there, on which thou canst sleep.</q>
 <milestone id="p02030028" />Alessandro, satisfied that it might be managed without disturbing the
 abbot, accepted the offer, and made his arrangements for passing the
 night as quietly as he could.</p><p>The abbot was not asleep; his mind being far too overwrought
 by certain newly-awakened desires. He had heard what had passed
 between Alessandro and the host, he had marked the place where
 Alessandro had lain down, and in the great gladness of his heart had
 begun thus to commune with himself: <q direct="unspecified">God has sent me the
 opportunity of gratifying my desire; if I let it pass, perchance it
 will be long before another such opportunity occurs.</q> 
<milestone id="p02030029" />So, being
 minded by no means to let it slip, when all was quiet in the inn, he
 softly called Alessandro, and bade him lie down by his side. Alessandro
 made many excuses, but ended by undressing and obeying;
 <milestone id="p02030030" />whereupon the abbot laid a hand on Alessandro's breast, and began to
 caress him just as amorous girls do their lovers; whereat Alessandro
 marvelled greatly, doubting the abbot was prompted to such caresses
 by a shameful love. <milestone id="p02030031" />Which the abbot speedily divined, or else surmised
 from some movement on Alessandro's part, and, laughing,
 threw off a chemise which she had upon her, and taking Alessandro's
 hand, laid it on her bosom, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Alessandro, dismiss thy foolish
 thought, feel here, and learn what I conceal.</q> 
<milestone id="p02030032" />Alessandro obeyed,
 laying a hand upon the abbot's bosom, where he encountered two
 little teats, round, firm and delicate, as they had been of ivory;
 whereby he at once knew that 'twas a woman, and without awaiting
 further encouragement forthwith embraced her, and would have
 kissed her, when she said: 
<milestone id="p02030033" /><q direct="unspecified">Before thou art more familiar with me
 hearken to what I have to say to thee. As thou mayst perceive, I
 <pb n="84" />am no man, but a woman. Virgin I left my home, and was going
 to the Pope to obtain his sanction for my marriage, when, as Fortune
 willed, whether for thy gain or my loss, no sooner had I seen thee
 the other day, than I burned for thee with such a flame of love as
 never yet had lady for any man. Wherefore I am minded to have
 thee for my husband rather than any other; so, if thou wilt not
 have me to wife, depart at once, and return to thine own place.</q>
 <milestone id="p02030034" />Albeit he knew not who she was, Alessandro by the retinue which
 attended her conjectured that she must be noble and wealthy, and he
 saw that she was very fair; so it was not long before he answered
 that, if such were her pleasure, it was very much to his liking.
 <milestone id="p02030035" />Whereupon she sate up, set a ring on his finger, and espoused him
 before a tiny picture of our Lord; after which they embraced, and
 to their no small mutual satisfaction solaced themselves for the rest
 of the night. <milestone id="p02030036" />At daybreak Alessandro rose, and by preconcert with
 the lady, left the chamber as he had entered it, so that none knew
 where he had passed the night: then, blithe at heart beyond measure,
 he rejoined the abbot and his train, and so, resuming their journey,
 they after many days arrived at Rome. <milestone id="p02030037" />They had not been there
 more than a few days, when the abbot, attended by the two knights
 and Alessandro, waited on the Pope, whom, after making the due
 obeisance, he thus addressed: <q direct="unspecified">Holy Father, as you must know
 better than any other, whoso intends to lead a true and honourable
 life ought, as far as may be, to shun all occasion of error; for which
 cause I, having a mind to live honourably, did, the better to accomplish
 my purpose, assume the habit in which you see me, and depart
 by stealth from the court of my father, the King of England, who
 was minded to marry me, young as you see me to be, to the aged
 King of Scotland; and, carrying with me not a little of his treasure,
 set my face hitherward that your Holiness might bestow me in
 marriage. <milestone id="p02030038" />Nor was it the age of the King of Scotland that moved
 me to flee so much as fear lest the frailty of my youth should, were I
 married to him, betray me to commit some breach of divine law, and
 sully the honour of my father's royal blood. <milestone id="p02030039" />And as in this frame of
 mind I journeyed, God, who knows best what is meet for every
 one, did, as I believe, of His mercy shew me him whom He is pleased
 to appoint me for my husband, even this young man</q> (pointing to
 Alessandro) <q direct="unspecified">whom you see by my side, who for nobility of nature
 <pb n="85" />and bearing is a match for any great lady, though the strain of his
 blood, perhaps, be not of royal purity. <milestone id="p02030040" />Him, therefore, have I
 chosen, him will I have, and no other, no matter what my father or
 any one else may think. And albeit the main purpose with which I
 started is fulfilled, yet I have thought good to continue my journey,
 that I may visit the holy and venerable places which abound in this
 city, and your Holiness, and that so in your presence, and by consequence
 in the presence of others, I may renew my marriage-vow with
 Alessandro, whereof God alone was witness. <milestone id="p02030041" />Wherefore I humbly
 pray you that God's will and mine may be also yours, and that you
 pronounce your benison thereon, that therewith, having the more
 firm assurance of the favour of Him, whose vicar you are, we may
 both live together, and, when the time comes, die to God's glory
 and yours.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02030042" />Alessandro was filled with wonder and secret delight, when he
 heard that his wife was the daughter of the King of England; but
 greater still was the wonder of the two knights, and such their
 wrath that, had they been anywhere else than in the Pope's presence,
 they would not have spared to affront Alessandro, and perhaps the
 lady too. <milestone id="p02030043" />The Pope, on his part, found matter enough for wonder
 as well in the lady's habit as in her choice; but, knowing that he
 could not refuse, he consented to grant her request.</p><p>He therefore began by smoothing the ruffled tempers of the
 knights, and having reconciled them with the lady and Alessandro,
 proceeded to put matters in train for the marriage. <milestone id="p02030044" />When the day
 appointed was come, he gave a great reception, at which were
 assembled all the cardinals and many other great lords; to whom he
 presented the lady royally robed, and looking so fair and so gracious
 that she won, as she deserved, the praise of all, and likewise Alessandro,
 splendidly arrayed, and bearing himself not a whit like the young
 usurer but rather as one of royal blood, for which cause he received
 due honour from the knights. There, before the Pope himself, the
 marriage-vows were solemnly renewed; and afterwards the marriage,
 which was accompanied by every circumstance that could add grace
 and splendour to the ceremony, received the sanction of his benediction.
 <milestone id="p02030045" />Alessandro and the lady on leaving Rome saw fit to visit
 Florence, whither fame had already wafted the news, so that they
 were received by the citizens with every token of honour. The
 <pb n="86" />lady set the three brothers at liberty, paying all their creditors, and
 reinstated them and their wives in their several properties. So, leaving
 gracious memories behind them, Alessandro and his lady, accompanied
 by Agolante, quitted Florence, and arriving at Paris were
 honourably received by the King. <milestone id="p02030046" />The two knights went before
 them to England, and by their influence induced the King to restore
 the lady to his favour, and receive her and his son-in-law with every
 circumstance of joy and honour. Alessandro he soon afterwards
 knighted with unwonted ceremony, and bestowed on him the earldom
 of Cornwall. <milestone id="p02030047" />And such was the Earl's consequence and influence
 at court that he restored peace between father and son, thereby
 conferring a great boon on the island and gaining the love and esteem
 of all the people. Agolante, whom he knighted, recovered all the
 outstanding debts in full, and returned to Florence immensely rich.
 <milestone id="p02030048" />The Earl passed the rest of his days with his lady in great renown.
 Indeed there are those who say, that with the help of his father-in-law
 he effected by his policy and valour the conquest of Scotland,
 and was crowned king of that country.</p></div2>