<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0608"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06080001" />Fresco admonishes his niece not to look at herself
	in the glass, if'tis, as she says, grievous to her to see nasty
	folk.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06080002" />'Twas not
	at first without some flutterings of shame, evinced by
	the modest blush
	mantling on their cheeks, that the ladies heard
	Filostrato's story; but
	afterwards, exchanging glances, they could
	scarce forbear to laugh, and
	hearkened tittering. <milestone id="p06080003" />However, when
	he had done, the queen turning to
	Emilia bade her follow suit.
	Whereupon Emilia, fetching a deep breath as
	if she were roused
	from sleep, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06080004" />Loving ladies, brooding thought has kept my spirit for so long time
	remote from here that perchance I may make a shift to satisfy our queen with a much
	shorter story than would
	have been forthcoming but for my absence of mind, wherein I purpose to tell you how a
	young woman's folly was corrected by her uncle with a pleasant jest, had she but had the
	sense to apprehend it.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06080005" />My story, then,
is of one, Fresco da Celatico by name, that had a
 niece, Ciesca, as she
was playfully called, who, being fair of face and
 person, albeit she had
none of those angelical charms that we ofttimes
 see, had so superlative a
conceit of herself, that she had contracted
 a habit of disparaging both
men and women and all that she
 saw, entirely regardless of her own
defects, though for odiousness,
 tiresomeness,
 and petulance she had not
her match among women,
 insomuch that there was nought that could be done
to her mind:
 besides which, such was her pride that had she been of the
blood royal
 of France, 'twould have been inordinate. <milestone id="p06080006" />And when she walked
abroad, so fastidious was her humour, she was ever averting her
 head, as
if there was never a soul she saw or met but reeked with a
 <pb n="94" />foul
smell. <milestone id="p06080007" />Now one day--not to speak of other odious and tiresome
 ways that
she had--it so befell that being come home, where
 Fresco was, she sat
herself down beside him with a most languishing
 air, and did nought but
fume and chafe. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Ciesca,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what means this,
that, though 'tis a feast-day, yet thou
 art come back so soon?</q> <milestone id="p06080008" />She,
all but dissolved with her vapourish
 humours, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Why, the
truth is, that I am come back
 early because never, I believe, were there
such odious and tiresome
 men and women in this city as there are to-day. I
cannot pass a
 soul in the street that I loathe not like ill-luck; and I
believe there is
 not a woman in the world that is so distressed by the
sight of odious
 people as I am; and so I am come home thus soon to avoid
the sight
 of them.</q> <milestone id="p06080009" />Whereupon Fresco, to whom his niece's bad manners
were distasteful in the extreme: <q direct="unspecified">Daughter,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">if thou
loathe odious folk as much as thou sayest, thou wert best, so thou
 wouldst
live happy, never to look at thyself in the glass.</q> <milestone id="p06080010" />But she,
 empty as a
reed, albeit in her own conceit a match for Solomon in
 wisdom, was as far
as any sheep from apprehending the true sense of
 her uncle's jest; but
answered that on the contrary she was minded
 to look at herself in the
glass like otherwomen. And so she
 remained, and yet remains, hidebound in
her folly.</p></div2>