<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d03intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p03980002" />The dawn of Sunday was already changing from vermilion to
 orange, as the sun hasted to the horizon, when the queen rose and
 roused all the company. The seneschal had early sent forward to
 their next place of sojourn ample store of things meet with folk to
 make all things ready, and now seeing the queen on the road, and
 the decampment, as it were, begun, he hastily completed the equipment
 of the baggage-train, and set off therewith, attended by the
      rest of the servants, in rear of the ladies and gentlemen. <milestone id="p03980003" />So, to the
 chant of, perhaps, a score of nightingales and other birds, the queen,
 her ladies and the three young men trooping beside or after her,
 paced leisurely westward by a path little frequented and overgrown
 with herbage and flowers, which, as they caught the sunlight, began
 one and all to unfold their petals. So fared she on with her train,
 while the quirk and the jest and the laugh passed from mouth to
 mouth; nor had they completed more than two thousand paces
 when, well before half tierce,<note>I. e. midway between prime and
 tierce, about 7.30 a.m.</note> they arrived at a palace most fair
 and sumptuous, which stood out somewhat from the plain, being
 situate upon a low eminence. <milestone id="p03980004" />On entering, they first traversed its
 great halls and dainty chambers furnished throughout with all brave
 and meet appointments; and finding all most commendable, they
 reputed its lord a magnifico. Then descending, they surveyed its
 spacious and cheerful court, its vaults of excellent wines and copious
 springs of most cool water, and found it still more commendable.
 After which, being fain of rest, they sat them down in a gallery
 <pb n="175" />which commanded the court, and was close imbosked with leafage
 and such flowers as the season afforded, and thither the discreet
 seneschal brought comfits and wines most choice and excellent,
 wherewith they were refreshed. <milestone id="p03980005" />Whereupon they hied them to a
 walled garden adjoining the palace; which, the gate being opened,
 they entered, and wonder-struck by the beauty of the whole passed
 on to examine more attentively the several parts. <milestone id="p03980006" />It was bordered
 and traversed in many parts by alleys, each very wide and straight as
 an arrow and roofed in with trellis of vines, which gave good promise
 of bearing clusters that year, and, being all in flower, dispersed such
 fragrance throughout the garden as blended with that exhaled by
 many another plant that grew therein made the garden seem
 redolent of all the spices that ever grew in the East. The sides of
 the alleys were all, as it were, walled in with roses white and red
 and jasmine; insomuch that there was no part of the garden but one
 might walk there not merely in the morning but at high noon in
 grateful shade and fragrance, completely screened from the sun. <milestone id="p03980007" />As
 for the plants that were in the garden, 'twere long to enumerate
 them, to specify their sorts, to describe the order of their arrangement;
 enough, in brief, that there was abundance of every rarer species that
 our climate allows. <milestone id="p03980008" />In the middle of the garden, a thing not less
 but much more to be commended than aught else, was a lawn of
 the finest turf, and so green that it seemed almost black, pranked with
 flowers of, perhaps, a thousand sorts, and girt about with the richest
 living verdure of orange-trees and cedars, which shewed not only
 flowers but fruits both new and old, and were no less grateful to the
 smell by their fragrance than to the eye by their shade. <milestone id="p03980009" />In the
 middle of the lawn was a basin of whitest marble, graven with
 marvellous art; in the centre whereof--whether the spring were
 natural or artificial I know not--rose a column supporting a figure
 which sent forth a jet of water of such volume and to such an
 altitude that it fell, not without a delicious plash, into the basin in
 quantity amply sufficient to turn a mill-wheel. <milestone id="p03980010" />The overflow was
 carried away from the lawn by a hidden conduit, and then, reemerging,
 was distributed through tiny channels, very fair and
 cunningly contrived, in such sort as to flow round the entire lawn,
 and by similar derivative channels to penetrate almost every part of
 the fair garden, until, re-uniting at a certain point, it issued thence,
 <pb n="176" />and, clear as crystal, slid down towards the plain, turning by the way
 two mill-wheels with extreme velocity to the no small profit of the
 lord. <milestone id="p03980011" />The aspect of this garden, its fair order, the plants and the
 fountain and the rivulets that flowed from it, so charmed the ladies
 and the three young men that with one accord they affirmed that
 they knew not how it could receive any accession of beauty, or what
 other form could be given to Paradise, if it were to be planted on
 earth. <milestone id="p03980012" />So, excellently well pleased, they roved about it, plucking
 sprays from the trees, and weaving them into the fairest of garlands,
 while songsters of, perhaps, a score of different sorts warbled as if in
 mutual emulation, when suddenly a sight as fair and delightsome as
 novel, which, engrossed by the other beauties of the place, they had
 hitherto overlooked, met their eyes. <milestone id="p03980013" />For the garden, they now saw,
 was peopled with a host of living creatures, fair and of, perhaps, a
 hundred sorts; and they pointed out to one another how here
 emerged a cony, or there scampered a hare, or couched a goat, or
 grazed a fawn, or many another harmless, all but domesticated,
 creature roved carelessly seeking his pleasure at his own sweet will.
 All which served immensely to reinforce their already abundant
 delight. <milestone id="p03980014" />At length, however, they had enough of wandering about
 the garden and observing this thing and that: wherefore they
 repaired to the beautiful fountain, around which were ranged the
 tables, and there, after they had sung half-a-dozen songs and trod
 some measures, they sat them down, at the queen's command, to
 breakfast, which was served with all celerity and in fair and orderly
 manner, the viands being both good and delicate; whereby their
 spirits rose, and up they got, and betook themselves again to music
 and song and dance, and so sped the hours, until, as the heat increased,
 the queen deemed it time that whoso was so minded should go to
 sleep. <milestone id="p03980015" />Some there were that did so; others were too charmed by
 the beauty of the place to think of leaving it; but tarried there, and,
 while the rest slept, amused themselves with reading romances or
 playing at chess or dice. <milestone id="p03980016" />However, after none, there was a general
 lev&#232;e; and, with faces laved and refreshed with cold water,
 they
 gathered by the queen's command upon the lawn, and, having sat
 them down in their wonted order by the fountain, waited for the
 story-telling to begin upon the theme assigned by the queen. With
 this duty the queen first charged Filostrato, who began on this wise.</p></div2>