<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0609"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06090001" />Guido Cavalcanti by a quip meetly rebukes certain
	Florentine gentlemen who had taken him at a disadvantage.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06090002" />The queen, perceiving that Emilia had finished
	her story, and that none but she, and he who had the privilege of speaking last, now
	remained to tell, began on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06090003" />Albeit, debonair my ladies, you have forestalled me to-day of
      more than two of the stories, of which I had thought to tell one, yet one is still left me
      to recount, which carries at the close of it a quip of such a sort, that perhaps we have
      as yet heard nought so pregnant.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06090004" />You are to know, then, that in former times there obtained
in
 our city customs excellent and commendable not a few, whereof today
not one is left to us, thanks to the greed which, growing with
 the wealth
of our folk, has banished them all from among us. <milestone id="p06090005" />One
 of which customs was
that in divers quarters of Florence the gentlemen
 that there resided would
assemble together in companies of a
 limited number, taking care to include
therein only such as might
 conveniently bear the expenses, and to-day one,
another to-morrow,
 each in his turn for a day, would entertain the rest of
the company;
 and so they would not seldom do honour to gentlemen from
distant
 parts when they visited the city, and also to their
fellow-citizens;
 <milestone id="p06090006" />and in like manner they would meet together at least once
a year all
 in the same trim, and on the most notable days would ride
together
 through the city, and now and again they would tilt together,
more
 especially on the greater feasts, or when the city was rejoiced by
tidings of victory or some other glad event. <milestone id="p06090007" />Among which companies
 was one
of which Messer Betto Brunelleschi was the leading
 spirit, into which
Messer Betto and his comrades had striven hard
 <pb n="96" />to bring Guido,
son of Cavalcante de' Cavalcanti, and not without
 reason, <milestone id="p06090008" />inasmuch as,
besides being one of the best logicians in the
 world, and an excellent
natural philosopher (qualities of which the
 company made no great
account), he was without a peer for gallantry
 and courtesy and excellence
of discourse and aptitude for all matters
 which he might set his mind to,
and that belonged to a gentleman;
 and therewithal he was very rich, and,
when he deemed
 any worthy of honour, knew how to bestow it to the
uttermost.
 <milestone id="p06090009" />But, as Messer Betto had never been able to gain him over, he
and his comrades supposed that 'twas because Guido, being addicted
 to
speculation, was thereby estranged from men. And, for that he
 was somewhat
inclined to the opinion of the Epicureans, the vulgar
 averred that these
speculations of his had no other scope than to
 prove that God did not
exist. <milestone id="p06090010" />Now one day it so befell that, Guido
 being come, as was not seldom
his wont, from Or San Michele by
 the Corso degli Adimari as far as San
Giovanni, around which were
 then the great tombs of marble that are to-day
in Santa Reparata,
 besides other tombs not a few, and Guido being between
the columns
 of porphyry, that are there, and the tombs and the door of
San
 Giovanni, which was locked, Messer Betto and his company came
 riding
on to the piazza of Santa Reparata, and seeing him among the
 tombs, said:
<milestone id="p06090011" /><q direct="unspecified">Go we and flout him.</q> So they set spurs to their
 horses, and making
a mock onset, were upon him almost before he
 saw them. Whereupon:
<q direct="unspecified">Guido,</q> they began, <q direct="unspecified">thou wilt be
 none of our company; but, lo
now, when thou hast proved that
 God does not exist, what wilt thou have
achieved?</q> <milestone id="p06090012" />Guido, seeing
 that he was surrounded, presently answered:
<q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, you
 may say to me what you please in your own house.</q>
Thereupon he
 laid his hand on one of the great tombs, and being very
nimble,
 vaulted over it, and so evaded them, and went his way, <milestone id="p06090013" />while they
remained gazing in one another's faces, and some said that he had
 taken
leave of his wits, and that his answer was but nought, seeing
 that the
ground on which they stood was common to them with the
 rest of the
citizens, and among them Guido himself. <milestone id="p06090014" />But Messer
 Betto, turning to them:
<q direct="unspecified">Nay but,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis ye that have
 taken leave of your wits,
if ye have not understood him; for meetly
 and in few words he has given us
never so shrewd a reprimand;
 seeing that, if you consider it well, these
tombs are the houses of the
 <pb n="97" />dead, that are laid and tarry
therein; which he calls our house, to
 shew us that we, and all other
simple, unlettered men, are, in comparison
 of him and the rest of the
learned, in sorrier case than dead
 men, and so being here, we are in our
own house.</q> <milestone id="p06090015" />Then none was
 there but understood Guido's meaning and was
abashed, insomuch
 that they flouted him no more, and thenceforth reputed
Messer Betto
 a gentleman of a subtle and discerning wit.</p></div2>