<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0801"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08010001" />Gulfardo borrows moneys of Guasparruolo, which he has
	agreed to give Guasparruolo's wife, that he may lie
	with her. He gives them to her, and in her presence
	tells Guasparruolo that he has done so, and she
	acknowledges that 'tis true.</p></argument><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08010002" />Sith God has ordained that 'tis for me to take the lead to-day
      with
      my story, well pleased am I. And for that, loving ladies, much has
      been said touching the tricks that women play men, I am minded to
      tell you of one that a man played a woman, not because I would
      censure what the man did, or say that 'twas not merited by the
      woman, but rather to commend the man and censure the woman,
      and to shew that men may beguile those that think to beguile them,
      as well as be beguiled by those they think to beguile; <milestone id="p08010003" />for peradventure
      what I am about to relate should in strictness of speech not be
      termed beguilement, but rather retaliation; for, as it behoves woman
      to be most strictly virtuous, and to guard her chastity as her very life,
      nor on any account to allow herself to sully it, which notwithstanding,
      'tis not possible by reason of our frailty that there should be as perfect
      an observance of this law as were meet, I affirm, that she that allows
      herself to infringe it for money merits the fire; <milestone id="p08010004" />whereas she that so
      offends under the prepotent stress of Love will receive pardon from
      any judge that knows how to temper justice with mercy: witness
      what but the other day we heard from Filostrato touching Madonna
      Filippa at Prato.<note>Cf. Sixth Day, Novel VII.</note></p></div3><p><milestone id="p08010005" />Know, then, that there was once at Milan a German mercenary,
      Gulfardo by name, a doughty man, and very loyal to those with <pb n="178" />whom
      he took service; a quality most uncommon in Germans.
      And as he was wont to be most faithful in repaying whatever moneys
      he borrowed, he would have had no difficulty in finding a merchant
      to advance him any amount of money at a low rate of interest.
      <milestone id="p08010006" />Now, tarrying thus at Milan, Gulfardo fixed his affection on a very
      fine woman, named Madonna Ambruogia, the wife of a wealthy
      merchant, one Guasparruolo Cagastraccio, with whom he was well
      acquainted and on friendly terms: which amour he managed with
      such discretion that neither the husband nor any one else wist aught
      of it. So one day he sent her a message, beseeching her of her
      courtesy to gratify his passion, and assuring her that he on his part
      was ready to obey her every behest.</p><p><milestone id="p08010007" />The lady made a great many words about the affair, the upshot
      of which was that she would do as Gulfardo desired upon the following
      terms: to wit, that, in the first place, he should never discover
      the matter to a soul, and, secondly, that, as for some purpose or another
      she required two hundred florins of gold, he out of his abundance
      should supply her necessity; these conditions being satisfied she
      would be ever at his service. <milestone id="p08010008" />Offended by such base sordidness in
      one whom he had supposed to be an honourable woman, Gulfardo
      passed from ardent love to something very like hatred, and cast about
      how he might flout her. So he sent her word that he would right
      gladly pleasure her in this and in any other matter that might be in
      his power; let her but say when he was to come to see her, and he
      would bring the moneys with him, and none should know of the
      matter except a comrade of his, in whom he placed much trust, and
      who was privy to all that he did. <milestone id="p08010009" />The lady, if she should not rather
      be called the punk, gleefully made answer that in the course of a few
      days her husband, Guasparruolo, was to go to Genoa on business, and
      that, when he was gone, she would let Gulfardo know, and appoint a
      time for him to visit her. <milestone id="p08010010" />Gulfardo thereupon chose a convenient
      time, and hied him to Guasparruolo, to whom: <q direct="unspecified">I am come,</q>
      quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">about a little matter of business which I have on hand,
	for which I require two hundred florins of gold, and I should be glad
	if thou wouldst lend them me at the rate of interest which thou
	art wont to charge me.</q> <q direct="unspecified">That gladly will I,</q> replied Guasparruolo,
      and told out the money at once. <milestone id="p08010011" />A few days later Guasparruolo
      being gone to Genoa, as the lady had said, she sent word to Gulfardo
      <pb n="179" />that
      he should bring her the two hundred florins of gold. <milestone id="p08010012" />So Gulfardo
      hied him with his comrade to the lady's house, where he found
      her expecting him, and lost no time in handing her the two
      hundred florins of gold in his comrade's presence, saying: <q direct="unspecified">You
	will keep the money, Madam, and give it to your husband when he returns.</q>
      <milestone id="p08010013" />Witting not why Gulfardo so said, but thinking that 'twas
      but to conceal from his comrade that it was given by way of price,
      the lady made answer: <q direct="unspecified">That will I gladly; but I must first see
	whether the amount is right;</q> whereupon she told the florins out
      upon a table, and when she found that the two hundred were there,
      she put them away in high glee, <milestone id="p08010014" />and turning to Gulfardo, took him
      into her chamber, where, not on that night only but on many
      another night, while her husband was away, he had of her all that
      he craved. <milestone id="p08010015" />On Guasparruolo's return Gulfardo presently paid him a
      visit, having first made sure that the lady would be with him, and so
      in her presence: <q direct="unspecified">Guasparruolo,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I had after all no
	occasion for the money, to wit, the two hundred florins of gold that
	thou didst lend me the other day, being unable to carry through the
	transaction for which I borrowed them, and so I took an early opportunity
	of bringing them to thy wife, and gave them to her: thou
	wilt therefore cancel the account.</q> <milestone id="p08010016" />Whereupon Guasparruolo
      turned to the lady, and asked her if she had had them. She, not
      daring to deny the fact in presence of the witness, answered:
      <q direct="unspecified">Why, yes, I had them, and quite forgot to tell thee.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08010017" /><q direct="unspecified">Good,</q>
      quoth then Guasparruolo, <q direct="unspecified">we are quits, Gulfardo; make thy mind
	easy; I will see that thy account is set right.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08010018" />Gulfardo then
      withdrew, leaving the flouted lady to hand over her ill-gotten gains
      to her husband; and so the astute lover had his pleasure of his greedy
      mistress for nothing.</p></div2>