<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d07conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p07970001" />The sun was westering, and a light breeze blew,
when the king, his story ended, and none else being left to speak, arose, and taking off
the crown, set it on Lauretta's head, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, I crown you with yourself<note>A
play upon laurea (laurel wreath) and Lauretta.</note> queen of our
company: 'tis now for you, as our sovereign lady, to make such ordinances as you shall
deem meet for our common solace and delectation;</q> and having so said, he sat him
down again. <milestone id="p07970002" />Queen Lauretta sent for the seneschal, and bade him have a care
that the tables should be set in the pleasant vale somewhat earlier than had been their
wont, that their return to the palace might be more leisurely; after which she gave him to
know what else he had to do during her sovereignty. <milestone id="p07970003" />Then turning to the
company: <q direct="unspecified">Yesterday,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">Dioneo would have it that to-day we should
discourse of the tricks that wives play their husbands; and but that I am minded not to
shew as of the breed of yelping curs, that are ever prompt to retaliate, I would ordain
that to-morrow we discourse of the tricks that husbands play their wives.
<milestone id="p07970004" />However, in lieu thereof, I will have every one take thought to tell of those
tricks <pb n="173" />that, daily, woman plays man, or man woman, or one man another;
wherein, I doubt not, there will be matter of discourse no less agreeable than has been
that of to-day.</q> So saying, she rose and dismissed the company until
supper-time. <milestone id="p07970005" />So the ladies and the men being risen, some bared their feet and
betook them to the clear water, there to disport them, while others took their pleasure
upon the green lawn amid the trees that there grew goodly and straight. <milestone id="p07970006" />For no
brief
while Dioneo and Fiammetta sang in concert of Arcite and Palamon.  And so, each and all
taking their several pastimes, they sped the hours with exceeding great delight until
supper-time. Which being come, they sat them down at table beside the little lake, and
there, while a thousand songsters charmed their ears, and a gentle breeze, that blew from
the environing hills, fanned them, and never a fly annoyed them, reposefully and joyously
they supped. <milestone id="p07970007" />The tables removed, they roved a while about the pleasant vale,
and then, the sun being still high, for 'twas but half vespers, the queen gave the word,
and they wended their way back to their wonted abode, and going slowly, and beguiling the
way with quips and quirks without number upon divers matters, nor those alone of which
they had that day discoursed, they arrived, hard upon nightfall, at the goodly palace.
<milestone id="p07970008" />There, the short walk's fatigue dispelled by wines most cool and
comfits, they presently gathered for the dance about the fair fountain,
and now they footed it to the strains of Tindaro's cornemuse, and now to other
music. <milestone id="p07970009" />Which done, the queen bade Filomena give them a song; and thus Filomena
sang:</p><div3 who="filomena" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p07970010" /><l>Ah! woe
is me, my soul!</l>
<l>Ah! shall I ever thither fare again</l>
<l>Whence I
was parted to my grievous dole?</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p07970011" /><l>Full sure I know not; but
within my breast</l>
<l>Throbs ever the same fire</l>
<l>Of yearning there
where erst I was to be.</l>
<l>O thou in whom is all my weal, my
rest,</l>
<l>Lord of my heart's desire,</l>
<l>Ah! tell me thou! for none
to ask save thee</l>
<l>Neither dare I, nor see.</l>
<l>Ah! dear my Lord,
this wasted heart disdain</l>
<l>Thou wilt not, but with hope at length
console.</l></lg><pb n="174" /><lg><milestone id="p07970012" /><l>Kindled the flame I know not what
delight,</l>
<l>Which me doth so devour,</l>
<l>That day and night alike I
find no ease;</l>
<l>For whether it was by hearing, touch, or
sight,</l>
<l>Unwonted was the power,</l>
<l>And fresh the fire that me
each way did seize;</l>
<l>Wherein without release</l>
<l>I languish still,
and of thee, Lord, am fain,</l>
<l>For thou alone canst comfort and make
whole.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p07970013" /><l>Ah! tell me if it shall be, and how
soon,</l>
<l>That I again thee meet</l>
<l>Where those death-dealing eyes I
kissed. Thou, chief</l>
<l>Weal of my soul, my very soul, this
boon</l>
<l>Deny not; say that fleet</l>
<l>Thou hiest hither: comfort thus
my grief.</l>
<l>Ah! let the time be brief</l>
<l>Till thou art here, and
then long time remain;</l>
<l>For I, Love-stricken, crave but Love's
control.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p07970014" /><l>Let me but once again mine own thee
call,</l>
<l>No more so indiscreet</l>
<l>As erst, I'll be, to let thee
from me part:</l>
<l>Nay, I'll still hold thee, let what may
befall,</l>
<l>And of thy mouth so sweet</l>
<l>Such solace take as may
content my heart:</l>
<l>So this be all my art,</l>
<l>Thee to entice, me
with thine arms to enchain:</l>
<l>Whereon but musing inly chants my
soul.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p07970015" />This song set all the company conjecturing what new and delightsome love might now hold
Filomena in its sway; and as its words imported that she had had more joyance thereof than
sight alone

might yield, some that were there grew envious of her excess of happiness.  However, the
song being ended, the queen, bethinking her that the morrow was Friday, thus graciously
addressed them all: <milestone id="p07970016" /><q direct="unspecified">Ye wot, noble ladies, and ye also, my gallants, that
to-morrow is the day that is sacred to the passion of our Lord, which, if ye remember, we
kept devoutly when Neifile was queen, intermitting delectable discourse, as we did also on
the ensuing Saturday.  <milestone id="p07970017" />Where<pb n="175" />fore, being minded to follow Neifile's
excellent example, I deem that now, as then, 'twere a seemly thing to surcease from this
our pastime of story-telling for those two days, and compose our minds to meditation on
what was at that season accomplished for the weal of our souls.</q> <milestone id="p07970018" />All the
company having approved their queen's devout speech, she, as the night was now far spent,
dismissed them; and so they all betook them to slumber.</p></div2>