<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0503"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05030001" /> Pietro Boccamazza runs away with Agnolella, and
 encounters a gang of robbers: the girl takes refuge in
 a wood, and is guided to a castle. Pietro is taken, but
 escapes out of the hands of the robbers, and after some
 adventures arrives at the castle where Agnolella is,
 marries her, and returns with her to Rome.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05030002" />Ended Emilia's story, which none of the company
	spared to commend, the queen, turning to Elisa, bade her follow suit; and she, with glad
	obedience, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05030003" />'Tis a story, sweet ladies, of a woeful night passed by two indiscreet
	young lovers that I have in mind; but, as thereon ensued not a
	few days of joy, 'tis not inapposite to our argument, and shall be
	narrated.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p05030004" />'Tis no long time since at Rome, which, albeit now the tail,<note>In
 reference to the forlorn condition of the city while the seat of the
 papacy was at Avignon, 1308-1377.</note>
 was of yore the head, of the world, there dwelt a young man, Pietro
 Boccamazza by name, a scion of one of the most illustrious of the
 Roman houses, who became enamoured of a damsel exceeding fair, and
 amorous withal--her name Agnolella--the daughter of one Gigliuozzo
 Saullo, a plebeian, but in high repute among the Romans.  <milestone id="p05030005" />Nor, loving
 thus, did Pietro lack the address to inspire in Agnolella a love as ardent
 as his own.  <milestone id="p05030006" />Wherefore, overmastered by his passion, and minded no
 longer to endure the sore suffering that it caused him, he asked her
 in marriage. Whereof his kinsfolk were no sooner apprised, than
 with one accord they came to him and strongly urged him to desist
 from his purpose: they also gave Gigliuozzo Saullo to understand <pb n="19" />that
 he were best to pay no sort of heed to Pietro's words, for that,
 if he so did, they would never acknowledge him as friend or relative.
  <milestone id="p05030007" />Thus to see himself debarred of the one way by which he deemed
 he might attain to his desire, Pietro was ready to die for grief, and,
 all his kinsfolk notwithstanding, he would have married Gigliuozzo's
 daughter, had but the father consented.  <milestone id="p05030008" />Wherefore at length he
 made up his mind that, if the girl were willing, nought should stand
 in the way; and having through a common friend sounded the
 damsel and found her apt, he brought her to consent to elope with
 him from Rome.  <milestone id="p05030009" />The affair being arranged, Pietro and she took
 horse betimes one morning, and sallied forth for Anagni, where
 Pietro had certain friends, in whom he placed much trust; and as
 they rode, time not serving for full joyance of their love, for they
 feared pursuit, they held converse thereof, and from time to time
 exchanged a kiss.  <milestone id="p05030010" />Now it so befell, that, the way being none too
 well known to Pietro, when, perhaps eight miles from Rome, they
 should have turned to the right, they took instead a leftward road.
 Whereon when they had ridden but little more than two miles, they
 found themselves close to a petty castle, whence, so soon as they
 were observed, there issued some dozen men at arms;  <milestone id="p05030011" />and, as they
 drew near, the damsel, espying them, gave a cry, and said: <q direct="unspecified">We are
 attacked, Pietro, let us flee;</q> and guiding her nag as best she knew
 towards a great forest, she planted the spurs in his sides, and so, holding
 on by the saddle-bow, was borne by the goaded creature into the
 forest at a gallop.  <milestone id="p05030012" />Pietro, who had been too engrossed with her face
 to give due heed to the way, and thus had not been ware, as soon as
 she, of the approach of the men at arms, was still looking about to
 see whence they were coming, when they came up with him, and
 took him prisoner, and forced him to dismount. Then they asked
 who he was, and, when he told them, they conferred among themselves,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">This is one of the friends of our enemies: what
 else can we do but relieve him of his nag and of his clothes, and hang
 him on one of these oaks in scorn of the Orsini?</q>  <milestone id="p05030013" />To which
 proposal all agreeing, they bade Pietro strip himself: but while,
 already divining his fate, he was so doing, an ambuscade of full
 five-and-twenty
 men at arms fell suddenly upon them, crying: <milestone id="p05030014" /><q direct="unspecified">Death,
 death!</q> Thus surprised, they let Pietro go, and stood on the
 defensive; but, seeing that the enemy greatly outnumbered them, <pb n="20" />they
 took to their heels, the others giving chase. Whereupon Pietro
 hastily resumed his clothes, mounted his nag, and fled with all speed
 in the direction which he had seen the damsel take.  <milestone id="p05030015" />But finding no
 road or path through the forest, nor discerning any trace of a horse's
 hooves, he was--for that he found not the damsel--albeit he deemed
 himself safe out of the clutches of his captors and their assailants, the
 most wretched man alive, and fell a weeping and wandering hither and
 thither about the forest, uttering Agnolella's name.  <milestone id="p05030016" />None answered;
 but turn back he dared not: so on he went, not knowing whither
 he went; besides which, he was in mortal dread of the wild beasts
 that infest the forest, as well on account of himself as of the damsel,
 whom momently he seemed to see throttled by some bear or wolf.
  <milestone id="p05030017" />Thus did our unfortunate Pietro spend the whole day, wandering
 about the forest, making it to resound with his cries of Agnolella's
 name, and harking at times back, when he thought to go forward;
 until at last, what with his cries and his tears and his fears and his
 long fasting, he was so spent that he could go no further.  <milestone id="p05030018" />'Twas
 then nightfall, and, as he knew not what else to do, he dismounted
 at the foot of an immense oak, and having tethered his nag to the
 trunk, climbed up into the branches, lest he should be devoured by
 the wild beasts during the night.  <milestone id="p05030019" />Shortly afterwards the moon rose
 with a very clear sky, and Pietro, who dared not sleep, lest he should
 fall, and indeed, had he been secure from that risk, his misery and
 his anxiety on account of the damsel would not have suffered him to
 sleep, kept watch, sighing and weeping and cursing his evil luck.</p><p><milestone id="p05030020" />Now the damsel, who, as we said before, had fled she knew not
 whither, allowing her nag to carry her whithersoever he would,
 strayed so far into the forest that she lost sight of the place where
 she had entered it, and spent the whole day just as Pietro had done,
 wandering about the wilderness, pausing from time to time, and
 weeping, and uttering his name, and bewailing her evil fortune.  <milestone id="p05030021" />At
 last, seeing that 'twas now the vesper hour and Pietro came not, she
 struck into a path, which the nag followed, until, after riding some
 two miles, she espied at some distance a cottage, for which she made
 with all speed, and found there a good man, well stricken in years,
 with his wife, who was likewise aged.  <milestone id="p05030022" />Seeing her ride up alone,
 they said: <q direct="unspecified">Daughter, wherefore ridest thou thus alone at this
 hour in these parts?</q>  <milestone id="p05030023" />Weeping, the damsel made answer that she <pb n="21" />had
 lost her companion in the forest, and asked how far might
 Anagni be from there? <q direct="unspecified">My daughter,</q> returned the good man,
 <q direct="unspecified">this is not the road to Anagni; 'tis more than twelve miles away.</q>
 <milestone id="p05030024" /><q direct="unspecified">And how far off,</q> inquired the damsel, <q direct="unspecified">are the nearest houses in
 which one might find lodging for the night?</q> <milestone id="p05030025" /><q direct="unspecified">There are none
 so near,</q> replied the good man, <q direct="unspecified">that thou canst reach them to-day.</q>
 <milestone id="p05030026" /><q direct="unspecified">Then, so please you,</q> said the damsel, <q direct="unspecified">since go elsewhither I
 cannot, for God's sake let me pass the night here with you.</q>  <milestone id="p05030027" />Whereto
 the good man made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Damsel, welcome art thou to tarry
 the night with us; but still thou art to know that these parts are infested
 both by day and by night by bands, which, be they friends or be they
 foes, are alike ill to meet with, and not seldom do much despite and
 mischief, and if by misadventure one of these bands should visit us
 while thou wert here, and marking thy youth and beauty should do
 thee despite and dishonour, we should be unable to afford thee any
 succour.  <milestone id="p05030028" />This we would have thee know, that if it should so come
 to pass, thou mayst not have cause to reproach us.</q>  <milestone id="p05030029" />The damsel
 heard not the old man's words without dismay; but, seeing that the
 hour was now late, she answered: <q direct="unspecified">God, if He be so pleased, will
 save both you and me from such molestation, and if not, 'tis a much
 lesser evil to be maltreated by men than to be torn in pieces by the
 wild beasts in the forest.</q>  <milestone id="p05030030" />So saying, she dismounted, and entered
 the cottage, where, having supped with the poor man and his wife
 on such humble fare as they had, she laid herself in her clothes
 beside them in their bed. She slept not, however; for her own evil
 plight and that of Pietro, for whom she knew not how to augur
 aught but evil, kept her sighing and weeping all night long.  <milestone id="p05030031" />And
 towards matins she heard a great noise as of men that marched; so
 up she got and hied her into a large courtyard that was in rear of the
 cottage, and part of which was covered with a great heap of hay,
 which she espying, hid herself therein, that, if the men came there,
 they might not so readily find her.  <milestone id="p05030032" />Scarce had she done so than the
 men, who proved to be a strong company of marauders, were at the
 door of the cottage, which they forced open; and having entered,
 and found the damsel's nag, still saddled, they asked who was there.
  <milestone id="p05030033" />The damsel being out of sight, the good man answered: <q direct="unspecified">There
 is none here but my wife and I; but this nag, which has given some
 one the slip, found his way hither last night, and we housed him, lest
 <pb n="22" />he
 should be devoured by the wolves.</q> <milestone id="p05030034" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> said the chief of the
 band, <q direct="unspecified">as he has no owner, he will come in very handy for us.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05030035" />Whereupon, in several parties, they ransacked the cottage from
 top to bottom; and one party went out into the courtyard, where,
 as they threw aside their lances and targets, it so befell that one of
 them, not knowing where else to bestow his lance, tossed it into the
 hay, and was within an ace of killing the damsel that lay hid there,
 as likewise she of betraying her whereabouts, for the lance all but
 grazing her left breast, insomuch that the head tore her apparel, she
 doubted she was wounded, and had given a great shriek, but that,
 remembering where she was, she refrained for fear.  <milestone id="p05030036" />By and by the
 company cooked them a breakfast of kid's and other meat, and having
 eaten and drunken, dispersed in divers directions, as their affairs
 required, taking the girl's nag with them.  <milestone id="p05030037" />And when they were
 gotten some little way off, the good man asked his wife: <q direct="unspecified">What
 became of the damsel, our guest of last night, that I have not seen
 her since we rose?</q>  <milestone id="p05030038" />The good woman answered that she knew
 not where the damsel was, and went to look for her.  <milestone id="p05030039" />The damsel,
 discovering that the men were gone, came forth of the hay, and
 the good man, seeing her, was overjoyed that she had not fallen into
 the hands of the ruffians, and, as day was breaking, said to her:
 <q direct="unspecified">Now that day is at hand, we will, so it like thee, escort thee to a
 castle, some five miles hence, where thou wilt be in safety; but thou
 must needs go afoot, because these villains, that are but just gone,
 have taken thy nag with them.</q>  <milestone id="p05030040" />The damsel, resigning herself to
 her loss, besought them for God's sake to take her to the castle:
 whereupon they set forth, and arrived there about half tierce.  <milestone id="p05030041" />Now
 the castle belonged to one of the Orsini, Liello di Campo di Fiore
 by name, whose wife, as it chanced, was there. A most kindly
 and good woman she was, and, recognizing the damsel as soon as she
 saw her, gave her a hearty welcome and would fain have from her a
 particular account of how she came there.  <milestone id="p05030042" />So the damsel told her
 the whole story. The lady, to whom Pietro was also known, as
 being a friend of her husband, was distressed to hear of his misadventure,
 and being told where he was taken, gave him up for dead.
 So she said to the damsel: <q direct="unspecified">Since so it is that thou knowest not
 how Pietro has fared, thou shalt stay here with me until such time
 as I may have opportunity to send thee safely back to Rome.</q></p><pb n="23" /><p><milestone id="p05030043" />Meanwhile Pietro, perched on his oak in as woeful a plight as
 might be, had espied, when he should have been in his first sleep, a
 full score of wolves, that, as they prowled, caught sight of the nag,
 and straightway were upon him on all sides.  <milestone id="p05030044" />The horse, as soon as he
 was ware of their approach, strained on the reins till they snapped,
 and tried to make good his escape; but, being hemmed in, was
 brought to bay, and made a long fight of it with his teeth and hooves;
 but in the end they bore him down and throttled him and forthwith
 eviscerated him, and, the whole pack falling upon him, devoured him
 to the bone before they had done with him.  <milestone id="p05030045" />Whereat Pietro, who
 felt that in the nag he had lost a companion and a comfort in his
 travail, was sorely dismayed, and began to think that he should never
 get out of the forest.  <milestone id="p05030046" />But towards dawn, he, perched there in the
 oak, almost dead with cold, looking around him as he frequently did,
 espied about a mile off a huge fire. Wherefore, as soon as 'twas
 broad day, he got down, not without trepidation, from the oak, and
 bent his steps towards the fire; and being come to it, he found,
 gathered about it, a company of shepherds, eating and making merry,
 who took pity on him and made him welcome.  <milestone id="p05030047" />And when he had
 broken his fast and warmed himself, he told them the mishap that
 had befallen him, and how it was that he was come there alone, and
 asked them if there was a farm or castle in those parts, whither he
 might betake him.  <milestone id="p05030048" />The shepherds said that about three miles away
 there was a castle belonging to Liello di Campo di Fiore, where his lady
 was then tarrying. Pietro, much comforted, requested to be guided
 thither by some of their company; whereupon two of them right
 gladly escorted him.  <milestone id="p05030049" />So Pietro arrived at the castle, where he found
 some that knew him; and while he was endeavouring to set on foot
 a search for the damsel in the forest, the lady summoned him to her
 presence, and he, forthwith obeying, and seeing Agnolella with her,
 was the happiest man that ever was.  <milestone id="p05030050" />He yearned till he all but
 swooned to go and embrace her, but refrained, for bashfulness, in the
 lady's presence. And overjoyed as he was, the joy of the damsel
 was no less.  <milestone id="p05030051" />The lady received him with great cheer, and though,
 when she had heard the story of his adventures from his own lips, she
 chid him not a little for having set at nought the wishes of his kinsfolk;
 yet, seeing that he was still of the same mind, and that the
 damsel was also constant, she said to herself: To what purpose <pb n="24" />give
 I myself all this trouble? they love one another, they know
 one another; they love with equal ardour; their love is honourable,
 and I doubt not is well pleasing to God, seeing that the one has
 escaped the gallows and the other the lance, and both the wild beasts:
 wherefore be it as they would have it.  <milestone id="p05030052" />Then, turning to them, she
 said: <q direct="unspecified">If 'tis your will to be joined in wedlock as man and wife,
 mine jumps with it: here shall your nuptials be solemnized and at
 Liello's charges, and for the rest I will see that your peace is made
 with your kinsfolk.</q>  <milestone id="p05030053" />So in the castle the pair were wedded, Pietro
 only less blithe than Agnolella, the lady ordering the nuptials as
 honourably as might be in her mountain-home, and there they had
 most sweet joyance of the first fruits of their love.  <milestone id="p05030054" />So some days
 they tarried there, and then accompanied by the lady with a strong
 escort, they took horse and returned to Rome, where, very wroth
 though she found Pietro's kinsfolk for what he had done, the lady
 re-established solid peace between him and them; and so at Rome
 Pietro and Agnolella lived together to a good old age in great
 tranquillity and happiness.</p></div2>