<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d09conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p09970001" />What laughter this story drew from the ladies, who understood it
 better than Dioneo had wished, may be left to the imagination of
 the fair one that now laughs thereat.  <milestone id="p09970002" />However, as the stories were
 ended, and the sun now shone with a tempered radiance, the queen,
 witting that the end of her sovereignty was come, stood up and took
 off the crown, and set it on the head of Pamfilo, whom alone it now
 remained thus to honour; and said with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, 'tis
 a great burden that falls upon thee, seeing that thou, coming last, art
 bound to make good my shortcomings and those of my predecessors;
 which God give thee grace to accomplish, even as He has given me
 grace to make thee king.</q>  <milestone id="p09970003" />With gladsome acknowledgment of the
 honour: <q direct="unspecified">I doubt not,</q> replied Pamfilo, <q direct="unspecified">that, thanks to your
 noble qualities and those of my other subjects, I shall win even such
 praise as those that have borne sway before me.</q> Then, following
 the example of his predecessors, he made all meet arrangements in
 concert with the seneschal: after which, he turned to the expectant
 ladies, and thus spoke:  <milestone id="p09970004" /><q direct="unspecified">Enamoured my ladies, Emilia, our queen
 of to-day, deeming it proper to allow you an interval of rest to recruit
 your powers, gave you license to discourse of such matters as should
 most commend themselves to each in turn; and as thereby you are
 now rested, I judge that 'tis meet to revert to our accustomed rule.
 Wherefore I ordain that for to-morrow you do each of you take
 thought how you may discourse of the ensuing theme: to wit, of
 such as in matters of love, or otherwise, have done something with
 liberality or magnificence.  <milestone id="p09970005" />By the telling, and (still more) by the
 doing of such things, your spirits will assuredly be duly attuned and
 <pb n="311" />animated
 to emprise high and noble; whereby our life, which cannot
 but be brief, seeing that 'tis enshrined in a mortal body, fame
 shall perpetuate in glory; which whoso serves not the belly, as do the
 beasts, must not only covet, but with all zeal seek after and labour to
 attain.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09970006" />The gay company having, one and all, approved the theme, rose
 at a word from their new king, and betook them to their wonted
 pastimes, and so, according as they severally had most lief, diverted
 them,  <milestone id="p09970007" />until they blithely reunited for supper, which being served
 with all due care and despatched, they rose up to dance, as they were
 wont, and when they had sung, perhaps, a thousand ditties, fitter to
 please by their words than by any excellence of musical art, the king
 bade Neifile sing one on her own account. And promptly and
 graciously, with voice clear and blithe, thus Neifile sang:</p><div3 who="neifile" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p09970008" /><l>In prime of maidenhood, and fair and feat</l>
<l>'Mid spring's fresh foison chant I merrily:</l>
<l>Thanks be to Love and to my fancies sweet.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p09970009" /><l>As o'er the grassy mead I, glancing, fare,</l>
<l>I mark it white and yellow and vermeil dight</l>
<l>With flowers, the thorny rose, the lily white:</l>
<l>And all alike to his face I compare,</l>
<l>Who, loving, hath me ta'en, and me shall e'er</l>
<l>Hold bounden to his will, sith I am she</l>
<l>That in his will findeth her joy complete.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p09970010" /><l>Whereof if so it be that I do find</l>
<l>Any that I most like to him approve,</l>
<l>That pluck I straight and kiss with words of love,</l>
<l>Discovering all, as best I may, my mind;</l>
<l>Yea, all my heart's desire; and then entwined</l>
<l>I set it in the chaplet daintily,</l>
<l>And with my yellow tresses bind and pleat.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p09970011" /><l>And as mine eyes do drink in the delight</l>
<l>Which the flower yields them, even so my mind,</l>
<l>Fired with his sweet love, doth such solace find,</l>
<l>As he himself were present to the sight:</l>
<l>But never word of mine discover might</l>
<l>That which the flower's sweet smell awakes in me:</l>
<l>Witness the true tale that my sighs repeat.</l></lg><pb n="312" /><lg><milestone id="p09970012" /><l>For from my bosom gentle and hot they fly,</l>
<l>Not like the gusty sighs that others heave,</l>
<l>Whenas they languish and do sorely grieve;</l>
<l>And to my love incontinent they hie:</l>
<l>Whereof when he is ware, he, by and by,</l>
<l>To meward hasting, cometh suddenly,</l>
<l>When: <q direct="unspecified">Lest I faint,</q> I cry, <q direct="unspecified">come, I entreat.</q></l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p09970013" />The king and all the ladies did not a little commend Neifile's
 song; after which, as the night was far spent, the king bade all go to
 rest until the morrow.</p></div2>