<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0607"><head>Novel VII</head><argument>      <p><milestone id="p06070001" />Madonna Filippa, being found by her husband with her
	lover, is cited before the court, and by a ready and
	jocund answer acquits herself, and brings about an alteration of the
	statute.</p>
    </argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06070002" />Fiammetta had been silent some time, but Scalza's
	novel argument to prove the pre-eminent nobility of the Baronci kept all still laughing,
	when the queen called for a story from Filostrato, who thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06070003" />Noble ladies, an excellent thing is apt speech on all occasions,
	but to be proficient therein I deem then most excellent when the occasion does most
	imperatively demand it. As was the case with a gentlewoman, of whom I purpose to speak to
	you, who not only ministered gaiety and merriment to her hearers, but extricated herself,
	as you shall hear, from the toils of an ignominious death.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06070004" />There was aforetime in the city of Prato a statute
no less censurable
 than harsh, which, making no distinction between the
wife
 whom her husband took in adultery with her lover, and the woman
found pleasuring a stranger for money, condemned both alike to be
 burned.
<milestone id="p06070005" />While this statute was in force, it befell that a gentle-woman,
 fair and
beyond measure enamoured, Madonna Filippa by
 name, was by her husband,
Rinaldo de' Pugliesi, found in her own
 chamber one night in the arms of
Lazzarino de' Guazzagliotri, a
 handsome young noble of the same city, whom
she loved even as
 herself. <milestone id="p06070006" />Whereat Rinaldo, very wroth, scarce refrained
from falling
 upon them and killing them on the spot; and indeed, but that
he
 doubted how he should afterwards fare himself, he had given way to
 the
vehemence of his anger, and so done. <milestone id="p06070007" />Nor, though he so far
 <pb n="91" />mastered himself, could he forbear recourse to the statute, thereby
to compass that which he might not otherwise lawfully compass, to
 wit, the
death of his lady. <milestone id="p06070008" />Wherefore, having all the evidence
 needful to prove her
guilt, he took no further counsel; but, as soon
 as 'twas day, he charged
the lady and had her summoned. <milestone id="p06070009" />Like
 most ladies that are veritably
enamoured, the lady was of a high
 courage; and, though not a few of her
friends and kinsfolk sought
 to dissuade her, she resolved to appear to the
summons, having liefer
 die bravely confessing the truth than basely flee
and for defiance of
 the law live in exile, and shew herself unworthy of
such a lover as
 had had her in his arms that night. <milestone id="p06070010" />And so, attended by
many ladies
 and gentlemen, who all exhorted her to deny the charge, she
came
 before the Podest&#224;, and with a composed air and unfaltering
voice
 asked whereof he would interrogate her. <milestone id="p06070011" />The Podest&#224;,
surveying her,
 and taking note of her extraordinary beauty, and exquisite
manners,
 and the high courage that her words evinced, was touched with
compassion
 for her, fearing she might make some admission, by reason
whereof, to save his honour, he must needs do her to death. <milestone id="p06070012" />But
 still, as
he could not refrain from examining her of that which was
 laid to her
charge, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, here, as you see, is your
 husband, Rinaldo, who
prefers a charge against you, alleging that he
 has taken you in adultery,
and so he demands that, pursuant to a
 statute which is in force here, I
punish you with death: but this I
 may not do, except you confess;
wherefore be very careful what you
 answer, and tell me if what your
husband alleges against you be true.</q>
 <milestone id="p06070013" />The lady, no wise dismayed, and
in a tone not a little jocund, thus
 made answer: <q direct="unspecified">True it is, Sir, that
Rinaldo is my husband, and
 that last night he found me in the arms of
Lazzarino, in whose arms
 for the whole-hearted love that I bear him I have
ofttimes lain; nor
 shall I ever deny it; but, as well I wot you know, the
laws ought
 to be common and enacted with the common consent of all that
they
 affect; <milestone id="p06070014" />which conditions are wanting to this law, inasmuch as it
binds only us poor women, in whom to be liberal is much less reprehensible
than it were in men; and furthermore the consent of no
 woman was--I say
not had, but--so much as asked before 'twas
 made; for which reasons it
justly deserves to be called a bad law.
 <milestone id="p06070015" />However, if in scathe of my body
and your own soul, you are
 minded to put it in force, 'tis your affair;
but, I pray you, go not
 <pb n="92" />on to try this matter in any wise,
until you have granted me this
 trifling grace, to wit, to ask my husband
if I ever gainsaid him, but
 did not rather accord him, when and so often
as he craved it, complete
 enjoyment of myself.</q> <milestone id="p06070016" />Whereto Rinaldo,
without awaiting
 the Podest&#224;'s question, forthwith answered, that
assuredly the lady
 had ever granted him all that he had asked of her for
his gratification.
 <milestone id="p06070017" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> promptly continued the lady, <q direct="unspecified">if he has
ever had of me as
 much as sufficed for his solace, what was I or am I to
do with the
 surplus? Am I to cast it to the dogs? Is it not much better
to
 bestow it on a gentleman that loves me more dearly than himself,
 than
to suffer it to come to nought or worse?</q> <milestone id="p06070018" />Which jocund
 question being
heard by well-nigh all the folk of Prato, who had
 flocked thither all agog
to see a dame so fair and of such quality on
 her trial for such an
offence, they laughed loud and long, and then
 all with one accord, and as
with one voice, exclaimed that the lady
 was in the right and said well;
nor left they the court until in
 concert with the Podest&#224; they had
so altered the harsh statute as
 that
 thenceforth only such women as
should wrong their husbands for
 money should be within its
purview.</p><p><milestone id="p06070019" />Wherefore Rinaldo left the court, discomfited of his
foolish
 enterprise; and the lady blithe and free, as if rendered back to
life
 from the burning, went home triumphant.</p></div2>