<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d06intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p06980002" />Still in mid heaven, the moon had lost her radiance, nor was any
part of our world unillumined by the fresh splendour of the dawn, when, the queen being
risen and having mustered her company, they hied them, gently sauntering, across the dewy
mead some distance from the beautiful hill, conversing now of this, now of the other
matter, canvassing the stories, their greater or less degree of beauty, and laughing
afresh at divers of their incidents, until, the sun being now in his higher ascendant,
they began to feel his heat, and turning back by common consent, retraced their steps to
the palace, <milestone id="p06980003" />where, the tables being already set, and fragrant herbs and fair
flowers
strewn all about, they by the queen's command, before it should grow hotter, addressed
themselves to their meal. So, having blithely
breakfasted, they first of all sang some dainty and jocund ditties, and
then, as they were severally minded, composed them to sleep or sat them down to chess or
dice, while Dioneo and Lauretta fell a singing of Troilus and Cressida.</p><p><milestone id="p06980004" />The hour of session being come, they took their places, at the queen's summons, in
their wonted order by the fountain; but, when the queen was about to call for the first
story, that happened which had not happened before; to wit, there being a great uproar in
the
kitchen among the maids and men, the sound thereof reached the ears of the queen and all
the company. <milestone id="p06980005" />Whereupon the queen called the seneschal and asked him who bawled
so loud, and what was the occasion of the uproar. The seneschal made answer that <pb n="72" />'twas some contention between Licisca and Tindaro; but the occasion he knew not,
having but just come to quiet them, when he received her summons. <milestone id="p06980006" />The queen
then bade him cause Licisca and Tindaro to come thither forthwith: so they came, and the
queen enquired of them the cause of the uproar. <milestone id="p06980007" />Tindaro was about to make
answer, when Licisca, who was somewhat advanced in years, and disposed to give herself
airs, and heated to the strife of words, turned to Tindaro,
and scowling upon him said: <q direct="unspecified">Unmannerly varlet that makest bold to speak before me;
leave me to tell the story.</q> Then, turning to the queen, she said: 
      <milestone id="p06980008" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam, this
fellow would fain instruct me as to Sicofante's wife, and--neither more or less--as if I
had not known her well--would have me believe that, the first night that Sicofante lay
with her, 'twas by force and not without effusion of blood that Master Yard made his way
into Dusky Hill; which I deny, averring that he met with no resistance, but, on the
contrary, with a hearty welcome on the part of the garrison. <milestone id="p06980009" />And such a
numskull is he as fondly to believe that the girls are so simple as to let slip their
opportunities, while they wait on the caprice of father or brothers, who six times out of
	seven delay to marry them for three or four years after they should. <milestone id="p06980010" />Ay, ay indeed,
doubtless they were well advised to tarry so long! Christ's faith! I should know the truth
of what I swear; there is never a woman in my neighbour-hood whose husband had her
virginity; and well I know how many and what manner of tricks our married dames play their
husbands; and yet this booby would fain teach me to know women as if I were but born
yesterday.</q></p><p><milestone id="p06980011" />While Licisca thus spoke, the ladies laughed till all their teeth were ready to start
from their heads. Six times at least the queen bade her be silent: but all in vain; she
      halted not till she had said all that she had a mind to. <milestone id="p06980012" />When she had done, the queen
turned with a smile to Dioneo saying: <q direct="unspecified">This is a question for thee to deal with, Dioneo;
so hold thyself in readiness to give final judgment upon it, when our stories are
ended.</q> <milestone id="p06980013" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied Dioneo forthwith, <q direct="unspecified">I give judgment without
more ado: I say that Licisca is in the right; I believe that 'tis even as she says, and
that Tindaro is a fool.</q> <milestone id="p06980014" />Whereupon Licisca burst out laughing, and turning
to Tindaro: <q direct="unspecified">Now did I not tell thee so?</q> quoth she. <q direct="unspecified">Begone in

God's name: dost think to know more than I, thou that art but a <pb n="73" />sucking babe?
Thank God, I have not lived for nothing, not I.</q>

<milestone id="p06980015" />And had not the queen sternly bade her be silent, and make no more

disturbance, unless she had a mind to be whipped, and sent both her and Tindaro back to
the kitchen, the whole day would have been spent in nought but listening to
her. <milestone id="p06980016" />So Licisca and Tindaro having withdrawn, the queen charged Filomena to
tell the first story: and gaily thus Filomena began.</p></div2>