<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0902"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09020001" />An abbess rises in haste and in the dark, with intent to
 surprise an accused nun abed with her lover: thinking
 to put on her veil, she puts on instead the breeches
 of a priest that she has with her: the nun, espying
 her headgear, and doing her to wit thereof, is acquitted,
 and thenceforth finds it easier to forgather with her
 lover.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09020002" />So ended Filomena; and when all had commended the address
 shewn by the lady in ridding herself of the two lovers that she
 affected not, and contrariwise had censured the hardihood of the two
 lovers as not love but madness, the queen turned to Elisa, and with
 a charming air: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Elisa, follow,</q> quoth she: whereupon Elisa
 began on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09020003" />Dearest ladies, 'twas cleverly done of Madonna
 Francesca, to disembarrass herself in the way we have heard: but I
 have to tell of a young nun, who by a happy retort, and the favour
 of Fortune, delivered herself from imminent peril.  <milestone id="p09020004" />And as you
 know that there are not a few most foolish folk, who, notwithstanding
 their folly, take upon themselves the governance and correction of
 others; so you may learn from my story that Fortune at times justly
 puts them to shame; which befell the abbess, who was the superior
 of the nun of whom I am about to speak.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09020005" />You are to know, then, that in a convent in Lombardy of very
 great repute for strict and holy living there was, among other ladies
 that there wore the veil, a young woman of noble family, and extraordinary
 beauty. Now Isabetta--for such was her name--having
 speech one day of one of her kinsmen at the grate, became enamoured
 <pb n="272" />of a fine young gallant that was with him; who, seeing her to be
 very fair, and reading her passion in her eyes, was kindled with a like
 flame for her: which mutual and unsolaced love they bore a great
 while not without great suffering to both.  <milestone id="p09020006" />But at length, both being
 intent thereon, the gallant discovered a way by which he might with
 all secrecy visit his nun; and she approving, he paid her not one visit
 only, but many, to their no small mutual solace.  <milestone id="p09020007" />But, while thus they
 continued their intercourse, it so befell that one night one of the
 sisters observed him take his leave of Isabetta and depart, albeit neither
 he nor she was ware that they had thus been discovered. The sister
 imparted what she had seen to several others. At first they were
 minded to denounce her to the abbess, one Madonna Usimbalda,
 who was reputed by the nuns, and indeed by all that knew her, to
 be a good and holy woman; but on second thoughts they deemed it
 expedient, that there might be no room for denial, to cause the abbess
 to take her and the gallant in the act. So they held their peace, and
 arranged between them to keep her in watch and close espial, that
 they might catch her unawares.  <milestone id="p09020008" />Of which practice Isabetta recking,
 witting nought, it so befell that one night, when she had her lover
 to see her, the sisters that were on the watch were soon ware of it,
 and at what they deemed the nick of time parted into two companies,
 of which one mounted guard at the threshold of Isabetta's cell, while
 the other hasted to the abbess's chamber, and knocking at the door,
 roused her, and as soon as they heard her voice, said: <q direct="unspecified">Up, Madam,
 without delay: we have discovered that Isabetta has a young man
 with her in her cell.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09020009" />Now that night the abbess had with her a priest whom she used
 not seldom to have conveyed to her in a chest; and the report of the
 sisters making her apprehensive lest for excess of zeal and hurry they
 should force the door open, she rose in a trice; and huddling on
 her clothes as best she might in the dark, instead of the veil that
 they wear, which they call the psalter, she caught up the priest's
 breeches, and having clapped them on her head,  <milestone id="p09020010" />hied her forth,
 and locked the door behind her, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Where is this woman
 accursed of God?</q>  <milestone id="p09020011" />And so, guided by the sisters, all so agog to catch
 Isabetta a sinning that they perceived not what manner of headgear
 the abbess wore, she made her way to the cell, and with their
 aid broke open the door; and entering they found the two lovers
 <pb n="273" />abed in one another's arms; who, as it were, thunderstruck to be
 thus surprised, lay there, witting not what to do.  <milestone id="p09020012" />The sisters took
 the young nun forthwith, and by command of the abbess brought her
 to the chapter-house. The gallant, left behind in the cell, put on
 his clothes and waited to see how the affair would end, being minded
 to make as many nuns as he might come at pay dearly for any despite
 that might be done his mistress, and to bring her off with him.  <milestone id="p09020013" />The
 abbess, seated in the chapter-house with all her nuns about her, and
 all eyes bent upon the culprit, began giving her the severest reprimand
 that ever woman got, for that by her disgraceful and abominable conduct,
 should it get wind, she had sullied the fair fame of the convent;
 whereto she added menaces most dire.  <milestone id="p09020014" />Shamefast and timorous, the
 culprit essayed no defence, and her silence begat pity of her in
 the rest; but, while the abbess waxed more and more voluble, it
 chanced that the girl raised her head and espied the abbess's headgear,
 and the points that hung down on this side and that.  <milestone id="p09020015" />The significance
 whereof being by no means lost upon her, she quite plucked
 up heart, and: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">so help you God, tie up
 your coif, and then you may say what you will to me.</q>  <milestone id="p09020016" />Whereto
 the abbess, not understanding her, replied: <q direct="unspecified">What coif, lewd
 woman? So thou hast the effrontery to jest! Think'st thou that
 what thou hast done is a matter meet for jests?</q>  <milestone id="p09020017" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth the girl again, <q direct="unspecified">I pray you, tie up your coif, and
 then you may say to me whatever you please.</q> Which occasioned
 not a few of the nuns to look up at the abbess's head, and the abbess
 herself to raise her hands thereto, and so she and they at one and the
 same time apprehended Isabetta's meaning.  <milestone id="p09020018" />Wherefore the abbess,
 finding herself detected by all in the same sin, and that no disguise
 was possible, changed her tone, and held quite another sort of language
 than before, the upshot of which was that 'twas impossible to withstand
 the assaults of the flesh, and that, accordingly, observing due
 secrecy as theretofore, all might give themselves a good time, as they
 had opportunity. So, having dismissed Isabetta to rejoin her lover in
 her cell, she herself returned to lie with her priest.  <milestone id="p09020019" />And many a
 time thereafter, in spite of the envious, Isabetta had her gallant to
 see her, the others, that lacked lovers, doing in secret the best they
 might to push their fortunes.</p></div2>