<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0210"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02100001" />Paganino da Monaco carries off the wife of Messer
 Ricciardo di Chinzica, who, having learned where
 she is, goes to Paganino and in a friendly manner
 asks him to restore her. He consents, provided she
 be willing. She refuses to go back with her husband.
 Messer Ricciardo dies, and she marries Paganino.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02100002" />Their queen's story, by its beauty, elicited hearty commendation
 from all the honourable company, and most especially from Dioneo,
 with whom it now rested to conclude the day's narration. Again and
 again he renewed his eulogy of the queen's story; and then began
 on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02100003" />Fair ladies, there is that in the queen's story which has caused
	me to change my purpose, and substitute another story for that
	which I had meant to tell: I refer to the insensate folly of
	Bernab&#242; (well though it was with him in the end) and of all
	others, who delude themselves, as he seemed to do, with the vain
	imagination that, while they go about the world, taking their
	pleasure now of this, now of the other woman, their wives, left
	at home, suffer not their hands to stray from their girdles; as if
	we, who are born of them and bred among them, could be ignorant
	of the bent of their desires. <milestone id="p02100004" />Wherefore, by my story I purpose
	at one and the same time to shew you how great is the folly of
	all such, and how much greater is the folly of those who, deeming
	themselves mightier than nature, think by sophistical arguments to
	bring that to pass which is beyond their power, and strive might
	and main to conform others to their own pattern, however little
	<pb n="165" />the nature of the latter may brook such treatment.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02100005" />Know then
 that there was in Pisa a judge, better endowed with mental than
 with physical vigour, by name Messer Ricciardo di Chinzica, who,
 being minded to take a wife, and thinking, perhaps, to satisfy her
 by the same resources which served him for his studies, was to be
 suited with none that had not both youth and beauty, qualities
 which he would rather have eschewed, if he had known how to
 give himself as good counsel as he gave to others. However, being
 very rich, he had his desire. 
<milestone id="p02100006" />Messer Lotto Gualandi gave him in
 marriage one of his daughters, Bartolomea by name, a maid as fair
 and fit for amorous dalliance as any in Pisa, though few maids be
 there that do not shew as spotted lizards. 
<milestone id="p02100007" />The judge brought her
 home with all pomp and ceremony, and had a brave and lordly
 wedding; but in the essay which he made the very first night to
 serve her so as to consummate the marriage he made a false move,
 and drew the game much to his own disadvantage; for next morning
 his lean, withered and scarce animate frame was only to be
 re-quickened by draughts of vernaccia,<note>A strong white wine.</note>
 artificial restoratives and the
 like remedies. 
<milestone id="p02100008" />So, taking a more sober estimate of his powers than
 he had been wont, the worthy judge began to give his wife lessons
 from a calendar, which might have served as a horn-book, and
 perhaps had been put together at Ravenna:<note>The saying went, that owing
 to the multitude of churches at Ravenna
 every day was there a saint's day.</note> 
<milestone id="p02100009" />inasmuch as, according
 to his shewing, there was not a day in the year but was sacred,
 not to one saint only, but to many; in honour of whom for divers
 reasons it behoved men and women to abstain from carnal intercourse;
 whereto he added fast-days, Ember-days, vigils of Apostles
 and other saints, Friday, Saturday, Sunday, the whole of Lent,
 certain lunar mansions, and many other exceptions, arguing perchance,
 that the practice of men with women abed should have
 its times of vacation no less than the administration of the law.
 <milestone id="p02100010" />In this method, which caused the lady grievous dumps, he long
 persisted, hardly touching her once a month, and observing her
 closely, lest another should give her to know working-days, as he
 had taught her holidays.</p><pb n="166" /><p><milestone id="p02100011" />Now it so befell that, one hot season, Messer Ricciardo thought
 he would like to visit a very beautiful estate which he had near
 Monte Nero, there to take the air and recreate himself for some
 days, and thither accordingly he went with his fair lady. 
<milestone id="p02100012" />While
 there, to amuse her, he arranged for a day's fishing; and so, he in
 one boat with the fishermen, and she in another with other ladies,
 they put out to watch the sport, which they found so delightsome,
 that almost before they knew where they were they were some miles
 out to sea. <milestone id="p02100013" />And while they were thus engrossed with the sport, a
 galliot of Paganino da Mare, a very famous corsair of those days,
 hove in sight and bore down upon the boats, and, for all the speed
 they made, came up with that in which were the ladies; and on
 sight of the fair lady Paganino, regardless of all else, bore her off to
 his galliot before the very eyes of Messer Ricciardo, who was by this
 time ashore, and forthwith was gone. <milestone id="p02100014" />The chagrin of the judge,
 who was jealous of the very air, may readily be imagined. But
 'twas to no purpose that, both at Pisa and elsewhere, he moaned and
 groaned over the wickedness of the corsairs, for he knew neither by
 whom his wife had been abducted, nor whither she had been taken.
 <milestone id="p02100015" />Paganino, meanwhile, deemed himself lucky to have gotten so
 beautiful a prize; and being unmarried, he was minded never to
 part with her, and addressed himself by soft words to soothe the
 sorrow which kept her in a flood of tears. <milestone id="p02100016" />Finding words of little
 avail, he at night passed--the more readily that the calendar had
 slipped from his girdle, and all feasts and holidays from his  mind--to
 acts of love, and on this wise administered consolation so effective
 that before they were come to Monaco she had completely forgotten
 the judge and his canons, and had begun to live with Paganino as
 merrily as might be. So he brought her to Monaco, where, besides
 the daily and nightly solace which he gave her, he honourably
 entreated her as his wife.</p><p><milestone id="p02100017" />Not long afterwards Messer Ricciardo coming to know where
 his wife was, and being most ardently desirous to have her back, and
 thinking none but he would understand exactly what to do in the
 circumstances, determined to go and fetch her himself, being prepared
 to spend any sum of money that might be demanded by way of
 ransom. So he took ship, and being come to Monaco, he both saw
 her and was seen by her; which news she communicated to
 <pb n="167" />Paganino in the evening, and told him how she was minded to
 behave. <milestone id="p02100018" />Next morning Messer Ricciardo, encountering Paganino,
 made up to him; and soon assumed a very familiar and friendly air,
 while Paganino pretended not to know him, being on his guard to see
 what he would be at. So Messer Ricciardo, as soon as he deemed
 the time ripe, as best and most delicately he was able, disclosed to
 Paganino the business on which he had come, praying him to take
 whatever in the way of ransom he chose and restore him the lady.
 <milestone id="p02100019" />Paganino replied cheerily: <q direct="unspecified">Right glad I am to see you here, Sir;
 and briefly thus I answer you: True it is that I have here a young
 woman; whether she be your wife or another man's, I know not,
 for you are none of my acquaintance, nor is she, except for the short
 time that she has been with me. <milestone id="p02100020" />If, as you say, you are her husband,
 why, as you seem to me to be a pleasant gentleman, I will even take
 you to her, and I doubt not she will know you well; if she says that
 it is even as you say, and is minded to go with you, you shall give
 me just what you like by way of ransom, so pleasant have I found
 you; otherwise 'twill be churlish in you to think of taking her from
 me, who am a young man, and as fit to keep a woman as another,
 and moreover never knew any woman so agreeable.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100021" /><q direct="unspecified">My wife,</q>
 said Ricciardo, <q direct="unspecified">she is beyond all manner of doubt, as thou shalt
 see; for so soon as thou bringest me to her, she will throw her arms
 about my neck; wherefore as thou art minded, even so be it; I ask
 no more.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100022" /><q direct="unspecified">Go we then,</q> said Paganino; 
<milestone id="p02100023" />and forthwith they
 went into the house, and Paganino sent for the lady while they
 waited in one of the halls. By and by she entered from one of the
 adjoining rooms all trim and tricked out, and advanced to the place
 where Paganino and Messer Ricciardo were standing, but never a
 word did she vouchsafe to her husband, any more than if he had been
 some stranger whom Paganino had brought into the house. Whereat
 the judge was mightily amazed, having expected to be greeted by
 her with the heartiest of cheer, and began to ruminate thus:
 Perhaps I am so changed by the melancholy and prolonged heartache,
 to which I have been a prey since I lost her, that she does not
 recognise me. 
<milestone id="p02100024" />Wherefore he said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, cause enough have
 I to rue it that I took thee a fishing, for never yet was known such
 grief as has been mine since I lost thee; and now it seems as if thou
 dost not recognise me, so scant of courtesy is thy greeting. Seest
 <pb n="168" />thou not that I am thy Messer Ricciardo, come hither prepared to
 pay whatever this gentleman, in whose house we are, may demand,
 that I may have thee back and take thee away with me: and he is
 so good as to surrender thee on my own terms?</q> 
<milestone id="p02100025" />The lady turned
 to him with a slight smile, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Is it to me you speak, Sir?
 Bethink you that you may have mistaken me for another, for I, for
 my part, do not remember ever to have seen you.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100026" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> said
 Messer Ricciardo, <q direct="unspecified">but bethink thee what thou sayst; scan me
 closely; and if thou wilt but search thy memory, thou wilt find that
 I am thy Ricciardo di Chinzica.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100027" /><q direct="unspecified">Your pardon, Sir,</q> answered
 the lady, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not, perhaps, as seemly for me, as you imagine, to
 gaze long upon you; but I have gazed long enough to know that I
 never saw you before.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100028" />Messer Ricciardo supposed that she so spoke
 for fear of Paganino, in whose presence she durst not acknowledge
 that she knew him: so, after a while, he craved as a favour of
 Paganino that he might speak with her in a room alone. 
<milestone id="p02100029" />Which
 request Paganino granted, so only that he did not kiss her against her
 will. He then bade the lady go with Messer Ricciardo into a room
 apart, and hear what he had to say, and give him such answer as she
 deemed meet. <milestone id="p02100030" />So the lady and Messer Ricciardo went together into
 a room alone, and sate down, and Messer Ricciardo began on this
 wise: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! dear heart of me, sweet soul of me, hope of me, dost
 not recognise thy Ricciardo that loves thee better than himself?
 how comes it thus to pass? am I then so changed? Ah! goodly
 eye of me, do but look on me a little.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100031" />Whereat the lady burst into
 a laught, and interrupting him, said: <q direct="unspecified">Rest assured that my memory
 is not so short but that I know you for what you are, my husband,
 Messer Ricciardo di Chinzica; but far enough you shewed yourself
 to be, while I was with you, from knowing me for what I was,
 young, lusty, lively; which, had you been the wise man you would
 fain be reputed, you would not have ignored, nor by consequence
 that which, besides food and clothing, it behoves men to give young
 ladies, albeit for shame they demand it not; which in what sort you
 gave, you know. <milestone id="p02100032" />You should not have taken a wife if she was to
 be less to you than the study of the law, albeit 'twas never as a judge
 that I regarded you, but rather as a bellman of enc&#230;nia and saints'
 days, so well you knew them all, and fasts and vigils. And I tell
 you that, had you imposed the observance of as many saints' days on
 <pb n="169" />the labourers that till your lands as on yourself who had but my little
 plot to till, you would never have harvested a single grain of corn.
 <milestone id="p02100033" />God in His mercy, having regard unto my youth, has caused me to
 fall in with this gentleman, with whom I am much closeted in this
 room, where nought is known of feasts, such feasts, I mean, as you,
 more devoted to the service of God than to the service of ladies, were
 wont to observe in such profusion; nor was this threshold ever
 crossed by Saturday or Friday or vigil or Ember-days or Lent, that
 is so long; rather here we are at work day and night, threshing the
 wool, and well I know how featly it went when the matin bell last
 sounded. <milestone id="p02100034" />Wherefore with him I mean to stay, and to work while
 I am young, and postpone the observance of feasts and times of
 indulgence and fasts until I am old: so get you hence, and good luck
 go with you, but depart with what speed you may, and observe as
 many feasts as you like, so I be not with you.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02100035" />The pain with which Messer Ricciardo followed this outburst
 was more than he could bear, and when she had done, he exclaimed:
 <q direct="unspecified">Ah! sweet soul of me, what words are these that thou
 utterest? Hast thou no care for thy parents' honour and thine
 own? Wilt thou remain here to be this man's harlot, and to live
 in mortal sin, rather than live with me at Pisa as my wife? Why,
 when he is tired of thee, he will cast thee out to thy most grievous
 dishonour. I will ever cherish thee, and ever, will I nill I, thou
 wilt be the mistress of my house. <milestone id="p02100036" />Wouldst thou, to gratify this
 unbridled and unseemly passion, part at once with thy honour and
 with me, who love thee more dearly than my very life? Ah!
 cherished hope of me, say not so again: make up thy mind to come
 with me. As I now know thy bent, I will henceforth constrain
 myself to pleasure thee: wherefore, sweet my treasure, think better
 of it, and come with me, who have never known a happy hour since
 thou wert reft from me.</q> 
<milestone id="p02100037" />The lady answered: <q direct="unspecified">I expect not, nor
 is it possible, that another should be more tender of my honour than
 I am myself. Were my parents so, when they gave me to you? I
 trow not; nor mean I to be more tender of their honour now than
 they were then of mine. And if now I live in mortar sin, I will
 ever abide there until it be pestle sin:<note>A poor jeu de mots, mortaio,
 mortar, being substituted for mortale.</note> concern yourself no further
 <pb n="170" />on my account. 
<milestone id="p02100038" />Moreover, let me tell you, that, whereas at Pisa
 'twas as if I were your harlot, seeing that the planets in conjunction
 according to lunar mansion and geometric square intervened between
 you and me, here with Paganino I deem myself a wife, for he holds
 me in his arms all night long and hugs and bites me, and how he
 serves me, God be my witness. 
<milestone id="p02100039" />Ah! but you say you will constrain
 yourself to serve me: to what end? to do it on the third essay,
 and raise it by stroke of b&#226;ton? I doubt not you are become a
 perfect knight since last I saw you. Begone, and constrain yourself
 to live; for here, methinks, your tenure is but precarious, so hectic
 and wasted is your appearance. <milestone id="p02100040" />Nay more; I tell you this, that,
 should Paganino desert me (which he does not seem disposed to do
 so long as I am willing to stay with him), never will I return to
 your house, where for one while I staid to my most grievous loss
 and prejudice, but will seek my commodity elsewhere, than with
 one from whose whole body I could not wring a single cupful of sap.
 <milestone id="p02100041" />So, again, I tell you that here is neither feast nor vigil; wherefore
 here I mean to abide; and you, get you gone, in God's name with
 what speed you may, lest I raise the cry that you threaten to
 violate me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02100042" />Messer Ricciardo felt himself hard bested, but he could not but
 recognise that, worn out as he was, he had been foolish to take a
 young wife; so sad and woebegone he quitted the room, and, after
 expending on Paganino a wealth of words which signified nothing,
 he at last gave up his bootless enterprise, and leaving the lady to her
 own devices, returned to Pisa; where for very grief he lapsed into
 such utter imbecility that, when he was met by any with greeting or
 question in the street, he made no other answer than <q direct="unspecified">the evil hole
 brooks no holiday,</q> and soon afterwards died. <milestone id="p02100043" />Which when Paganino
 learned, being well assured of the love the lady bore him, he made
 her his lawful wife; and so, keeping neither feast nor vigil nor Lent,
 they worked as hard as their legs permitted, and had a good time.
 Wherefore, dear my ladies, I am of opinion that Messer Bernab&#242; in
 his altercation with Ambrogiuolo rode the goat downhill.<note>I. e.
 argued preposterously, the goat being the last animal to carry a
 rider comfortably downhill.</note></p></div2>