<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0807"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08070001" />A scholar loves a widow lady, who, being enamoured of
 another, causes him to spend a winter's night awaiting
 her in the snow. He afterwards by a stratagem
 causes her to stand for a whole day in July, naked
 upon a tower, exposed to the flies, the gadflies, and
 the sun.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08070002" />Over the woes of poor Calandrino the
	ladies laughed not a little,
	and had laughed yet more, but that it irked them that those that had
	robbed him of the pig should also take from him the capons. However, the story being
	ended, the queen bade Pampinea give them
	hers: and thus forthwith Pampinea began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08070003" />Dearest ladies, it happens oftentimes that the artful scorner
      meets his match; wherefore
      'tis only little wits that delight to scorn. In a series of stories we have heard
      tell of tricks played without aught in the way of reprisals
      following: by mine I purpose in some degree to excite your compassion
      for a gentlewoman of our city (albeit the retribution that
      came upon her was but just) whose flout was returned in the like
      sort, and to such effect that she well-nigh died thereof. The which
      to hear will not be unprofitable to you, for thereby you will learn to
      be more careful how you flout others, and therein you will do very
      wisely.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08070004" />'Tis not many years since there dwelt at Florence a lady young
 and fair, and of a high spirit, as also of right gentle lineage, and
 tolerably well endowed with temporal goods. Now Elena--such
 was the lady's name--being left a widow, was minded never to marry
 again, being enamoured of a handsome young gallant of her own
 choosing, with whom she, recking nought of any other lover, did, by
 <pb n="210" />the help of a maid in whom she placed much trust, not seldom speed
 the time gaily and with marvellous delight. <milestone id="p08070005" />Meanwhile it so befell
 that a young nobleman of our city, Rinieri by name, who had spent
 much time in study at Paris, not that he might thereafter sell his
 knowledge by retail, but that he might learn the reasons and causes
 of things, which accomplishment shews to most excellent advantage
 in a gentleman, returned to Florence, and there lived as a citizen in
 no small honour with his fellows, both by reason of his rank and of
 his learning. <milestone id="p08070006" />But as it is often the case that those who are most
 versed in deep matters are the soonest mastered by Love, so was it
 with Rinieri. For at a festal gathering, to which one day he went,
 there appeared before his eyes this Elena, of whom we spoke, clad in
 black, as is the wont of our Florentine widows, and shewing to his
 mind so much fairer and more debonair than any other woman that
 he had ever seen, that happy indeed he deemed the man might call
 himself, to whom God in His goodness should grant the right to hold
 her naked in his arms. <milestone id="p08070007" />So now and again he eyed her stealthily, and
 knowing that boons goodly and precious are not to be gotten without
 trouble, he made up his mind to study and labour with all assiduity
 how best to please her, that so he might win her love, and thereby
 the enjoyment of her.</p><p><milestone id="p08070008" />The young gentlewoman was not used to keep her eyes bent
 ever towards the infernal regions; but, rating herself at no less, if not
 more, than her deserts, she was dexterous to move them to and fro,
 and thus busily scanning her company, soon detected the men who
 regarded her with pleasure. By which means having discovered
 Rinieri's passion, she inly laughed, and said: 'Twill turn out that
 'twas not for nothing that I came here to-day, for, if I mistake not,
 I have caught a gander by the bill. <milestone id="p08070009" />So she gave him an occasional
 sidelong glance, and sought as best she might to make him believe
 that she was not indifferent to him, deeming that the more men she
 might captivate by her charms, the higher those charms would be
 rated, and most especially by him whom she had made lord of them
 and her love. <milestone id="p08070010" />The erudite scholar bade adieu to philosophical meditation,
 for the lady entirely engrossed his mind; and, having discovered
 her house, he, thinking to please her, found divers pretexts
 for frequently passing by it. <milestone id="p08070011" />Whereon the lady, her vanity flattered
 for the reason aforesaid, plumed herself not a little, and shewed herself
 <pb n="211" />pleased to see him. Thus encouraged, the scholar found means to
 make friends with her maid, to whom he discovered his love, praying
 her to do her endeavour with her mistress, that he might have her
 favour. <milestone id="p08070012" />The maid was profuse of promises, and gave her mistress his
 message, which she no sooner heard, than she was convulsed with
 laughter, and replied: <q direct="unspecified">He brought sense enough hither from
 Paris: knowest thou where he has since been to lose it? Go to,
 now; let us give him that which he seeks. Tell him, when he next
 speaks to you of the matter, that I love him vastly more than he
 loves me, but that I must have regard to my reputation, so that I
 may be able to hold my head up among other ladies; which, if he is
 really the wise man they say, will cause him to affect me much more.</q>
 <milestone id="p08070013" />Ah! poor woman! poor woman! she little knew, my ladies, how
 rash it is to try conclusions with scholars.</p><p><milestone id="p08070014" />The maid found the scholar, and did her mistress's errand. 
<milestone id="p08070015" />The
 scholar, overjoyed, proceeded to urge his suit with more ardour, to
 indite letters, and send presents. The lady received all that he sent
 her, but vouchsafed no answers save such as were couched in general
 terms: and on this wise she kept him dangling a long while. 
<milestone id="p08070016" />At last,
 having disclosed the whole affair to her lover, who evinced some
 resentment and jealousy, she, to convince him that his suspicions
 were groundless, and for that she was much importuned by the
 scholar, sent word to him by her maid, that never since he had
 assured her of his love, had occasion served her to do him pleasure,
 but that next Christmastide she hoped to be with him; <milestone id="p08070017" />wherefore, if
 he were minded to await her in the courtyard of her house on the
 night of the day next following the feast, she would meet him there as
 soon as she could. <milestone id="p08070018" />Elated as ne'er another, the scholar hied him at
 the appointed time to the lady's house, and being ushered into a courtyard
 by the maid, who forthwith turned the key upon him, addressed
 himself there to await the lady's coming.</p><p><milestone id="p08070019" />Now the lady's lover, by her appointment, was with her that
 evening; and, when they had gaily supped, she told him what she had
 in hand that night, adding: <q direct="unspecified">And so thou wilt be able to gauge the
 love which I have borne and bear this scholar, whom thou hast
 foolishly regarded as a rival.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070020" />The lover heard the lady's words with
 no small delight, and waited in eager expectancy to see her make
 them good. The scholar, hanging about there in the courtyard,
 <pb n="212" />began to find it somewhat chillier than he would have liked, for it
 had snowed hard all day long, so that the snow lay everywhere
 thick on the ground; however, he bore it patiently, expecting to be
 recompensed by and by. 
<milestone id="p08070021" />After a while the lady said to her lover:
 <q direct="unspecified">Go we to the chamber and take a peep through a lattice at him of
 whom thou art turned jealous, and mark what he does, and how he
 will answer the maid, whom I have bidden go speak with him.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070022" />So
 the pair hied them to a lattice, wherethrough they could see without
 being seen, and heard the maid call from another lattice to the
 scholar, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Rinieri, my lady is distressed as never woman
 was, for that one of her brothers is come here to-night, and after
 talking a long while with her, must needs sup with her, and is not
 yet gone, but, I think, he will soon be off; and that is the reason
 why she has not been able to come to thee, but she will come soon
 now. She trusts it does not irk thee to wait so long.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070023" />Whereto the
 scholar, supposing that 'twas true, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Tell my lady to
 give herself no anxiety on my account, until she can conveniently
 come to me, but to do so as soon as she may.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070024" />Whereupon the maid
 withdrew from the window, and went to bed; while the lady said
 to her lover: <q direct="unspecified">Now, what sayst thou? Thinkst thou that, if I had
 that regard for him, which thou fearest, I would suffer him to tarry
 below there to get frozen?</q> Which said, the lady and her now
 partly reassured lover got them to bed, where for a great while they
 disported them right gamesomely, laughing together and making
 merry over the luckless scholar.</p><p><milestone id="p08070025" />The scholar, meanwhile, paced up and down the courtyard to
 keep himself warm, nor indeed had he where to sit, or take shelter:
 in this plight he bestowed many a curse upon the lady's brother for
 his long tarrying, and never a sound did he hear but he thought that
 'twas the lady opening the door. But vain indeed were his hopes:
 <milestone id="p08070026" />the lady, having solaced herself with her lover until hard upon midnight,
 then said to him: <q direct="unspecified">How ratest thou our scholar, my soul?
 whether is the greater his wit, or the love I bear him, thinkst thou?
 Will the cold, that, of my ordaining, he now suffers, banish from thy
 breast the suspicion which my light words the other day implanted
 there?</q> 
<milestone id="p08070027" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, indeed, heart of my body!</q> replied the lover, <q direct="unspecified">well
 wot I now that even as thou art to me, my weal, my consolation,
 my bliss, so am I to thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070028" /><q direct="unspecified">So:</q> quoth the lady, <q direct="unspecified">then I must
 <pb n="213" />have full a thousand kisses from thee, to prove that thou sayst
 sooth.</q>
 The lover's answer was to strain her to his heart, and give her not
 merely a thousand but a hundred thousand kisses. 
<milestone id="p08070029" />In such converse
 they dallied a while longer, and then: <q direct="unspecified">Get we up, now,</q> quoth
 the lady, <q direct="unspecified">that we may go see if 'tis quite spent, that fire, with
 which, as he wrote to me daily, this new lover of mine used to
 burn.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070030" />So up they got and hied them to the lattice which they had
 used before, and peering out into the courtyard, saw the scholar
 dancing a hornpipe to the music that his own teeth made, a chattering
 for extremity of cold; nor had they ever seen it footed so nimbly
 and at such a pace. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">How sayst thou, sweet my
 hope?</q> quoth the lady. <q direct="unspecified">Know I not how to make men dance
 without the aid of either trumpet or cornemuse?</q> 
<milestone id="p08070031" /><q direct="unspecified">Indeed thou
 dost, my heart's delight,</q> replied the lover. <milestone id="p08070032" />Quoth then the lady:
 <q direct="unspecified">I have a mind that we go down to the door. Thou wilt keep
 quiet, and I will speak to him, and we shall hear what he says,
 which, peradventure, we shall find no less diverting than the sight
 of him.</q></p><p>So they stole softly out of the chamber and down to the door,
 which leaving fast closed, the lady set her lips to a little hole that
 was there, and with a low voice called the scholar, <milestone id="p08070033" />who, hearing her
 call him, praised God, making too sure that he was to be admitted,
 and being come to the door, said: <q direct="unspecified">Here am I, Madam; open for
 God's sake; let me in, for I die of cold.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070034" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh! ay,</q> replied the
 lady, <q direct="unspecified">I know thou hast a chill, and of course, there being a little
 snow about, 'tis mighty cold; but well I wot the nights are colder
 far at Paris. I cannot let thee in as yet, because my accursed
 brother, that came to sup here this evening, is still with me; but he
 will soon take himself off, and then I will let thee in without a
 moment's delay. I have but now with no small difficulty given him
 the slip, to come and give thee heart that the waiting irk thee not.</q>
 <milestone id="p08070035" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay but, Madam,</q> replied the scholar, <q direct="unspecified">for the love of God, I
 entreat you, let me in, that I may have a roof over my head, because
 for some time past there has been never so thick a fall of snow, and
 'tis yet snowing; and then I will wait as long as you please.</q>
<milestone id="p08070036" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas! sweet my love,</q> quoth the lady, <q direct="unspecified">that I may not, for this
 door makes such a din, when one opens it, that my brother would be
 sure to hear, were I to let thee in; but I will go tell him to get him
 <pb n="214" />gone, and so come back and admit thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070037" /><q direct="unspecified">Go at once, then,</q>
 returned the scholar, <q direct="unspecified">and prithee, see that a good fire be kindled,
 that, when I get in, I may warm myself, for I am now so chilled
 through and through that I have scarce any feeling left.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070038" /><q direct="unspecified">That
 can scarce be,</q> rejoined the lady, <q direct="unspecified">if it be true, what thou hast so
 protested in thy letters, that thou art all afire for love of me: 'tis
 plain to me now that thou didst but mock me. I now take my leave
 of thee: wait and be of good cheer.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070039" />So the lady and her lover, who, to his immense delight, had heard
 all that passed, betook them to bed; however, little sleep had they
 that night, but spent the best part of it in disporting themselves and
 making merry over the unfortunate scholar, <milestone id="p08070040" />who, his teeth now
 chattering to such a tune that he seemed to have been metamorphosed
 into a stork, perceived that he had been befooled, and after making
 divers fruitless attempts to open the door and seeking means of egress
 to no better purpose, paced to and fro like a lion, cursing the villainous
 weather, the long night, his simplicity, and the perversity of the
 lady, <milestone id="p08070041" />against whom (the vehemence of his wrath suddenly converting
 the love he had so long borne her to bitter and remorseless enmity)
 he now plotted within himself divers and grand schemes of revenge,
 on which he was far more bent than ever he had been on forgathering
 with her.</p><p><milestone id="p08070042" />Slowly the night wore away, and with the first streaks of dawn
 the maid, by her mistress's direction, came down, opened the door of
 the courtyard, and putting on a compassionate air, greeted Rinieri
 with: <q direct="unspecified">Foul fall him that came here yestereve; he has afflicted us
 with his presence all night long, and has kept thee a freezing out
 here: but harkye, take it not amiss; that which might not be
 to-night shall be another time: well wot I that nought could have
 befallen that my lady could so ill brook.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070043" />For all his wrath, the
 scholar, witting, like the wise man he was, that menaces serve but to
 put the menaced on his guard, kept pent within his breast that which
 unbridled resentment would have uttered, and said quietly, and
 without betraying the least trace of anger: 
<milestone id="p08070044" /><q direct="unspecified">In truth 'twas the
 worst night I ever spent, but I understood quite well that the lady
 was in no wise to blame, for that she herself, being moved to pity of
 me, came down here to make her excuses, and to comfort me; and,
 as thou sayst, what has not been to-night will be another time:
 <pb n="215" />wherefore commend me to her, and so, adieu!</q> 
<milestone id="p08070045" />Then, well-nigh
 paralysed for cold, he got him, as best he might, home, where, weary
 and fit to die for drowsiness, he threw himself on his bed, and fell
 into a deep sleep, from which he awoke to find that he had all but
 lost the use of his arms and legs. He therefore sent for some
 physicians, and having told them what a chill he had gotten, caused
 them have a care to his health. <milestone id="p08070046" />But, though they treated him with
 active and most drastic remedies, it cost them some time and no little
 trouble to restore to the cramped muscles their wonted pliancy, and,
 indeed, but for his youth and the milder weather that was at hand,
 'twould have gone very hard with him.</p><p><milestone id="p08070047" />However, recover he did his health and lustihood, and nursing
 his enmity, feigned to be vastly more enamoured of his widow than
 ever before. <milestone id="p08070048" />And so it was that after a while Fortune furnished him
 with an opportunity of satisfying his resentment, for the gallant of
 whom the widow was enamoured, utterly regardless of the love she
 bore him, grew enamoured of another lady, and was minded no more
 to pleasure the widow in aught either by word or by deed; wherefore
 she now pined in tears and bitterness of spirit. <milestone id="p08070049" />However, her
 maid, who commiserated her not a little, and knew not how to dispel
 the dumps that the loss of her lover had caused her, espying the
 scholar pass along the street, as he had been wont, conceived the
 silly idea that the lady's lover might be induced to return to his old
 love by some practice of a necromantic order, wherein she doubted
 not that the scholar must be a thorough adept; which idea she
 imparted to her mistress. <milestone id="p08070050" />The lady, being none too well furnished
 with sense, never thinking that, if the scholar had been an adept in
 necromancy, he would have made use of it in his own behoof, gave
 heed to what her maid said, and forthwith bade her learn of the
 scholar whether he would place his skill at her service, and assure
 him that, if he so did, she, in guerdon thereof, would do his pleasure.
 <milestone id="p08070051" />The maid did her mistress's errand well and faithfully. The scholar
 no sooner heard the message, than he said to himself: Praised be
 Thy name, O God, that the time is now come, when with Thy
 help I may be avenged upon this wicked woman of the wrong she
 did me in requital of the great love I bore her. <milestone id="p08070052" />Then, turning to
 the maid, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Tell my lady to set her mind at ease touching
 this matter; for that, were her lover in India, I would forthwith
 <pb n="216" />bring him hither to crave her pardon of that wherein he has offended
 her. As to the course she should take in the matter, I tarry but her
 pleasure to make it known to her, when and where she may think
 fit: tell her so, and bid her from me to be of good cheer.</q> The
 maid carried his answer to her mistress, and arranged that they should
 meet in the church of Santa Lucia of Prato. <milestone id="p08070053" />Thither accordingly
 they came, the lady and the scholar, and conversed apart, and the
 lady, quite oblivious of the ill-usage by which she had well-nigh done
 him to death, opened all her mind to him, and besought him, if he had
 any regard to her welfare, to aid her to the attainment of her desire.
 <milestone id="p08070054" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied the scholar, <q direct="unspecified">true it is that among other lore
 that I acquired at Paris was this of necromancy, whereof, indeed, I
 know all that may be known; but, as 'tis in the last degree displeasing
 to God, I had sworn never to practise it either for my own or for any
 other's behoof. <milestone id="p08070055" />'Tis also true that the love I bear you is such that I
 know not how to refuse you aught that you would have me do for
 you; and so, were this single essay enough to consign me to hell,
 I would adventure it to pleasure you. <milestone id="p08070056" />But I mind me that 'tis a
 matter scarce so easy of performance as, perchance, you suppose,
 most especially when a woman would fain recover the love of a man,
 or a man that of a woman, for then it must be done by the postulant
 in proper person, and at night, and in lonely places, and unattended,
 so that it needs a stout heart; nor know I whether you are disposed
 to comply with these conditions.</q> <milestone id="p08070057" />The lady, too enamoured to be
 discreet, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">So shrewdly does Love goad me, that
 there is nought I would not do to bring him back to me who wrongfully
 has deserted me; but tell me, prithee, wherein it is that I have
 need of this stout heart.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070058" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> returned the despiteful scholar,
 <q direct="unspecified">'twill be my part to fashion in tin an image of him you would fain
 lure back to you: and when I have sent you the image, 'twill be for
 you, when the moon is well on the wane, to dip yourself, being stark
 naked, and the image, seven times in a flowing stream, and this you
 must do quite alone about the hour of first sleep, <milestone id="p08070059" />and afterwards, still
 naked, you must get you upon some tree or some deserted house, and
 facing the North, with the image in your hand, say certain words
 that I shall give you in writing seven times; which, when you have
 done, there will come to you two damsels, the fairest you ever saw,
 who will greet you graciously, and ask of you what you would fain
 <pb n="217" />have; <milestone id="p08070060" />to whom you will disclose frankly and fully all that you
 crave; and see to it that you make no mistake in the name; and
 when you have said all, they will depart, and you may then descend
 and return to the spot where you left your clothes, and resume them,
 and go home. <milestone id="p08070061" />And rest assured, that before the ensuing midnight
 your lover will come to you in tears, and crave your pardon and
 mercy, and that thenceforth he will never again desert you for any
 other woman.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070062" />The lady gave entire credence to the scholar's words, and deeming
 her lover as good as in her arms again, recovered half her wonted
 spirits: wherefore: <q direct="unspecified">Make no doubt,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">that I shall do
 as thou biddest; and indeed I am most favoured by circumstance;
 for in upper Val d'Arno I have an estate adjoining the river, and 'tis
 now July, so that to bathe will be delightful. <milestone id="p08070063" />Ay, and now I mind
 me that at no great distance from the river there is a little tower,
 which is deserted, save that now and again the shepherds will get
 them up by the chestnut-wood ladder to the roof, thence to look out
 for their strayed sheep; 'tis a place lonely indeed, and quite out of
 ken; and when I have clomb it, as climb it I will, I doubt not 'twill
 be the best place in all the world to give effect to your
 instructions.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070064" />Well pleased to be certified of the lady's intention, the scholar,
 to whom her estate and the tower were very well known, made
 answer: <q direct="unspecified">I was never in those parts, Madam, and therefore know
 neither your estate nor the tower, but, if 'tis as you say, 'twill certainly
 be the best place in the world for your purpose. So, when
 time shall serve, I will send you the image and the orison. But I
 pray you, when you shall have your heart's desire, and know that
 I have done you good service, do not forget me, but keep your
 promise to me.</q> <q direct="unspecified">That will I without fail,</q> quoth the lady; and
 so she bade him farewell, and went home. <milestone id="p08070065" />The scholar, gleefully
 anticipating the success of his enterprise, fashioned an image, and
 inscribed it with certain magical signs, and wrote some gibberish
 by way of orison, which in due time he sent to the lady, bidding her
 the very next night do as he had prescribed: and thereupon he
 hied him privily with one of his servants to the house of a friend
 hard by the tower, there to carry his purpose into effect. <milestone id="p08070066" />The lady,
 on her part, set out with her maid, and betook her to her estate, and,
 night being come, sent the maid to bed, as if she were minded to go
 <pb n="218" />to rest herself; and about the hour of first sleep stole out of the
 house and down to the tower, beside the Arno; and when, having
 carefully looked about her, she was satisfied that never a soul was to
 be seen or heard, she took off her clothes and hid them under a bush;
 then, with the image in her hand, she dipped herself seven times in
 the river; which done, she hied her with the image to the tower.
 <milestone id="p08070067" />The scholar, having at nightfall couched himself with his servant
 among the willows and other trees that fringed the bank, marked
 all that she did, and how, as she passed by him, the whiteness of her
 flesh dispelled the shades of night, and scanning attentively her
 bosom and every other part of her body, and finding them very fair,
 felt, as he bethought him what would shortly befall them, some pity
 of her; <milestone id="p08070068" />while, on the other hand, he was suddenly assailed by the
 solicitations of the flesh which caused that to stand which had been
 inert, and prompted him to sally forth of his ambush and take her by
 force, and have his pleasure of her. And, what with his compassion
 and passion, he was like to be worsted; <milestone id="p08070069" />but then, as he bethought
 him who he was, and what a grievous wrong had been done him,
 and for what cause, and by whom, his wrath, thus rekindled, got the
 better of the other affections, so that he swerved not from his resolve,
 but suffered her to go her way.</p><p><milestone id="p08070070" />The lady ascended the tower, and standing with her face to the
 North, began to recite the scholar's orison, while he, having stolen
 into the tower but a little behind her, cautiously shifted the ladder
 that led up to the roof on which the lady stood, and waited to
 observe what she would say and do. <milestone id="p08070071" />Seven times the lady said the
 orison, and then awaited the appearance of the two damsels; and so
 long had she to wait--not to mention that the night was a good deal
 cooler than she would have liked--that she saw day break; whereupon,
 disconcerted that it had not fallen out as the scholar had
 promised, she said to herself: I misdoubt me he was minded to
 give me such a night as I gave him; but if such was his intent, he
 is but maladroit in his revenge, for this night is not as long by a third
 as his was, besides which, the cold is of another quality. <milestone id="p08070072" />And that
 day might not overtake her there, she began to think of descending,
 but, finding that the ladder was removed, <milestone id="p08070073" />she felt as if the world had
 come to nought beneath her feet, her senses reeled, and she fell in a
 swoon upon the floor of the roof. When she came to herself, she
 <pb n="219" />burst into tears and piteous lamentations, and witting now very well
 that 'twas the doing of the scholar, she began to repent her that she
 had first offended him, and then trusted him unduly, having such
 good cause to reckon upon his enmity; in which frame she abode
 long time. <milestone id="p08070074" />Then, searching if haply she might find some means of
 descent, and finding none, she fell a weeping again, and bitterly to
 herself she said: Alas for thee, wretched woman! what will thy
 brothers, thy kinsmen, thy neighbours, nay, what will all Florence
 say of thee, when 'tis known that thou hast been found here naked?
 <milestone id="p08070075" />Thy honour, hitherto unsuspect, will be known to have been but
 a shew, and shouldst thou seek thy defence in lying excuses, if any
 such may be fashioned, the accursed scholar, who knows all thy
 doings, will not suffer it. Ah! poor wretch! that at one and the
 same time hast lost thy too dearly cherished gallant and thine own
 honour! And therewith she was taken with such a transport of
 grief, that she was like to cast herself from the tower to the ground.
 <milestone id="p08070076" />Then, bethinking her that if she might espy some lad making towards
 the tower with his sheep, she might send him for her maid, for the
 sun was now risen, she approached one of the parapets of the tower,
 and looked out, and so it befell that the scholar, awakening from a
 slumber, in which he had lain a while at the foot of a bush, espied
 her, and she him. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Good-day, Madam,</q> quoth he:
 <q direct="unspecified">are the damsels yet come?</q> <milestone id="p08070077" />The lady saw and heard him not
 without bursting afresh into a flood of tears, and besought him to
 come into the tower, that she might speak with him: a request which
 the scholar very courteously granted. <milestone id="p08070078" />The lady then threw herself
 prone on the floor of the roof; and, only her head being visible
 through the aperture, thus through her sobs she spoke: <q direct="unspecified">Verily,
 Rinieri, if I gave thee a bad night, thou art well avenged on me, for,
 though it be July, meseemed I was sore a cold last night, standing
 here with never a thread upon me, and, besides, I have so bitterly
 bewept both the trick I played thee and my own folly in trusting
 thee, that I marvel that I have still eyes in my head. <milestone id="p08070079" />Wherefore
 I implore thee, not for love of me, whom thou hast no cause to love,
 but for the respect thou hast for thyself as a gentleman, that thou let
 that which thou hast already done suffice thee to avenge the wrong
 I did thee, and bring me my clothes, that I may be able to get me
 down from here, and spare to take from me that which, however
 <pb n="220" />thou mightst hereafter wish, thou couldst not restore to me, to wit,
 my honour; whereas, if I deprived thee of that one night with me,
 'tis in my power to give thee many another night in recompense
 thereof, and thou hast but to choose thine own times. <milestone id="p08070080" />Let this,
 then, suffice, and like a worthy gentleman be satisfied to have taken
 thy revenge, and to have let me know it: put not forth thy might
 against a woman: 'tis no glory to the eagle to have vanquished a
 dove; wherefore for God's and thine own honour's sake have mercy
 on me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070081" />The scholar, albeit his haughty spirit still brooded on her evil
 entreatment of him, yet saw her not weep and supplicate without
 a certain compunction mingling with his exultation; but vengeance
 he had desired above all things, to have wreaked it was indeed sweet,
 and albeit his humanity prompted him to have compassion on the
 hapless woman, yet it availed not to subdue the fierceness of his
 resentment; wherefore thus he made answer: 
<milestone id="p08070082" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam Elena,
 had my prayers (albeit art I had none to mingle with them tears
 and honeyed words as thou dost with thine) inclined thee that night,
 when I stood perishing with cold amid the snow that filled thy
 courtyard, to accord me the very least shelter, 'twere but a light
 matter for me to hearken now to thine; <milestone id="p08070083" />but, if thou art now so
 much more careful of thy honour than thou wast wont to be, and
 it irks thee to tarry there naked, address thy prayers to him in whose
 arms it irked thee not naked to pass that night thou mindest thee
 of, albeit thou wist that I with hasty foot was beating time upon
 the snow in thy courtyard to the accompaniment of chattering
 teeth: 'tis he that thou shouldst call to succour thee, to fetch thy
 clothes, to adjust the ladder for thy descent; 'tis he in whom thou
 shouldst labour to inspire this tenderness thou now shewest for thy
 honour, that honour which for his sake thou hast not scrupled to
 jeopardize both now and on a thousand other occasions. <milestone id="p08070084" />Why,
 then, call'st thou not him to come to thy succour? To whom
 pertains it rather than to him? Thou art his. And of whom will
 he have a care, whom will he succour, if not thee? Thou askedst
 him that night, when thou wast wantoning with him, whether
 seemed to him the greater, my folly or the love thou didst bear
 him: call him now, foolish woman, and see if the love thou bearest
 him, and thy wit and his, may avail to deliver thee from my folly.
 <pb n="221" />
<milestone id="p08070085" />'Tis now no longer in thy power to shew me courtesy of that which
 I no more desire, nor yet to refuse it, did I desire it. Reserve thy
 nights for thy lover, if so be thou go hence alive. Be they all thine
 and his. One of them was more than I cared for; 'tis enough for
 me to have been flouted once. <milestone id="p08070086" />Ay, and by thy cunning of speech
 thou strivest might and main to conciliate my good-will, calling me
 worthy gentleman, by which insinuation thou wouldst fain induce
 me magnanimously to desist from further chastisement of thy baseness.
 But thy cajoleries shall not now cloud the eyes of my mind,
 as did once thy false promises. I know myself, and better now for
 thy one night's instruction than for all the time I spent at Paris.
 <milestone id="p08070087" />But, granted that I were disposed to be magnanimous, thou art not
 of those to whom 'tis meet to shew magnanimity. A wild beast
 such as thou, having merited vengeance, can claim no relief
 from suffering save death, though in the case of a human being
 'twould suffice to temper vengeance with mercy, as thou saidst.
 <milestone id="p08070088" />Wherefore I, albeit no eagle, witting thee to be no dove, but a
 venomous serpent, mankind's most ancient enemy, am minded,
 bating no jot of malice or of might, to harry thee to the bitter end:
 natheless this which I do is not properly to be called vengeance but
 rather just retribution; seeing that vengeance should be in excess
 of the offence, and this my chastisement of thee will fall short of
 it; for, <milestone id="p08070089" />were I minded to be avenged on thee, considering what
 account thou madest of my heart and soul, 'twould not suffice me
 to take thy life, no, nor the lives of a hundred others such as thee;
 for I should but slay a vile and base and wicked woman. 
<milestone id="p08070090" />And
 what the Devil art thou more than any other pitiful baggage, that
 I should spare thy little store of beauty, which a few years will
 ruin, covering thy face with wrinkles? And yet 'twas not for
 want of will that thou didst fail to do to death a worthy gentleman,
 as thou but now didst call me, of whom in a single day of his life
 the world may well have more profit than of a hundred thousand
 like thee while the world shall last. <milestone id="p08070091" />Wherefore by this rude
 discipline I will teach thee what it is to flout men of spirit, and
 more especially what it is to flout scholars, that if thou escape with
 thy life thou mayst have good cause ever hereafter to shun such
 folly. <milestone id="p08070092" />But if thou art so fain to make the descent, why cast not
 thyself down, whereby, God helping, thou wouldst at once
 <pb n="222" />break thy neck, be quit of the torment thou endurest, and make
 me the happiest man alive? I have no more to say to thee. 'Twas
 my art and craft thus caused thee climb; be it thine to find the
 way down: thou hadst cunning enough, when thou wast minded
 to flout me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070093" />While the scholar thus spoke, the hapless lady wept incessantly,
 and before he had done, to aggravate her misery, the sun was high
 in the heaven. However, when he was silent, thus she made
 answer: <milestone id="p08070094" /><q direct="unspecified">Ah! ruthless man, if that accursed night has so rankled
 with thee, and thou deemest my fault so grave that neither my youth
 and beauty, nor my bitter tears, nor yet my humble supplications may
 move thee to pity, let this at least move thee, and abate somewhat
 of thy remorseless severity, that 'twas my act alone, in that of late
 I trusted thee, and discovered to thee all my secret, that did open
 the way to compass thy end, and make me cognizant of my guilt,
 seeing that, had I not confided in thee, on no wise mightst thou
 have been avenged on me; which thou wouldst seem so ardently
 to have desired. <milestone id="p08070095" />Turn thee, then, turn thee, I pray thee, from thy
 wrath, and pardon me. So thou wilt pardon me, and get me down
 hence, right gladly will I give up for ever my faithless gallant, and
 thou shalt be my sole lover and lord, albeit thou sayst hard things
 of my beauty, slight and shortlived as thou wouldst have it to be,
 which, however it may compare with others, is, I wot, to be prized,
 if for no other reason, yet for this, that 'tis the admiration
 and solace and delight of young men, and thou art not yet old.
 <milestone id="p08070096" />And albeit I have been harshly treated by thee, yet believe I cannot
 that thou wouldst have me do myself so shamefully to death as to
 cast me down, like some abandoned wretch, before thine eyes, in
 which, unless thou wast then, as thou hast since shewn thyself, a
 liar, I found such favour. <milestone id="p08070097" />Ah! have pity on me for God's and
 mercy's sake! The sun waxes exceeding hot, and having suffered
 not a little by the cold of last night, I now begin to be sorely afflicted
 by the heat.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070098" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> rejoined the scholar, who held her in parley with no
 small delight, <q direct="unspecified">'twas not for any love that thou didst bear me that
 thou trustedst me, but that thou mightst recover that which thou
 hadst lost, for which cause thou meritest but the greater punishment;
 and foolish indeed art thou if thou supposest that such was the sole
 <pb n="223" />means available for my revenge. I had a thousand others, and, while
 I feigned to love thee, <milestone id="p08070099" />I had laid a thousand gins for thy feet, into
 one or other of which in no long time, though this had not occurred,
 thou must needs have fallen, and that too to thy more grievous
 suffering and shame; nor was it to spare thee, but that I might be
 the sooner rejoiced by thy discomfiture that I took my present
 course. <milestone id="p08070100" />And though all other means had failed me, I had still the
 pen, with which I would have written of thee such matters and in
 such a sort, that when thou wist them, as thou shouldst have done,
 thou wouldst have regretted a thousand times that thou hadst ever
 been born. The might of the pen is greater far than they suppose,
 who have not proved it by experience. <milestone id="p08070101" />By God I swear,
 so may He, who has prospered me thus far in this my revenge,
 prosper me to the end! that I would have written of thee things
 that would have so shamed thee in thine own--not to speak of
 others'--sight that thou hadst put out thine eyes that thou mightst
 no more see thyself; wherefore chide not the sea, for that it has
 sent forth a tiny rivulet. <milestone id="p08070102" />For thy love, or whether thou be mine or
 no, nought care I. Be thou still his, whose thou hast been, if thou
 canst. Hate him as I once did, I now love him, by reason of his
 present entreatment of thee. <milestone id="p08070103" />Ye go getting you enamoured, ye
 women, and nought will satisfy you but young gallants, because ye
 mark that their flesh is ruddier, and their beards are blacker, than other
 folk's, and that they carry themselves well, and foot it featly in the
 dance, and joust; but those that are now more mature were even as
 they, and possess a knowledge which they have yet to acquire. And
 therewithal ye deem that they ride better, and cover more miles in a
 day, than men of riper age. <milestone id="p08070104" />Now that they dust the pelisse with
 more vigour I certainly allow, but their seniors, being more experienced,
 know better the places where the fleas lurk; and spare and
 dainty diet is preferable to abundance without savour: moreover
 hard trotting will gall and jade even the youngest, whereas an easy
 pace, though it bring one somewhat later to the inn, at any rate
 brings one thither fresh. <milestone id="p08070105" />Ye discern not, witless creatures that ye
 are, how much of evil this little shew of bravery serves to hide.
 Your young gallant is never content with one woman, but lusts
 after as many as he sets eyes on; nor is there any but he deems
 himself worthy of her: wherefore 'tis not possible that their love
 <pb n="224" />should be lasting, as thou hast but now proved and mayst only too
 truly witness. <milestone id="p08070106" />Moreover to be worshipped, to be caressed by their
 ladies they deem but their due; nor is there aught whereon they
 plume and boast them so proudly as their conquests: which impertinence
 has caused not a few women to surrender to the friars, who
 keep their own counsel. Peradventure thou wilt say that never a
 soul save thy maid and I wist aught of thy loves; but, if so, thou
 hast been misinformed, and if thou so believest, thou dost misbelieve.
 Scarce aught else is talked of either in his quarter or in thine; but
 most often 'tis those most concerned whose ears such matters reach
 last. Moreover, they rob you, these young gallants, whereas the
 others make you presents. <milestone id="p08070107" />So, then, having made a bad choice, be
 thou still his to whom thou hast given thyself, and leave me, whom
 thou didst flout, to another, for I have found a lady of much greater
 charms than thine, and that has understood me better than thou
 didst. <milestone id="p08070108" />And that thou mayst get thee to the other world better
 certified of the desire of my eyes than thou wouldst seem to be here
 by my words, delay no more, but cast thyself down, whereby thy
 soul, taken forthwith, as I doubt not she will be, into the embrace
 of the Devil, may see whether thy headlong fall afflicts mine eyes, or
 no. <milestone id="p08070109" />But, for that I doubt thou meanest not thus to gladden me,
 I bid thee, if thou findest the sun begin to scorch thee, remember the
 cold thou didst cause me to endure, wherewith, by admixture, thou
 mayst readily temper the sun's heat.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08070110" />The hapless lady, seeing that the scholar's words were ever to the
 same ruthless effect, burst afresh into tears, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now,
 since nought that pertains to me may move thee, be thou at least
 moved by the love thou bearest this lady of whom thou speakest, who,
 thou sayst, is wiser than I, and loves thee, and for love of her pardon me,
 and fetch me my clothes, that I may resume them, and get me down
 hence.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070111" />Whereat the scholar fell a laughing, and seeing that 'twas
 not a little past tierce, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now, I know not how
 to deny thee, adjuring me as thou dost by such a lady: tell me, then,
 where thy clothes are, and I will go fetch them, and bring thee
 down.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070112" />The lady, believing him, was somewhat comforted, and
 told him where she had laid her clothes. The scholar then quitted
 the tower, bidding his servant on no account to stir from his post,
 but to keep close by, and, as best he might, bar the tower against all
 <pb n="225" />comers until his return: which said, he betook him to the house of
 his friend, where he breakfasted much at his ease, and thereafter
 went to sleep. 
<milestone id="p08070113" />Left alone upon the tower, the lady, somewhat
 cheered by her fond hope, but still exceeding sorrowful, drew nigh
 to a part of the wall where there was a little shade, and there sate
 down to wait. And now lost in most melancholy brooding, now
 dissolved in tears, now plunged in despair of ever seeing the scholar
 return with her clothes, but never more than a brief while in any one
 mood, spent with grief and the night's vigil, she by and by fell asleep.
 <milestone id="p08070114" />The sun was now in the zenith, and smote with extreme fervour
 full and unmitigated upon her tender and delicate frame, and upon
 her bare head, insomuch that his rays did not only scorch but bit by
 bit excoriate every part of her flesh that was exposed to them, and so
 shrewdly burn her that, albeit she was in a deep sleep, the pain
 awoke her. <milestone id="p08070115" />And as by reason thereof she writhed a little, she felt
 the scorched skin part in sunder and shed itself, as will happen when
 one tugs at a parchment that has been singed by the fire, while her
 head ached so sore that it seemed like to split, and no wonder. <milestone id="p08070116" />Nor
 might she find place either to lie or to stand on the floor of the roof,
 but ever went to and fro, weeping. <milestone id="p08070117" />Besides which there stirred not
 the least breath of wind, and flies and gadflies did swarm in prodigious
 quantity, which, settling upon her excoriate flesh, stung her so shrewdly
 that 'twas as if she received so many stabs with a javelin, and she was
 ever restlessly feeling her sores with her hands, and cursing herself,
 her life, her lover, and the scholar.</p><p><milestone id="p08070118" />Thus by the exorbitant heat of the sun, by the flies and gadflies,
 harassed, goaded, and lacerated, tormented also by hunger, and yet
 more by thirst, and thereto by a thousand distressful thoughts, she
 planted herself erect on her feet, and looked about her, if haply she
 might see or hear any one, with intent, come what might, to call
 to him and crave his succour. But even this hostile Fortune had
 disallowed her. <milestone id="p08070119" />The husbandmen were all gone from the fields by
 reason of the heat, and indeed there had come none to work that
 day in the neighbourhood of the tower, for that all were employed in
 threshing their corn beside their cottages: wherefore she heard but
 the cicalas, while Arno, tantalizing her with the sight of his waters,
 increased rather than diminished her thirst. Ay, and in like manner,
 wherever she espied a copse, or a patch of shade, or a house, 'twas a
 <pb n="226" />torment to her, for the longing she had for it. 
<milestone id="p08070120" />What more is to be
 said of this hapless woman? Only this: that what with the heat of
 the sun above and the floor beneath her, and the scarification of her
 flesh in every part by the flies and gadflies, that flesh, which in the
 night had dispelled the gloom by its whiteness, was now become red
 as madder, and so besprent with clots of blood, that whoso had seen
 her would have deemed her the most hideous object in the world.</p><p><milestone id="p08070121" />Thus resourceless and hopeless, she passed the long hours, expecting
 death rather than aught else, until half none was come and gone;
 when, his siesta ended, the scholar bethought him of his lady, and
 being minded to see how she fared, hied him back to the tower, and
 sent his servant away to break his fast. As soon as the lady espied
 him, she came, spent and crushed by her sore affliction, to the aperture,
 and thus addressed him: 
<milestone id="p08070122" /><q direct="unspecified">Rinieri, the cup of thy vengeance
 is full to overflowing: for if I gave thee a night of freezing in my
 courtyard, thou hast given me upon this tower a day of scorching,
 nay, of burning, and therewithal of perishing of hunger and thirst:
 wherefore, by God I entreat thee to come up hither, and as my heart
 fails me to take my life, take it thou, for 'tis death I desire of all
 things, such and so grievous is my suffering. 
<milestone id="p08070123" />But if this grace thou
 wilt not grant, at least bring me a cup of water wherewith to lave
 my mouth, for which my tears do not suffice, so parched and torrid is
 it within.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070124" />Well wist the scholar by her voice how spent she was;
 he also saw a part of her body burned through and through by the
 sun; whereby, and by reason of the lowliness of her entreaties, he
 felt some little pity for her; but all the same he made answer:
 <milestone id="p08070125" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, wicked woman, 'tis not by my hands thou shalt die; thou
 canst die by thine own whenever thou art so minded; and to temper
 thy heat thou shalt have just as much water from me as I had fire
 from thee to mitigate my cold. <milestone id="p08070126" />I only regret that for the cure of
 my chill the physicians were fain to use foul-smelling muck, whereas
 thy burns can be treated with fragrant rose-water; and that, whereas
 I was like to lose my muscles and the use of my limbs, thou, for all
 thy excoriation by the heat, wilt yet be fair again, like a snake that
 has sloughed off the old skin.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070127" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas! woe's me!</q> replied the
 lady, <q direct="unspecified">for charms acquired at such a cost, God grant them to those
 that hate me. But thou, most fell of all wild beasts, how hast thou
 borne thus to torture me? What more had I to expect of thee or
 <pb n="227" />any other, had I done all thy kith and kin to death with direst
 torments? <milestone id="p08070128" />Verily, I know not what more cruel suffering thou
 couldst have inflicted on a traitor that had put a whole city to the
 slaughter than this which thou hast allotted to me, to be thus roasted,
 and devoured of the flies, and therewithal to refuse me even a cup of
 water, though the very murderers condemned to death by the law,
 as they go to execution, not seldom are allowed wine to drink, so they
 but ask it. 
<milestone id="p08070129" />Lo now, I see that thou art inexorable in thy ruthlessness,
 and on no wise to be moved by my suffering: wherefore with
 resignation I will compose me to await death, that God may have
 mercy on my soul. And may this that thou doest escape not the
 searching glance of His just eyes.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070130" />Which said, she dragged herself,
 sore suffering, toward the middle of the floor, despairing of ever
 escaping from her fiery torment, besides which, not once only, but a
 thousand times she thought to choke for thirst, and ever she wept
 bitterly and bewailed her evil fate. 
<milestone id="p08070131" />But at length the day wore to
 vespers, and the scholar, being sated with his revenge, caused his
 servant to take her clothes and wrap them in his cloak, and hied him
 with the servant to the hapless lady's house, where, finding her maid
 sitting disconsolate and woebegone and resourceless at the door:
 <q direct="unspecified">Good woman,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what has befallen thy mistress?</q>
 <milestone id="p08070132" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, I know not,</q> replied the maid. <q direct="unspecified">I looked to find
 her this morning abed, for methought she went to bed last night,
 but neither there nor anywhere else could I find her, nor know I
 what is become of her; wherefore exceeding great is my distress;
 but have you, Sir, nought to say of the matter?</q> 
<milestone id="p08070133" /><q direct="unspecified">Only this,</q>
 returned the scholar, <q direct="unspecified">that I would I had had thee with her there
 where I have had her, that I might have requited thee of thy offence,
 even as I have requited her of hers. But be assured that thou shalt
 not escape my hands, until thou hast from me such wage of thy
 labour that thou shalt never flout man more, but thou shalt mind
 thee of me.</q> Then, turning to his servant, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Give her
 these clothes, and tell her that she may go bring her mistress away,
 if she will.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070134" />The servant did his bidding; and the maid, what
 with the message and her recognition of the clothes, was mightily
 afraid, lest they had slain the lady, and scarce suppressing a shriek,
 took the clothes, and, bursting into tears, set off, as soon as the
 scholar was gone, at a run for the tower.</p><pb n="228" /><p><milestone id="p08070135" />Now one of the lady's husbandmen had had the misfortune to
 lose two of his hogs that day, and, seeking them, came to the tower
 not long after the scholar had gone thence, and peering about in all
 quarters, if haply he might have sight of his hogs, heard the woeful
 lamentation that the hapless lady made, and got him up into the
 tower, and called out as loud as he might: <q direct="unspecified">Who wails up there?</q>
 <milestone id="p08070136" />The lady recognized her husbandman's voice, and called him by
 name, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Prithee, go fetch my maid, and cause her come
 up hither to me.</q> <milestone id="p08070137" />The husbandman, knowing her by her voice,
 replied: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! Madam, who set you there? Your maid has
 been seeking you all day long: but who would ever have supposed
 that you were there?</q> 
<milestone id="p08070138" />Whereupon he took the props of the ladder,
 and set them in position, and proceeded to secure the rounds to
 them with withies. Thus engaged he was found by the maid, who,
 as she entered the tower, beat her face and breast, and unable longer
 to keep silence, cried out: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, sweet my lady, where are you?</q>
 <milestone id="p08070139" />Whereto the lady made answer as loud as she might: <q direct="unspecified">O my sister,
 here above am I, weep not, but fetch me my clothes forthwith.</q> 
<milestone id="p08070140" />Well-nigh
 restored to heart, to hear her mistress's voice, the maid, assisted
 by the husbandman, ascended the ladder, which he had now all but
 set in order, and gaining the roof, and seeing her lady lie there
 naked, spent and fordone, and liker to a half-burned stump than to a
 human being, she planted her nails in her face and fell a weeping
 over her, as if she were a corpse. 
<milestone id="p08070141" />However, the lady bade her for
 God's sake be silent, and help her to dress, and having learned from
 her that none knew where she had been, save those that had brought
 her her clothes and the husbandman that was there present, was
 somewhat consoled, and besought her for God's sake to say nought
 of the matter to any. 
<milestone id="p08070142" />Thus long time they conversed, and then
 the husbandman took the lady on his shoulders, for walk she could
 not, and bore her safely out of the tower. The unfortunate maid,
 following after with somewhat less caution, slipped, and falling from
 the ladder to the ground, broke her thigh, and roared for pain like
 any lion. 
<milestone id="p08070143" />So the husbandman set the lady down upon a grassy mead,
 while he went to see what had befallen the maid, whom, finding her
 thigh broken, he brought, and laid beside the lady: who, seeing her
 woes completed by this last misfortune, and that she of whom, most
 of all, she had expected succour, was lamed of a thigh, was distressed
 <pb n="229" />beyond measure, and wept again so piteously that not only was the
 husbandman powerless to comfort her, but was himself fain to weep.
 <milestone id="p08070144" />However, as the sun was now low, that they might not be there
 surprised by night, he, with the disconsolate lady's approval, hied him
 home, and called to his aid two of his brothers and his wife, who
 returned with him, bearing a plank, whereon they laid the maid, and
 so they carried her to the lady's house. There, by dint of cold
 water and words of cheer, they restored some heart to the lady,
 whom the husbandman then took upon his shoulders, and bore to her
 chamber. <milestone id="p08070145" />The husbandman's wife fed her with sops of bread, and
 then undressed her, and put her to bed. They also provided the
 means to carry her and the maid to Florence; and so 'twas done.
 <milestone id="p08070146" />There the lady, who was very fertile in artifices, invented an entirely
 fictitious story of what had happened as well in regard of her maid
 as of herself, whereby she persuaded both her brothers and her sisters
 and every one else, that 'twas all due to the enchantments of evil
 spirits. <milestone id="p08070147" />The physicians lost no time, and, albeit the lady's suffering
 and mortification were extreme, for she left more than one skin sticking
 to the sheets, they cured her of a high fever, and certain attendant
 maladies; as also the maid of her fractured thigh. <milestone id="p08070148" />The end of all
 which was that the lady forgot her lover, and having learned discretion,
 was thenceforth careful neither to love nor to flout; and the
 scholar, learning that the maid had broken her thigh, deemed his
 vengeance complete, and was satisfied to say never a word more of
 the affair. <milestone id="p08070149" />Such then were the consequences of her flouts to this
 foolish young woman, who deemed that she might trifle with a
 scholar with the like impunity as with others, not duly understanding
 that they--I say not all, but the more part--know where the Devil
 keeps his tail.<note>I.e. are a match for the Devil himself in
 cunning.</note> Wherefore, my ladies, have a care how you flout
 men, and more especially scholars.</p></div2>