<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d03conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p03970001" />A thousand times or more had Dioneo's story brought the laugh to
 the lips of the honourable ladies, so quaint and curiously entertaining
 found they the fashion of it. And now at its close the queen, seeing the
 term of her sovereignty come, took the laurel wreath from her head,
 and with mien most debonair, set it on the brow of Filostrato,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">We shall soon see whether the wolf will know better
 how to guide the sheep than the sheep have yet succeeded in guiding
 the wolves.</q> 
      <milestone id="p03970002" />Whereat Filostrato said with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">Had I been
 hearkened to, the wolves would have taught the sheep to put the
 Devil in hell even as Rustico taught Alibech. Wherefore call us not
 wolves, seeing that you have not shewn yourselves sheep: however,
 as best I may be able, I will govern the kingdom committed to my
 <pb n="255" />charge.</q> 
<milestone id="p03970003" />Whereupon Neifile took him up: <q direct="unspecified">Hark ye, Filostrato,</q>
 she said, <q direct="unspecified">while you thought to teach us, you might have learnt a
 lesson from us, as did Masetto da Lamporecchio from the nuns, and
 have recovered your speech when the bones had learned to whistle
 without a master.</q><note>I.e. when you were so emaciated that your
 bones made music like a skeleton in the wind.</note>
 <milestone id="p03970004" />Filostrato, perceiving that there was a scythe
 for each of his arrows, gave up jesting, and addressed himself to the
 governance of his kingdom. He called the seneschal, and held him
 strictly to account in every particular; he then judiciously ordered
 all matters as he deemed would be best and most to the satisfaction of
 the company, while his sovereignty should last; and having so done,
 he turned to the ladies, and said: 
<milestone id="p03970005" /><q direct="unspecified">Loving ladies, as my ill luck
 would have it, since I have had wit to tell good from evil, the charms
 of one or other of you have kept me ever a slave to Love: and for
 all I shewed myself humble and obedient and conformable, so far as
 I knew how, to all his ways, my fate has been still the same, to be
 discarded for another, and go ever from bad to worse; and so, I
 suppose, 'twill be with me to the hour of my death. <milestone id="p03970006" />Wherefore I am
 minded that to-morrow our discourse be of no other topic than that
	which is most germane to my condition, to wit, <seg type="topic">of those whose loves
 had a disastrous close</seg>: because mine, I expect, will in the long
 run be most disastrous; nor for other cause was the name, by which
 you address me, given me by one that well knew its signification.</q>
 Which said, he arose, and dismissed them all until supper-time.</p><p><milestone id="p03970007" />So fair and delightsome was the garden that none saw fit to quit
 it, and seek diversion elsewhere. Rather--for the sun now shone
 with a tempered radiance that caused no discomfort--some of the
 ladies gave chase to the kids and conies and other creatures that
 haunted it, and, scampering to and fro among them as they sate,
 had caused them a hundred times, or so, some slight embarrassment.
 <milestone id="p03970008" />Dioneo and Fiammetta fell a singing of Messer Guglielmo
 and the lady of Vergi&#249;.<note>Evidently some version of the tragical
 conte <q direct="unspecified">de la
 Chastelaine de
 Vergi, qui mori por laialment amer son ami.</q> See <q direct="unspecified">Fabliaux et
 Contes,</q>
 ed. Barbazan, iv. 296: and cf. Bandello, Pt. iv. Nov. v, and Heptameron,
 Journ&#233;e vii. Nouvelle lxx.</note>
 Filomena and Pamfilo sat them down to
 a game of chess and, as thus they pursued each their several
 <pb n="256" />diversions, time sped so swiftly that the supper-hour stole upon them
 almost unawares: whereupon they ranged the tables round the
 beautiful fountain, and supped with all glad and festal cheer.</p><p><milestone id="p03970009" />When the tables were removed, Filostrato, being minded to
 follow in the footsteps of his fair predecessors in sway, bade Lauretta
 lead a dance and sing a song. She answered: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, songs of
 others know I none, nor does my memory furnish me with any of
 mine own that seems meet for so gay a company; but, if you will
 be content with what I have, gladly will I give you thereof.</q>
 <milestone id="p03970010" /><q direct="unspecified">Nought of thine,</q> returned the king, <q direct="unspecified">could be other than
 goodly and delectable. Wherefore give us even what thou hast.</q> 
<milestone id="p03970011" />So
 encouraged, Lauretta, with dulcet voice, but manner somewhat
 languishing, raised the ensuing strain, to which the other ladies
 responded:</p><div3 who="lauretta" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p03970012" />
	<l>What dame disconsolate</l>
	<l>May so lament as I,</l>
	<l>That vainly sigh, to Love still dedicate?</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p03970013" />
	<l>He that the heaven and every orb doth move</l>
	<l>Formed me for His delight</l>
	<l>Fair, debonair and gracious, apt for love;</l>
	<l>That here on earth each soaring spirit might</l>
	<l>Have foretaste how, above,</l>
	<l>That beauty shews that standeth in His sight.</l>
	<l>Ah! but dull wit and slight,</l>
	<l>For that it judgeth ill,</l>
	<l>Liketh me not, nay, doth me vilely rate.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p03970014" />
	<l>There was who loved me, and my maiden grace</l>
	<l>Did fondly clip and strain,</l>
	<l>As in his arms, so in his soul's embrace,</l>
	<l>And from mine eyes Love's fire did drink amain,</l>
	<l>And time that glides apace</l>
	<l>In nought but courting me to spend was fain;</l>
	<l>Whom courteous I did deign</l>
	<l>Ev'n as my peer to entreat;</l>
	<l>But am of him bereft! Ah! dolorous fate!</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p03970015" />
	<l>Came to me next a gallant swol'n with pride</l>
	<l>Brave, in his own conceit,</l>
	<pb n="257" />
	<l>And no less noble eke. Whom woe betide</l>
	<l>That he me took, and holds in all unmeet</l>
	<l>Suspicion, jealous-eyed!</l>
	<l>And I, who wot that me the world should greet</l>
	<l>As the predestined sweet</l>
	<l>Of many men, well-nigh</l>
	<l>Despair, to be to one thus subjugate.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p03970016" /><l>Ah! woe is me! cursed be the luckless day,</l>
	<l>When, a new gown to wear,</l>
	<l>I said the fatal ay; for blithe and gay</l>
	<l>In that plain gown I lived, no whit less fair;</l>
	<l>While in this rich array</l>
	<l>A sad and far less honoured life I bear!</l>
	<l>Would I had died, or e'er</l>
	<l>Sounded those notes of joy</l>
	<l>(Ah! dolorous cheer!) my woe to celebrate!</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p03970017" /><l>So list my supplication, lover dear,</l>
	<l>Of whom such joyance I,</l>
	<l>As ne'er another, had. Thou that in clear</l>
	<l>Light of the Maker's presence art, deny</l>
	<l>Not pity to thy fere,</l>
	<l>Who thee may ne'er forget; but let one sigh</l>
	<l>Breathe tidings that on high</l>
	<l>Thou burnest still for me;</l>
	<l>And sue of God that He me there translate.</l>
      </lg></div3><p><milestone id="p03970018" />So ended Lauretta her song, to which all hearkened attentively,
 though not all interpreted it alike. Some were inclined to give it a
 moral after the Milanese fashion, to wit, that a good porker was
 better than pretty quean. Others construed it in a higher, better
 and truer sense, which 'tis not to the present purpose to unfold.
 <milestone id="p03970019" />Some more songs followed by command of the king, who caused
 torches not a few to be lighted and ranged about the flowery mead;
 and so the night was prolonged until the last star that had risen had
 begun to set. Then, bethinking him that 'twas time for slumber,
 the king bade all good-night, and dismissed them to their several
 chambers.</p></div2>