<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d02conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p02970001" />This story provoked so much laughter that the jaws of every one
 in the company ached; and all the ladies by common consent
 <pb n="171" />acknowledged that Dioneo was right, and pronounced Bernab&#242; a
 blockhead. <milestone id="p02970002" />But when the story was ended and the laughter had
 subsided, the queen, observing that the hour was now late, and that
 with the completion of the day's story-telling the end of her
 sovereignty was come, followed the example of her predecessor, and
 took off her wreath and set it on Neifile's brow, saying with gladsome
 mien, <q direct="unspecified">Now, dear gossip, thine be the sovereignty of this little
	people;</q> and so she resumed her seat. <milestone id="p02970003" />Neifile coloured somewhat
 to receive such honour, shewing of aspect even as the fresh-blown
 rose of April or May in the radiance of the dawn, her eyes rather
 downcast, and glowing with love's fire like the morning-star. But
 when the respectful murmur, by which the rest of the company gave
 blithe token of the favour in which they held their queen, was
 hushed, and her courage revived, she raised herself somewhat more
 in her seat than she was wont, and thus spoke: 
<milestone id="p02970004" /><q direct="unspecified">As so it is that
 I am your queen, I purpose not to depart from the usage observed
 by my predecessors, whose rule has commanded not only your
 obedience but your approbation. I will therefore in few words
 explain to you the course which, if it commend itself to your
 wisdom, we will follow. <milestone id="p02970005" />To-morrow, you know, is Friday, and the
 next day Saturday, days which most folk find somewhat wearisome
 by reason of the viands which are then customary, to say nothing of
 the reverence in which Friday is meet to be held, seeing that 'twas
 on that day that He who died for us bore His passion; wherefore
 'twould be in my judgment both right and very seemly, if, in honour
 of God, we then bade story-telling give place to prayer. 
<milestone id="p02970006" />On
 Saturday ladies are wont to wash the head, and rid their persons of
 whatever of dust or other soilure they may have gathered by the
 labours of the past week; not a few, likewise, are wont to practise
 abstinence for devotion to the Virgin Mother of the Son of God,
 and to honour the approaching Sunday by an entire surcease from
 work. Wherefore, as we cannot then completely carry out our
 plan of life, we shall, I think, do well to intermit our story-telling
 on that day also. <milestone id="p02970007" />We shall then have been here four days; and
 lest we should be surprised by new-comers, I deem it expedient that
 we shift our quarters, and I have already taken thought for our next
 place of sojourn. <milestone id="p02970008" />Where, being arrived on Sunday, we will assemble
 after our sleep; and, whereas to-day our discourse has had an ample
 <pb n="172" />field to range in, I propose, both because you will thereby have more
 time for thought, and it will be best to set some limits to the license
 of our story-telling, that of the many diversities of Fortune's handiwork
 we make one our theme, whereof I have also made choice, 
<milestone id="p02970009" />to
 wit, the luck of such as have painfully acquired some much-coveted
 thing, or having lost, have recovered it. Whereon let each meditate
 some matter, which to tell may be profitable or at least delectable to
 the company, saving always Dioneo's privilege.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02970010" />All applauded the queen's speech and plan, to which, therefore,
 it was decided to give effect. Thereupon the queen called her
 seneschal, told him where to place the tables that evening, and then
 explained to him all that he had to do during the time of her
 sovereignty. This done, she rose with her train, and gave leave to
 all to take their pleasure as to each might seem best. 
<milestone id="p02970011" />So the ladies
 and the men hied them away to a little garden, where they diverted
 themselves a while; then supper-time being come, they supped with
 all gay and festal cheer. When they were risen from the table,
 Emilia, at the queen's command, led the dance, while Pampinea,
 the other ladies responding, sang the ensuing song.</p><div3 who="pampinea" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p02970012" />
	<l>Shall any lady sing, if I not sing,</l>
	<l>I to whom Love did full contentment bring?</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p02970013" />
	<l>Come hither, Love, thou cause of all my joy,</l>
	<l>Of all my hope, and all its sequel blest,</l>
	<l>And with me tune the lay,</l>
	<l>No more to sighs and bitter past annoy,</l>
	<l>That now but serve to lend thy bliss more zest;</l>
	<l>But to that fire's clear ray,</l>
	<l>Wherewith enwrapt I blithely live and gay,</l>
	<l>Thee as my God for ever worshipping.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p02970014" />
	<l>'Twas thou, O Love, didst set before mine eyes,</l>
	<l>When first thy fire my sould did penetrate,</l>
	<l>A youth to be my fere,</l>
	<l>So fair, so fit for deeds of high emprise,</l>
	<l>That ne'er another shall be found more great,</l>
	<l>Nay, nor, I ween, his peer:</l>
	<l>Such flame he kindled that my heart's full cheer</l>
	<l>I now pour out in chant with thee, my King.</l>
      </lg><pb n="173" /><lg><milestone id="p02970015" />
	<l>And that wherein I most delight is this,</l>
	<l>That as I love him, so he loveth me:</l>
	<l>So thank thee, Love, I must.</l>
	<l>For whatsoe'er this world can yield of bliss</l>
	<l>Is mine, and in the next at peace to be</l>
	<l>I hope through that full trust</l>
	<l>I place in him. And thou, O God, that dost</l>
	<l>It see, wilt grant of joy thy plenishing.</l>
      </lg></div3><p><milestone id="p02970016" />Some other songs and dances followed, to the accompaniment
      of divers sorts of music; after which, the queen deeming it time to
      go to rest, all, following in the wake of the torches, sought their
      several chambers. The next two days they devoted to the duties
      to which the queen had adverted, looking forward to the Sunday
      with eager expectancy.</p></div2>