<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov0806"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08060001" />Bruno and Buffalmacco steal a pig from Calandrino, and
	induce him to essay its recovery by means of pills of
	ginger and vernaccia. Of the said pills they give
	him two, one after the other, made of dog-ginger
	compounded with aloes; and it then appearing as if
	he had had the pig himself, they constrain him to buy
	them off, if he would not have them tell his wife.</p>
    </argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08060002" />Filostrato's story, which elicited
      not a little laughter, was no
      sooner ended, than the queen bade Filomena follow suit. Wherefore
      thus Filomena began:</p></div3><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08060003" />As, gracious ladies, 'twas the name of
      Maso del Saggio that prompted Filostrato to tell the story that you
      have but now heard, even so 'tis with me in regard of Calandrino
      and his comrades, of whom I am minded to tell you another story,
      which you will, I think, find entertaining.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08060004" />Who Calandrino,
      Bruno and Buffalmacco were, I need not explain; you know them
      well enough from the former story; and therefore I will tarry no
      longer than to say that Calandrino had a little estate not far from
      Florence, which his wife had brought him by way of dowry, and
      which yielded them yearly, among other matters, a pig; and 'twas
      his custom every year in the month of December to resort to the
      farm with his wife, there to see to the killing and salting of the
      said pig. <milestone id="p08060005" />Now, one of these years it so happened that his wife
      being unwell, Calandrino went thither alone to kill the pig. And
      Bruno and Buffalmacco learning that he was gone to the farm, and
      that his wife was not with him, betook them to the house of a
      priest that was their especial friend and a neighbour of Calandrino,
      <pb n="204" />there to tarry a while. <milestone id="p08060006" />Upon their arrival Calandrino, who had
      that very morning killed the pig, met them with the priest, and
      accosted them, saying: <q direct="unspecified">A hearty welcome to you. I should
	like you to see what an excellent manager I am;</q> and so he took
      them into his house, and shewed them the pig. <milestone id="p08060007" />They observed
      that 'twas a very fine pig; and learned from Calandrino that he was
      minded to salt it for household consumption. <q direct="unspecified">Then thou art but
	a fool,</q> quoth Bruno. <q direct="unspecified">Sell it, man, and let us have a jolly time
	with the money; and tell thy wife that 'twas stolen.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060008" /><q direct="unspecified">Not I,</q>
      replied Calandrino: <q direct="unspecified">she would never believe me, and would drive
	me out of the house. Urge me no further, for I will never do it.</q>
      The others said a great deal more, but to no purpose; and Calandrino
      bade them to supper, but so coldly that they declined, and left him.</p><p><milestone id="p08060009" />Presently: <q direct="unspecified">Should we not steal this pig from him to-night?</q>
      quoth Bruno to Buffalmacco. 
      <milestone id="p08060010" /><q direct="unspecified">Could we so?</q> returned Buffalmacco.
      <q direct="unspecified">How?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060011" /><q direct="unspecified">Why as to that,</q> rejoined Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">I have
	already marked how it may be done, if he bestow not the pig
	elsewhere.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060012" /><q direct="unspecified">So be it, then,</q> said Buffalmacco: <q direct="unspecified">we will steal
	it; and then, perchance, our good host, Master Priest, will join us
	in doing honour to such good cheer?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060013" /><q direct="unspecified">That right gladly will I,</q>
      quoth the priest. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Some address, though,</q> quoth
      Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">will be needful: thou knowest, Buffalmacco, what a
	niggardly fellow Calandrino is, and how greedily he drinks at other
	folk's expense. Go we, therefore, and take him to the tavern,
	and there let the priest make as if, to do us honour, he would pay
	the whole score, and suffer Calandrino to pay never a soldo, and he
	will grow tipsy, and then we shall speed excellent well, because he
	is alone in the house.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08060014" />As Bruno proposed, so they did: and Calandrino, finding that
      the priest would not suffer him to pay, drank amain, and took a great
      deal more aboard than he had need of; and the night being far spent
      when he left the tavern, he dispensed with supper, and went home,
      and thinking to have shut the door, got him to bed, leaving it open.
      <milestone id="p08060015" />Buffalmacco and Bruno went to sup with the priest; and after supper,
      taking with them certain implements with which to enter Calandrino's
      house, where Bruno thought it most feasible, they stealthily approached
      it; but finding the door open, they entered, and took down the pig,
      and carried it away to the priest's house, and having there bestowed
      <pb n="205" />it safely, went to bed. <milestone id="p08060016" />In the morning when Calandrino, his head at
      length quit of the fumes of the wine, got up, and came downstairs
      and found that his pig was nowhere to be seen, and that the door
      was open, he asked this, that, and the other man, whether they wist
      who had taken the pig away, and getting no answer, he began to
      make a great outcry: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, alas! luckless man that I am, that
	my pig should have been stolen from me!</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060017" />Meanwhile Bruno and
      Buffalmacco, being also risen, made up to him, to hear what he would
      say touching the pig. Whom he no sooner saw, than well-nigh
      weeping he called them, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! my friends! my pig is
	stolen from me.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060018" />Bruno stepped up to him and said in a low tone:
      <q direct="unspecified">'Tis passing strange if thou art in the right for once.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060019" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas!</q>
      returned Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">what I say is but too true.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060020" /><q direct="unspecified">Why, then,
	out with it, man,</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">cry aloud, that all folk may know
	that 'tis so.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060021" />Calandrino then raised his voice and said: <q direct="unspecified">By the
	body o' God I say of a truth that my pig has been stolen from me.</q>
      <milestone id="p08060022" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">but publish it, man, publish it; lift up thy
	voice, make thyself well heard, that all may believe thy report.</q>
      <milestone id="p08060023" /><q direct="unspecified">Thou art enough to make me give my soul to the Enemy,</q> replied
      Calandrino. <q direct="unspecified">I say--dost not believe me?--that hang me by the
	neck if the pig is not stolen from me!</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060024" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but,</q> quoth Bruno,
      <q direct="unspecified">how can it be? I saw it here but yesterday. Dost think to make
	me believe that it has taken to itself wings and flown away?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060025" /><q direct="unspecified">All
	the same 'tis as I tell thee,</q> returned Calandrino. 
      <milestone id="p08060026" /><q direct="unspecified">Is it possible?</q> quoth Bruno. 
      <milestone id="p08060027" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay indeed,</q> replied Calandrino; <q direct="unspecified">'tis even so: and
	I am undone, and know not how to go home. Never will my wife
	believe me; or if she do so, I shall know no peace this year.</q>
      <milestone id="p08060028" /><q direct="unspecified">Upon my hope of salvation,</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">'tis indeed a bad
	business, if so it really is. But thou knowest, Calandrino, that 'twas
	but yesterday I counselled thee to make believe that 'twas so. I
	should be sorry to think thou didst befool thy wife and us at the same
	time.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060029" /><q direct="unspecified">Ah!</q> vociferated Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">wilt thou drive me to
	despair and provoke me to blaspheme God and the saints and all the
	company of heaven? I tell thee that the pig has been stolen from
	me in the night.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060030" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">If so it be,</q> quoth Buffalmacco,
      <q direct="unspecified">we must find a way, if we can, to recover it.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060031" /><q direct="unspecified">Find a way?</q>
      said Calandrino: <q direct="unspecified">how can we compass that?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060032" /><q direct="unspecified">Why,</q> replied
      Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">'tis certain that no one has come from India to steal
	<pb n="206" />thy pig: it must have been one of thy neighbours, and it thou
	couldst bring them together, I warrant thee, I know how to make
	the assay with bread and cheese, and we will find out in a trice who
	has had the pig.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060033" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay,</q> struck in Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">make thy assay with
	bread
	and cheese in the presence of these gentry hereabout, one of whom
	I am sure has had the pig! why, the thing would be seen through:
	and they would not come.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060034" /><q direct="unspecified">What shall we do, then?</q> said
      Buffalmacco. 
      <milestone id="p08060035" />Whereto Bruno made answer: <q direct="unspecified">It must be done
	with good pills of ginger and good vernaccia; and they must be
	bidden come drink with us. They will suspect nothing, and will
	come; and pills of ginger can be blessed just as well as bread and
	cheese.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060036" /><q direct="unspecified">Beyond a doubt, thou art right,</q> quoth Buffalmacco;
      <q direct="unspecified">and thou, Calandrino, what sayst thou? Shall we do as Bruno
	says?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060037" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, I entreat you, for the love of God,</q> quoth Calandrino,
      <q direct="unspecified">do even so: for if I knew but who had had the pig, I should
	feel myself half consoled for my loss.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060038" /><q direct="unspecified">Go to, now,</q> quoth Bruno,
      <q direct="unspecified">I am willing to do thy errand to Florence for these commodities, if
	thou givest me the money.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08060039" />Calandrino had some forty soldi upon him, which he gave to
      Bruno, who thereupon hied him to Florence to a friend of his that
      was an apothecary, and bought a pound of good pills of ginger, two
      of which, being of dog-ginger, he caused to be compounded with
      fresh hepatic aloes, and then to be coated with sugar like the others;
      and lest they should be lost, or any of the others mistaken for them,
      he had a slight mark set upon them by which he might readily
      recognize them. He also bought a flask of good vernaccia, and, thus
      laden, returned to the farm, and said to Calandrino: 
      <milestone id="p08060040" /><q direct="unspecified">To-morrow
	morning thou wilt bid those whom thou suspectest come hither to
	drink with thee: as 'twill be a saint's day, they will all come readily
	enough; and to-night I and Buffalmacco will say the incantation
	over the pills, which in the morning I will bring to thee here, and
	for our friendship's sake will administer them myself, and do and say
	all that needs to be said and done.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08060041" />So Calandrino did as Bruno
      advised; and on the morrow a goodly company, as well of young
      men from Florence, that happened to be in the village, as of husbandmen,
      being assembled in front of the church around the elm, Bruno
      and Buffalmacco came, bearing a box containing the ginger, and the
      flask of wine, and ranged the folk in a circle. Whereupon:
      <pb n="207" />
      <milestone id="p08060042" /><q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> said Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">'tis meet I tell you the reason why
	you
	are gathered here, that if aught unpleasant to you should befall, you
	may have no ground for complaint against me. 
	<milestone id="p08060043" />Calandrino here was
	the night before last robbed of a fine pig, and cannot discover who
	has had it; and, for that it must have been stolen by some one of us
	here, he would have each of you take and eat one of these pills and
	drink of this vernaccia. Wherefore I forthwith do you to wit, that
	whoso has had the pig will not be able to swallow the pill, but will
	find it more bitter than poison, and will spit it out; and so, rather
	than he should suffer this shame in presence of so many, 'twere
	perhaps best that he that has had the pig should confess the fact to
	the priest, and I will wash my hands of the affair.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08060044" />All professed themselves ready enough to eat the pills; and so,
 having set them in a row with Calandrino among them, Bruno,
 beginning at one end, proceeded to give each a pill, and when he
 came to Calandrino he chose one of the pills of dog-ginger and put it
 in his hand. <milestone id="p08060045" />Calandrino thrust it forthwith between his teeth and
 began to chew it; but no sooner was his tongue acquainted with the
 aloes, than, finding the bitterness intolerable, he spat it out. 
<milestone id="p08060046" />Now,
 the eyes of all the company being fixed on one another to see who should
 spit out his pill, Bruno, who, not having finished the distribution,
 feigned to be concerned with nought else, heard some one in his rear
 say: <q direct="unspecified">Ha! Calandrino, what means this?</q> and at once turning
 round, and marking that Calandrino had spit out his pill: 
<milestone id="p08060047" /><q direct="unspecified">Wait a
 while,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">perchance 'twas somewhat else that caused thee
 to spit: take another;</q> and thereupon whipping out the other pill of
 dog-ginger, he set it between Calandrino's teeth, and finished the
 distribution. <milestone id="p08060048" />Bitter as Calandrino had found the former pill, he
 found this tenfold more so; but being ashamed to spit it out, he kept
 it a while in his mouth and chewed it, and, as he did so, tears stood in
 his eyes that shewed as large as filberts, and at length, being unable
 to bear it any longer, he spat it out, as he had its predecessor. 
<milestone id="p08060049" />Which
 being observed by Buffalmacco and Bruno, who were then administering
 the wine, and by all the company, 'twas averred by common
 consent that Calandrino had committed the theft himself; for which
 cause certain of them took him severely to task.</p><p><milestone id="p08060050" />However, the company being dispersed, and Bruno and Buffalmacco
 left alone with Calandrino, Buffalmacco began on this wise:
 <pb n="208" /><q direct="unspecified">I never doubted but that thou hadst had it thyself, and wast minded
 to make us believe that it had been stolen from thee, that we might
 not have of thee so much as a single drink out of the price which
 thou gottest for it.</q> 
<milestone id="p08060051" />Calandrino, with the bitterness of the aloes
 still on his tongue, fell a swearing that he had not had it. 
<milestone id="p08060052" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but, comrade,</q> quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">upon thy honour,
 what did it fetch? Six florins?</q> 
<milestone id="p08060053" />Whereto, Calandrino being now
 on the verge of desperation, Bruno added: <q direct="unspecified">Now be reasonable,
 Calandrino; among the company that ate and drank with us there
 was one that told me that thou hadst up there a girl that thou didst
 keep for thy pleasure, giving her what by hook or by crook thou
 couldst get together, and that he held it for certain that thou hadst
 sent her this pig. And thou art grown expert in this sort of cozenage.
 <milestone id="p08060054" />Thou tookest us one while adown the Mugnone a gathering black
 stones, and having thus started us on a wild-goose chase, thou madest
 off; and then wouldst fain have us believe that thou hadst found the
 stone: and now, in like manner, thou thinkest by thine oaths to
 persuade us that this pig which thou hast given away or sold, has
 been stolen from thee. <milestone id="p08060055" />But we know thy tricks of old; never
 another couldst thou play us; and, to be round with thee, this spell
 has cost us some trouble: wherefore we mean that thou shalt give
 us two pair of capons, or we will let Monna Tessa know all.</q> 
<milestone id="p08060056" />Seeing
 that he was not believed, and deeming his mortification ample without
 the addition of his wife's resentment, Calandrino gave them the
 two pair of capons, with which, when the pig was salted, they
 returned to Florence, leaving Calandrino with the loss and the laugh
 against him.</p></div2>