<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0305"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03050001" />Zima gives a palfrey to Messer Francesco Vergellesi,
 who in return suffers him to speak with his wife.
 She keeping silence, he answers in her stead, and
 the sequel is in accordance with his answer.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03050002" />When Pamfilo had brought the story of Fra Puccio to a close
	amid the laughter of the ladies, the queen debonairly bade Elisa
	follow suit; and she, whose manner had in it a slight touch of
	severity, which betokened not despite, but was habitual to her, thus
	began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03050003" />Many there are that, being very knowing, think that others
	are quite the reverse; and so, many a time, thinking to beguile
	others, are themselves beguiled; wherefore I deem it the height of
	folly for any one wantonly to challenge another to a contest of
	wit. But, as, perchance, all may not be of the same opinion, I
	am minded, without deviating from the prescribed order, to acquaint
	you with that which thereby befell a certain knight of Pistoia.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p03050004" />Know then that at Pistoia there lived a knight, Messer Francesco,
 by name, of the Vergellesi family, a man of much wealth and good
 parts, being both wise and clever, but withal niggardly beyond
 measure. Which Messer Francesco, having to go to Milan in the
 capacity of podest&#224;, had provided himself with all that was meet
 for the honourable support of such a dignity, save only a palfrey
 handsome enough for him; and not being able to come by any
 such, he felt himself at a loss. <milestone id="p03050005" />Now there was then in Pistoia
 a young man, Ricciardo by name, of low origin but great wealth,
 who went always so trim and fine and foppish of person, that folk
 <pb n="204" />had bestowed upon him the name of Zima,<note>From the Low Latin
 aczima, explained by Du Cange as <q direct="unspecified">tonture de
 draps,</q> the process of dressing cloth so as to give it an even nap. Zima
 is thus equivalent to <q direct="unspecified">nitidus.</q> Cf. Vocab. degli Accademici della
 Crusca,
 <q direct="unspecified">Azzimare.</q></note> by which he was
 generally known. Zima had long and to no purpose burned and
 yearned for love of Messer Francesco's very fair and no less virtuous
 wife. <milestone id="p03050006" />His passion was matter of common notoriety; and so it befell
 that some one told Messer Francesco that he had but to ask Zima,
 who was the possessor of one of the handsomest palfreys in Tuscany,
 which on that account he greatly prized, and he would not hesitate
 to give him the horse for the love which he bore his wife. So our
 niggardly knight sent for Zima, and offered to buy the horse of
 him, hoping thereby to get him from Zima as a gift. 
<milestone id="p03050007" />Zima
 heard the knight gladly, and thus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Sell you my
 horse, Sir, I would not, though you gave me all that you have in
 the world; but I shall be happy to give him to you, when you will,
 on this condition, that, before he pass into your hands, I may by your
 leave and in your presence say a few words to your wife so privately
 that I may be heard by her alone.</q> 
<milestone id="p03050008" />Thinking at once to gratify
 his cupidity and to outwit Zima, the knight answered that he was
 content that it should be even as Zima wished. Then, leaving him
 in the hall of the palace, he went to his lady's chamber, and told her
 the easy terms on which he might acquire the palfrey, bidding her
 give Zima his audience, but on no account to vouchsafe him a word
 of reply. <milestone id="p03050009" />This the lady found by no means to her mind, but, as
 she must needs obey her husband's commands, she promised compliance,
 and followed him into the hall to hear what Zima might
 have to say. <milestone id="p03050010" />Zima then renewed his contract with the knight in due
 form; whereupon, the lady being seated in a part of the hall where
 she was quite by herself, he sate down by her side, and thus began:
 <q direct="unspecified">Noble lady, I have too much respect for your understanding
 to doubt that you have long been well aware of the extremity of
 passion whereto I have been brought by your beauty, which certainly
 exceeds that of any other lady that I have ever seen, to say nothing
 of your exquisite manners and incomparable virtues, which might
 well serve to captivate every soaring spirit that is in the world;
 <milestone id="p03050011" />wherefore there need no words of mine to assure you that I love
 <pb n="205" />you with a love greater and more ardent than any that man yet
 bore to woman, and so without doubt I shall do, as long as my
 woful life shall hold this frame together; nay, longer yet, for, if
 love there be in the next world as in this, I shall love you evermore.
 And so you may make your mind secure that there is nothing that
 is yours, be it precious or be it common, which you may count as
 in such and so sure a sort your own as me, for all that I am and have.
 <milestone id="p03050012" />And that thereof you may not lack evidence of infallible cogency,
 I tell you, that I should deem myself more highly favoured, if I
 might at your command do somewhat to pleasure you, than if at
 my command the whole world were forthwith to yield me obedience.
 <milestone id="p03050013" />And as 'tis even in such sort that I am yours, 'tis not unworthily
 that I make bold to offer my petitions to Your Highness, as being
 to me the sole, exclusive source of all peace, of all bliss, of all health.
 Wherefore, as your most lowly vassal, I pray you, dear my bliss,
 my soul's one hope, wherein she nourishes herself in love's devouring
 flame, that in your great benignity you deign so far to mitigate the
 harshness which in the past you have shewn towards me, yours though
 I am, that, consoled by your compassion, I may say, that, as 'twas
 by your beauty that I was smitten with love, so 'tis to your pity
 that I owe my life, which, if in your haughtiness you lend not ear
 unto my prayers, will assuredly fail, so that I shall die, and, it may
 be, 'twill be said that you slew me. <milestone id="p03050014" />'Twould not redound to your
 honour that I died for love of you; but let that pass; I cannot but
 think, however, that you would sometimes feel a touch of remorse,
 and would grieve that 'twas your doing, and that now and again,
 relenting, you would say to yourself: 'Ah! how wrong it was of
 me that I had not pity on my Zima;' by which too late repentance
 you would but enhance your grief. <milestone id="p03050015" />Wherefore, that this come not
 to pass, repent you while it is in your power to give me ease, and
 shew pity on me before I die, seeing that with you it rests to make
 me either the gladdest or the saddest man that lives. My trust is
 in your generosity, that 'twill not brook that a love so great and
 of such a sort as mine should receive death for guerdon, and that
 by a gladsome and gracious answer you will repair my shattered
 spirits, which are all a-tremble in your presence for very fear.</q>
 <milestone id="p03050016" />When he had done, he heaved several very deep sighs, and a few
 tears started from his eyes, while he awaited the lady's answer.</p><pb n="206" /><p><milestone id="p03050017" />Long time he had wooed her with his eyes, had tilted in her
 honour, had greeted her rising with music; and against these and
 all like modes of attack she had been proof; but the heartfelt words
 of her most ardent lover were not without their effect, and she now
 began to understand what she had never till then understood, to wit,
 what love really means. So, albeit she obeyed her lord's behest, and
 kept silence, yet she could not but betray by a slight sigh that which,
 if she might have given Zima his answer, she would readily have
 avowed. <milestone id="p03050018" />After waiting a while, Zima found it strange that no
 answer was forthcoming; and he then began to perceive the trick
 which the knight had played him. However, he kept his eyes fixed
 on the lady, and observing that her eyes glowed now and again, as
 they met his, and noting the partially suppressed sighs which escaped
 her, he gathered a little hope, which gave him courage to try a novel
 plan of attack. So, while the lady listened, he began to make answer
 for her to himself on this wise: 
<milestone id="p03050019" /><q direct="unspecified">Zima mine, true indeed it is that
 long since I discerned that thou didst love me with a love exceeding
 great and whole-hearted, whereof I have now yet ampler assurance
 by thine own words, and well content I am therewith, as indeed
 I ought to be. <milestone id="p03050020" />And however harsh and cruel I may have seemed
 to thee, I would by no means have thee believe, that I have been such
 at heart as I have seemed in aspect; rather, be assured that I have
 ever loved thee and held thee dear above all other men; the mien
 which I have worn was but prescribed by fear of another and
 solicitude for my fair fame. <milestone id="p03050021" />But a time will soon come when I
 shall be able to give thee plain proof of my love, and to accord
 the love which thou hast borne and dost bear me its due guerdon.
 Wherefore be comforted and of good hope; for, Messer Francesco
 is to go in a few days' time to Milan as podest&#224;, as thou well
 knowest, seeing that for love of me thou hast given him thy fine
 palfrey; and I vow to thee upon my faith, upon the true love
 which I bear thee, that without fail, within a few days thereafter
 thou shalt be with me, and we will give our love complete and
 gladsome consummation. <milestone id="p03050022" />And that I may have no more occasion
 to speak to thee of this matter, be it understood between us that
 henceforth when thou shalt observe two towels disposed at the
 window of my room which overlooks the garden, thou shalt come
 to me after nightfall of that same day by the garden door (and look
 <pb n="207" />well to it that thou be not seen), and thou shalt find me waiting
 for thee, and we will have our fill of mutual cheer and solace all
 night long.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03050023" />Having thus answered for the lady, Zima resumed his own
 person and thus replied to the lady: <q direct="unspecified">Dearest madam, your boon
 response so overpowers my every faculty that scarce can I frame
 words to render you due thanks; and, were I able to utter all I feel,
 time, however long, would fail me fully to thank you as I would
 fain and as I ought: wherefore I must even leave it to your sage
 judgment to divine that which I yearn in vain to put in words.
<milestone id="p03050024" />Let this one word suffice, that as you bid me, so I shall not fail
 to do; and then, having, perchance, firmer assurance of the great
 boon which you have granted me, I will do my best endeavour to
 thank you in terms the amplest that I may command. For the
 present there is no more to say; and so, dearest my lady, I commend
 you to God; and may He grant you your heart's content of
 joy and bliss.</q> 
<milestone id="p03050025" />To all which the lady returned never a word:
 wherefore Zima rose and turned to rejoin the knight, who, seeing
 him on his feet, came towards him, and said with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">How
 sayst thou? Have I faithfully kept my promise to thee?</q> 
<milestone id="p03050026" /><q direct="unspecified">Not so,
 Sir,</q> replied Zima; <q direct="unspecified">for by thy word I was to have spoken with thy
 wife, and by thy deed I have spoken to a statue of marble.</q> 
<milestone id="p03050027" />Which
 remark was much relished by the knight, who, well as he had thought
 of his wife, thought now even better of her, and said: <q direct="unspecified">So thy
 palfrey, that was, is now mine out and out.</q> 
<milestone id="p03050028" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis even so, Sir,</q>
 replied Zima; <q direct="unspecified">but had I thought to have gotten such fruit as I
 have from this favour of yours, I would not have craved it, but
 would have let you have the palfrey as a free gift: and would to
 God I had done so, for, as it is, you have bought the palfrey and
 I have not sold him.</q> 
<milestone id="p03050029" />This drew a laugh from the knight, who
 within a few days thereafter mounted the palfrey which he had
 gotten, and took the road for Milan, there to enter on his podestate.
 The lady, now mistress of herself, bethought her of Zima's words,
 and the love which he bore her, and for which he had parted with
 his palfrey; and observing that he frequently passed her house, said
 to herself: 
<milestone id="p03050030" /><q direct="unspecified">What am I about? Why throw I my youth away?
 My husband is gone to Milan, and will not return for six months,
 and when can he ever restore them to me? When I am old!
 <pb n="208" />And besides, shall I ever find another such lover as Zima? I am
 quite by myself. There is none to fear. I know not why I take
 not my good time while I may: I shall not always have the like
 opportunity as at present: no one will ever know; and if it should
 get known, 'tis better to do and repent than to forbear and repent.</q>
 <milestone id="p03050031" />Of which meditations the issue was that one day she set two towels
 in the window overlooking the garden, according to Zima's word;
 and Zima having marked them with much exultation, stole at
 nightfall alone to the door of the lady's garden, and finding it open,
 crossed to another door that led into the house, where he found the
 lady awaiting him. <milestone id="p03050032" />On sight of him she rose to meet him, and
 gave him the heartiest of welcomes. A hundred thousand times
 he embraced and kissed her, as he followed her upstairs: then
 without delay they hied them to bed, and knew love's furthest
 bourne. <milestone id="p03050033" />And so far was the first time from being in this case the
 last, that, while the knight was at Milan, and indeed after his return,
 there were seasons not a few at which Zima resorted thither to the
 immense delight of both parties.</p></div2>