<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0704"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p07040001" />Tofano one night locks his
wife out of the house: she, finding that by no entreaties may she prevail upon him to let
her in, feigns to throw herself into a well, throwing therein a great stone. Tofano hies
him forth of the house, and runs to the spot: she goes into the house, and locks him out,
and hurls abuse at him from
within.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07040002" />The king no sooner wist that
	Elisa's story was ended, than, turning to Lauretta, he signified his will that she should
	tell somewhat: wherefore without delay she began:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07040003" />O Love, how great and signal
	is thy potency! how notable thy stratagems, thy devices!  Was there ever, shall there ever
	be, philosopher or adept competent to inspire, counsel and teach in such sort as thou by
	thine unpremeditated art dost tutor those that follow thy lead? 
	<milestone id="p07040004" />Verily laggard
	teachers are they all in comparison of thee, as by the matters heretofore set forth may
	very well be understood. To which store I will
	add, loving ladies, a stratagem used by a woman of quite ordinary
	understanding, and of such a sort that I know not by whom she could have been taught it
	save by Love.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p07040005" />Know, then, that there dwelt aforetime at Arezzo a rich man, Tofano
by name, who took to wife Monna Ghita, a lady exceeding fair, of whom, for what cause he
knew not, he presently grew jealous.  Whereof the lady being ware, waxed resentful, and
having on divers occasions demanded of him the reason of his jealousy, and gotten from him
nought precise, but only generalities and trivialities, resolved at last to give him cause
enough to die of that evil which without cause he so much dreaded. <milestone id="p07040006" />And being
ware that a gallant, whom she deemed well
<pb n="130" />worthy of her, was enamoured of her, she, using due discretion, came to an
understanding with him; which being brought to the point that it only remained to give
effect to their words in act, the lady cast about to devise how this might
be. <milestone id="p07040007" />And witting that, among other bad habits that her husband had, he was too
fond of his cups, she would not only commend indulgence, but cunningly and not seldom
incite him thereto; <milestone id="p07040008" />insomuch that, well-nigh as often as she was so minded, she
led him to drink to excess; and when she saw that he was well drunken, she would put him
to bed; and so not once only but divers times without any manner of risk she forgathered
with her lover; nay, presuming upon her husband's intoxication, she grew so bold that, not
content with bringing her lover into her house, she would at times go spend a great part
of the night with him at his house, which was not far off.</p><p><milestone id="p07040009" />Now such being the
enamoured lady's constant practice, it so befell that the dishonoured husband took note
that, while she egged him on to drink, she herself drank never a drop; whereby he came to
suspect the truth, to wit, that the lady was making him drunk, that afterwards she might
take her pleasure while he slept. <milestone id="p07040010" />And being minded to put his surmise to the
proof, one evening, having drunken nought all day, he mimicked never so drunken a sot both
in
speech and in carriage. The lady, deeming him to be really as he appeared, and that 'twas
needless to ply him with liquor, presently put him to bed.  Which done, she, as she at
times was wont, hied her forth to her lover's house, where she tarried until midnight.
<milestone id="p07040011" />Tofano no sooner perceived that his wife was gone, than up he got, hied him to
the door, locked it, and then posted himself at the window to observe her return, and let
her know that he was ware of her misconduct. So there he stood until the lady returned,
and finding herself locked out, was annoyed beyond measure, and sought to force the door
open. <milestone id="p07040012" />Tofano let her try her strength upon it a while, and then: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q>
quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis all to no purpose: thou canst not get in. Go get thee back thither where
thou hast tarried all this while, and rest assured that thou shalt never recross this
threshold, until I have done thee such honour as is meet for thee in the presence of thy
kinsfolk and neighbours.</q> <milestone id="p07040013" />Thereupon the lady fell entreating him to be
pleased to open to her for the love of God, for that she was not come whence he supposed,
but had only been passing the time
<pb n="131" />with one of her gossips, because the nights were long, and she could not spend
the whole time either in sleep or in solitary watching.
But her supplications availed her nothing, for the fool was determined
that all Arezzo should know their shame, whereof as yet none wist aught.  <milestone id="p07040014" />So as
'twas idle to entreat, the lady assumed a menacing tone, saying: <q direct="unspecified">So thou open not to
me, I will make thee the saddest man alive.</q> <milestone id="p07040015" />Whereto Tofano made answer:
<q direct="unspecified">And what then canst thou do?</q> <milestone id="p07040016" />The lady, her wits sharpened by Love,
rejoined: <q direct="unspecified">Rather than endure the indignity to which thou wouldst unjustly subject me, I
will cast myself into the well hard by here, and when I am found dead there, all the world
will believe that 'twas thou that didst it in thy cups, and so thou wilt either have to
flee and lose all that thou hast and be outlawed, or forfeit thy head as guilty of my
death, as indeed thou wilt be.</q> <milestone id="p07040017" />But, for all she said, Tofano wavered not a
jot in his foolish purpose. So at last: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now,</q> quoth the lady, <q direct="unspecified">I can no more
abide thy surly humour: God forgive thee: I leave thee my distaff here, which be careful
to bestow in a safe place.</q> <milestone id="p07040018" />So saying, away she hied her to the well, and,
the night being so dark that wayfarers could scarce see one another as they passed, she
took up a huge stone that was by the well, and ejaculating, <q direct="unspecified">God forgive me!</q> dropped
it therein. <milestone id="p07040019" />Tofano, hearing the mighty splash that the stone made as it struck
the water, never doubted that she had cast herself in: so, bucket and rope in hand, he
flung himself out of the house, and came running to the well to her rescue. <milestone id="p07040020" />The
lady had meanwhile hidden herself hard by the door, and seeing him make for the well, was
in the house in a trice, and having locked the door, hied her to the window, and greeted
him with: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis while thou art drinking, not now, when the night is far spent, that thou
shouldst temper thy wine with water.</q> <milestone id="p07040021" />Thus derided, Tofano came back to the
door, and finding his ingress barred, began adjuring her to let him
in. <milestone id="p07040022" />Whereupon, changing the low tone she had hitherto used for one so shrill
that 'twas well-nigh a shriek, she broke out with: <q direct="unspecified">By the Holy Rood, tedious drunken
sot that thou art, thou gettest no admittance here to-night; thy ways are more than I can
endure: 'tis time I let all the world know what manner of man thou art, and at what hour
of the night thou comest home.</q> <milestone id="p07040023" />Tofano, on his part, now grew angry, and
began loudly to upbraid her; insomuch that the neighbours, aroused by the noise, 
<pb n="132" />got up, men and women alike, and looked out of the windows, and asked what was the
matter. <milestone id="p07040024" />Whereupon the lady fell a weeping and saying: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis this wicked man,
who comes home drunk at even, or falls asleep in some tavern, and then returns at this
hour.  Long and to no purpose have I borne with him; but 'tis now past endurance, and I
have done him this indignity of locking him out of
the house in the hope that perchance it may cause him to mend his
ways.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07040025" />Tofano, on his part, told, dolt that he was, just what had happened, and
was mighty menacing. <milestone id="p07040026" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Now mark,</q> quoth the lady to the
neighbours, <q direct="unspecified">the sort of man he is!  What would you say if I were, as he is, in the
street, and he were in the house, as I am?  God's faith, I doubt you would believe what he
said. Hereby you may gauge his sense. He tells you that I have done just what, I doubt
not, he has done himself. <milestone id="p07040027" />He thought to terrify me by throwing I know not what
into the well, wherein would to God he had thrown himself indeed, and drowned himself,
whereby the wine of which he has taken more than enough, had
been watered to some purpose!</q> <milestone id="p07040028" />The neighbours, men and women alike, now with
one accord gave tongue, censuring Tofano, throwing all the blame upon him, and answering
what he alleged against the lady with loud recrimination; and in short the bruit, passing
from neighbour to neighbour, reached at last the ears of the lady's kinsfolk;
<milestone id="p07040029" />who hied them to the spot, and being apprised of the affair from this, that and
the other of the neighbours, laid hands on Tofano, and beat him till he was black and blue
from head to foot. Which done, they entered his house, stripped it of all that belonged to
the lady, and took her home with them, bidding Tofano look for worse to come.
<milestone id="p07040030" />Thus hard bested, and ruing the plight in which his jealousy had landed him,
Tofano, who loved his wife with all his heart, set some friends to work to patch matters
up, whereby he did in fact induce his lady to forgive him and live with him again; albeit
he was fain to promise her never again to be jealous, and to give her leave to amuse
herself to her heart's content, provided she used such discretion that he should not be
ware of it. <milestone id="p07040031" />On such wise, like the churl and booby that he was, being
despoiled, he made terms. Now long live
Love, and perish war, and all that wage it!</p></div2>