<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov0405"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04050001" />Lisabetta's brothers slay her lover: he appears to her in
 a dream, and shews her where he is buried: she
 privily disinters the head, and sets it in a pot of
 basil, whereon she daily weeps a great while. The
 pot being taken from her by her brothers, she dies
 not long after.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04050002" />Elisa's story ended, the king bestowed a few
	words of praise
	upon it, and then laid the burden of discourse upon Filomena, who,
	full of compassion for the woes of Gerbino and his lady, heaved a
	piteous sigh, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04050003" />My story, gracious ladies, will not
	be of folk of so high a rank as those of whom Elisa has told us, but
	perchance 'twill not be less touching. 'Tis brought to my mind by
	the recent mention of Messina, where the matter befell.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04050004" />Know then that there were at Messina three young men, that
 were brothers and merchants, who were left very rich on the death
 of their father, who was of San Gimignano; and they had a sister,
 Lisabetta by name, a girl fair enough, and no less debonair, but
 whom, for some reason or another, they had not as yet bestowed in
 marriage. <milestone id="p04050005" />The three brothers had also in their shop a young Pisan,
 Lorenzo by name, who managed all their affairs, and who was so
 goodly of person and gallant, that Lisabetta bestowed many a glance
 upon him, and began to regard him with extraordinary favour;
 which Lorenzo marking from time to time, gave up all his other
 amours, and in like manner began to affect her, and so, their loves
 being equal, 'twas not long before they took heart of grace, and did
 that which each most desired. <milestone id="p04050006" />Wherein continuing to their no
 small mutual solace and delight, they neglected to order it with due
 <pb n="297" />secrecy, whereby one night as Lisabetta was going to Lorenzo's
 room, she, all unwitting, was observed by the eldest of the brothers,
 who, albeit much distressed by what he had learnt, yet, being a
 young man of discretion, was swayed by considerations more seemly,
 and, allowing no word to escape him, spent the night in turning the
 affair over in his mind in divers ways. <milestone id="p04050007" />On the morrow he told his
 brothers that which, touching Lisabetta and Lorenzo, he had observed
 in the night, which, that no shame might thence ensue either to
 them or to their sister, they after long consultation determined to pass
 over in silence, making as if they had seen or heard nought thereof,
 until such time as they in a safe and convenient manner might
 banish this disgrace from their sight before it could go further.
 <milestone id="p04050008" />Adhering to which purpose, they jested and laughed with Lorenzo
 as they had been wont; and after a while pretending that they were
 all three going forth of the city on pleasure, they took Lorenzo with
 them; and being come to a remote and very lonely spot, seeing that
 'twas apt for their design, they took Lorenzo, who was completely
 off his guard, and slew him, and buried him on such wise that none
 was ware of it. <milestone id="p04050009" />On their return to Messina they gave out that they
 had sent him away on business; which was readily believed, because
 'twas what they had been frequently used to do. <milestone id="p04050010" />But as Lorenzo
 did not return, and Lisabetta questioned the brothers about him with
 great frequency and urgency, being sorely grieved by his long
 absence, it so befell that one day, when she was very pressing in her
 enquiries, one of the brothers said: <q direct="unspecified">What means this? What
 hast thou to do with Lorenzo, that thou shouldst ask about him so
 often? Ask us no more, or we will give thee such answer as thou
 deservest.</q> 
<milestone id="p04050011" />So the girl, sick at heart and sorrowful, fearing she
 knew not what, asked no questions; but many a time at night she
 called piteously to him, and besought him to come to her, and
 bewailed his long tarrying with many a tear, and ever yearning for
 his return, languished in total dejection.</p><p><milestone id="p04050012" />But so it was that one night, when, after long weeping that her
 Lorenzo came not back, she had at last fallen asleep, Lorenzo
 appeared to her in a dream, wan and in utter disarray, his clothes
 torn to shreds and sodden; and thus, as she thought, he spoke:
 <milestone id="p04050013" /><q direct="unspecified">Lisabetta, thou dost nought but call me, and vex thyself for my
 long tarrying, and bitterly upbraid me with thy tears; wherefore be
 <pb n="298" />it known to thee that return to thee I may not, because the last day
 that thou didst see me thy brothers slew me.</q> After which, he
 described the place where they had buried him, told her to call and
 expect him no more, and vanished. <milestone id="p04050014" />The girl then awoke, and
 doubting not that the vision was true, wept bitterly. And when
 morning came, and she was risen, not daring to say aught to her
 brothers, she resolved to go to the place indicated in the vision, and
 see if what she had dreamed were even as it had appeared to her.
 <milestone id="p04050015" />So, having leave to go a little way out of the city for recreation in
 company with a maid that had at one time lived with them and
 knew all that she did, she hied her thither with all speed; and having
 removed the dry leaves that were strewn about the place, she began
 to dig where the earth seemed least hard. Nor had she dug long,
 before she found the body of her hapless lover, whereon as yet
 there was no trace of corruption or decay; and thus she saw without
 any manner of doubt that her vision was true. <milestone id="p04050016" />And so, saddest of
 women, knowing that she might not bewail him there, she would
 gladly, if she could, have carried away the body and given it more
 honourable sepulture elsewhere; but as she might not so do, she
 took a knife, and, as best she could, severed the head from the trunk,
 and wrapped it in a napkin and laid it in the lap of her maid; and
 having covered the rest of the corpse with earth, she left the spot,
 having been seen by none, and went home. <milestone id="p04050017" />There she shut herself
 up in her room with the head, and kissed it a thousand times in every
 part, and wept long and bitterly over it, till she had bathed it in her
 tears. She then wrapped it in a piece of fine cloth, and set it in a
 large and beautiful pot of the sort in which marjoram or basil is
 planted, and covered it with earth, and therein planted some roots
 of the goodliest basil of Salerno, and drenched them only with her
 tears, or water perfumed with roses or orange-blossoms. <milestone id="p04050018" />And 'twas
 her wont ever to sit beside this pot, and, all her soul one yearning, to
 pore upon it, as that which enshrined her Lorenzo, <milestone id="p04050019" />and when long
 time she had so done, she would bend over it, and weep a great
 while, until the basil was quite bathed in her tears.</p><p><milestone id="p04050020" />Fostered with such constant, unremitting care, and nourished by
 the richness given to the soil by the decaying head that lay therein,
 the basil burgeoned out in exceeding great beauty and fragrance.
 And, the girl persevering ever in this way of life, the neighbours from
 <pb n="299" />time to time took note of it, and when her brothers marvelled to see
 her beauty ruined, and her eyes as it were evanished from her head,
 they told them of it, saying: <q direct="unspecified">We have observed that such is her
 daily wont.</q> Whereupon the brothers, marking her behaviour, chid
 her therefore once or twice, and as she heeded them not, caused the
 pot to be taken privily from her. Which, so soon as she missed it,
 she demanded with the utmost instance and insistence, and, as they
 gave it not back to her, ceased not to wail and weep, insomuch that
 she fell sick; nor in her sickness craved she aught but the pot of
 basil. <milestone id="p04050021" />Whereat the young men, marvelling mightily, resolved to
 see what the pot might contain; and having removed the earth they
 espied the cloth, and therein the head, which was not yet so decayed,
 but that by the curled locks they knew it for Lorenzo's head. <milestone id="p04050022" />Passing
 strange they found it, and fearing lest it should be bruited abroad,
 they buried the head, and, with as little said as might be, took order
 for their privy departure from Messina, and hied them thence to
 Naples. <milestone id="p04050023" />The girl ceased not to weep and crave her pot, and, so
 weeping, died. Such was the end of her disastrous love; but not a
 few in course of time coming to know the truth of the affair, there
 was one that made the song that is still sung: to wit:</p><div3 type="song"><lg><milestone id="p04050024" />
	<l>A thief he was, I swear,</l>
	<l>A sorry Christian he,</l>
	<l>That took my basil of Salerno fair, etc.</l></lg><note>This Sicilian folk-song, of which Boccaccio quotes only the first two
	lines, is given in extenso from MS. Laurent. 38, plut. 42, by Fanfani in his
	edition of the Decameron (Florence, 1857). The following is a free
	rendering:
	<lg>	  <l>A thief he was, I swear,</l>
	  <l>A sorry Christian he,</l>
	  <l>That took my basil of Salerno fair,</l>
	  <l>That flourished mightily.</l>
	  <l>Planted by mine own hands with loving care</l>
	  <l>What time they revelled free:</l>
	  <l>To spoil another's goods is churlish spite.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg><l>To spoil another's goods is churlish spite,</l>
	  <l>Ay, and most heinous sin.</l>
	  <pb n="300" />
	  <l>A basil had I (alas! luckless wight!),</l>
	  <l>The fairest plant: within</l>
	  <l>Its shade I slept: 'twas grown to such a height.</l>
	  <l>But some folk for chagrin</l>
	  <l>'Reft me thereof, ay, and before my door.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>	  <l>'Reft me thereof, ay, and before my door.</l>
	  <l>Ah! dolorous day and drear!</l>
	  <l>Ah! woe is me! Would God I were no more!</l>
	  <l>My purchase was so dear!</l>
	  <l>Ah! why that day did I to watch give o'er?</l>
	  <l>For him my cherished fere</l>
	  <l>With marjoram I bordered it about.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg><l>With marjoram I bordered it about</l>
	  <l>In May-time fresh and fair,</l>
	  <l>And watered it thrice ere each week was out,</l>
	  <l>And marked it grow full yare:</l>
	  <l>But now 'tis stolen. Ah! too well 'tis known!<note>This stanza is
	  defective
	  in the original.</note></l>
      </lg>
	<lg><l>But now 'tis stolen. Ah! too well 'tis known!</l>
	  <l>That no more may I hide:</l>
	  <l>But had to me a while before been shewn</l>
	  <l>What then should me betide,</l>
	  <l>At night before my door I had laid me down</l>
	  <l>To watch my plant beside.</l>
	  <l>Yet God Almighty sure me succour might.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg><l>Ay, God Almighty sure me succour might,</l>
	  <l>So were it but His will,</l>
	  <l>'Gainst him that me hath done so foul despite,</l>
	  <l>That in dire torment still</l>
	  <l>I languish, since the thief reft from my sight</l>
	  <l>My plant that did me thrill,</l>
	  <l>And to my inmost soul such comfort lent!</l>
	</lg>
	<lg><l>And to my inmost soul such comfort lent!</l>
	  <l>So fresh its fragrance blew,</l>
	  <l>That when, what time the sun uprose, I went</l>
	  <l>My watering to do,</l>
	  <l>I'd hear the people all in wonderment</l>
	  <l>Say, whence this perfume new?</l>
	  <l>And I for love of it of grief shall die.</l>
	</lg>
	<pb n="301" />
	<lg><l>And I for love of it of grief shall die,</l>
	  <l>Of my fair plant for dole.</l>
	  <l>Would one but shew me how I might it buy!</l>
	  <l>Ah! how 'twould me con???ole!</l>
	  <l>Ounces<note>The <q direct="unspecified">oncia</q> was a Sicilian gold coin worth rather more
	  than
	  a zecchino.</note> an hundred of fine gold have I:</l>
	  <l>Him would I give the whole,</l>
	<l>Ay, and a kiss to boot, so he were fain.</l></lg>
      </note></div3></div2>