<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 type="Day" ruler="panfilo" id="day10"><pb n="313" /><head>Tenth Day</head><argument><p><milestone id="p10990001" />Endeth here the ninth day of the Decameron, and
 beginneth the tenth, in which, under the rule of
 Pamfilo, discourse is had of such as in matters of
 love, or otherwise, have done something with liberality
 or magnificence.</p></argument><div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d10intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p10980002" />Some cloudlets in the West still shewed a vermeil flush, albeit
      those of the eastern sky, as the sun's rays smote them anear, were
 already fringed as with most lucent gold, when uprose Pamfilo, and
 roused the ladies and his comrades. <milestone id="p10980003" />And all the company being
 assembled, and choice made of the place whither they should betake
 them for their diversion, he, accompanied by Filomena and Fiammetta,
 led the way at a slow pace, followed by all the rest. So fared they
 no little space, beguiling the time with talk of their future way of
 life, whereof there was much to tell and much to answer, until, as
 the sun gained strength, they returned, having made quite a long
 round, to the palace;  <milestone id="p10980004" />and being gathered about the fountain, such as
 were so minded drank somewhat from beakers rinsed in its pure
 waters; and then in the delicious shade of the garden they hied them
 hither and thither, taking their pleasure until breakfast-time. Their
 meal taken, they slept as they were wont; and then, at a spot chosen
 by the king, they reassembled, where Neifile, having received his
 command to lead the way, blithely thus began.</p></div2><pb n="314" /><div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov1001"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00010001" />A knight in the service of the King of Spain deems
 himself ill requited. Wherefore the King, by most
 cogent proof, shews him that the blame rests not with
 him, but with the knight's own evil fortune; after
 which, he bestows upon him a noble gift.</p></argument><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00010002" />Highly graced, indeed, do I deem myself, honourable my ladies,
 that our king should have given to me the precedence in a matter so
 arduous to tell of as magnificence: for, as the sun irradiates all the
 heaven with his glory and beauty, even so does magnificence enhance
 the purity and the splendour of every other virtue. I shall therefore
 tell you a story, which, to my thinking, is not a little pretty; and
 which, assuredly, it must be profitable to call to mind.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00010003" />You are to know, then, that, among other honourable knights
 that from days of old even until now have dwelt in our city, one, and
 perchance the worthiest of all, was Messer Ruggieri de' Figiovanni.
  <milestone id="p00010004" />Who, being wealthy and magnanimous, reflecting on the customs and
 manner of life of Tuscany, perceived that by tarrying there he was
 like to find little or no occasion of shewing his mettle, and accordingly
 resolved to pass some time at the court of Alfonso, King of Spain,
 who for the fame of his high qualities was without a peer among the
 potentates of his age. So, being well provided with arms and horses
 and retinue suitable to his rank, he hied him to Spain, where he was
 graciously received by the King.  <milestone id="p00010005" />There tarrying accordingly, Messer
 Ruggieri very soon, as well by the splendid style in which he lived
 as by the prodigious feats of arms that he did, gave folk to know his
 high desert.</p><p>Now, having tarried there some while, and observed the King's
 <pb n="315" />ways with much care, and how he would grant castles, cities, or
 baronies, to this, that, or the other of his subjects, he deemed that
 the King shewed therein but little judgment, seeing that he would
 give them to men that merited them not. And for that nought was
 given to him, he, knowing his merit, deemed himself gravely injured
 in reputation; wherefore he made up his mind to depart the realm,
 and to that end craved license of the King;  <milestone id="p00010006" />which the King granted
 him, and therewith gave him one of the best and finest mules that
 was ever ridden, a gift which Messer Ruggieri, as he had a long
 journey to make, did not a little appreciate.  <milestone id="p00010007" />The King then bade
 one of his discreet domestics contrive, as best he might, to ride with
 Messer Ruggieri on such wise that it might not appear that he did
 so by the King's command, and charge his memory with whatever
 Messer Ruggieri might say of him, so that he might be able to repeat
 it; which done, he was on the very next morning to bid Ruggieri
 return to the King forthwith.  <milestone id="p00010008" />The King's agent was on the
 alert, and no sooner was Ruggieri out of the city, than without any
 manner of difficulty he joined his company, giving out that he was
 going towards Italy.  <milestone id="p00010009" />As thus they rode, talking of divers matters,
 Messer Ruggieri being mounted on the mule given him by the
 King: <q direct="unspecified">Methinks,</q> quoth the other, it being then hard upon
 tierce, <q direct="unspecified">that 'twere well to give the beasts a voidance;</q>  <milestone id="p00010010" />and by and
 by, being come to a convenient place, they voided all the beasts save
 the mule. Then, as they continued their journey, the squire
 hearkening attentively to the knight's words, they came to a river,
 and while there they watered the beasts, the mule made a voidance
 in the stream. Whereat: <q direct="unspecified">Ah, foul fall thee, beast,</q> quoth
 Messer Ruggieri, <q direct="unspecified">that art even as thy master, that gave thee to me!</q>
  <milestone id="p00010011" />Which remark, as also many another that fell from Ruggieri as they
 rode together throughout the day, the squire stored in his memory;
 but never another word did he hear Ruggieri say touching the King,
 that was not laudatory to the last degree.</p><p><milestone id="p00010012" />On the morrow, when they were gotten to horse, and had set
 their faces towards Tuscany, the squire apprised Ruggieri of the
 King's command, and thereupon Ruggieri turned back.  <milestone id="p00010013" />On his
 arrival the King, having already heard what he had said touching the
 mule, gave him gladsome greeting, and asked him wherefore he had
 likened him to the mule, or rather the mule to him.  <milestone id="p00010014" />Whereto
 <pb n="316" />Messer Ruggieri answered frankly: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, I likened you to the
 mule, for that, as you bestow your gifts where 'tis not meet, and
 where meet it were, bestow them not, so the mule where 'twas meet,
 voided not, and where 'twas not meet, voided.</q>  <milestone id="p00010015" /><q direct="unspecified">Messer Ruggieri,</q>
 replied the King, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not because I have not discerned in you a
 knight most good and true, for whose desert no gift were too great,
 that I have not bestowed on you such gifts as I have bestowed upon
 many others, who in comparison of you are nothing worth: the
 fault is none of mine but solely of your fortune, which would not
 suffer me; and that this which I say is true, I will make abundantly
 plain to you.</q>  <milestone id="p00010016" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> returned Messer Ruggieri, <q direct="unspecified">mortified
 am I, not that you gave me no gift, for thereof I had no desire, being
 too rich, but that you made no sign of recognition of my desert;
 however, I deem your explanation sound and honourable, and
 whatever you shall be pleased that I should see, that gladly will I,
 albeit I believe you without attestation.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00010017" />The King then led him into one of the great halls, in which, by
 his preordinance, were two chests closed under lock and key, and, not
 a few others being present, said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Messer Ruggieri, one of
 these chests contains my crown, sceptre and orb, with many a fine
 girdle, buckle, ring, and whatever else of jewellery I possess; the
 other is full of earth: choose then, and whichever you shall choose,
 be it yours; thereby you will discover whether 'tis due to me or to
 your fortune that your deserts have lacked requital.</q>  <milestone id="p00010018" />Such being the
 King's pleasure, Messer Ruggieri chose one of the chests, which at
 the King's command being opened and found to be that which
 contained the earth: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Messer Ruggieri,</q> quoth the King
 with a laugh, <q direct="unspecified">your own eyes may warrant you of the truth of what
 I say touching Fortune; but verily your merit demands that I take
 arms against her in your cause.  <milestone id="p00010019" />I know that you are not minded to
 become a Spaniard, and therefore I shall give you neither castle nor
 city; but that chest, which Fortune denied you, I bestow on you in
 her despite, that you may take it with you to your own country, and
 there with your neighbours justly vaunt yourself of your deserts,
 attested by my gifts.</q>  <milestone id="p00010020" />Messer Ruggieri took the chest, and having
 thanked the King in a manner befitting such a gift, returned therewith,
 well pleased, to Tuscany.</p></div2><pb n="317" /><div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov1002"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00020001" />Ghino di Tacco captures the Abbot of Cluny, cures him of
 a disorder of the stomach, and releases him. The
 abbot, on his return to the court of Rome, reconciles
 Ghino with Pope Boniface, and makes him prior of
 the Hospital.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00020002" />When an end was made of extolling the magnificence shewn by
 King Alfonso towards the Florentine knight, the king, who had
 listened to the story with no small pleasure, bade Elisa follow suit;
 and forthwith Elisa began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00020003" />Dainty my ladies, undeniable it is that
 for a king to be magnificent, and to entreat magnificently one that
 has done him service, is a great matter, and meet for commendation.
 What then shall we say when the tale is of a dignitary of the Church
 that shewed wondrous magnificence towards one whom he might
 well have entreated as an enemy, and not have been blamed by a
 soul?  <milestone id="p00020004" />Assuredly nought else than that what in the king was virtue
 was in the prelate nothing less than a miracle, seeing that for superlative
 greed the clergy, one and all, outdo us women, and wage war
 to the knife upon every form of liberality. And albeit all men are
 by nature prone to avenge their wrongs, 'tis notorious that the clergy,
 however they may preach longsuffering, and commend of all things
 the forgiving of trespasses, are more quick and hot to be avenged
 than the rest of mankind. Now this, to wit, after what manner a
 prelate shewed magnificence, will be made manifest to you in my
 story.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00020005" />Ghino di Tacco, a man redoubtable by reason of his truculence
 and his high-handed deeds, being banished from Siena, and at enmity
 with the Counts of Santa Fiore, raised Radicofani in revolt against
 <pb n="318" />the Church of Rome, and there abiding, harried all the surrounding
 country with his soldiers, plundering all wayfarers.  <milestone id="p00020006" />Now Pope
 Boniface VIII. being at Rome, there came to court the Abbot
 of Cluny, who is reputed one of the wealthiest prelates in the
 world; and having there gotten a disorder of the stomach, he was
 advised by the physicians to go to the baths of Siena, where (they
 averred) he would certainly be cured. So, having obtained the
 Pope's leave, reckless of the bruit of Ghino's exploits, he took the
 road, being attended by a great and well-equipped train of sumpter-horses
 and servants.  <milestone id="p00020007" />Ghino di Tacco, getting wind of his approach,
 spread his nets to such purpose as without the loss of so much as a
 boy to surround the abbot, with all his servants and effects, in a
 strait pass, from which there was no exit. Which done, he sent
 one of his men, the cunningest of them all, with a sufficient retinue to
 the abbot, who most lovingly on Ghino's part besought the abbot to
 come and visit Ghino at the castle.  <milestone id="p00020008" />Whereto the abbot, very wroth,
 made answer that he would none of it, for that nought had he to do
 with Ghino; but that he purposed to continue his journey, and
 would fain see who would hinder him.  <milestone id="p00020009" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> returned the envoy,
 assuming a humble tone, <q direct="unspecified">you are come to a part of the country
 where we have no fear of aught save the might of God, and where
 excommunications and interdicts are one and all under the ban;
 wherefore you were best be pleased to shew yourself agreeable to
 Ghino in this particular.</q>  <milestone id="p00020010" />As they thus spoke, Ghino's soldiers
 shewed themselves on every side, and it being thus manifest to the
 abbot that he and his company were taken prisoners, he, albeit
 mightily incensed, suffered himself with all his train and effects to be
 conducted by the envoy to the castle; where the abbot, being
 alighted, was lodged in a small and very dark and discomfortable
 room, while his retinue, according to their several conditions, were
 provided with comfortable quarters in divers parts of the castle, the
 horses well stabled and all the effects secured, none being in any
 wise tampered with.  <milestone id="p00020011" />Which done, Ghino hied him to the abbot,
 and: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">Ghino, whose guest you are, sends me to
 entreat you to be pleased to inform him of your destination, and the
 purpose of your journey.</q>  <milestone id="p00020012" />The abbot, vailing his pride like a wise
 man, told whither he was bound and for what purpose. Whereupon
 Ghino left him, casting about how he might cure him without a
 <pb n="319" />bath. To which end he kept a great fire ever burning in the little
 chamber, and had it closely guarded, and returned not to the abbot
 until the ensuing morning, when he brought him in a spotless napkin
 two slices of toast and a great beaker of vernaccia of Corniglia, being
 of the abbot's own vintage;  <milestone id="p00020013" />and: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he to the abbot,
 <q direct="unspecified">Ghino, as a young man, made his studies in medicine, and avers that
 he then learned that there is no better treatment for disorder of the
 stomach than that which he will afford you, whereof the matters
 that I bring you are the beginning; wherefore take them and be of
 good cheer.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00020014" />The abbot, being far too hungry to make many words about the
 matter, ate (albeit in high dudgeon) the toast, and drank the vernaccia;
 which done, he enlarged on his wrongs in a high tone, with
 much questioning and perpending; and above all he demanded to see
 Ghino.  <milestone id="p00020015" />Part of what the abbot said Ghino disregarded as of no
 substance, to other part he replied courteously enough; and having
 assured him that Ghino would visit him as soon as might be, he took
 his leave of him; nor did he return until the morrow, when he
 brought him toast and vernaccia in the same quantity as before;
 and so he kept him several days: then, having marked that the
 abbot had eaten some dried beans that he had secretly brought and
 left there of set purpose,  <milestone id="p00020016" />he asked him in Ghino's name how he
 felt in the stomach. <q direct="unspecified">Were I but out of Ghino's hands,</q> replied the
 abbot, <q direct="unspecified">I should feel myself well, indeed: next to which, I desire
 most of all a good breakfast, so excellent a cure have his medicines
 wrought on me.</q>  <milestone id="p00020017" />Whereupon Ghino caused the abbot's servants to
 furnish a goodly chamber with the abbot's own effects, and there
 on the morrow make ready a grand banquet, at which all the abbot's
 suite and not a few of the garrison being assembled, he hied him to
 the abbot, and: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis time you left the infirmary,
 seeing that you now feel yourself well;</q> and so saying, he took him
 by the hand, and led him into the chamber made ready for him, and
 having left him there with his own people, made it his chief concern
 that the banquet should be magnificent.  <milestone id="p00020018" />The abbot's spirits revived
 as he found himself again among his men, with whom he talked a
 while, telling them how he had been entreated, wherewith they
 contrasted the signal honour which they, on the other hand, had,
 one and all, received from Ghino.</p><pb n="320" /><p>Breakfast-time came, and with order meet the abbot and the
 rest were regaled with good viands and good wines, Ghino still
 suffering not the abbot to know who he was.  <milestone id="p00020019" />But when the abbot
 had thus passed several days, Ghino, having first had all his effects
 collected in a saloon, and all his horses, to the poorest jade, in the
 courtyard below, hied him to the abbot and asked him how he felt,
 and if he deemed himself strong enough to ride. The abbot replied
 that he was quite strong enough, and that 'twould be well indeed
 with him, were he once out of Ghino's hands.  <milestone id="p00020020" />Ghino then led him
 into the saloon in which were his effects and all his retinue, and
 having brought him to a window, whence he might see all his horses:
  <milestone id="p00020021" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir Abbot,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">you must know that 'tis not for that he
 has an evil heart, but because, being a gentleman, he is banished from
 his home, and reduced to poverty, and has not a few powerful enemies,
 that in defence of his life and honour, Ghino di Tacco, whom you see
 before you, has become a robber of highways and an enemy to the
 court of Rome.  <milestone id="p00020022" />But such as I am, I have cured you of your malady
 of the stomach, and taking you to be a worthy lord, I purpose not to
 treat you as I would another, from whom, were he in my hands, as
 you are, I should take such part of his goods as I should think fit;
 but I shall leave it to you, upon consideration of my need, to assign
 to me such portion of your goods as you yourself shall determine.
  <milestone id="p00020023" />Here are they before you undiminished and unimpaired, and from
 this window you may see your horses below in the courtyard;
 wherefore take the part or take the whole, as you may see fit, and
 be it at your option to tarry here, or go hence, from this hour
 forth.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00020024" />The abbot marvelled to hear a highway robber speak thus
 liberally, and such was his gratification that his wrath and fierce
 resentment departed from him, nay, were transformed into kindness,
 insomuch that in all cordial amity he hasted to embrace Ghino,
 saying:  <milestone id="p00020025" /><q direct="unspecified">By God I swear, that to gain the friendship of a man such
 I now deem thee to be, I would be content to suffer much greater
 wrong than that which until now, meseemed, thou hadst done me.
 Cursed be Fortune that constrains thee to ply so censurable a trade.</q>
  <milestone id="p00020026" />Which said, he selected a very few things, and none superfluous,
 from his ample store, and having done likewise with the horses, ceded
 all else to Ghino, and hied him back to Rome;  <milestone id="p00020027" />where, seeing him,
 the Pope, who to his great grief had heard of his capture, asked him
 <pb n="321" />what benefit he had gotten from the baths. Whereto the abbot
 made answer with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">Holy Father, I found nearer here than
 the baths a worthy physician who has wrought a most excellent cure
 on me:</q> he then recounted all the circumstances, whereat the Pope
 laughed. Afterwards, still pursuing the topic, the abbot, yielding to
 the promptings of magnificence, asked a favour of the Pope;  <milestone id="p00020028" />who,
 expecting that he would ask somewhat else than he did, liberally
 promised to give him whatever he should demand. Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Holy Father,</q> quoth the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">that which I would crave of you
 is that you restore Ghino di Tacco, my physician, to your favour;
 seeing that among the good men and true and meritorious that I have
 known, he is by no means of the least account. And for the evil life
 that he leads, I impute it to Fortune rather than to him:  <milestone id="p00020029" />change then
 his fortune, by giving him the means whereby he may live in manner
 befitting his rank, and I doubt not that in a little while your
 judgment of him will jump with mine.</q> 
	<milestone id="p00020030" />Whereto the Pope, being
 magnanimous, and an admirer of good men and true, made answer
 that so he would gladly do, if Ghino should prove to be such as the
 abbot said; and that he would have him brought under safe conduct
 to Rome.  <milestone id="p00020031" />Thither accordingly under safe conduct came Ghino, to
 the abbot's great delight; nor had he been long at court before the
 Pope approved his worth, and restored him to his favour, granting
 him a great office, to wit, that of prior of the Hospital, whereof he
 made him knight. Which office he held for the rest of his life,
 being ever a friend and vassal of Holy Church and the Abbot of
 Cluny.</p></div2><pb n="322" /><div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov1003"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00030001" />Mitridanes, holding Nathan in despite by reason of his
 courtesy, journeys with intent to kill him, and falling
 in with him unawares, is advised by him how to
 compass his end. Following his advice, he finds him
 in a copse, and recognizing him, is shame-stricken,
 and becomes his friend.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00030002" />Verily like to a miracle seemed it to all to hear that a prelate
 had
 done aught with magnificence; but when the ladies had made an end
 of their remarks, the king bade Filostrato follow suit; and forthwith
 Filostrato began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00030003" />Noble ladies, great was the magnificence of the
 King of Spain, and perchance a thing unheard-of the magnificence
 of the Abbot of Cluny; but peradventure 'twill seem not a whit less
 marvellous to you to hear of one who, to shew liberality towards
 another, did resolve artfully to yield to him his blood, nay, his very
 life, for which the other thirsted, and had so done, had the other
 chosen to take them, as I shall shew you in a little story.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00030004" />Beyond all question, if we may believe the report of certain
 Genoese, and other folk that have been in those regions, there dwelt
 of yore in the parts of Cathay one Nathan, a man of noble lineage
 and incomparable wealth.  <milestone id="p00030005" />Who, having a seat hard by a road, by
 which whoso would travel from the West eastward, or from the East
 westward, must needs pass, and being magnanimous and liberal, and
 zealous to approve himself such in act, did set on work cunning
 artificers not a few, and cause one of the finest and largest and most
 luxurious palaces that ever were seen, to be there builded and
 furnished in the goodliest manner with all things meet for the
 reception and honourable entertainment of gentlemen.  <milestone id="p00030006" />And so,
 <pb n="323" />keeping a great array of excellent servants, he courteously and
 hospitably did the honours of his house to whoso came and went: in
 which laudable way of life he persevered, until not only the East, but
 well-nigh all the West had heard his fame;  <milestone id="p00030007" />which thus, what time
 he was well-stricken in years, albeit not for that cause grown weary
 of shewing courtesy, reached the ears of one Mitridanes, a young man
 of a country not far distant. Who, knowing himself to be no less
 wealthy than Nathan, grew envious of the renown that he had of his
 good deeds, and resolved to obliterate, or at least to obscure it, by a
 yet greater liberality.  <milestone id="p00030008" />So he had built for himself a palace like that
 of Nathan, of which he did the honours with a lavish courtesy that
 none had ever equalled, to whoso came or went that way; and verily
 in a short while he became famous enough.</p><p><milestone id="p00030009" />Now it so befell that on a day when the young man was all alone
 in the courtyard of the palace, there came in by one of the gates a
 poor woman, who asked of him an alms, and had it; but, not content
 therewith, came again to him by the second gate, and asked another
 alms, and had it, and after the like sort did even unto the twelfth
 time; but, she returning for the thirteenth time: <q direct="unspecified">My good
 woman,</q> quoth Mitridanes, <q direct="unspecified">thou art not a little pertinacious in thy
 begging:</q> howbeit he gave her an alms.  <milestone id="p00030010" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Ah!
 the wondrous liberality of Nathan!</q> quoth the beldam: <q direct="unspecified">thirty-two
 gates are there to his palace, by every one of which I have entered,
 and asking alms of him, was never--for aught he shewed--recognized,
 or refused, and here, though I have entered as yet by but
 thirteen gates, I am recognized and reprimanded.</q> And therewith
 she departed, and returned no more.  <milestone id="p00030011" />Mitridanes, who accounted
 the mention of Nathan's fame an abatement of his own, was kindled
 by her words with a frenzy of wrath, and began thus to commune
 with himself: Alas! when shall I attain to the grandeur of
 Nathan's liberality, to say nought of transcending it, as I would fain,
 seeing that in the veriest trifles I cannot approach him? Of a surety
 my labour is in vain, if I rid not the earth of him: which, since old
 age relieves me not of him, I must forthwith do with mine own
 hands.  <milestone id="p00030012" />And in the flush of his despite up he started, and giving
 none to know of his purpose, got to horse with a small company,
 and after three days arrived at the place where Nathan abode; and
 having enjoined his comrades to make as if they were none of his,
 <pb n="324" />and knew him not, and to go quarter themselves as best they might
 until they had his further orders, he, being thus alone, towards
 evening came upon Nathan, also alone, at no great distance from
 his splendid palace. Nathan was recreating himself by a walk, and
 was very simply clad; so that Mitridanes, knowing him not, asked
 him if he could shew him where Nathan dwelt.  <milestone id="p00030013" /><q direct="unspecified">My son,</q> replied
 Nathan gladsomely, <q direct="unspecified">that can none in these parts better than I;
 wherefore, so it please thee, I will bring thee thither.</q> 
      <milestone id="p00030014" />The young
 man replied that 'twould be mighty agreeable to him, but that, if so
 it might be, he had a mind to be neither known nor seen by Nathan.
 <q direct="unspecified">And herein also,</q> returned Nathan, <q direct="unspecified">since 'tis thy pleasure, I will
 gratify thee.</q>  <milestone id="p00030015" />Whereupon Mitridanes dismounted, and with Nathan,
 who soon engaged him in delightsome discourse, walked to the
 goodly palace. Arrived there Nathan caused one of his servants
 take the young man's horse, and drawing close to him, bade him
 in a whisper to see to it without delay that none in the house should
 tell the young man that he was Nathan: and so 'twas done.</p><p><milestone id="p00030016" />Being come into the palace, Nathan quartered Mitridanes in a
 most goodly chamber, where none saw him but those whom he had
 appointed to wait upon him; and he himself kept him company,
 doing him all possible honour.  <milestone id="p00030017" />Of whom Mitridanes, albeit he
 reverenced him as a father, yet, being thus with him, forbore not to
 ask who he was. Whereto Nathan made answer: <q direct="unspecified">I am a petty
 servant of Nathan: old as I am, I have been with him since my
 childhood, and never has he advanced me to higher office than this
 wherein thou seest me: wherefore, howsoever other folk may praise
 him, little cause have I to do so.</q>  <milestone id="p00030018" />Which words afforded Mitridanes
 some hope of carrying his wicked purpose into effect with more of
 plan and less of risk than had otherwise been possible. By and by
 Nathan very courteously asked him who he was, and what business
 brought him thither; offering him such counsel and aid as he might
 be able to afford him.  <milestone id="p00030019" />Mitridanes hesitated a while to reply: but
 at last he resolved to trust him, and when with no little circumlocution
 he had demanded of him fidelity, counsel and aid, he fully
 discovered to him who he was, and the purpose and motive of his
 coming thither.  <milestone id="p00030020" />Now, albeit to hear Mitridanes thus unfold his
 norrid design caused Nathan no small inward commotion, yet 'twas
 not long before courageously and composedly he thus made answer:
 <pb n="325" /><q direct="unspecified">Noble was thy father, Mitridanes, and thou art minded to shew
 thyself not unworthy of him by this lofty emprise of thine, to wit,
 of being liberal to all comers: and for that thou art envious of
 Nathan's merit I greatly commend thee; for were many envious
 for a like cause, the world, from being a most wretched, would soon
 become a happy place.  <milestone id="p00030021" />Doubt not that I shall keep secret the
 design which thou hast confided to me, for the furtherance whereof
 'tis good advice rather than substantial aid that I have to offer thee.
 Which advice is this.  <milestone id="p00030022" />Hence, perhaps half a mile off, thou mayst
 see a copse, in which almost every morning Nathan is wont to walk,
 taking his pleasure, for quite a long while: 'twill be an easy matter
 for thee to find him there, and deal with him as thou mayst be
 minded.  <milestone id="p00030023" />Now, shouldst thou slay him, thou wilt get thee home with
 less risk of let, if thou take not the path by which thou camest
 hither, but that which thou seest issue from the copse on the left,
 for, though 'tis somewhat more rough, it leads more directly to thy
 house, and will be safer for thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030024" />Possessed of this information, Mitridanes, when Nathan had left
 him, privily apprised his comrades, who were likewise lodged in the
 palace, of the place where they were to await him on the ensuing
 day; which being come, Nathan, inflexibly determined to act in all
 respects according to the advice which he had given Mitridanes,
 hied him forth to the copse unattended, to meet his death.  <milestone id="p00030025" />Mitridanes,
 being risen, took his bow and sword, for other arms he had
 none with him, mounted his horse, and rode to the copse, through
 which, while he was yet some way off, he saw Nathan passing, quite
 alone. And being minded, before he fell upon him, to see his face
 and hear the sound of his voice, as, riding at a smart pace, he came
 up with him, he laid hold of him by his head-gear, exclaiming:
 <q direct="unspecified">Greybeard, thou art a dead man.</q>  <milestone id="p00030026" />Whereto Nathan answered
 nought but: <q direct="unspecified">Then 'tis but my desert.</q>  <milestone id="p00030027" />But Mitridanes, hearing
 the voice, and scanning the face, forthwith knew him for the same
 man that had welcomed him heartily, consorted with him familiarly,
 and counselled him faithfully; whereby his wrath presently subsided,
 and gave place to shame. Wherefore, casting away the sword that
 he held drawn in act to strike, he sprang from his horse, and weeping,
 threw himself at Nathan's feet, saying:  <milestone id="p00030028" /><q direct="unspecified">Your liberality, dearest
 father, I acknowledge to be beyond all question, seeing with what
 craft you did plot your coming hither to yield me your life, for
 <pb n="326" />which, by mine own avowal, you knew that I, albeit cause I had
 none, did thirst. But God, more regardful of my duty than I
 myself, has now, in this moment of supreme stress, opened the eyes
 of my mind, that wretched envy had fast sealed.  <milestone id="p00030029" />The prompter
 was your compliance, the greater is the debt of penitence that I owe
 you for my fault; wherefore wreak even such vengeance upon me
 as you may deem answerable to my transgression.</q>  <milestone id="p00030030" />But Nathan
 raised Mitridanes to his feet, and tenderly embraced him, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">My son, thy enterprise, howsoever thou mayst denote it, whether
 evil or otherwise, was not such that thou shouldst crave, or I give,
 pardon thereof; for 'twas not in malice but in that thou wouldst
 fain have been reputed better than I that thou ensuedst it.  <milestone id="p00030031" />Doubt
 then no more of me; nay, rest assured that none that lives bears
 thee such love as I, who know the loftiness of thy spirit, bent not
 to heap up wealth, as do the caitiffs, but to dispense in bounty thine
 accumulated store.  <milestone id="p00030032" />Think it no shame that to enhance thy reputation
 thou wouldst have slain me; nor deem that I marvel thereat.
 To slay not one man, as thou wast minded, but countless multitudes,
 to waste whole countries with fire, and to raze cities to the ground
 has been well-nigh the sole art, by which the mightiest emperors and
 the greatest kings have extended their dominions, and by consequence
 their fame. Wherefore, if thou, to increase thy fame, wouldst fain
 have slain me, 'twas nothing marvellous or strange, but wonted.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030033" />Whereto Mitridanes made answer, not to excuse his wicked
 design, but to commend the seemly excuse found for it by Nathan,
 whom at length he told how beyond measure he marvelled that
 Nathan had not only been consenting to the enterprise, but had
 aided him therein by his counsel. But Nathan answered:  <milestone id="p00030034" /><q direct="unspecified">Liefer
 had I, Mitridanes, that thou didst not marvel either at my consent
 or at my counsel, for that, since I was my own master and of a mind
 to that emprise whereon thou art also bent, never a soul came to my
 house, but, so far as in me lay, I gave him all that he asked of me.
  <milestone id="p00030035" />Thou camest, lusting for my life; and so, when I heard thee crave
 it of me, I forthwith, that thou mightst not be the only guest to
 depart hence ill content, resolved to give it thee; and to that end I
 gave thee such counsel as I deemed would serve thee both to the
 taking of my life and the preservation of thine own. Wherefore
 yet again I bid thee, nay, I entreat thee, if so thou art minded, to
 take it for thy satisfaction: I know not how I could better bestow
 <pb n="327" />it.  <milestone id="p00030036" />I have had the use of it now for some eighty years, and
 pleasure and solace thereof; and I know that, by the course of
 Nature and the common lot of man and all things mundane, it can
 continue to be mine for but a little while; and so I deem that 'twere
 much better to bestow it, as I have ever bestowed and dispensed my
 wealth, than to keep it, until, against my will, it be reft from me by
 Nature.  <milestone id="p00030037" />'Twere but a trifle, though 'twere a hundred years: how
 insignificant, then, the six or eight years that are all I have to give!
 Take it, then, if thou hadst lief, take it, I pray thee; for, long as
 I have lived here, none have I found but thee to desire it; nor know
 I when I may find another, if thou take it not, to demand it of me.
  <milestone id="p00030038" />And if, peradventure, I should find one such, yet I know that the
 longer I keep it, the less its worth will be; wherefore, ere it be thus
 cheapened, take it, I implore thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030039" />Sore shame-stricken, Mitridanes made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Now God
 forefend that I should so much as harbour, as but now I did, such a
 thought, not to say do such a deed, as to wrest from you a thing
 so precious as your life, the years whereof, so far from abridging, I
 would gladly supplement with mine own.</q>  <milestone id="p00030040" /><q direct="unspecified">So then,</q> rejoined
 Nathan promptly, <q direct="unspecified">thou wouldst, if thou couldst, add thy years to
 mine, and cause me to serve thee as I never yet served any man, to
 wit, to take from thee that which is thine, I that never took aught
	from a soul!</q> <milestone id="p00030041" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, that would I,</q> returned Mitridanes.  
<milestone id="p00030042" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q>
 quoth Nathan, <q direct="unspecified">do as I shall bid thee. Thou art young: tarry
 here in my house, and call thyself Nathan; and I will get me to
 thy house, and ever call myself Mitridanes.</q>  <milestone id="p00030043" />Whereto Mitridanes
 made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Were I but able to discharge this trust, as you
 have been and are, scarce would I hesitate to accept your offer; but,
 as too sure am I that aught that I might do would but serve to
 lower Nathan's fame, and I am not minded to mar that in another
 which I cannot mend in myself, accept it I will not.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030044" />After which and the like interchange of delectable discourse,
 Nathan and Mitridanes, by Nathan's desire, returned to the palace;
 where Nathan for some days honourably entreated Mitridanes, and
 by his sage counsel confirmed and encouraged him in his high and
 noble resolve; after which, Mitridanes, being minded to return
 home with his company, took his leave of Nathan, fully persuaded
 that 'twas not possible to surpass him in liberality.</p></div2><pb n="328" /><div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov1004"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00040001" />Messer Gentile de' Carisendi, being come from Modena,
 disinters a lady that he loves, who has been buried for
 dead. She, being reanimated, gives birth to a male
 child; and Messer Gentile restores her, with her son,
 to Niccoluccio Caccianimico, her husband.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00040002" />A thing marvellous seemed it to all that for liberality a man
 should be ready to sacrifice his own life; and herein they averred
 that Nathan had without doubt left the King of Spain and the Abbot
 of Cluny behind. However, when they had discussed the matter
 diversely and at large, the king, bending his regard on Lauretta,
 signified to her his will that she should tell; and forthwith, accordingly,
 Lauretta began:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00040003" />Goodly matters are they and magnificent that
 have been recounted to you, young ladies; nay, so much of our
 field of discourse is already filled by their grandeur, that for us that
 are yet to tell, there is, methinks, no room left, unless we seek our
 topic there where matter of discourse germane to every theme does
 most richly abound, to wit, in the affairs of love.  <milestone id="p00040004" />For which cause,
 as also for that our time of life cannot but make us especially
 inclinable thereto, I am minded that my story shall be of a feat of
 magnificence done by a lover: which, all things considered, will,
 peradventure, seem to you inferior to none that have been shewn
 you; so it be true that to possess the beloved one, men will part
 with their treasures, forget their enmities, and jeopardize their own
 lives, their honour and their reputation, in a thousand ways.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00040005" />Know, then, that at Bologna, that most famous city of Lombardy,
 there dwelt a knight, Messer Gentile Carisendi by name, worshipful
 alike for his noble lineage and his native worth: who in his youth,
 <pb n="329" />being enamoured of a young gentlewoman named Madonna Catalina,
 wife of one Niccoluccio Caccianimico, and well-nigh despairing, for
 that the lady gave him but a sorry requital of his love, betook him
 to Modena, being called thither as Podest&#224;.  <milestone id="p00040006" />Now what time he
 was there, Niccoluccio being also away from Bologna, and his lady
 gone, for that she was with child, to lie in at a house she had some
 three miles or so from the city, it befell that she was suddenly
 smitten with a sore malady of such and so virulent a quality that it
 left no sign of life in her, so that the very physicians pronounced her
 dead.  <milestone id="p00040007" />And for that the women that were nearest of kin to her
 professed to have been told by her, that she was not so far gone in
 pregnancy that the child could be perfectly formed, they, without
 more ado, laid her in a tomb in a neighbouring church, and after
 long lamentation closed it upon her.</p><p><milestone id="p00040008" />Whereof Messer Gentile being forthwith apprised by one of his
 friends, did, for all she had been most niggardly to him of her favour,
 grieve not a little, and at length fell a communing with himself on
 this wise: So, Madonna Catalina, thou art dead! While thou
 livedst, never a glance of thine might I have; wherefore, now that
 thou art dead, 'tis but right that I go take a kiss from thee.  <milestone id="p00040009" />'Twas
 night while he thus mused; and forthwith, observing strict secrecy
 in his departure, he got him to horse with a single servant, and
 halted not until he was come to the place where the lady was interred;
 and having opened the tomb he cautiously entered it. Then, having
 lain down beside her, he set his face against hers; and again and
 again, weeping profusely the while, he kissed it.  <milestone id="p00040010" />But as 'tis matter
 of common knowledge that the desires of men, and more especially
 of lovers, know no bounds, but crave ever an ampler satisfaction;
 even so Messer Gentile, albeit he had been minded to tarry there
 no longer, now said to himself: Wherefore touch I not her bosom
 a while? I have never yet touched it, nor shall I ever touch it
 again.  <milestone id="p00040011" />Obeying which impulse, he laid his hand on her bosom, and
 keeping it there some time, felt, as he thought, her heart faintly
 beating.  <milestone id="p00040012" />Whereupon, banishing all fear, and examining the body
 with closer attention, he discovered that life was not extinct, though
 he judged it but scant and flickering: and so, aided by his servant,
 he bore her, as gently as he might, out of the tomb; and set her
 before him upon his horse, and brought her privily to his house at
 <pb n="330" />Bologna,  <milestone id="p00040013" />where dwelt his wise and worthy mother, who, being fully
 apprised by him of the circumstances, took pity on the lady, and had
 a huge fire kindled, and a bath made ready, whereby she restored
 her to life. Whereof the first sign she gave was to heave a great
 sigh, and murmur: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! where am I?</q>  <milestone id="p00040014" />To which the worthy
 lady made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Be of good cheer; thou art well lodged.</q>
  <milestone id="p00040015" />By and by the lady, coming to herself, looked about her; and finding
 herself she knew not where, and seeing Messer Gentile before her,
 was filled with wonder, and besought his mother to tell her how she
 came to be there.</p><p>Messer Gentile thereupon told her all.  <milestone id="p00040016" />Sore distressed thereat,
 the lady, after a while, thanked him as best she might; after which
 she besought him by the love that he had borne her, and of his
 courtesy, that she might, while she tarried in his house, be spared
 aught that could impair her honour and her husband's; and that at
 daybreak he would suffer her to return home.  <milestone id="p00040017" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied
 Messer Gentile, <q direct="unspecified">however I did affect you in time past, since God
 in His goodness has, by means of the love I bore you, restored you
 to me alive, I mean not now, or at any time hereafter, to entreat
 you either here or elsewhere, save as a dear sister;  <milestone id="p00040018" />but yet the
 service I have to-night rendered you merits some guerdon: and
 therefore lief had I that you deny me not a favour which I shall ask
 of you.</q>  <milestone id="p00040019" />Whereto the lady graciously made answer that she would
 be prompt to grant it, so only it were in her power, and consonant
 with her honour. Said then Messer Gentile: <q direct="unspecified">Your kinsfolk,
 Madam, one and all, nay, all the folk in Bologna are fully persuaded
 that you are dead: there is therefore none to expect you at home:
 wherefore the favour I crave of you is this, that you will be pleased
 to tarry privily here with my mother, until such time--which will
 be speedily--as I return from Modena.  <milestone id="p00040020" />And 'tis for that I purpose
 to make solemn and joyous donation of you to your husband in
 presence of the most honourable folk of this city that I ask of you
 this grace.</q>  <milestone id="p00040021" />Mindful of what she owed the knight, and witting
 that what he craved was seemly, the lady, albeit she yearned not a
 little to gladden her kinsfolk with the sight of her in the flesh, consented
 to do as Messer Gentile besought her, and thereto pledged
 him her faith.  <milestone id="p00040022" />And scarce had she done so, when she felt that the
 hour of her travail was come; and so, tenderly succoured by Messer
 <pb n="331" />Gentile's mother, she not long after gave birth to a fine boy. Which
 event did mightily enhance her own and Messer Gentile's happiness.
 Then, having made all meet provision for her, and left word that
 she was to be tended as if she were his own wife, Messer Gentile,
 observing strict secrecy, returned to Modena.</p><p><milestone id="p00040023" />His time of office there ended, in anticipation of his return to
 Bologna, he appointed for the morning of his arrival in the city a
 great and goodly banquet at his house, whereto were bidden not a
 few of the gentlemen of Bologna, and among them Niccoluccio
 Caccianimico. Whom, when he was returned and dismounted, he
 found awaiting him, as also the lady, fairer and more healthful than
 ever, and her little son doing well; and so with a gladness beyond
 compare he ranged his guests at table, and regaled them with many
 a course magnificently served.  <milestone id="p00040024" />And towards the close of the feast,
 having premonished the lady of his intention, and concerted with
 her how she should behave, thus he spoke: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, I mind
 me to have once heard tell of (as I deem it) a delightsome custom
 which they have in Persia; to wit, that, when one would do his
 friend especial honour, he bids him to his house, and there shews him
 that treasure, be it wife, or mistress, or daughter, or what not, that
 he holds most dear; assuring him that yet more gladly, were it
 possible, he would shew him his heart. Which custom I am minded
 to observe here in Bologna.  <milestone id="p00040025" />You, of your courtesy, have honoured
 my feast with your presence, and I propose to do you honour in the
 Persian fashion, by shewing you that which in all the world I do,
 and must ever, hold most dear. But before I do so, tell me, I pray
 you, how you conceive of a nice question that I shall lay before you.
	  <milestone id="p00040026" />Suppose that one has in his house a good and most faithful servant,
 who falls sick of a grievous disorder; and that the master tarries not
 for the death of the servant, but has him borne out into the open
 street, and concerns himself no more with him: that then a stranger
 comes by, is moved to pity of the sick man, and takes him to his
 house, and by careful tendance and at no small cost restores him to
 his wonted health.  <milestone id="p00040027" />Now I would fain know whether the first
 master has in equity any just cause to complain of or be aggrieved
 with the second master, if he retain the servant in his employ, and
 refuse to restore him, when so required.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00040028" />The gentlemen discussed the matter after divers fashions, and
 <pb n="332" />all agreed in one sentence, which they committed to Niccoluccio
 Caccianimico, for that he was an eloquent and accomplished speaker,
 to deliver on the part of them all.  <milestone id="p00040029" />Niccoluccio began by commending
 the Persian custom: after which he said that he and the others were
 all of the same opinion, to wit, that the first master had no longer
 any right in his servant, since he had not only abandoned but cast
 him forth; and that by virtue of the second master's kind usage of
 him he must be deemed to have become his servant; wherefore, by
 keeping him, he did the first master no mischief, no violence, no
 wrong. Whereupon the rest that were at the table said, one and all,
 being worthy men, that their judgment jumped with Niccoluccio's
 answer.  <milestone id="p00040030" />The knight, well pleased with the answer, and that 'twas
 Niccoluccio that gave it, affirmed that he was of the same opinion;
 adding: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis now time that I shew you that honour which I
 promised you.</q> He then called two of his servants, and sent them
 to the lady, whom he had caused to be apparelled and adorned with
 splendour, charging them to pray her to be pleased to come and
 gladden the gentlemen with her presence.  <milestone id="p00040031" />So she, bearing in her
 arms her most lovely little son, came, attended by the two servants,
 into the saloon, and by the knight's direction, took a seat beside a
 worthy gentleman: whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> quoth the knight,
 <q direct="unspecified">this is the treasure that I hold, and mean ever to hold, more dear
 than aught else. Behold, and judge whether I have good cause.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00040032" />The gentlemen said not a little in her honour and praise, averring
 that the knight ought indeed to hold her dear: then, as they
 regarded her more attentively, there were not a few that would have
 pronounced her to be the very woman that she was, had they not
 believed that woman to be dead. But none scanned her so closely as
 Niccoluccio, who, the knight being withdrawn a little space, could
 no longer refrain his eager desire to know who she might be, but
 asked her whether she were of Bologna, or from other parts.  <milestone id="p00040033" />The
 lady, hearing her husband's voice, could scarce forbear to answer;
 but yet, not to disconcert the knight's plan, she kept silence.
 Another asked her if that was her little boy; and yet another, if she
 were Messer Gentile's wife, or in any other wise his connection. To
 none of whom she vouchsafed an answer.  <milestone id="p00040034" />Then, Messer Gentile
 coming up: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth one of the guests, <q direct="unspecified">this treasure of
 yours is goodly indeed; but she seems to be dumb: is she so?</q>
 <pb n="333" /> <milestone id="p00040035" /><q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> quoth Messer Gentile, <q direct="unspecified">that she has not as yet
 spoken is no small evidence of her virtue.</q>  <milestone id="p00040036" /><q direct="unspecified">Then tell us, you, who she
 is,</q> returned the other.  <milestone id="p00040037" /><q direct="unspecified">That,</q> quoth the knight, <q direct="unspecified">will I right
 gladly, so you but promise me, that, no matter what I may say, none
 of you will stir from his place, until I have ended my story.</q>  <milestone id="p00040038" />All
 gave the required promise, and when the tables had been cleared,
 Messer Gentile, being seated beside the lady, thus spoke:
 <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, this lady is that loyal and faithful servant, touching
 whom a brief while ago I propounded to you my question, whom her
 own folk held none too dear, but cast out into the open street as a
 thing vile and no longer good for aught, but I took thence, and by
 my careful tendance wrested from the clutch of death; whom God,
 regardful of my good will, has changed from the appalling aspect of
 a corpse to the thing of beauty that you see before you.  <milestone id="p00040039" />But for
 your fuller understanding of this occurrence, I will briefly explain it
 to you.</q>  <milestone id="p00040040" />He then recounted to them in detail all that had happened
 from his first becoming enamoured of the lady to that very hour;
 whereto they hearkened with no small wonder; after which:
 <q direct="unspecified">And so,</q> he added, <q direct="unspecified">unless you, and more especially Niccoluccio,
 are now of another opinion than you were a brief while ago, the
 lady rightly belongs to me, nor can any man lawfully reclaim her
 of me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00040041" />None answered, for all were intent to hear what more he would
 say. But, while Niccoluccio, and some others that were there, wept
 for sympathy, Messer Gentile stood up, and took the little boy in his
 arms and the lady by the hand, and approached Niccoluccio, saying:
  <milestone id="p00040042" /><q direct="unspecified">Rise, my gossip: I do not, indeed, restore thee thy wife, whom thy
 kinsfolk and hers cast forth; but I am minded to give thee this lady,
 my gossip, with this her little boy, whom I know well to be thy son,
 and whom I held at the font, and named Gentile:  <milestone id="p00040043" />and I pray thee that
 she be not the less dear to thee for that she has tarried three months
 in my house; for I swear to thee by that God, who, peradventure,
 ordained that I should be enamoured of her, to the end that my love
 might be, as it has been, the occasion of her restoration to life, that
 never with her father, or her mother, or with thee, did she live more
 virtuously than with my mother in my house.</q>  <milestone id="p00040044" />Which said, he
 turned to the lady, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, I now release you from all
 promises made to me, and so deliver you to Niccoluccio.</q> Then,
 <pb n="334" />leaving the lady and the child in Niccoluccio's embrace, he returned
 to his seat.</p><p><milestone id="p00040045" />Thus to receive his wife and son was to Niccoluccio a delight
 great in the measure of its remoteness from his hope. Wherefore in
 the most honourable terms at his command he thanked the knight,
 whom all the rest, weeping for sympathy, greatly commended for
 what he had done, as did also all that heard thereof.  <milestone id="p00040046" />The lady,
 welcomed home with wondrous cheer, was long a portent to the
 Bolognese, who gazed on her as on one raised from the dead.
 Messer Gentile lived ever after as the friend of Niccoluccio, and his
 and the lady's kinsfolk.</p><p><milestone id="p00040047" />Now what shall be your verdict, gracious ladies? A king's largess,
 though it was of his sceptre and crown, an abbot's reconciliation,
 at no cost to himself, of a malefactor with the Pope, or an old man's
 submission of his throat to the knife of his enemy--will you adjudge
 that such acts as these are comparable to the deed of Messer Gentile?
  <milestone id="p00040048" />Who, though young, and burning with passion, and deeming himself
 justly entitled to that which the heedlessness of another had discarded,
 and he by good fortune had recovered, not only tempered his ardour
 with honour, but having that which with his whole soul he had long
 been bent on wresting from another, did with liberality restore it.
 Assuredly none of the feats aforesaid seem to me like unto this.</p></div2><pb n="335" /><div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov1005"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00050001" />Madonna Dianora craves of Messer Ansaldo a garden
 that shall be as fair in January as in May. Messer
 Ansaldo binds himself to a necromancer, and thereby
 gives her the garden. Her husband gives her leave
 to do Messer Ansaldo's pleasure: he, being apprised
 of her husband's liberality, releases her from her
 promise; and the necromancer releases Messer Ansaldo
 from his bond, and will take nought of his.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00050002" />Each of the gay company had with superlative commendation
 extolled Messer Gentile to the skies, when the king bade Emilia
 follow suit; and with a good courage, as burning to speak, thus
 Emilia began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00050003" />Delicate my ladies, none can justly say that 'twas
 not magnificently done of Messer Gentile; but if it be alleged that
 'twas the last degree of magnificence, 'twill perchance not be
 difficult to shew that more was possible, as is my purpose in the little
 story that I shall tell you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00050004" />In Friuli, a country which, though its air is shrewd, is pleasantly
 diversified by fine mountains and not a few rivers and clear
 fountains, is a city called Udine, where dwelt of yore a fair and
 noble lady, Madonna Dianora by name, wife of a wealthy grandee
 named Giliberto, a very pleasant gentleman, and debonair. Now
 this lady, for her high qualities, was in the last degree beloved by
 a great and noble baron, Messer Ansaldo Gradense by name, a
 man of no little consequence, and whose fame for feats of arms and
 courtesy was spread far and wide.  <milestone id="p00050005" />But, though with all a lover's
 ardour he left nought undone that he might do to win her love, and
 to that end frequently plied her with his ambassages, 'twas all in
 <pb n="336" />vain. And the lady being distressed by his importunity, and chat,
 refuse as she might all that he asked of her, he none the less
 continued to love her and press his suit upon her, bethought her how
 she might rid herself of him by requiring of him an extraordinary
 and, as she deemed, impossible feat.  <milestone id="p00050006" />So one day, a woman that came
 oftentimes from him to her being with her: <q direct="unspecified">Good woman,</q>
 quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">thou hast many a time affirmed that Messer Ansaldo
 loves me above all else; and thou hast made proffer to me on his
 part of wondrous rich gifts which I am minded he keep to himself,
 for that I could never bring myself to love him or pleasure him for
 their sake; but, if I might be certified that he loves me as
 much as thou sayst, then without a doubt I should not fail to love
 him, and do his pleasure; wherefore, so he give me the assurance
 that I shall require, I shall be at his command.</q>  <milestone id="p00050007" /><q direct="unspecified">What is it,
 Madam,</q> returned the good woman, <q direct="unspecified">that you would have him do?</q>
  <milestone id="p00050008" /><q direct="unspecified">This,</q> replied the lady; <q direct="unspecified">I would have this next ensuing January,
 hard by this city, a garden full of green grass and flowers and
 flowering trees, just as if it were May; and if he cannot provide me
 with this garden, bid him never again send either thee or any other
 to me, for that, should he harass me any further, I shall no longer
 keep silence, as I have hitherto done, but shall make my complaint
 to my husband and all my kinsmen, and it shall go hard but I will be
 quit of him.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00050009" />The gentleman being apprised of his lady's stipulation and
 promise, notwithstanding that he deemed it no easy matter, nay, a
 thing almost impossible, to satisfy her, and knew besides that 'twas
 but to deprive him of all hope that she made the demand, did nevertheless
 resolve to do his endeavour to comply with it, and causing
 search to be made in divers parts of the world, if any he might find
 to afford him counsel or aid, he lit upon one, who for a substantial
 reward offered to do the thing by necromancy.  <milestone id="p00050010" />So Messer Ansaldo,
 having struck the bargain with him for an exceeding great sum of
 money, gleefully expected the appointed time. Which being come
 with extreme cold, insomuch that there was nought but snow and
 ice, the adept on the night before the calends of January wrought
 with his spells to such purpose that on the morrow, as was averred by
 eye-witnesses, there appeared in a meadow hard by the city one of
 the most beautiful gardens that was ever seen, with no lack of grass
 <pb n="337" />and trees and fruits of all sorts.  <milestone id="p00050011" />At sight whereof Messer Ansaldo
 was overjoyed, and caused some of the finest fruits and flowers that
 it contained to be gathered, and privily presented to his lady, whom
 he bade come and see the garden that she had craved, that thereby
 she might have assurance of his love, and mind her of the promise
 that she had given him and confirmed with an oath, and, as a loyal
 lady, take thought for its performance.  <milestone id="p00050012" />When she saw the flowers
 and fruits, the lady, who had already heard not a few folk speak of
 the wondrous garden, began to repent her of her promise. But for
 all that, being fond of strange sights, she hied her with many other
 ladies of the city to see the garden, and having gazed on it with
 wonderment, and commended it not a little, she went home the
 saddest woman alive, bethinking her to what it bound her:  <milestone id="p00050013" />and so
 great was her distress that she might not well conceal it; but, being
 written on her face, 'twas marked by her husband, who was minded
 by all means to know the cause thereof.</p><p>The lady long time kept silence: but at last she yielded to his
 urgency, and discovered to him the whole matter from first to last.
  <milestone id="p00050014" />Whereat Giliberto was at first very wroth; but on second thoughts,
 considering the purity of the lady's purpose, he was better advised,
 and dismissing his anger: <q direct="unspecified">Dianora,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not the act
 of a discreet or virtuous lady to give ear to messages of such a sort,
 nor to enter into any compact touching her chastity with any man
 on any terms. Words that the ears convey to the heart have a
 potency greater than is commonly supposed, and there is scarce
 aught that lovers will not find possible.  <milestone id="p00050015" />'Twas then ill done of thee
 in the first instance to hearken, as afterwards to make the compact;
 but, for that I know the purity of thy soul, that thou mayst be quit
 of thy promise, I will grant thee that which, perchance, no other man
 would grant, being also swayed thereto by fear of the necromancer,
 whom Messer Ansaldo, shouldst thou play him false, might, peradventure,
 cause to do us a mischief.  <milestone id="p00050016" />I am minded, then, that thou
 go to him, and contrive, if on any wise thou canst, to get thee quit of
 this promise without loss of virtue; but if otherwise it may not be,
 then for the nonce thou mayst yield him thy body, but not thy soul.</q>
  <milestone id="p00050017" />Whereat the lady, weeping, would none of such a favour at her
 husband's hands. But Giliberto, for all the lady's protestations, was
 minded that so it should be.</p><pb n="338" /><p>Accordingly, on the morrow about dawn, apparelled none too
 ornately, preceded by two servants and followed by a chambermaid,
 the lady hied her to Messer Ansaldo's house.  <milestone id="p00050018" />Apprised that his lady
 was come to see him, Messer Ansaldo, marvelling not a little, rose,
 and having called the necromancer: <q direct="unspecified">I am minded,</q> quoth he,
 <q direct="unspecified">that thou see what goodly gain I have gotten by thine art.</q> And
 the twain having met the lady, Ansaldo gave way to no unruly
 appetite, but received her with a seemly obeisance; and then the
 three repaired to a goodly chamber, where there was a great fire, and
 having caused the lady to be seated, thus spoke Ansaldo:  <milestone id="p00050019" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,
 if the love that I have so long borne you merit any guerdon, I pray
 you that it be not grievous to you to discover to me the true occasion
 of your coming to me at this hour, and thus accompanied.</q>  <milestone id="p00050020" />Shamefast,
 and the tears all but standing in her eyes, the lady made
 answer: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, 'tis neither love that I bear you, nor faith that I
 pledged you, that brings me hither, but the command of my husband,
 who, regarding rather the pains you have had of your unbridled
 passion than his own or my honour, has sent me hither; and for that
 he commands it, I, for the nonce, am entirely at your pleasure.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00050021" />If Messer Ansaldo had marvelled to hear of the lady's coming,
 he now marvelled much more, and touched by Giliberto's liberality,
 and passing from passion to compassion:  <milestone id="p00050022" /><q direct="unspecified">Now, God forbid,
 Madam,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that, it being as you say, I should wound the
 honour of him that has compassion on my love; wherefore, no
 otherwise than as if you were my sister shall you abide here, while
 you are so minded, and be free to depart at your pleasure; nor crave
 I aught of you but that you shall convey from me to your husband
 such thanks as you shall deem meet for courtesy such as his has been,
 and entreat me ever henceforth as your brother and servant.</q>
  <milestone id="p00050023" />Whereat overjoyed in the last degree: <q direct="unspecified">Nought,</q> quoth the lady,
 <q direct="unspecified">by what I noted of your behaviour, could ever have caused me to
 anticipate other sequel of my coming hither than this which I see is
 your will, and for which I shall ever be your debtor.</q> She then
 took her leave, and, attended by a guard of honour, returned to
 Giliberto, and told him what had passed; between whom and Messer
 Ansaldo there was thenceforth a most close and loyal friendship.</p><p><milestone id="p00050024" />Now the liberality shewn by Giliberto towards Messer Ansaldo,
 and by Messer Ansaldo towards the lady, having been marked by
 <pb n="339" />the necromancer, when Messer Ansaldo made ready to give him the
 promised reward: <q direct="unspecified">Now God forbid,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that, as I have
 seen Giliberto liberal in regard of his honour, and you liberal in
 regard of your love, I be not in like manner liberal in regard of my
 reward, which accordingly, witting that 'tis in good hands, I am
 minded that you keep.</q>  <milestone id="p00050025" />The knight was abashed, and strove hard
 to induce him to take, if not the whole, at least a part of the money;
 but finding that his labour was in vain, and that the necromancer,
 having caused his garden to vanish after the third day, was minded
 to depart, he bade him adieu. And the carnal love he had borne
 the lady being spent, he burned for her thereafter with a flame of
 honourable affection.  <milestone id="p00050026" />Now what shall be our verdict in this case,
 lovesome ladies? A lady, as it were dead, and a love grown lukewarm
 for utter hopelessness! Shall we set a liberality shewn in such
 a case above this liberality of Messer Ansaldo, loving yet as ardently,
 and hoping, perchance, yet more ardently than ever, and holding
 in his hands the prize that he had so long pursued? Folly indeed
 should I deem it to compare that liberality with this.</p></div2><pb n="340" /><div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov1006"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00060001" />King Charles the Old, being conqueror, falls in love with
 a young maiden, and afterward growing ashamed of
 his folly bestows her and her sister honourably in
 marriage.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00060002" />Who might fully recount with what diversity of argument the
 ladies debated which of the three, Giliberto, or Messer Ansaldo, or
 the necromancer, behaved with the most liberality in the affair of
 Madonna Dianora? Too long were it to tell. However, when the
 king had allowed them to dispute a while, he, with a glance at
 Fiammetta, bade her rescue them from their wrangling by telling her
 story. Fiammetta made no demur, but thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00060003" />Illustrious my
 ladies, I have ever been of opinion that in companies like ours one
 should speak so explicitly that the import of what is said should
 never by excessive circumscription afford matter for disputation;
 which is much more in place among students in the schools, than
 among us, whose powers are scarce adequate to the management of
 the distaff and the spindle.  <milestone id="p00060004" />Wherefore I, that had in mind a matter
 of, perchance, some nicety, now that I see you all at variance
 touching the matters last mooted, am minded to lay it aside, and
 tell you somewhat else, which concerns a man by no means of slight
 account, but a valiant king, being a chivalrous action that he did,
 albeit in no wise thereto actuated by his honour.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00060005" />There is none of you but may not seldom have heard tell of King
 Charles the Old, or the First, by whose magnificent emprise, and the
 ensuing victory gained over King Manfred, the Ghibellines were driven
 forth of Florence, and the Guelfs returned thither. For which cause a
 knight, Messer Neri degli Uberti by name, departing Florence with
 <pb n="341" />his household and not a little money, resolved to fix his abode under
 no
 other sway than that of King Charles.  <milestone id="p00060006" />And being fain of a lonely
 place in which to end his days in peace, he betook him to Castello
 da Mare di Stabia; and there, perchance a cross-bow-shot from the
 other houses of the place, amid the olives and hazels and chestnuts
 that abound in those parts, he bought an estate, on which he built a
 goodly house and commodious, with a pleasant garden beside it, in the
 midst of which, having no lack of running water, he set, after our
 Florentine fashion, a pond fair and clear, and speedily filled it with
 fish.  <milestone id="p00060007" />And while thus he lived, daily occupying himself with nought
 else but how to make his garden more fair, it befell that King
 Charles in the hot season betook him to Castello da Mare to refresh
 himself a while, and hearing of the beauty of Messer Neri's garden,
 was desirous to view it. And having learned to whom it belonged,
 he bethought him that, as the knight was an adherent of the party
 opposed to him, he would use more familiarity towards him than he
 would otherwise have done; and so he sent him word that he and
 four comrades would sup privily with him in his garden on the
 ensuing evening.  <milestone id="p00060008" />Messer Neri felt himself much honoured; and
 having made his preparations with magnificence, and arranged the
 order of the ceremonies with his household, did all he could and
 knew to make the King cordially welcome to his fair garden.</p><p><milestone id="p00060009" />When the King had viewed the garden throughout, as also Messer
 Neri's house, and commended them, he washed, and seated himself at
 one of the tables, which were set beside the pond, and bade Count
 Guy de Montfort, who was one of his companions, sit on one side
 of him, and Messer Neri on the other, and the other three to
 serve, as they should be directed by Messer Neri.  <milestone id="p00060010" />The dishes that
 were set before them were dainty, the wines excellent and rare, the
 order of the repast very fair and commendable, without the least
 noise or aught else that might distress; whereon the King bestowed
 no stinted praise.  <milestone id="p00060011" />As thus he gaily supped, well-pleased with the
 lovely spot, there came into the garden two young maidens, each
 perhaps fifteen years old, blonde both, their golden tresses falling all
 in ringlets about them, and crowned with a dainty garland of
 periwinkle-flowers; and so delicate and fair of face were they that
 they shewed liker to angels than aught else, each clad in a robe of
 finest linen, white as snow upon their flesh, close-fitting as might be
 <pb n="342" />from the waist up, but below the waist ample, like a pavilion to the
 feet.  <milestone id="p00060012" />She that was foremost bore on her shoulders a pair of nets,
 which she held with her left hand, carrying in her right a long pole.
 Her companion followed, bearing on her left shoulder a frying-pan,
 under her left arm a bundle of faggots, and in her left hand a tripod,
 while in the other hand she carried a cruse of oil and a lighted taper.
 At sight of whom the King marvelled, and gazed intent to learn
 what it might import.  <milestone id="p00060013" />The two young maidens came forward with
 becoming modesty, and did obeisance to the King; which done they
 hied them to the place of ingress to the pond, and she that had the
 frying-pan, having set it down, and afterward the other things, took
 the pole that the other carried, and so they both went down into the
 pond, being covered by its waters to their breasts.  <milestone id="p00060014" />Whereupon one
 of Messer Neri's servants, having forthwith lit a fire, and set the tripod
 on the faggots and oil therein, addressed himself to wait, until some
 fish should be thrown to him by the girls.  <milestone id="p00060015" />Who, the one searching
 with the pole in those parts where she knew the fish lay hid, while
 the other made ready the nets, did in a brief space of time, to the
 exceeding great delight of the King, who watched them attentively,
 catch fish not a few, which they tossed to the servant, who set them,
 before the life was well out of them, in the frying-pan. After
 which, the maidens, as pre-arranged, addressed them to catch some
 of the finest fish, and cast them on to the table before the King, and
 Count Guy, and their father.  <milestone id="p00060016" />The fish wriggled about the table to
 the prodigious delight of the King, who in like manner took some
 of them, and courteously returned them to the girls; with which
 sport they diverted them, until the servant had cooked the fish that
 had been given him: which, by Messer Neri's command, were set
 before the King rather as a side-dish than as aught very rare or
 delicious.</p><p><milestone id="p00060017" />When the girls saw that all the fish were cooked, and that there
 was no occasion for them to catch any more, they came forth of the
 pond, their fine white garments cleaving everywhere close to their
 flesh so as to hide scarce any part of their delicate persons, took up
 again the things that they had brought, and passing modestly before
 the King, returned to the house.  <milestone id="p00060018" />The King, and the Count, and
 the other gentlemen that waited, had regarded the maidens with no
 little attention, and had, one and all, inly bestowed on them no little
 <pb n="343" />praise, as being fair and shapely, and therewithal sweet and debonair;
 but 'twas in the King's eyes that they especially found favour.
 Indeed, as they came forth of the water, the King had scanned each
 part of their bodies so intently that, had one then pricked him, he
 would not have felt it,  <milestone id="p00060019" />and his thoughts afterwards dwelling upon
 them, though he knew not who they were, nor how they came to
 be there, he felt stir within his heart a most ardent desire to pleasure
 them, whereby he knew very well that, if he took not care, he
 would grow enamoured; howbeit he knew not whether of the
 twain pleased him the more, so like was each to the other.  <milestone id="p00060020" />Having
 thus brooded a while, he turned to Messer Neri, and asked who the
 two damsels were. Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Sire,</q> replied Messer Neri, <q direct="unspecified">they
 are my twin daughters, and they are called, the one, Ginevra the Fair,
 and the other, Isotta the Blonde.</q> Whereupon the King was loud
 in praise of them, and exhorted Messer Neri to bestow them in
 marriage. To which Messer Neri demurred, for that he no longer
 had the means.  <milestone id="p00060021" />And nought of the supper now remaining to serve,
 save the fruit, in came the two young damsels in gowns of taffeta
 very fine, bearing in their hands two vast silver salvers full of divers
 fruits, such as the season yielded, and set them on the table before
 the King.  <milestone id="p00060022" />Which done, they withdrew a little space and fell a
 singing to music a ditty, of which the opening words were as
 follows:</p><p> <q type="song" direct="unspecified"><l>Love, many words would not suffice</l>
<l>There where I am come to tell.</l></q></p><p>And so dulcet and delightsome was the strain that to the King,
 his eyes and ears alike charmed, it seemed as if all the nine orders
 of angels were descended there to sing. The song ended, they
 knelt and respectfully craved the King's leave to depart; which,
 though sorely against his will, he gave them with a forced gaiety.</p><p><milestone id="p00060023" />Supper ended, the King and his companions, having remounted
 their horses, took leave of Messer Neri, and conversing of divers
 matters, returned to the royal quarters;  <milestone id="p00060024" />where the King, still harbouring
 his secret passion, nor, despite affairs of state that supervened,
 being able to forget the beauty and sweetness of Ginevra the Fair,
 for whose sake he likewise loved her twin sister, was so limed by
 Love that he could scarce think of aught else. So, feigning other
 <pb n="344" />reasons, he consorted familiarly with Messer Neri, and did much
 frequent his garden, that he might see Ginevra.  <milestone id="p00060025" />And at length,
 being unable to endure his suffering any longer, and being minded,
 for that he could devise no other expedient, to despoil their father not
 only of the one but of the other damsel also, he discovered both his
 love and his project to Count Guy;  <milestone id="p00060026" />who, being a good man and true,
 thus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Sire, your tale causes me not a little astonishment,
 and that more especially because of your conversation from
 your childhood to this very day, I have, methinks, known more than
 any other man.  <milestone id="p00060027" />And as no such passion did I ever mark in you,
 even in your youth, when Love should more readily have fixed you
 with his fangs, as now I discern, when you are already on the
 verge of old age, 'tis to me so strange, so surprising that you
 should veritably love, that I deem it little short of a miracle.  <milestone id="p00060028" />And
 were it meet for me to reprove you, well wot I the language I should
 hold to you, considering that you are yet in arms in a realm but
 lately won, among a people as yet unknown to you, and wily and
 treacherous in the extreme, and that the gravest anxieties and
 matters of high policy engross your mind, so that you are not
 as yet able to sit you down, and nevertheless amid all these weighty
 concerns you have given harbourage to false, flattering Love.  <milestone id="p00060029" />This
 is not the wisdom of a great king, but the folly of a feather-pated
 boy. And moreover, what is far worse, you say that you are
 resolved to despoil this poor knight of his two daughters, whom,
 entertaining you in his house, and honouring you to the best of his
 power, he brought into your presence all but naked, testifying
 thereby, how great is his faith in you, and how assured he is that
 you are a king, and not a devouring wolf.  <milestone id="p00060030" />Have you so soon forgotten
 that 'twas Manfred's outrageous usage of his subjects that
 opened you the way into this realm? What treachery was he ever
 guilty of that better merited eternal torment, than 'twould be in you
 to wrest from one that honourably entreats you at once his hope and
 his consolation? What would be said of you if so you should do?
  <milestone id="p00060031" />Perchance you deem that 'twould suffice to say: 'I did it because
 he is a Ghibelline.' Is it then consistent with the justice of a king
 that those, be they who they may, who seek his protection, as this
 man has sought yours, should be entreated after this sort?  <milestone id="p00060032" />King, I
 bid you remember that exceeding great as is your glory to have
 <pb n="345" />vanquished Manfred, yet to conquer oneself is a still greater glory:
 wherefore you, to whom belongs the correction of others, see to it
 that you conquer yourself, and refrain this unruly passion; and let
 not such a blot mar the splendour of your achievements.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00060033" />Sore stricken at heart by the Count's words, and the more
 mortified that he acknowledged their truth, the King heaved a
 fervent sigh or two, and then: <q direct="unspecified">Count,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that enemy
 there is none, however mighty, but to the practised warrior is weak
 enough and easy to conquer in comparison of his own appetite, I
 make no doubt; but, great though the struggle will be and immeasurable
 the force that it demands, so shrewdly galled am I by
 your words, that not many days will have gone by before I shall
 without fail have done enough to shew you that I, that am the
 conqueror of others, am no less able to gain the victory over myself.</q>
  <milestone id="p00060034" />And indeed but a few days thereafter, the King, on his return to
 Naples, being minded at once to leave himself no excuse for dishonourable
 conduct, and to recompense the knight for his honourable
 entreatment of him, did, albeit 'twas hard for him to endow
 another with that which he had most ardently desired for himself,
 none the less resolve to bestow the two damsels in marriage, and that
 not as Messer Neri's daughters, but as his own.  <milestone id="p00060035" />Wherefore, Messer
 Neri consenting, he provided both with magnificent dowries, and
 gave Ginevra the Fair to Messer Maffeo da Palizzi, and Isotta the
 Blonde to Messer Guglielmo della Magna, noble knights and great
 barons both; which done, sad at heart beyond measure, he betook
 him to Apulia, and by incessant travail did so mortify his vehement
 appetite that he snapped and broke in pieces the fetters of Love, and
 for the rest of his days was no more vexed by such passion.</p><p><milestone id="p00060036" />Perchance there will be those who say that 'tis but a trifle for
 a king to bestow two girls in marriage; nor shall I dispute it: but
 say we that a king in love bestowed in marriage her whom he loved,
 neither having taken nor taking, of his love, leaf or flower or fruit;
 then this I say was a feat great indeed, nay, as great as might be.</p><p>After such a sort then did this magnificent King, at once
 generously rewarding the noble knight, commendably honouring
 the damsels that he loved, and stoutly subduing himself.</p></div2><pb n="346" /><div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov1007"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00070001" />King Pedro, being apprised of the fervent love borne him
 by Lisa, who thereof is sick, comforts her, and forthwith
 gives her in marriage to a young gentleman, and
 having kissed her on the brow, ever after professes
 himself her knight.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00070002" />When Fiammetta was come to the end of her story, and
 not a little praise had been accorded to the virile magnificence
 of King Charles, albeit one there was of the ladies, who, being a
 Ghibelline, joined not therein, Pampinea, having received the king's
 command, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00070003" />None is there of discernment, worshipful
 my ladies, that would say otherwise than you have said touching
 good King Charles, unless for some other cause she bear him a
 grudge; however, for that there comes to my mind the, perchance
 no less honourable, entreatment of one of our Florentine girls by one
 of his adversaries, I am minded to recount the same to you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00070004" />What time the French were driven forth of Sicily there dwelt
 at Palermo one of our Florentines, that was an apothecary, Bernardo
 Puccini by name, a man of great wealth, that by his lady had an
 only and exceeding fair daughter, then of marriageable age.  <milestone id="p00070005" />Now
 King Pedro of Arragon, being instated in the sovereignty of the
 island, did at Palermo make with his barons marvellous celebration
 thereof; during which, as he tilted after the Catalan fashion, it
 befell that Bernardo's daughter, Lisa by name, being with other
 ladies at a window, did thence espy him in the course, whereat being
 prodigiously delighted, she regarded him again and again, and grew
 fervently enamoured of him;  <milestone id="p00070006" />nor yet, when the festivities were
 ended, and she was at home with her father, was there aught she
 <pb n="347" />could think of but this her exalted and aspiring love. In regard
 whereof that which most irked her was her sense of her low rank,
 which scarce permitted her any hope of a happy issue; but, for all
 that, give over her love for the King she would not; nor yet, for
 fear of worse to come, dared she discover it.  <milestone id="p00070007" />The King, meanwhile,
 recking, witting nothing of the matter, her suffering waxed immeasurable,
 intolerable;  <milestone id="p00070008" />and her love ever growing with ever fresh
 accessions of melancholy, the fair maiden, overborne at last, fell sick,
 and visibly day by day wasted like snow in sunlight.  <milestone id="p00070009" />Distraught
 with grief thereat, her father and mother afforded her such succour
 as they might with words of good cheer, and counsel of physicians,
 and physic; but all to no purpose; for that she in despair of her
 love was resolved no more to live.</p><p><milestone id="p00070010" />Now her father assuring her that there was no whim of hers but
 should be gratified, the fancy took her that, if she might find apt
 means, she would, before she died, make her love and her resolve
 known to the King: wherefore one day she besought her father to
 cause Minuccio d'Arezzo to come to her;  <milestone id="p00070011" />which Minuccio was a
 singer and musician of those days, reputed most skilful, and well seen
 of King Pedro. Bernardo, deeming that Lisa desired but to hear
 him play and sing a while, conveyed her message to him; and he,
 being an agreeable fellow, came to her forthwith, and after giving her
 some words of loving cheer, sweetly discoursed some airs upon his
 viol, and then sang her some songs; whereby, while he thought to
 comfort her, he did but add fire and flame to her love.  <milestone id="p00070012" />Presently
 the girl said that she would fain say a few words to him in private,
 and when all else were withdrawn from the chamber: <q direct="unspecified">Minuccio,</q>
 quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">thee have I chosen, deeming thee most trusty, to be the
 keeper of my secret, relying upon thee in the first place never to
 betray it to a soul, and next to lend me in regard thereof such aid as
 thou mayst be able; and so I pray thee to do.  <milestone id="p00070013" />Thou must know,
 then, Minuccio mine, that on the day when our lord King Pedro
 held the great festival in celebration of his triumph, I, seeing him
 tilt, was so smitten with love of him that thereof was kindled within
 my soul the fire which has brought me, as thou seest, to this pass;
 and knowing how ill it beseems me to love a king, and being unable,
 I say not to banish it from my heart, but so much as to bring it
 within bounds, and finding it exceeding grievous to bear, I have
 <pb n="348" />made choice of death as the lesser pain; and die I shall.  <milestone id="p00070014" />But should
 he wot not of my love before I die, sore disconsolate should I depart;
 and knowing not by whom more aptly than by thee I might give
 him to know this my frame, I am minded to entrust the communication
 thereof to thee; which office I entreat thee not to refuse, and
 having discharged it, to let me know, that dying thus consoled, I may
 depart this pain.</q> Which said, she silently wept.</p><p><milestone id="p00070015" />Marvelling at the loftiness of the girl's spirit and her desperate
 determination, Minuccio commiserated her not a little; and presently
 it occurred to him that there was a way in which he might honourably
 serve her: wherefore:  <milestone id="p00070016" /><q direct="unspecified">Lisa,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">my faith I plight
 thee, wherein thou mayst place sure confidence that I shall never
 play thee false, and lauding thy high emprise, to wit, the setting thine
 affections upon so great a king, I proffer thee mine aid, whereby,
 so thou wilt be of good cheer, I hope, and believe, that, before thou
 shalt see the third day from now go by, I shall have brought thee
 tidings which will be to thee for an exceeding great joy; and, not
 to lose time, I will set to work at once.</q>  <milestone id="p00070017" />And so Lisa, assuring
 him that she would be of good cheer, and plying him afresh with
 instant obsecrations, bade him Godspeed;  <milestone id="p00070018" />and Minuccio, having
 taken leave of her, hied him to one Mico da Siena, a very expert
 rhymester of those days, who at his instant request made the ensuing
 song:</p><div3 type="song"><lg><milestone id="p00070019" /><l>Hence hie thee, Love; and hasting to my King,</l>
<l>Give him to know what torment dire I bear,</l>
<l>How that to death I fare,</l>
<l>Still close, for fear, my passion harbouring.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00070020" /><l>Lo, Love, to thee with clasp&#232;d hands I turn,</l>
<l>And pray thee seek him where he tarrieth,</l>
<l>And tell him how I oft for him do yearn,</l>
<l>So sweetly he my heart enamoureth;</l>
<l>And of the fire, wherewith I throughly burn,</l>
<l>I think to die, but may the hour uneath</l>
<l>Say, when my grievous pain shall with my breath</l>
<l>Surcease; till when, neither may fear nor shame</l>
<l>The least abate the flame.</l>
<l>Ah! to his ears my woeful story bring.</l></lg><pb n="349" /><lg><milestone id="p00070021" /><l>Since of him I was first enamour&#232;d,</l>
<l>Never hast thou, O Love, my fearful heart</l>
<l>With any such fond hope encourag&#232;d,</l>
<l>As e'er its message to him to impart,</l>
<l>To him, my lord, that me so sore bested</l>
<l>Holds: dying thus, 'twere grievous to depart:</l>
<l>Perchance, were he to know my cruel smart,</l>
<l>'Twould not displease him; might I but make bold</l>
<l>My soul to him to unfold,</l>
<l>And shew him all my woeful languishing.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00070022" /><l>Love, since 'twas not thy will me to accord</l>
<l>Such boldness as that e'er unto my King</l>
<l>I may discover my sad heart's full hoard,</l>
<l>Or any word or sign thereof him bring:</l>
<l>This all my prayer to thee, O sweet my Lord:</l>
<l>Hie thee to him, and so him whispering</l>
<l>Mind of the day I saw him tourneying</l>
<l>With all his paladins environ&#232;d,</l>
<l>And grew enamour&#232;d</l>
<l>Ev'n to my very heart's disrupturing.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p00070023" />Which words Minuccio forthwith set to music after a soft and
 plaintive fashion befitting their sense; and on the third day thereafter
 hied him to court, while King Pedro was yet at breakfast.
 And being bidden by the King to sing something to the accompaniment
 of his viol,  <milestone id="p00070024" />he gave them this song with such sweet concord of
 words and music that all the folk that were in the King's hall seemed,
 as it were, entranced, so intent and absorbed stood they to listen,
 and the King rather more than the rest.  <milestone id="p00070025" />And when Minuccio had
 done singing, the King asked whence the song came, that, as far as
 he knew, he had never heard it before.  <milestone id="p00070026" /><q direct="unspecified">Sire,</q> replied Minuccio,
 <q direct="unspecified">'tis not yet three days since 'twas made, words and music alike.</q>
 And being asked by the King in regard of whom 'twas made:
 <q direct="unspecified">I dare not,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">discover such a secret save to you
 alone.</q>
  <milestone id="p00070027" />Bent on hearing the story, the King, when the tables were cleared,
 took Minuccio into his privy chamber; and there Minuccio told
 him everything exactly as he had heard it from Lisa's lips. Whereby
 the King was much gratified, and lauded the maiden not a little, and
 <pb n="350" />said that a girl of such high spirit merited considerate treatment, and
 bade Minuccio be his envoy to her, and comfort her, and tell her
 that without fail that very day at vespers he would come to visit her.
  <milestone id="p00070028" />Overjoyed to bear the girl such gladsome tidings, Minuccio tarried
 not, but hied him back to the girl with his viol, and being closeted
 with her, told her all that had passed, and then sang the song to the
 accompaniment of his viol.  <milestone id="p00070029" />Whereby the girl was so cheered and
 delighted that forthwith there appeared most marked and manifest
 signs of the amendment of her health, while with passionate longing
 (albeit none in the house knew or divined it) she awaited the vesper
 hour, when she was to see her lord.</p><p><milestone id="p00070030" />Knowing the girl very well, and how fair she was, and pondering
 divers times on what Minuccio had told him, the King, being a prince
 of a liberal and kindly disposition, grew ever more compassionate.
 So, about vespers, he mounted his horse, and rode forth, as if for
 mere pleasure, and being come to the apothecary's house, demanded
 access to a very goodly garden that the apothecary had, and having
 dismounted, after a while enquired of Bernardo touching his
 daughter, and whether he had yet bestowed her in marriage.  <milestone id="p00070031" /><q direct="unspecified">Sire,</q>
 replied Bernardo, <q direct="unspecified">she is not yet married; and indeed she has been
 and still is very ill: howbeit since none she is wonderfully amended.</q>
  <milestone id="p00070032" />The significance of which amendment being forthwith apprehended
 by the King: <q direct="unspecified">In good faith,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'twere a pity so fair
 a creature were reft from the world so early; we would go in and
 visit her.</q>  <milestone id="p00070033" />And presently, attended only by two of his lords and
 Bernardo, he betook him to her chamber, where being entered,
 he drew nigh the bed, whereon the girl half reclined, half sate in
 eager expectation of his coming; and taking her by the hand:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madonna,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what means this? A maiden like you
 should be the comfort of others, and you suffer yourself to languish.
 We would entreat you that for love of us you be of good cheer, so
 as speedily to recover your health.</q>  <milestone id="p00070034" />To feel the touch of his hand
 whom she loved above all else, the girl, albeit somewhat shamefast,
 was so enraptured that 'twas as if she was in Paradise; and as soon
 as she was able: <q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> she said, <q direct="unspecified">'twas the endeavour, weak
 as I am, to sustain a most grievous burden that brought this sickness
 upon me; but 'twill not be long ere you will see me quit thereof,
 thanks to your courtesy.</q>  <milestone id="p00070035" />The hidden meaning of which words
 <pb n="351" />was apprehended only by the King, who momently made more
 account of the girl, and again and again inly cursed Fortune, that had
 decreed that she should be the daughter of such a man. And yet a
 while he tarried with her, and comforted her, and so took his leave.
  <milestone id="p00070036" />Which gracious behaviour of the King was not a little commended,
 and accounted a signal honour to the apothecary and his daughter.</p><p>The girl, glad at heart as was ever lady of her lover, mended
 with reviving hope, and in a few days recovered her health, and
 therewith more than all her wonted beauty.  <milestone id="p00070037" />Whereupon the King,
 having taken counsel with the Queen how to reward so great a love,
 got him one day to horse with a great company of his barons, and
 hied him to the apothecary's house; and being come into the garden,
 he sent for the apothecary and his daughter; and there, being joined
 by the Queen with not a few ladies, who received the girl into their
 company, they made such cheer as 'twas a wonder to see.  <milestone id="p00070038" />And
 after a while the King and Queen having called Lisa to them, quoth
 the King: <q direct="unspecified">Honourable damsel, by the great love that you have
 borne us we are moved greatly to honour you; and we trust that,
 for love of us, the honour that we design for you will be acceptable
 to you. Now 'tis thus we would honour you: to wit, that, seeing
 that you are of marriageable age, we would have you take for
 husband him that we shall give you; albeit 'tis none the less our
 purpose ever to call ourself your knight, demanding no other tribute
 of all your love but one sole kiss.</q>  <milestone id="p00070039" />Scarlet from brow to neck,
 the girl, making the King's pleasure her own, thus with a low
 voice replied: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, very sure am I that, should it come to
 be known that I was grown enamoured of you, most folk would hold
 me for a fool, deeming, perchance, that I was out of my mind, and
 witless alike of my own rank and yours;  <milestone id="p00070040" />but God, who alone reads
 the hearts of us mortals, knows that even then, when first I did
 affect you, I wist that you were the King, and I but the daughter of
 Bernardo the apothecary, and that to suffer my passion to soar so
 high did ill become me;  <milestone id="p00070041" />but, as you know far better than I, none
 loves of set and discreet purpose, but only according to the dictates
 of impulse and fancy; which law my forces, albeit not seldom
 opposed, being powerless to withstand, I loved and still love and
 shall ever love you.  <milestone id="p00070042" />But as no sooner knew I myself subjugated to
 your love, than I vowed to have ever no will but yours; therefore not
 <pb n="352" />only am I compliant to take right gladly him whom you shall be
 pleased to give me for husband, thereby conferring upon me great
 honour and dignity; but if you should bid me tarry in the fire,
 delighted were I to obey, so thereby I might pleasure you.  <milestone id="p00070043" />How
 far it beseems me to have you, my King, for my knight, you best
 know; and therefore I say nought thereof; nor will the kiss which
 you crave as your sole tribute of my love be granted you save by
 leave of my Lady the Queen.  <milestone id="p00070044" />Natheless, may you have of this
 great graciousness that you and my Lady the Queen have shewn
 me, and which I may not requite, abundant recompense in the blessing
 and favour of God;</q> and so she was silent.</p><p><milestone id="p00070045" />The Queen was mightily delighted with the girl's answer, and
 deemed her as discreet as the King had said. The King then sent
 for the girl's father and mother, and being assured that his intention
 had their approval, summoned to his presence a young man, Perdicone
 by name, that was of gentle birth, but in poor circumstances, and
 put certain rings into his hand, and (he nowise gainsaying) wedded
 him to Lisa.  <milestone id="p00070046" />Which done, besides jewels many and precious that
 he and the Queen gave the girl, he forthwith bestowed upon Perdicone
 two domains, right goodly and of ample revenues, to wit,
 Ceffal&#249; and Calatabellotta, saying: <q direct="unspecified">We give them to thee for thy
 wife's dowry; what we have in store for thee thou wilt learn hereafter.</q>
 Which said, he turned to the girl, and:  <milestone id="p00070047" /><q direct="unspecified">Now,</q> quoth
 he, <q direct="unspecified">we are minded to cull that fruit which is due to us of thy
 love;</q> and so, taking her head between both his hands, he kissed her
 brow.  <milestone id="p00070048" />Wherefore, great was the joy of Perdicone, and the father
 and mother of Lisa, and Lisa herself, and mighty the cheer they
 made, and gaily did they celebrate the nuptials. And, as many
 affirm, right well did the King keep his promise to the girl; for that
 ever, while he lived, he called himself her knight, nor went to any
 passage of arms bearing other device than that which he had
 from her.</p><p><milestone id="p00070049" />Now 'tis by doing after this sort that sovereigns win the hearts
 of their subjects, give others occasion of well-doing, and gain for
 themselves an imperishable renown. At which mark few or none in
 our times have bent the bow of their understanding, the more part
 of the princes having become but cruel tyrants.</p></div2><pb n="353" /><div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov1008"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00080001" />Sophronia, albeit she deems herself wife to Gisippus, is
 wife to Titus Zuintius Fulvus, and goes with him to
 Rome, where Gisippus arrives in indigence, and deeming
 himself scorned by Titus, to compass his own death,
 avers that he has slain a man. Titus recognizes
 him, and to save his life, alleges that 'twas he that
 slew the man: whereof he that did the deed being
 witness, he discovers himself as the murderer. Whereby
 it comes to pass that they are all three liberated by
 Octavianus; and Titus gives Gisippus his sister to
 wife, and shares with him all his substance.</p></argument><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00080002" />So ceased Pampinea; and when all the ladies, and most of all
 the Ghibelline, had commended King Pedro, Filomena by command
 of the king thus began:</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00080003" />Magnificent my ladies, who wots not
 that there is nought so great but kings, when they have a mind, may
 accomplish it? As also that 'tis of them that magnificence is most
 especially demanded? Now whoso, being powerful, does that which
 it appertains to him to do, does well; but therein is no such matter of
 marvel, or occasion of extolling him to the skies, as in his deed, of
 whom, for that his power is slight, less is demanded.  <milestone id="p00080004" />Wherefore, as
 you are so profuse of your words in exaltation of the fine deeds, as
 you deem them, of monarchs, I make no manner of doubt, but that the
 doings of our peers must seem to you yet more delectable and commendable,
 when they equal or surpass those of kings. Accordingly
 'tis a transaction, laudable and magnificent, that passed between two
 <pb n="354" />citizens, who were friends, that I purpose to recount to you in my
 story.</p><p><milestone id="p00080005" />I say, then, that what time Octavianus Caesar, not as yet hight
 Augustus, but being in the office called Triumvirate, swayed the
 empire of Rome, there dwelt at Rome a gentleman, Publius Quintius
 Fulvus by name, who, having a son, Titus Quintius Fulvus, that
 was a very prodigy of wit, sent him to Athens to study philosophy,
 and to the best of his power commended him to a nobleman of that
 city, Chremes by name, who was his very old friend.  <milestone id="p00080006" />Chremes
 lodged Titus in his own house with his son Gisippus, and placed
 both Titus and Gisippus under a philosopher named Aristippus, to
 learn of him his doctrine.  <milestone id="p00080007" />And the two youths, thus keeping
 together, found each the other's conversation so congruous with his
 own, that there grew up between them a friendship so close and
 brotherly that 'twas never broken by aught but death; nor knew
 either rest or solace save when he was with the other.  <milestone id="p00080008" />So, gifted
 alike with pre-eminent subtlety of wit, they entered on their studies,
 and with even pace and prodigious applause scaled together the
 glorious heights of philosophy. In which way of life, to the exceeding
 great delight of Chremes, who entreated Titus as no less his son
 than Gisippus, they continued for full three years.  <milestone id="p00080009" />At the end
 whereof, it befell (after the common course of things mundane) that
 Chremes (being now aged) departed this life. Whom with equal
 grief they mourned as a common father; and the friends and kinsfolk
 of Chremes were alike at a loss to determine whether of the twain
 stood in need of the more consolation upon the bereavement.</p><p><milestone id="p00080010" />Some months afterward the friends and kinsfolk of Gisippus came
 to him and exhorted him, as did also Titus, to take a wife, and found
 him a maiden, wondrous fair, of one of the most noble houses of
 Athens, her name Sophronia, and her age about fifteen years.  <milestone id="p00080011" />So a
 time was appointed for their nuptials, and one day, when 'twas near
 at hand, Gisippus bade Titus come see the maiden, whom as yet he
 had not seen; and they being come into her house, and she sitting
 betwixt them, Titus, as he were fain to observe with care the several
 charms of his friend's wife that was to be, surveyed her with the
 closest attention, and being delighted beyond measure with all that
 he saw, grew, as inly he extolled her charms to the skies, enamoured
 of her with a love as ardent, albeit he gave no sign of it, as ever lover
 <pb n="355" />bore to lady. However, after they had tarried a while with her,
 they took their leave, and went home,  <milestone id="p00080012" />where Titus repaired to his
 chamber, and there gave himself over to solitary musing on the
 damsel's charms, and the longer he brooded, the more he burned for
 her. Whereon as he reflected, having heaved many a fervent sigh,
 thus he began to commune with himself:  <milestone id="p00080013" />Ah! woe worth thy
 life, Titus! Whom makest thou the mistress of thy soul, thy
 love, thy hope? Knowest thou not that by reason as well of thy
 honourable entreatment by Chremes and his kin as of the whole-hearted
 friendship that is between thee and Gisippus, it behoves thee
 to have his betrothed in even such pious regard as if she were thy
 sister? Whither art thou suffering beguiling love, delusive hope, to
 hurry thee?  <milestone id="p00080014" />Open the eyes of thine understanding, and see thyself,
 wretched man, as thou art; obey the dictates of thy reason, refrain thy
 carnal appetite, control thine inordinate desires, and give thy thoughts
 another bent; join battle with thy lust at the outset, and conquer
 thyself while there is yet time.  <milestone id="p00080015" />This which thou wouldst have is
 not meet, is not seemly: this which thou art minded to ensue, thou
 wouldst rather, though thou wert, as thou art not, sure of its attainment,
 eschew, hadst thou but the respect thou shouldst have, for the
 claims of true friendship. So, then, Titus, what wilt thou do?
 What but abandon this unseemly love, if thou wouldst do as it
 behoves thee?</p><p><milestone id="p00080016" />But then, as he remembered Sophronia, his thoughts took the
 contrary direction, and he recanted all he had said, musing on this
 wise: The laws of Love are of force above all others; they abrogate
 not only the law of human friendship, but the law Divine
 itself. How many times ere now has father loved daughter, brother
 sister, step-mother step-son? aberrations far more notable than that a
 friend should love his friend's wife, which has happened a thousand
 times.  <milestone id="p00080017" />Besides which, I am young, and youth is altogether subject
 to the laws of Love. Love's pleasure, then, should be mine. The
 seemly is for folk of riper years. 'Tis not in my power to will aught
 save that which Love wills.  <milestone id="p00080018" />So beauteous is this damsel that there
 is none but should love her; and if I love her, who am young, who
 can justly censure me? I love her not because she is the affianced
 of Gisippus; no matter whose she was, I should love her all the
 same.  <milestone id="p00080019" />Herein is Fortune to blame, that gave her to my friend,
 <pb n="356" />Gisippus, rather than to another. And if she is worthy of love, as
 for beauty she is, Gisippus, if he should come to know that I love
 her, ought to be less jealous than another.</p><p><milestone id="p00080020" />Then, scorning himself that he should indulge such thoughts, he
 relapsed into the opposing mood, albeit not to abide there, but ever
 veering to and fro, he spent not only the whole of that day and the
 ensuing night, but many others; insomuch that, being able neither
 to eat nor to sleep, he grew so weak that he was fain to take to his
 bed.  <milestone id="p00080021" />Gisippus, who had marked his moodiness for some days, and
 now saw that he was fairly sick, was much distressed; and with
 sedulous care, never quitting his side, he tended, and strove as best
 he might to comfort, him, not seldom and most earnestly demanding
 to know of him the cause of his melancholy and his sickness. Many
 were the subterfuges to which Titus resorted; but, as Gisippus was
 not to be put off with his fables, finding himself hard pressed by him,
 with sighs and sobs he made answer on this wise:  <milestone id="p00080022" /><q direct="unspecified">Gisippus, had
 such been the will of the Gods, I were fain rather to die than to
 live, seeing that Fortune has brought me to a strait in which needs
 must my virtue be put to the ordeal, and, to my most grievous
 shame, 'tis found wanting: whereof I confidently expect my due
 reward, to wit, death, which will be more welcome to me than to
 live, haunted ever by the memory of my baseness, which, as there is
 nought that from thee I either should or can conceal, I, not without
 burning shame, will discover to thee.</q>  <milestone id="p00080023" />And so he recounted the
 whole story from first to last, the occasion of his melancholy, its
 several moods, their conflict, and with which of them the victory
 rested, averring that he was dying of love for Sophronia, and that,
 knowing how ill such love beseemed him, he had, for penance, elected
 to die, and deemed the end was now not far off.  <milestone id="p00080024" />Gisippus, hearing
 his words and seeing his tears, for a while knew not what to say,
 being himself smitten with the damsel's charms, albeit in a less degree
 than Titus; but ere long he made up his mind that Sophronia must
 be less dear to him than his friend's life.</p><p>And so, moved to tears by his friend's tears:  <milestone id="p00080025" /><q direct="unspecified">Titus,</q> quoth
 he between his sobs, <q direct="unspecified">but that thou art in need of comfort, I should
 reproach thee, that thou hast offended against our friendship in that
 thou hast so long kept close from me this most distressful passion;
 and albeit thou didst deem it unseemly, yet unseemly things should
 <pb n="357" />no more than things seemly be withheld from a friend, for that, as a
 friend rejoices with his friend in things seemly, so he does his endeavour
 to wean his friend from things unseemly: but enough of this
 for the nonce: I pass to that which, I wot, is of greater moment.  <milestone id="p00080026" />If
 thou ardently lovest Sophronia, my affianced, so far from marvelling
 thereat, I should greatly marvel were it not so, knowing how fair
 she is, and how noble is thy soul, and thus the apter to be swayed by
 passion, the more excelling is she by whom thou art charmed.  <milestone id="p00080027" />And
 the juster the cause thou hast to love Sophronia, the greater is the
 injustice with which thou complainest of Fortune (albeit thou dost it
 not in so many words) for giving her to me, as if thy love of her had
 been seemly, had she belonged to any other but me;  <milestone id="p00080028" />whereas, if thou
 art still the wise man thou wast wont to be, thou must know that to
 none could Fortune have assigned her, with such good cause for thee
 to thank her, as to me. Had any other had her, albeit thy love had
 been seemly, he had loved her as his own, rather than as thine;
 which, if thou deem me even such a friend to thee as I am, thou wilt
 not apprehend from me, seeing that I mind me not that, since we
 were friends, I had ever aught that was not as much thine as mine.
  <milestone id="p00080029" />And so should I entreat thee herein as in all other matters, were the
 affair gone so far that nought else were possible; but as it is, I can
 make thee sole possessor of her; and so I mean to do; for I know
 not what cause thou shouldst have to prize my friendship, if, where
 in seemly sort it might be done, I knew not how to surrender my
 will to thine.  <milestone id="p00080030" />'Tis true that Sophronia is my betrothed, and that I
 loved her much, and had great cheer in expectation of the nuptials:
 but as thou, being much more discerning than I, dost more fervently
 affect this rare prize, rest assured that she will enter my chamber not
 mine but thine.  <milestone id="p00080031" />Wherefore, away with thy moodiness, banish thy
 melancholy, recover thy lost health, thy heartiness and jollity, and
 gladsomely, even from this very hour, anticipate the guerdon of thy
 love, a love worthier far than mine.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080032" />Delightful as was the prospect with which hope flattered Titus,
 as he heard Gisippus thus speak, no less was the shame with which
 right reason affected him, admonishing him that the greater was the
 liberality of Gisippus, the less it would become him to profit thereby.
 Wherefore, still weeping, he thus constrained himself to make
 answer:  <milestone id="p00080033" /><q direct="unspecified">Gisippus, thy generous and true friendship leaves me in
 <pb n="358" />no doubt as to the manner in which it becomes me to act. God forefend
 that her, whom, as to the more worthy, He has given to thee, I
 should ever accept of thee for mine. Had He seen fit that she should
 be mine, far be it from thee or any other to suppose that He would
 ever have awarded her to thee.  <milestone id="p00080034" />Renounce not, then, that which thy
 choice and wise counsel and His gift have made thine, and leave me,
 to whom, as unworthy, He has appointed no such happiness, to
 waste my life in tears; for either I shall conquer my grief, which
 will be grateful to thee, or it will conquer me, and so I shall be quit
 of my pain.</q>  <milestone id="p00080035" />Quoth then Gisippus: <q direct="unspecified">If our friendship, Titus, is
 of such a sort as may entitle me to enforce thee to ensue behests of
 mine, or as may induce thee of thine own free will to ensue the
 same, such is the use to which, most of all, I am minded to put it;
 and if thou lend not considerate ear unto my prayers, I shall by
 force, that force which is lawful in the interest of a friend, make
 Sophronia thine.  <milestone id="p00080036" />I know the might of Love, how redoubtable it is,
 and how, not once only, but oftentimes, it has brought ill-starred lovers
 to a miserable death; and thee I see so hard bested that turn back
 thou mightst not, nor get the better of thy grief, but holding on thy
 course, must succumb, and perish; and without doubt I should
 speedily follow thee.  <milestone id="p00080037" />And so, had I no other cause to love thee, thy
 life is precious to me in that my own is bound up with it. Sophronia,
 then, shall be thine; for thou wouldst not lightly find another so
 much to thy mind, and I shall readily find another to love, and so
 shall content both thee and me.  <milestone id="p00080038" />In which matter, peradventure, I
 might not be so liberal, were wives so scarce or hard to find as are
 friends; wherefore, as 'tis so easy a matter for me to find another
 wife, I had liefer--I say not lose her, for in giving her to thee lose
 her I shall not, but only transfer her to one that is my alter ego,
 and
 that to her advantage--I had liefer, I say, transfer her to thee than
 lose thee.  <milestone id="p00080039" />And so, if aught my prayers avail with thee, I entreat thee
 extricate thyself from this thy woeful plight, and comfort at once
 thyself and me, and in good hope, address thyself to pluck that boon
 which thy fervent love craves of her for whom thou yearnest.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080040" />Still scrupling, for shame, to consent that Sophronia should become
 his wife, Titus remained yet a while inexorable; but, yielding at
 last to the solicitations of Love, reinforced by the exhortations of
 Gisippus, thus he made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Lo now, Gisippus, I know not
 <pb n="359" />how to call it, whether 'tis more thy pleasure than mine, this which
 I do, seeing that 'tis as thy pleasure that thou so earnestly entreatest
 me to do it; but, as thy liberality is such that my shame, though
 becoming, may not withstand it, I will even do it.  <milestone id="p00080041" />But of this rest
 assured, that I do so, witting well that I receive from thee, not only
 the lady I love, but with her my very life. And, Fate permitting,
 may the Gods grant me to make thee such honourable and goodly
 requital as may shew thee how sensible I am of the boon, which
 thou, more compassionate of me than I am of myself, conferrest on
 me.</q>  <milestone id="p00080042" />Quoth then Gisippus: <q direct="unspecified">Now, for the giving effect to our
 purpose, methinks, Titus, we should proceed on this wise. Thou
 knowest that Sophronia, by treaty at length concluded between my
 family and hers, is become my betrothed: were I now to say that
 she should not be my wife, great indeed were the scandal that would
 come thereof, and I should affront both her family and mine own;
  <milestone id="p00080043" />whereof, indeed, I should make no account, so it gave me to see her
 become thine; but I fear that, were I to give her up at this juncture,
 her family would forthwith bestow her upon another, perchance,
 than thee, and so we should both be losers.  <milestone id="p00080044" />Wherefore
 methinks that, so thou approve, I were best to complete what I have
 begun, bring her home as my wife, and celebrate the nuptials, and
 thereafter we can arrange that thou lie with her, privily, as thy wife.
  <milestone id="p00080045" />Then, time and occasion serving, we will disclose the whole affair,
 and if they are satisfied, well and good; if not, 'twill be done all the
 same, and as it cannot be undone, they must perforce make the best
 of it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080046" />Which counsel being approved by Titus, Gisippus brought the
 lady home as his wife, Titus being now recovered, and quite himself
 again; and when they had made great cheer, and night was come,
 the ladies, having bedded the bride, took their departure.  <milestone id="p00080047" />Now the
 chambers of Titus and Gisippus were contiguous, and one might
 pass from one into the other: Gisippus, therefore, being come into
 his room, extinguished every ray of light, and stole into that of
 Titus, and bade him go get him to bed with his lady.  <milestone id="p00080048" />Whereat Titus
 gave way to shame, and would have changed his mind, and refused
 to go in; but Gisippus, no less zealous at heart than in words to
 serve his friend, after no small contention prevailed on him to go
 thither. Now no sooner was Titus abed with the lady, than, taking
 <pb n="360" />her in his arms, he, as if jestingly, asked in a low tone whether she
 were minded to be his wife.  <milestone id="p00080049" />She, taking him to be Gisippus,
 answered, yes; whereupon he set a fair and costly ring on her
 finger, saying: <q direct="unspecified">And I am minded to be thy husband.</q> And
 having presently consummated the marriage, he long and amorously
 disported him with her, neither she, nor any other, being ever aware
 that another than Gisippus lay with her.</p><p><milestone id="p00080050" />Now Titus and Sophronia being after this sort wedded, Publius,
 the father of Titus, departed this life. For which cause Titus was
 bidden by letter to return forthwith to Rome to see to his affairs;
 wherefore he took counsel with Gisippus how he might take
 Sophronia thither with him; which might not well be done without
 giving her to know how matters stood.  <milestone id="p00080051" />Whereof, accordingly, one
 day, having called her into the chamber, they fully apprised her,
 Titus for her better assurance bringing to her recollection not a little
 of what had passed between them.  <milestone id="p00080052" />Whereat she, after glancing from
 one to the other somewhat disdainfully, burst into a flood of tears,
 and reproached Gisippus that he had so deluded her; and forthwith,
 saying nought of the matter to any there, she hied her forth of
 Gisippus' house and home to her father, to whom and her mother
 she recounted the deceit which Gisippus had practised upon them as
 upon her, averring that she was the wife not of Gisippus, as they
 supposed, but of Titus.  <milestone id="p00080053" />Whereby her father was aggrieved exceedingly,
 and prolonged and grave complaint was made thereof by him
 and his own and Gisippus' families, and there was not a little parleying,
 and a world of pother. Gisippus earned the hatred of both his own and
 Sophronia's kin, and all agreed that he merited not only censure but
 severe punishment. He, however, averred that he had done a thing
 seemly, and that Sophronia's kinsfolk owed him thanks for giving her
 in marriage to one better than himself.</p><p><milestone id="p00080054" />All which Titus witnessed with great suffering, and witting that
 'twas the way of the Greeks to launch forth in high words and
 menaces, and refrain not until they should meet with one that
 answered them, whereupon they were wont to grow not only
 humble but even abject, was at length minded that their clavers
 should no longer pass unanswered;  <milestone id="p00080055" />and, as with his Roman temper he
 united Athenian subtlety, he cleverly contrived to bring the kinsfolk,
 as well of Gisippus as of Sophronia, together in a temple,
 <pb n="361" />where, being entered, attended only by Gisippus, thus (they being
 intent to hear) he harangued them:  <milestone id="p00080056" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis the opinion of not a
 few philosophers that whatsoever mortals do is ordained by the providence
 of the immortal Gods; for which cause some would have it
 that nought either is, or ever shall be, done, save of necessity, albeit
 others there are that restrict this necessity to that which is already
 done.  <milestone id="p00080057" />Regard we but these opinions with some little attention, and
 we shall very plainly perceive that to censure that which cannot be
 undone is nought else but to be minded to shew oneself wiser than
 the Gods; by whom we must suppose that we and our affairs are
 swayed and governed with uniform and unerring wisdom. Whereby
 you may very readily understand how vain and foolish a presumption
 it is to pass judgment on their doings, and what manner and might
 of chains they need who suffer themselves to be transported to such
 excess of daring.  <milestone id="p00080058" />Among whom, in my judgment, you must one
 and all be numbered, if 'tis true, what I hear, to wit, that you have
 complained and do continue to complain that Sophronia, albeit you
 gave her to Gisippus, is, nevertheless, become my wife; not considering
 that 'twas ordained from all eternity that she should become, not
 the wife of Gisippus, but mine, as the fact does now declare.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080059" /><q direct="unspecified">But, for that discourse of the secret providence and purposes of
 the Gods seems to many a matter hard and scarce to be understood,
 I am willing to assume that they meddle in no wise with our concerns,
 and to descend to the region of human counsels; in speaking
 whereof I must needs do two things quite at variance with my wont,
 to wit, in some degree praise myself and censure or vilify another.
  <milestone id="p00080060" />But, as in either case I mean not to deviate from the truth, and 'tis
 what the occasion demands, I shall not fail so to do.  <milestone id="p00080061" />With bitter
 upbraidings, animated rather by rage than by reason, you cease not
 to murmur, nay, to cry out, against Gisippus, and to harass him with
 your abuse, and hold him condemned, for that her, whom you saw
 fit to give him, he has seen fit to give me, to wife; wherein I deem
 him worthy of the highest commendation, and that for two reasons,
 first, because he has done the office of a friend, and secondly, because
 he has done more wisely than you did.  <milestone id="p00080062" />After what sort the sacred
 laws of friendship prescribe that friend shall entreat friend, 'tis not to
 my present purpose to declare; 'twill suffice to remind you that the
 tie of friendship should be more binding than that of blood, or
 <pb n="362" />kinship; seeing that our friends are of our own choosing, whereas our
 kinsfolk are appointed us by Fortune;  <milestone id="p00080063" />wherefore, if my life was more
 to Gisippus than your goodwill, since I am, as I hold myself, his
 friend, can any wonder thereat?</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080064" /><q direct="unspecified">But pass we to my second reason; in the exposition whereof I
 must needs with yet more cogency prove to you that he has been
 wiser than you, seeing that, methinks, you wot nought of the providence
 of the Gods, and still less of the consequences of friendship.  <milestone id="p00080065" />I
 say then, that, as 'twas your premeditated and deliberate choice that
 gave Sophronia to this young philosopher Gisippus, so 'twas his that
 gave her to another young philosopher. 'Twas your counsel that
 gave her to an Athenian; 'twas his that gave her to a Roman:
 'twas your counsel that gave her to a man of gentle birth; 'twas his
 that gave her to one of birth yet gentler: wealthy was he to whom
 your counsel gave her, most wealthy he to whom his counsel gave
 her. Not only did he to whom your counsel gave her, love her not,
 but he scarce knew her, whereas 'twas to one that loved her beyond
 all other blessings, nay, more dearly than his own life, that his
 counsel gave her.  <milestone id="p00080066" />And to the end that it may appear more plainly
 that 'tis even as I say, and Gisippus' counsel more to be commended
 than yours, let us examine it point by point. That I, like Gisippus,
 am young and a philosopher, my countenance and my pursuits may,
 without making more words about the matter, sufficiently attest.
 We are also of the same age, and have ever kept pace together in
 our studies.  <milestone id="p00080067" />Now true it is that he is an Athenian, and I am a
 Roman. But, as touching the comparative glory of the cities,
 should the matter be mooted, I say that I am of a free city, and he
 of a city tributary; that I am of a city that is mistress of all the
 world, and he of one that is subject to mine; that I am of a city
 that flourishes mightily in arms, in empire, and in arts; whereas he
 cannot boast his city as famous save in arts.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080068" /><q direct="unspecified">Moreover, albeit you see me here in the guise of a most humble
 scholar, I am not born of the dregs of the populace of Rome. My
 halls and the public places of Rome are full of the antique effigies of
 my forefathers, and the annals of Rome abound with the records of
 triumphs led by the Quintii to the Roman Capitol; and so far from
 age having withered it, to-day, yet more abundantly than ever of
 yore, flourishes the glory of our name.  <milestone id="p00080069" />Of my wealth I forbear, for
 <pb n="363" />shame, to speak, being mindful that honest poverty is the time-honoured
 and richest inheritance of the noble citizens of Rome;
 but, allowing for the nonce the opinion of the vulgar, which holds
 poverty in disrepute, and highly appraises wealth, I, albeit I never
 sought it, yet, as the favoured of Fortune, have abundant store
 thereof.  <milestone id="p00080070" />Now well I wot that, Gisippus being of your own city,
 you justly prized and prize an alliance with him; but not a whit
 less should you prize an alliance with me at Rome, considering that
 there you will have in me an excellent host, and a patron apt, zealous
 and potent to serve you as well in matters of public interest as in
 your private concerns.  <milestone id="p00080071" />Who, then, dismissing all bias from his
 mind, and judging with impartial reason, would deem your counsel
 more commendable than that of Gisippus? Assuredly none.
 Sophronia, then, being married to Titus Quintius Fulvus, a citizen
 of Rome, of an ancient and illustrious house, and wealthy, and a
 friend of Gisippus, whoso takes umbrage or offence thereat, does
 that which it behoves him not to do, and knows not what he does.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080072" /><q direct="unspecified">Perchance some will say that their complaint is not that
 Sophronia is the wife of Titus, but that she became his wife after
 such a sort, to wit, privily, by theft, neither friend nor any of her
 kin witting aught thereof; but herein is no matter of marvel, no
 prodigy as yet unheard-of.  <milestone id="p00080073" />I need not instance those who before
 now have taken to them husbands in defiance of their fathers' will,
 or have eloped with their lovers and been their mistresses before they
 were their wives, or of whose marriages no word has been spoken,
 until their pregnancy or parturition published them to the world,
 and necessity sanctioned the fact: nought of this has happened in
 the case of Sophronia; on the contrary, 'twas in proper form, and in
 meet and seemly sort, that Gisippus gave her to Titus.  <milestone id="p00080074" />And others,
 peradventure, will say that 'twas by one to whom such office belonged
 not that she was bestowed in marriage. Nay, but this is but
 vain and womanish querulousness, and comes of scant consideration.
 Know we not, then, that Fortune varies according to circumstances
 her methods and her means of disposing events to their predetermined
 ends?  <milestone id="p00080075" />What matters it to me, if it be a cobbler, rather than
 a philosopher, that Fortune has ordained to compass something for
 me, whether privily or overtly, so only the result is as it should be?
 I ought, indeed, to take order, if the cobbler be indiscreet, that he
 <pb n="364" />meddle no more in affairs of mine, but, at the same time, I ought to
 thank him for what he has done.  <milestone id="p00080076" />If Gisippus has duly bestowed
 Sophronia in marriage, it is gratuitous folly to find fault with the
 manner and the person. If you mistrust his judgment, have a care
 that it be not in his power to do the like again, but thank him
 for this turn.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080077" /><q direct="unspecified">Natheless, you are to know that I used no cunning practice or
 deceit to sully in any degree the fair fame of your house in the
 person of Sophronia;  <milestone id="p00080078" />and, albeit I took her privily to wife, I came
 not as a ravisher to despoil her of her virginity, nor in any hostile
 sort was I minded to make her mine on dishonourable terms, and
 spurn your alliance; but, being fervently enamoured of her bewitching
 beauty and her noble qualities, I wist well that, should I
 make suit for her with those formalities which you, perchance, will
 say were due, then, for the great love you bear her, and for fear lest I
 should take her away with me to Rome, I might not hope to have
 her.  <milestone id="p00080079" />Accordingly I made use of the secret practice which is now
 manifest to you, and brought Gisippus to consent in my interest to
 that whereto he was averse;  <milestone id="p00080080" />and thereafter, ardently though I loved
 her, I sought not to commingle with her as a lover, but as a husband,
 nor closed with her, until, as she herself by her true witness
 may assure you, I had with apt words and with the ring made her
 my lawful wife, asking her if she would have me to husband, whereto
 she answered, yes. Wherein if she seem to have been tricked, 'tis
 not I that am to blame, but she, for that she asked me not who I was.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080081" /><q direct="unspecified">This, then, is the great wrong, sin, crime, whereof for love and
 friendship's sake Gisippus and I are guilty, that Sophronia is privily
 become the wife of Titus Quintius: 'tis for this that you harass him
 with your menaces and hostile machinations.  <milestone id="p00080082" />What more would
 you do, had he given her to a villein, to a caitiff, to a slave? Where
 would you find fetters, dungeons, crosses adequate to your vengeance?
  <milestone id="p00080083" />But enough of this at present: an event, which I did not
 expect, has now happened; my father is dead; and I must needs
 return to Rome; wherefore, being fain to take Sophronia with me,
 I have discovered to you that which otherwise I had, perchance, still
 kept close. Whereto, if you are wise, you will gladly reconcile
 yourselves; for that, if I had been minded to play you false, or put
 an affront upon you, I might have scornfully abandoned her to you;
 <pb n="365" />but God forefend that such baseness be ever harboured in a Roman
 breast.  <milestone id="p00080084" />Sophronia, then, by the will of the Gods, by force of law,
 and by my own love-taught astuteness, is mine. The which it would
 seem that you, deeming yourselves, peradventure, wiser than the
 Gods, or the rest of mankind, do foolishly set at nought, and that in
 two ways alike most offensive to me; inasmuch as you both withhold
 from me Sophronia, in whom right, as against me, you have
 none, and also entreat as your enemy Gisippus, to whom you are
 rightfully bounden.  <milestone id="p00080085" />The folly whereof I purpose not at present
 fully to expound to you, but in friendly sort to counsel you to abate
 your wrath and abandon all your schemes of vengeance, and restore
 Sophronia to me, that I may part from you on terms of amity and
 alliance, and so abide:  <milestone id="p00080086" />but of this rest assured, that whether this,
 which is done, like you or not, if you are minded to contravene it, I
 shall take Gisippus hence with me, and once arrived in Rome, shall
 in your despite find means to recover her who is lawfully mine, and
 pursuing you with unremitting enmity, will apprise you by experience
 of the full measure and effect of a Roman's wrath.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080087" />Having so said, Titus started to his feet, his countenance distorted
 by anger, and took Gisippus by the hand, and with manifest
 contempt for all the rest, shaking his head at them and threatening
 them, led him out of the temple.  <milestone id="p00080088" />They that remained in the
 temple, being partly persuaded by his arguments to accept his
 alliance and friendship, partly terrified by his last words, resolved by
 common consent that 'twas better to have the alliance of Titus, as
 they had lost that of Gisippus, than to add to that loss the enmity of
 Titus.  <milestone id="p00080089" />Wherefore they followed Titus, and having come up with
 him, told him that they were well pleased that Sophronia should be
 his, and that they should prize his alliance and the friendship of dear
 Gisippus; and having ratified this treaty of amity and alliance with
 mutual cheer, they departed and sent Sophronia to Titus. Sophronia,
 discreetly making a virtue of necessity, transferred forthwith to Titus
 the love she had borne Gisippus, and being come with Titus to Rome,
 was there received with no small honour.  <milestone id="p00080090" />Gisippus tarried in Athens,
 held in little account by well-nigh all the citizens, and being involved
 in certain of their broils, was, not long afterwards, with all his
 household,
 banished the city, poor, nay, destitute, and condemned to perpetual
 exile.  <milestone id="p00080091" />Thus hard bested, and at length reduced to mendicancy,
 <pb n="366" />he made his way, so as least discomfortably he might, to Rome,
 being minded to see whether Titus would remember him: and
 there, learning that Titus lived, and was much affected by all the
 Romans, and having found out his house, he took his stand in front
 of it, and watched until Titus came by;  <milestone id="p00080092" />to whom, for shame of the
 sorry trim that he was in, he ventured no word, but did his endeavour
 that he might be seen of him, hoping that Titus might recognize
 him, and call him by his name: but Titus passing on, Gisippus
 deeming that he had seen and avoided him, and calling to mind that
 which aforetime he had done for him, went away wroth and
 desperate.  <milestone id="p00080093" />And fasting and penniless, and--for 'twas now night--knowing
 not whither he went, and yearning above all for death, he
 wandered by chance to a spot, which, albeit 'twas within the city,
 had much of the aspect of a wilderness, and espying a spacious
 grotto, he took shelter there for the night; and worn out at last with
 grief, on the bare ground, wretchedly clad as he was, he fell asleep.</p><p><milestone id="p00080094" />Now two men that had that night gone out a thieving, having
 committed the theft, came towards morning to the grotto, and there
 quarrelled, and the stronger slew the other, and took himself off.
  <milestone id="p00080095" />Aroused by the noise, Gisippus witnessed the murder, and deeming
 that he had now the means of compassing, without suicide, the death
 for which he so much longed, budged not a jot, but stayed there,
 until the serjeants of the court, which had already got wind of the
 affair, came on the scene, and laid violent hands upon him, and led
 him away.  <milestone id="p00080096" />Being examined, he confessed that he had slain the man,
 and had then been unable to make his escape from the grotto.
 Wherefore the praetor, Marcus Varro by name, sentenced him to
 death by crucifixion, as was then the custom.  <milestone id="p00080097" />But Titus, who
 happened at that moment to come into the praetorium, being told
 the crime for which he was condemned, and scanning the poor
 wretch's face, presently recognized him for Gisippus, and marvelled
 how he should come to be there, and in such a woeful plight. And
 most ardently desiring to succour him, nor seeing other way to save
 his life except to exonerate him by accusing himself, he straightway
 stepped forward, and said with a loud voice:  <milestone id="p00080098" /><q direct="unspecified">Marcus Varro, call
 back the poor man on whom thou hast passed sentence, for he is
 innocent. 'Tis enough that I have incurred the wrath of the Gods
 by one deed of violence, to wit, the murder of him whom your
 <pb n="367" />serjeants found dead this morning, without aggravating my offence
 by the death of another innocent man.</q>  <milestone id="p00080099" />Perplexed, and vexed that he
 should have been heard by all in the praetorium, but unable honourably
 to avoid compliance with that which the laws enjoined, Varro
 had Gisippus brought back, and in presence of Titus said to him:
  <milestone id="p00080100" /><q direct="unspecified">How camest thou to be so mad as, though no constraint was put
 upon thee, to confess a deed thou never didst, thy life being at stake?
 Thou saidst that 'twas thou by whom the man was slain last night,
 and now comes this other, and says that 'twas not thou but he that
 slew him.</q>  <milestone id="p00080101" />Gisippus looked, and seeing Titus, wist well that, being
 grateful for the service rendered by him in the past, Titus was now
 minded to save his life at the cost of his own: wherefore, affected to
 tears, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay but, Varro, in very sooth I slew him, and 'tis
 now too late, this tender solicitude of Titus for my deliverance.</q>
  <milestone id="p00080102" />But on his part: <q direct="unspecified">Praetor,</q> quoth Titus, <q direct="unspecified">thou seest this man is
 a stranger, and was found unarmed beside the murdered man; thou
 canst not doubt that he was fain of death for very wretchedness:
 wherefore discharge him, and let punishment light on me who have
 merited it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080103" />Marvelling at the importunity of both, Varro readily surmised
 that neither was guilty. And while he was casting about how he
 might acquit them, lo, in came a young man, one Publius Ambustus,
 a desperate character, and known to all the Romans for an arrant
 thief. He it was that had verily committed the murder,  <milestone id="p00080104" />and witting
 both the men to be innocent of that of which each accused himself, so
 sore at heart was he by reason of their innocence, that, overborne by
 an exceeding great compassion, he presented himself before Varro,
 and:  <milestone id="p00080105" /><q direct="unspecified">Praetor,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis destiny draws me hither to loose
 the knot of these men's contention; and some God within me leaves
 me no peace of his whips and stings, until I discover my offence:
 wherefore know that neither of these men is guilty of that of which
 each accuses himself.  <milestone id="p00080106" />'Tis verily I that slew the man this morning
 about daybreak; and before I slew him, while I was sharing our
 plunder with him, I espied this poor fellow asleep there. Nought
 need I say to clear Titus: the general bruit of his illustrious renown
 attests that he is not a man of such a sort. Discharge him, therefore,
 and exact from me the penalty prescribed by the laws.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080107" />The affair had by this time come to the ears of Octavianus, who
 <pb n="368" />caused all three to be brought before him, and demanded to know
 the causes by which they had been severally moved to accuse themselves;
 and, each having told his story, Octavianus released the two
 by reason of their innocence, and the third for love of them.  <milestone id="p00080108" />Titus
 took Gisippus home, having first chidden him not a little for his
 faint-heartedness and diffidence, and there, Sophronia receiving him as
 a brother, did him marvellous cheer;  <milestone id="p00080109" />and having comforted him a
 while, and arrayed him in apparel befitting his worth and birth, he
 first shared with him all his substance, and then gave him his sister,
 a young damsel named Fulvia, to wife, and said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Choose
 now, Gisippus, whether thou wilt tarry here with me, or go back
 to Achaia with all that I have given thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080110" />Partly perforce of his banishment from his city, partly for that
 the sweet friendship of Titus was justly dear to him, Gisippus
 consented to become a Roman. And so, long and happily they
 lived together at Rome, Gisippus with his Fulvia, and Titus with
 his Sophronia, in the same house, growing, if possible, greater friends
 day by day.</p><p><milestone id="p00080111" />Exceeding sacred then, is friendship, and worthy not only to be
 had in veneration, but to be extolled with never-ending praise, as the
 most dutiful mother of magnificence and seemliness, sister of gratitude
 and charity, and foe to enmity and avarice; ever, without waiting
 to be asked, ready to do as generously by another as she would be
 done by herself.  <milestone id="p00080112" />Rarely indeed is it to-day that twain are found, in
 whom her most holy fruits are manifest; for which is most shamefully
 answerable the covetousness of mankind, which, regarding only
 private interest, has banished friendship beyond earth's farthest bourne,
 there to abide in perpetual exile.  <milestone id="p00080113" />How should love, or wealth, or
 kinship, how should aught but friendship have so quickened the soul
 of Gisippus that the tears and sighs of Titus should incline his heart
 to cede to him the fair and gracious lady that was his betrothed and
 his beloved?  <milestone id="p00080114" />Laws, menaces, terror! How should these, how should
 aught but friendship, have withheld Gisippus, in lonely places, in
 hidden retreats, in his own bed, from enfolding (not perchance unsolicited
 by her) the fair damsel within his youthful embrace?
  <milestone id="p00080115" />Honours, rewards, gains! Would Gisippus for these, would he for
 aught but friendship, have made nothing of the loss of kindred--his
 own and Sophronia's--have made nothing of the injurious murmurs
 <pb n="369" />of the populace, have made nothing of mocks and scorns, so only
 he might content his friend?  <milestone id="p00080116" />And on the other hand, for what
 other cause than friendship had Titus, when he might decently have
 feigned not to see, have striven with the utmost zeal to compass his
 own death, and set himself upon the cross in Gisippus' stead?  
[*** missing sentence: please see Italian <milestone id="p00080117" /> ***] 
<milestone id="p00080118" />And
 what but friendship had left no place for suspicion in the soul of
 Titus, and filled it with a most fervent desire to give his sister to
 Gisippus, albeit he saw him to be reduced to extreme penury
 and destitution?  <milestone id="p00080119" />But so it is that men covet hosts of acquaintance,
 troops of kinsfolk, offspring in plenty; and the number of their
 dependants increases with their wealth; and they reflect not that
 there is none of these, be he who he may, but will be more apprehensive
 of the least peril threatening himself than cumbered to avert
 a great peril from his lord or kinsman, whereas between friends we
 know 'tis quite contrariwise.</p></div2><pb n="370" /><div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov1009"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00090001" />Saladin, in guise of a merchant, is honourably entreated
 by Messer Torello. The Crusade ensuing, Messer
 Torello appoints a date, after which his wife may
 marry again: he is taken prisoner, and by training
 hawks comes under the Soldan's notice. The Soldan
 recognizes him, makes himself known to him, and
 entreats him with all honour. Messer Torello falls
 sick, and by magic arts is transported in a single night
 to Pavia, where his wife's second marriage is then to be
 solemnized, and being present thereat, is recognized by
 her, and returns with her to his house.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00090002" />So ended Filomena her story, and when all alike had commended
 the magnificence shewn by Titus in his gratitude, the king, reserving
 the last place for Dioneo, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00090003" />Lovesome my ladies, true
 beyond all question is what Filomena reports of friendship, and with
 justice did she deplore in her closing words the little account in
 which 'tis held to-day among mortals.  <milestone id="p00090004" />And were we here for the
 purpose of correcting, or even of censuring, the vices of the age, I
 should add a copious sequel to her discourse; but as we have another
 end in view, it has occurred to me to set before you in a narrative,
 which will be of considerable length, but entertaining throughout,
 an instance of Saladin's magnificence, to the end that, albeit, by reason
 of our vices, it may not be possible for us to gain to the full the
 friendship of any, yet by the matters whereof you shall hear in my
 story we may at least be incited to take delight in doing good offices,
 <pb n="371" />in the hope that sooner or later we may come by our reward
 thereof.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00090005" />I say, then, that in the time of the Emperor Frederic I., as
 certain writers affirm, the Christians made common emprise for the
 recovery of the Holy Land. Whereof that most valiant prince,
 Saladin, then Soldan of Babylonia, being in good time apprised,
 resolved to see for himself the preparations made by the Christian
 potentates for the said emprise, that he might put himself in better
 trim to meet them.  <milestone id="p00090006" />So, having ordered all things to his mind in
 Egypt, he made as if he were bound on a pilgrimage, and attended
 only by two of his chiefest and sagest lords, and three servants, took
 the road in the guise of a merchant.  <milestone id="p00090007" />And having surveyed many
 provinces of Christendom, as they rode through Lombardy with
 intent to cross the Alps, they chanced, between Milan and Pavia, to
 fall in with a gentleman, one Messer Torello d'Istria da Pavia, who
 with his servants and his dogs and falcons was betaking him to a fine
 estate that he had on the Ticino, there to tarry a while.  <milestone id="p00090008" />Now
 Messer Torello no sooner espied Saladin and his lords than he
 guessed them to be gentlemen and foreigners; and, being zealous to
 do them honour, when Saladin asked one of his servants how far
 off Pavia might still be, and if he might win there in time to enter
 the town, he suffered not the servant to make answer, but: <q direct="unspecified">No,
 gentlemen,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">by the time you reach Pavia 'twill be too
 late for you to enter.</q>  <milestone id="p00090009" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> replied Saladin, <q direct="unspecified">then might you
 be pleased to direct us, as we are strangers, where we may best be
 lodged?</q> <q direct="unspecified"> <milestone id="p00090010" />That gladly will I,</q> returned Messer Torello. <q direct="unspecified">I
 was but now thinking to send one of these my men on an errand to
 Pavia; I will send him with you, and he will guide you to a place
 where you will find very comfortable quarters.</q>  <milestone id="p00090011" />Then, turning to
 one of his most trusty servants, he gave him his instructions, and
 despatched him with them: after which, he repaired to his estate,
 and forthwith, as best he might, caused a goodly supper to be made
 ready, and the tables set in his garden; which done, he stationed
 himself at the gate on the look-out for his guests.</p><p>The servant, conversing with the gentlemen of divers matters,
 brought them by devious roads to his lord's estate without their being
 ware of it.  <milestone id="p00090012" />Whom as soon as Messer Torello espied, he came forth
 afoot to meet them, and said with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">A hearty welcome to
 <pb n="372" />you, gentlemen.</q>  <milestone id="p00090013" />Now Saladin, being very quick of apprehension,
 perceived that the knight had doubted, when he met them, that, were
 he to bid them to his house, they might not accept his hospitality;
 and accordingly, that it might not be in their power to decline it, had
 brought them to his house by a ruse. And so, returning his greeting:
 <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">were it meet to find fault with those that shew
 courtesy, we should have a grievance against you, for that, to say
 nought of somewhat delaying our journey, you have in guerdon of
 a single greeting constrained us to accept so noble a courtesy as
 yours.</q>  <milestone id="p00090014" />Whereto the knight, who was of good understanding and
 well-spoken, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, such courtesy as we
 shew you will, in comparison of that which, by what I gather from
 your aspect, were meet for you, prove but a sorry thing; but in sooth
 this side of Pavia you might not anywhere have been well lodged;
 wherefore take it not amiss that you have come somewhat out of
 your way to find less discomfortable quarters.</q>  <milestone id="p00090015" />And as he spoke,
 about them flocked the servants, who, having helped them to dismount,
 saw to their horses; whereupon Messer Torello conducted them to
 the chambers that were made ready for them, where, having caused
 them to be relieved of their boots, and refreshed with the coolest of
 wines, he held pleasant converse with them until supper-time.
  <milestone id="p00090016" />Saladin and his lords and servants all knew Latin, so that they both
 understood and made themselves understood very well, and there
 was none of them but adjudged this knight to be the most agreeable
 and debonair man, and therewithal the best talker, that he had ever
 seen;  <milestone id="p00090017" />while to Messer Torello, on the other hand, they shewed as
 far greater magnificoes than he had at first supposed, whereby he was
 inly vexed that he had not been able that evening to do them the
 honours of company, and a more ceremonious banquet. For which
 default he resolved to make amends on the ensuing morning: wherefore,
 having imparted to one of his servants that which he would have
 done, he sent him to his most judicious and highminded lady at
 Pavia, which was close by, and where never a gate was locked.
  <milestone id="p00090018" />Which done, he brought the gentlemen into the garden, and courteously
 asked them who they were. <q direct="unspecified">We are Cypriote merchants,</q>
 replied Saladin, <q direct="unspecified">and 'tis from Cyprus we come, and we are on our
 way to Paris on business.</q> Quoth then Messer Torello: <q direct="unspecified">Would
 to God that our country bred gentlemen of such a quality as are the
 <pb n="373" />merchants that I see Cyprus breeds!</q>  <milestone id="p00090019" />From which they passed to
 discourse of other matters, until, supper-time being come, he
 besought them to seat them at table; whereat, considering that
 the supper was but improvised, their entertainment was excellent
 and well-ordered.</p><p>The tables being cleared, Messer Torello, surmising that they
 must be weary, kept them no long time from their rest, but bestowed
 them in most comfortable beds, and soon after went to rest himself.
  <milestone id="p00090020" />Meanwhile the servant that he had sent to Pavia did his lord's errand
 to the lady, who, in the style rather of a queen than of a housewife,
 forthwith assembled not a few of Messer Torello's friends and vassals,
 and caused all meet preparation to be made for a magnificent banquet,
 and by messengers bearing torches bade not a few of the noblest of
 the citizens thereto; and had store of silken and other fabrics and
 vair brought in, and all set in order in every point as her husband
 had directed.  <milestone id="p00090021" />Day came, and the gentlemen being risen, Messer
 Torello got him to horse with them, and having sent for his hawks,
 brought them to a ford, and shewed them how the hawks flew.
 By and by, Saladin requesting of him a guide to the best inn at
 Pavia: <q direct="unspecified">I myself will be your guide,</q> returned Messer Torello,
 <q direct="unspecified">for I have occasion to go thither.</q>  <milestone id="p00090022" />Which offer they, nothing
 doubting, did gladly accept, and so with him they set forth; and
 about tierce, being come to the city, and expecting to be directed to
 the best inn, they were brought by Messer Torello to his own house,
 where they were forthwith surrounded by full fifty of the greatest
 folk of the city, gathered there to give the gentlemen a welcome;
 and 'twas who should hold a bridle or a stirrup, while they dismounted.
  <milestone id="p00090023" />Whereby Saladin and his lords more than guessing the
 truth: <q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello,</q> quoth they, <q direct="unspecified">'twas not this that we
 craved of you. Honour enough had we from you last night, and
 far in excess of our desires; wherefore thou mightst very well have
 left us to go our own road.</q>  <milestone id="p00090024" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> replied
 Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">for that which was done yestereve I have to thank
 Fortune rather than you: seeing that Fortune surprised you on the
 road at an hour when you must needs repair to my little house: for
 that which shall be done this morning I shall be beholden to you, as
 will also these gentlemen that surround you, with whom, if you
 deem it courteous so to do, you may refuse to breakfast, if you
 like.</q></p><pb n="374" /><p><milestone id="p00090025" />Fairly conquered, Saladin and his lords dismounted, and heartily
 welcomed by the gentlemen, were conducted to the chambers which
 had been most sumptuously adorned for their use; and having laid
 aside their riding dress, and taken some refreshment, repaired to the
 saloon, where all had been made ready with splendour. There,
 having washed their hands, they sat them down to table, and were
 regaled with a magnificent repast of many courses, served with all
 stately and fair ceremony, insomuch that, had the Emperor himself
 been there, 'twould not have been possible to do him more honour.
  <milestone id="p00090026" />And albeit Saladin and his lords were grandees, and used to exceeding
 great displays of pomp and state, nevertheless this shewed to them
 as not a little marvellous, and one of the greatest they had ever seen,
 having regard to the quality of their host, whom they knew to be
 but a citizen, and no lord.  <milestone id="p00090027" />Breakfast done, and the tables cleared,
 they conversed a while of high matters, and then, as 'twas very hot,
 all the gentlemen of Pavia--so it pleased Messer Torello--retired for
 their siesta, while he remained with his three guests; with whom he
 presently withdrew into a chamber, whither, that there might be
 nought that he held dear which they had not seen, he called his
 noble lady.  <milestone id="p00090028" />And so the dame, exceeding fair and stately of person,
 and arrayed in rich apparel, with her two little boys, that shewed as
 two angels, on either hand, presented herself before them, and
 graciously greeted them. Whereupon they rose, and returned her
 salutation with reverence, and caused her to sit down among them,
 and made much of her two little boys.  <milestone id="p00090029" />But after some interchange
 of gracious discourse, Messer Torello being withdrawn somewhat
 apart, she asked them courteously, whence they came and whither
 they were bound, and had of them the same answer that Messer
 Torello had received.  <milestone id="p00090030" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> quoth the lady with a joyful air,
 <q direct="unspecified">then I see that my woman's wit will be of service to you; wherefore
 I pray you as a special favour neither to reject nor to despise the
 little gift that I am about to present to you; but reflecting that, as
 women have but small minds, so they make but small gifts, accept it,
 having regard rather to the good will of the giver than the magnitude
 of the gift.</q>  <milestone id="p00090031" />She then caused bring forth for each of them
 two pair of robes, lined the one with silk, the other with vair, no
 such robes as citizens or merchants, but such as lords, use to wear,
 and three vests of taffeta, besides linen clothes, and: <q direct="unspecified">Take them,</q>
 <pb n="375" />quoth she. <q direct="unspecified">The robes I give you are even such as I have arrayed
 my lord withal: the other things, considering that you are far from
 your wives, and have come a long way, and have yet a long way to
 go, and that merchants love to be neat and trim, may, albeit they
 are of no great value, be yet acceptable to you.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090032" />Wondering, the gentlemen acknowledged without reserve that
 there was no point of courtesy wherein Messer Torello was not
 minded to acquit himself towards them. And noting the lordly
 fashion of the robes, unsuited to the quality of merchants, they misdoubted
 that Messer Torello had recognized them. However, quoth
 one of them to the lady: <q direct="unspecified">Gifts great indeed are these, Madam,
 nor such as lightly to accept, were it not that thereto we are constrained
 by your prayers, to which we may on no account say, no.</q>
  <milestone id="p00090033" />Whereupon, Messer Torello being now come back, the lady bade
 them adieu, and took her leave of them; and in like manner did she
 cause their servants to be supplied with equipment suitable to them.
 The gentlemen, being much importuned thereto by Messer Torello,
 consented to tarry the rest of the day with him; and so, having
 slept, they donned their robes, and rode a while with him about the
 city; and supper-time being come, they feasted magnificently, and
 with a numerous and honourable company.  <milestone id="p00090034" />And so in due time
 they betook them to rest; and at daybreak, being risen, they found,
 in lieu of their jaded nags, three stout and excellent palfreys, and in
 like manner fresh and goodly mounts for their servants. Which
 Saladin marking turned to his lords, and:  <milestone id="p00090035" /><q direct="unspecified">By God,</q> quoth he,
 <q direct="unspecified">never was gentleman more complete and courteous and considerate
 than this Messer Torello, and if the Christian kings are as kingly as
 he is knightly, there is none of them whose onset the Soldan of
 Babylon might well abide, to say nought of so many as we see making
 ready to fall upon him.</q> However, knowing that 'twas not permissible
 to refuse, he very courteously thanked Messer Torello: and
 so they got them to horse.  <milestone id="p00090036" />Messer Torello with a numerous company
 escorted them far beyond the gate of the city, until, loath
 though Saladin was to part from him, so greatly did he now affect
 him, yet as he must needs speed on, he besought him to turn back.
 Whereupon, albeit it irked him to take leave of them:  <milestone id="p00090037" /><q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q>
 quoth Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">since such is your pleasure, I obey;
 but this I must say to you. Who you are I know not, nor would I
 <pb n="376" />know more than you are pleased to impart; but whoever you may
 be, you will not make me believe that you are merchants this while;
 and so adieu!</q>  <milestone id="p00090038" />To whom Saladin, having already taken leave of
 all his company, thus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Peradventure, Sir, we shall
 one day give you to see somewhat of our merchandise, and thereby
 confirm your belief: and so adieu!</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090039" />Thus parted Saladin and his company from Messer Torello,
 Saladin burning with an exceeding great desire, if life should be continued
 to him, and the war, which he anticipated, should not undo
 him, to shew Messer Torello no less honour than he had received at
 his hands, and conversing not a little with his lords both of Messer
 Torello himself and of his lady, and all that he did and that in any wise
 concerned him, ever more highly commending them.  <milestone id="p00090040" />However,
 having with much diligence spied out all the West, he put to sea,
 and returned with his company to Alexandria; and having now all
 needful information, he put himself in a posture of defence. Messer
 Torello, his mind full of his late guests, returned to Pavia; but,
 though he long pondered who they might be, he came never at or
 anywhere near the truth.</p><p><milestone id="p00090041" />Then with great and general mustering of forces came the time
 for embarking on the emprise, and Messer Torello, heeding not the
 tearful entreaties of his wife, resolved to join therein. So, being fully
 equipped and about to take horse, he said to his lady, whom he most
 dearly loved:  <milestone id="p00090042" /><q direct="unspecified">Wife, for honour's sake and for the weal of my
 soul, I go, as thou seest, on this emprise: our substance and our
 honour I commend to thy care. Certain I am of my departure, but,
 for the thousand accidents that may ensue, certitude have I none of
 my return: wherefore I would have thee do me this grace, that,
 whatever be my fate, shouldst thou lack certain intelligence that I
 live, thou wilt expect me a year and a month and a day from this
 my departure, before thou marry again.</q>  <milestone id="p00090043" />Whereto the lady, weeping
 bitterly, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello, I know not how I
 shall support the distress in which, thus departing, you leave me;
 but should my life not fail beneath it, and aught befall thee,
 live and die secure that I shall live and die the wife of Messer
 Torello, and of his memory.</q>  <milestone id="p00090044" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Wife,</q> returned
 Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">well assured I am that, so far as in thee
 shall lie, this promise of thine will be kept; but thou art
 <pb n="377" />young, and fair, and of a great family, and thy virtue is rare and
 generally known:  <milestone id="p00090045" />wherefore I make no doubt that, should there be
 any suspicion of my death, thou wilt be asked of thy brothers and
 kinsmen by many a great gentleman: against whose attacks, though
 thou desire it never so, thou wilt not be able to hold out, but wilt
 perforce be fain to gratify one or other of them; for which cause it
 is that I ask thee to wait just so long and no longer.</q>  <milestone id="p00090046" /><q direct="unspecified">As I have
 said,</q> replied the lady, <q direct="unspecified">so, in so far as I may, I shall do; and if I
 must needs do otherwise, rest assured that of this your behest I shall
 render you obedience. But I pray God that He bring neither you
 nor me to such a strait yet a while.</q>  <milestone id="p00090047" />Which said, the lady wept,
 and having embraced Messer Torello, drew from her finger a ring,
 and gave it to him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Should it betide that I die before I
 see you again, mind you of me, when you look upon it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090048" />Messer Torello took the ring, and got him to horse, and having
 bidden all adieu, fared forth on his journey; and being arrived with
 his company at Genoa, he embarked on a galley, and having departed
 thence, in no long time arrived at Acre, and joined the main
 Christian host;  <milestone id="p00090049" />wherein there by and by broke out an exceeding
 great and mortal sickness; during which, whether owing to Saladin's
 strategy, or his good fortune, he made an easy capture of well-nigh
 all the remnant of the Christians that were escaped, and quartered
 them in divers prisons in many cities;  <milestone id="p00090050" />of which captives Messer
 Torello being one, was brought to Alexandria and there confined.
 Where, not being known, and fearing to make himself known, he,
 under constraint of necessity, applied him to the training of hawks,
 whereof he was a very great master; and thereby he fell under the
 notice of Saladin, who took him out of the prison, and made him his
 falconer.  <milestone id="p00090051" />The Soldan called him by no other name than <q direct="unspecified">Christian,</q>
 and neither recognized, nor was recognized by, him, who, his
 whole soul ever in Pavia, essayed many a time to escape, that he
 might return thither, but still without success:  <milestone id="p00090052" />wherefore, certain
 Genoese, that were come to Alexandria as ambassadors to the Soldan
 for the redemption of some of their townsfolk, being about to return,
 he resolved to write to his lady, how that he lived, and would come
 back to her, as soon as he might, and that she should expect his
 return; and having so done, he earnestly besought one of the
 ambassadors, whom he knew, to see that the letter reached the
 <pb n="378" />hands of the Abbot of San Pietro in Ciel d'Oro, who was his
 uncle.</p><p><milestone id="p00090053" />Now, such being the posture of Messer Torello's affairs, it befell
 one day that, while he talked with Saladin of his hawks, he smiled;
 whereby his mouth shaped itself in a fashion, of which Saladin had
 taken particular note, while he was at Pavia. And so, recalling
 Messer Torello to mind, he fixed his gaze upon him, and it seemed
 to him that 'twas indeed Messer Torello; wherefore, leaving the
 matter of which they were conversing: <q direct="unspecified">Tell me, Christian,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">of what country art thou in the West?</q>  <milestone id="p00090054" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q>
 replied Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">I am a Lombard, of a city called Pavia, a
 poor man, and of humble condition.</q>  <milestone id="p00090055" />Which when he heard,
 Saladin, well-nigh resolved of his doubt, said joyfully to himself:
 <q direct="unspecified">God has provided me with occasion meet to prove to this man
 what store I set by his courtesy;</q> and without another word he
 brought him into a room where he kept all his wearing apparel, and
 said: <q direct="unspecified">Look, Christian, if among these robes there be any that
 thou hast ever seen before.</q>  <milestone id="p00090056" />So Messer Torello examined the robes,
 and espied those which his lady had given to Saladin; but, deeming
 they could not be the same, he replied: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, there is no robe
 here that I recognize, albeit 'tis true that those two robes are such as
 I once wore myself, in company with three merchants that came to
 my house.</q>  <milestone id="p00090057" />Whereupon Saladin could refrain himself no longer;
 but, tenderly embracing him: <q direct="unspecified">You,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">are Messer
 Torello d'Istria, and I am one of those three merchants to whom
 your lady gave these robes; and now is the time to warrant you of
 the quality of my merchandise, as, when I parted from you, I told
 you might come to pass.</q>  <milestone id="p00090058" />Which to hear, Messer Torello was at
 once overjoyed and abashed, overjoyed to have entertained so illustrious
 a guest, and abashed, for that it seemed to him that he
 had given him but a sorry entertainment. To whom: <q direct="unspecified">Messer
 Torello,</q> quoth Saladin, <q direct="unspecified">since hither has God sent you to me,
 deem that 'tis no more I that am lord here, but you.</q>  <milestone id="p00090059" />And so
 they made great cheer together; and then Saladin caused Messer
 Torello to be royally arrayed; and presented him to all his greatest
 lords, and having extolled his merit in no stinted measure, bade
 all, as they hoped for grace from him, honour Messer Torello
 even as himself. And so from that hour did they all; but most
 <pb n="379" />especially the two lords that had been with Saladin at Messer Torello's
 house.</p><p><milestone id="p00090060" />The glory, to which Messer Torello thus suddenly found himself
 raised, somewhat diverted his mind from the affairs of Lombardy,
 and the more so, for that he entertained no doubt that his letter
 had reached his uncle's hands.  <milestone id="p00090061" />But for that in the camp, or rather
 army, of the Christians, on the day when they were taken by Saladin,
 there died and was buried one Messer Torello de Dignes, an obscure
 knight of Provence, whereas Messer Torello d'Istria was known to
 all the host for a right noble gentleman, whoso heard tell that
 Messer Torello was dead, supposed that 'twas Messer Torello d'Istria,
 and not Messer Torello de Dignes; nor did what happened after,
 to wit, the capture, avail to undeceive them;  <milestone id="p00090062" />for not a few Italians
 had carried the report home with them; among whom there were
 some who made bold to say that they had seen Messer Torello
 d'Istria's dead body, and had been present at its interment.  <milestone id="p00090063" />Which
 rumour coming to the ears of his lady and his kinsfolk, great indeed,
 nay, immeasurable was the distress that it occasioned not only to
 them, but to all that had known him.  <milestone id="p00090064" />The mode and measure of his
 lady's grief, her mourning, her lamentation, 'twere tedious to describe.
 Enough that, after some months spent in almost unmitigated
 tribulation, her sorrow shewed signs of abatement; whereupon, suit
 being made for her hand by some of the greatest men of Lombardy,
 her brothers and other kinsfolk began to importune her to marry
 again. Times not a few, and with floods of tears, she refused; but,
 overborne at last, she consented to do as they would have her, upon
 the understanding that she was to remain unmarried until the term
 for which she had bound herself to Messer Torello was fulfilled.</p><p><milestone id="p00090065" />Now the lady's affairs being in this posture at Pavia, it befell
 that some eight days or so before the time appointed for her marriage,
 Messer Torello one day espied in Alexandria one that he had
 observed go with the Genoese ambassadors aboard the galley that
 took them to Genoa; wherefore he called him, and asked him what
 sort of a voyage they had had, and when they had reached Genoa.
  <milestone id="p00090066" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> replied the other, <q direct="unspecified">the galley made but a sorry voyage of
 it, as I learned in Crete, where I remained; for that, while she was
 nearing Sicily, there arose a terrible gale from the North that drove
 her on to the shoals of Barbary, and never a soul escaped, and among
 <pb n="380" />the rest my two brothers were lost.</q>  <milestone id="p00090067" />Which report believing--and
 'twas indeed most true--and calling to mind that in a few days the
 term that he had asked of his wife would be fulfilled, and surmising
 that there could be no tidings of him at Pavia, Messer Torello made
 no question but that the lady was provided with another husband;
 whereby he sank into such a depth of woe that he lost all power to
 eat, and betook him to his bed and resigned himself to die.  <milestone id="p00090068" />Which
 when Saladin, by whom he was most dearly beloved, learned, he
 came to him, and having plied him with many and most instant
 entreaties, learned at length the cause of his distress and sickness;
 and, having chidden him not a little that he had not sooner apprised
 him thereof, he besought him to put on a cheerful courage, assuring
 him, that, if so he did, he would bring it to pass that he should be in
 Pavia at the time appointed, and told him how.  <milestone id="p00090069" />Believing Saladin's
 words the more readily that he had many times heard that 'twas
 possible, and had not seldom been done, Messer Torello recovered
 heart, and was instant with Saladin that he should make all haste.</p><p><milestone id="p00090070" />Accordingly Saladin bade one of his necromancers, of whose skill
 he had already had proof, to devise a method whereby Messer Torello
 should be transported abed in a single night to Pavia: the necromancer
 made answer that it should be done, but that 'twere best
 he put Messer Torello to sleep.  <milestone id="p00090071" />The matter being thus arranged,
 Saladin hied him back to Messer Torello, and finding him most
 earnestly desirous to be in Pavia at the time appointed, if so it might
 be, and if not, to die:  <milestone id="p00090072" /><q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">if you dearly
 love your lady, and misdoubt that she may become the bride of
 another, no wise, God wot, do I censure you, for that, of all the
 ladies that ever I saw, she, for bearing, manners, and address--to say
 nought of beauty, which is but the flower that perishes--seems to
 me the most worthy to be lauded and cherished.  <milestone id="p00090073" />Much had I been
 gratified, since Fortune has sent you hither to me, that, while you and
 I yet live, we had exercised equal lordship in the governance of this
 my realm,  <milestone id="p00090074" />and, if such was not God's will, and this must needs come
 upon you, that you are fain either to be at Pavia at the time
 appointed or to die, I had desired of all things to have been apprised
 thereof at such a time that I might have sent you home with such
 honourable circumstance and state and escort as befit your high
 desert; which not being vouchsafed me, and as nought will content
 <pb n="381" />you but to be there forthwith, I do what I can, and speed you
 thither on such wise as I have told you.</q>  <milestone id="p00090075" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> replied Messer
 Torello, <q direct="unspecified">had you said nought, you have already done enough to
 prove your goodwill towards me, and that in so high a degree as is
 quite beyond my deserts, and most assured of the truth of what you
 say shall I live and die, and so had done, had you not said it; but,
 seeing that my resolve is taken, I pray you that that, which you
 promise to do, be done speedily, for that after to-morrow I may no
 longer count on being expected.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090076" />Saladin assured him that 'twas so ordered that he should not be
 disappointed. And on the morrow, it being his purpose to speed
 him on his journey that same night, he caused to be set up in one of
 his great halls a most goodly and sumptuous bed composed of mattresses,
 all, as was their wont, of velvet and cloth of gold, and had it
 covered with a quilt, adorned at certain intervals with enormous
 pearls, and most rare precious stones, insomuch that 'twas in after
 time accounted a priceless treasure, and furnished with two pillows
 to match it.  <milestone id="p00090077" />Which done, he bade array Messer Torello, who was
 now quite recovered, in a robe after the Saracenic fashion, the
 richest and goodliest thing of the kind that was ever seen, and wrap
 about his head, according to their wont, one of their huge turbans.
  <milestone id="p00090078" />Then, at a late hour, Saladin, attended by certain of his lords,
 entered the chamber where Messer Torello was, and seating himself
 beside him, all but wept as thus he began:  <milestone id="p00090079" /><q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello, the
 time is nigh at hand when you and I must part; wherefore, since
 I may neither give you my own, nor others' company (the journey
 that you are about to make not permitting it), I am come here, as
 'tis fitting, in this chamber to take my leave of you.  <milestone id="p00090080" />Wherefore,
 before I bid you adieu, I entreat you, by that friendship, that love,
 which is between us, that you forget me not, and that, if it be
 possible, when you have settled your affairs in Lombardy, you come
 at least once, before our days are ended, to visit me, that thereby I
 may both have the delight of seeing you again, and make good that
 omission which, by reason of your haste, I must needs now make;
  <milestone id="p00090081" />and that in the meanwhile it irk thee not to visit me by letter,
 and to ask of me whatever you shall have a mind to, and be sure
 that there lives not the man whom I shall content more gladly
 than you.</q>  <milestone id="p00090082" />Messer Torello could not refrain his tears, and so,
 <pb n="382" />with words few, and broken by his sobs, he answered that 'twas
 impossible that the Soldan's generous deeds and chivalrous character
 should ever be forgotten by him, and that without fail he would
 do as he bade him, so soon as occasion should serve him.  <milestone id="p00090083" />Whereupon
 Saladin tenderly embraced and kissed him, and with many a
 tear bade him adieu, and quitted the chamber. His lords then took
 leave of Messer Torello, and followed Saladin into the hall, where
 he had had the bed made ready.</p><p><milestone id="p00090084" />'Twas now late, and the necromancer being intent to hasten
 Messer Torello's transit, a physician brought him a potion, and
 having first shewn him what he was to give him by way of viaticum,
 caused him to drink it;  <milestone id="p00090085" />and not long after he fell asleep. In which
 state he was carried by Saladin's command, and laid on the goodly
 bed, whereon he set a large and fair and most sumptuous crown,
 marking it in such sort that there could be no mistake that it was
 sent by Saladin to Messer Torello's wife.  <milestone id="p00090086" />He next placed on
 Messer Torello's finger a ring, in which was set a carbuncle of
 such brilliance that it shewed as a lighted torch, and of well-nigh
 inestimable value. After which he girded on him a sword, the
 appointments of which might not readily be appraised. And therewithal
 he adorned him in front with a pendant, wherein were
 pearls, the like of which had never been seen, and not a few other
 rare jewels. And, moreover, on either side of him he set two
 vast basins of gold full of pistoles; and strings of pearls not a few,
 and rings and girdles, and other things, which 'twere tedious to
 enumerate, he disposed around him.  <milestone id="p00090087" />Which done, he kissed Messer
 Torello again, and bade the necromancer speed him on his journey.
 Whereupon, forthwith, the bed, with Messer Torello thereon, was
 borne away from before Saladin's eyes, and he and his barons
 remained conversing thereof.</p><p><milestone id="p00090088" />The bed, as Messer Torello had requested, had already been
 deposited in the church of San Piero in Ciel d'Oro at Pavia, and
 Messer Torello, with all the aforesaid jewels and ornaments upon
 and about him, was lying thereon, and still slept, when, upon the
 stroke of matins, the sacristan came into the church, light in hand,
 and presently setting eyes on the sumptuous bed, was not only
 amazed, but mightily terrified, insomuch that he turned back, and
 took to flight. Which the abbot and monks observing with no small
 <pb n="383" />surprise, asked wherefore he fled; and he told them. Whereupon:
  <milestone id="p00090089" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh,</q> quoth the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">thou art no longer a child, nor
 yet so new to this church, that thou shouldst so lightly be appalled:
 go we now, and see who it is that has given thee this childish fright.</q>
  <milestone id="p00090090" />So, with a blaze of torches, the abbot, attended by his monks, entered
 the church, and espied this wondrous costly bed whereon the knight
 slept, and while, hesitant and fearful, daring not to approach the bed,
 they scanned the rare and splendid jewels, it befell that, the efficacy
 of the potion being exhausted, Messer Torello awoke and heaved a
 great sigh.  <milestone id="p00090091" />Whereat the monks and the abbot quaking and crying
 out: <q direct="unspecified">Lord, help us!</q> one and all took to flight.  <milestone id="p00090092" />Messer Torello,
 opening his eyes and looking about him, saw, to his no small satisfaction,
 that without a doubt he was in the very place where he had craved of
 Saladin to be; so up he sate, and taking particular note of the
 matters with which he was surrounded, accounted the magnificence
 of Saladin to exceed even the measure, great though it was, that he
 already knew.  <milestone id="p00090093" />However, he still kept quiet, save that, perceiving
 the monks in flight, and surmising the reason, he began to call the
 abbot by name, bidding him be of good courage, for that he was his
 nephew, Torello.  <milestone id="p00090094" />Whereat the abbot did but wax more terrified,
 for that he deemed Torello had been many a month dead; but, after
 a while, as he heard himself still called, sound judgment got the
 better of his fears, and making the sign of the cross, he drew nigh
 Torello;  <milestone id="p00090095" />who said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Father, what is't you fear? By
 God's grace I live, and hither am come back from overseas.</q>  <milestone id="p00090096" />Whom,
 for all he had grown a long beard and was dressed in the Saracenic
 fashion, the abbot after a while recognized, and now, quite reassured,
 took by the hand, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Son, welcome home:</q> then: <q direct="unspecified">No
 cause hast thou to marvel at our fears,</q> he went on, <q direct="unspecified">seeing that
 there is never a soul in these parts but firmly believes thee to be
 dead, insomuch that I may tell thee that Madonna Adalieta, thy wife,
 overborne by the entreaties and menaces of her kinsfolk, and against
 her will, is provided with another husband, to whom she is this
 morning to go, and all is made ready for the nuptials and the
 attendant festivities.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090097" />Whereupon Messer Torello, being risen from the sumptuous
 bed, did the abbot and the monks wondrous cheer, and besought
 them, one and all, to tell never a soul of his return, until he had
 <pb n="384" />completed something that he had on hand. After which, having
 put the costly jewels in safe keeping, he recounted to the abbot all
 the story of his adventures to that very hour.  <milestone id="p00090098" />The abbot, rejoicing
 in his good fortune, joined with him in offering thanks to God.
 Messer Torello then asked him who might be his wife's new husband,
 and the abbot told him.  <milestone id="p00090099" />Quoth then Messer Torello:
 <q direct="unspecified">Before my return be known, I purpose to see how my wife will
 comport herself at the nuptials: wherefore, though 'tis not the wont
 of men of religion to go to such gatherings, I had lief that for love of
 me you arranged for us to go thither together.</q>  <milestone id="p00090100" />The abbot answered
 that he would gladly do so, and as soon as 'twas day, he sent word
 to the bridegroom that he had thoughts of being present at his
 nuptials, accompanied by a friend; whereto the gentleman made
 answer that he was much gratified.  <milestone id="p00090101" />So, at the breakfast hour Messer
 Torello, dressed as he was, hied him with the abbot to the bridegroom's
 house, as many as saw them gazing on him with wonder,
 but none recognizing him, and the abbot giving all to understand
 that he was a Saracen sent by the Soldan as ambassador to the King
 of France.  <milestone id="p00090102" />Messer Torello was accordingly seated at a table directly
 opposite that of his lady, whom he eyed with exceeding great delight,
 the more so that he saw that in her face which shewed him that she
 was chagrined by the nuptials. She in like manner from time to time
 bent her regard on him; howbeit, what with his long beard, and his
 foreign garb, and her firm persuasion that he was dead, she had still
 no sort of recollection of him.  <milestone id="p00090103" />However, Messer Torello at length
 deemed it time to make trial of her, whether she would remember
 him; wherefore he took the ring that the lady had given him on his
 departure, and keeping it close in the palm of his hand, he called to
 him a page that waited upon her, and said to him:  <milestone id="p00090104" /><q direct="unspecified">Tell the
 bride from me that 'tis the custom in my country, that, when a
 stranger, such as I, eats with a bride, like herself, at her wedding-feast,
 she, in token that he is welcome to her board, sends him the
 cup from which she herself drinks, full of wine; and when the
 stranger has drunk his fill, he closes the cup, and the bride drinks
 what is left therein.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090105" />The page carried the message to the lady, who, being of good
 understanding and manners, and supposing him to be some very great
 man, by way of shewing that she was gratified by his presence,
 com<pb n="385" />manded
 that a gilt cup, that was on the table before her, should be
 rinsed, and filled with wine, and borne to the gentleman.  <milestone id="p00090106" />Which
 being done, Messer Torello, having privily conveyed her ring into
 his mouth, let it fall (while he drank) into the cup on such wise that
 none wist thereof; and leaving but a little wine at the bottom, closed
 the cup and returned it to the lady;  <milestone id="p00090107" />who, having taken it, that she
 might do full honour to the custom of her guest's country, lifted
 the lid, and set the cup to her mouth; whereby espying the ring,
 she thereon mutely gazed a while, and recognizing it for that which
 she had given Messer Torello on his departure, she steadfastly
 regarded the supposed stranger, whom now she also recognized.
 Whereupon well-nigh distracted, oversetting the table in front of
 her, she exclaimed: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis my lord, 'tis verily Messer Torello;</q>
  <milestone id="p00090108" />and rushing to the table at which he sate, giving never a thought to
 her apparel, or aught that was on the table, she flung herself upon
 it; and reaching forward as far as she could, she threw her arms
 about him, and hugged him; nor, for aught that any said or did,
 could she be induced to release his neck, until Messer Torello himself
 bade her forbear a while, for that she would have time enough
 to kiss him thereafter.  <milestone id="p00090109" />The lady then stood up, and for a while all
 was disorder, albeit the feast was yet more gladsome than before by
 reason of the recovery of so honourable a knight: then, at Messer
 Torello's entreaty, all were silent, while he recounted to them the
 story of his adventures from the day of his departure to that hour,
 concluding by saying that the gentleman who, deeming him to be
 dead, had taken his lady to wife, ought not to be affronted, if he,
 being alive, reclaimed her.  <milestone id="p00090110" />The bridegroom, albeit he was somewhat
 crestfallen, made answer in frank and friendly sort, that 'twas
 for Messer Torello to do what he liked with his own.  <milestone id="p00090111" />The lady
 resigned the ring and the crown that her new spouse had given her,
 and put on the ring she had taken from the cup, and likewise the
 crown sent her by the Soldan; and so, forth they hied them, and
 with full nuptial pomp wended their way to Messer Torello's house;
 and there for a great while they made merry with his late disconsolate
 friends and kinsfolk and all the citizens, who accounted his
 restoration as little short of a miracle.</p><p><milestone id="p00090112" />Messer Torello, having bestowed part of his rare jewels upon
 him who had borne the cost of the wedding-feast, and part on the
 <pb n="386" />abbot, and many other folk; and having by more than one messenger
 sent word of his safe home-coming and prosperous estate to Saladin,
 acknowledging himself ever his friend and vassal, lived many years
 thereafter with his worthy lady, acquitting himself yet more courteously
 than of yore.  <milestone id="p00090113" />Such, then, was the end of the troubles of
 Messer Torello and his dear lady, and such the reward of their
 cheerful and ready courtesies.</p><p>Now some there are that strive to do offices of courtesy, and
 have the means, but do them with so ill a grace, that, ere they are
 done, they have in effect sold them at a price above their worth:
 wherefore, if no reward ensue to them thereof, neither they nor
 other folk have cause to marvel.</p></div2><pb n="387" /><div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov1010"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00100001" />The Marquis of Saluzzo, overborne by the entreaties of
 his vassals, consents to take a wife, but, being minded
 to please himself in the choice of her, takes a husbandman's
 daughter. He has two children by her, both
 of whom he makes her believe that he has put to death.
 Afterward, feigning to be tired of her, and to have
 taken another wife, he turns her out of doors in her
 shift, and brings his daughter into the house in guise
 of his bride; but, finding her patient under it all, he
 brings her home again, and shews her her children,
 now grown up, and honours her, and causes her to be
 honoured, as Marchioness.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00100002" />Ended the king's long story, with which all seemed to be very
 well pleased, quoth Dioneo with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">The good man that
 looked that night to cause the bogey's tail to droop, would scarce have
 contributed two pennyworth of all the praise you bestow on Messer
 Torello:</q> then, witting that it now only remained for him to tell,
 thus he began:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00100003" />Gentle my ladies, this day, meseems, is dedicate to
 Kings and Soldans and folk of the like quality; wherefore, that I
 stray not too far from you, I am minded to tell you somewhat of a
 Marquis; certes, nought magnificent, but a piece of mad folly, albeit
 there came good thereof to him in the end. The which I counsel
 none to copy, for that great pity 'twas that it turned out well with
 him.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00100004" />There was in olden days a certain Marquis of Saluzzo, Gualtieri
 <pb n="388" />by name, a young man, but head of the house, who, having
 neither wife nor child, passed his time in nought else but in hawking
 and hunting, and of taking a wife and begetting children had
 no thought; wherein he should have been accounted very wise:
  <milestone id="p00100005" />but his vassals, brooking it ill, did oftentimes entreat him to take
 a wife, that he might not die without an heir, and they be left
 without a lord; offering to find him one of such a pattern, and
 of such parentage, that he might marry with good hope, and be
 well content with the sequel.  <milestone id="p00100006" />To whom: <q direct="unspecified">My friends,</q> replied
 Gualtieri, <q direct="unspecified">you enforce me to that which I had resolved never to do,
 seeing how hard it is to find a wife, whose ways accord well with
 one's own, and how plentiful is the supply of such as run counter
 thereto, and how grievous a life he leads who chances upon a lady
 that matches ill with him.  <milestone id="p00100007" />And to say that you think to know the
 daughters by the qualities of their fathers and mothers, and thereby--so
 you would argue--to provide me with a wife to my liking, is but
 folly; for I wot not how you may penetrate the secrets of their
 mothers so as to know their fathers; and granted that you do know
 them, daughters oftentimes resemble neither of their parents.  <milestone id="p00100008" />However,
 as you are minded to rivet these fetters upon me, I am content
 that so it be; and that I may have no cause to reproach any but
 myself, should it turn out ill, I am resolved that my wife shall be of
 my own choosing; but of this rest assured, that, no matter whom
 I choose, if she receive not from you the honour due to a lady, you
 shall prove to your great cost, how sorely I resent being thus constrained
 by your importunity to take a wife against my will.</q></p><p>The worthy men replied that they were well content, so only he
 would marry without more ado.  <milestone id="p00100009" />And Gualtieri, who had long noted
 with approval the mien of a poor girl that dwelt on a farm hard by
 his house, and found her fair enough, deemed that with her he might
 pass a tolerably happy life. Wherefore he sought no further, but
 forthwith resolved to marry her; and having sent for her father, who
 was a very poor man, he contracted with him to take her to wife.
  <milestone id="p00100010" />Which done, Gualtieri assembled all the friends he had in those parts,
 and: <q direct="unspecified">My friends,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">you were and are minded that I
 should take a wife, and rather to comply with your wishes, than for
 any desire that I had to marry, I have made up my mind to do so.
  <milestone id="p00100011" />You remember the promise you gave me, to wit, that, whomsoever I
 <pb n="389" />should take, you would pay her the honour due to a lady. Which
 promise I now require you to keep, the time being come when I am
 to keep mine.  <milestone id="p00100012" />I have found hard by here a maiden after mine own
 heart, whom I purpose to take to wife, and to bring hither to my
 house in the course of a few days. Wherefore bethink you, how
 you may make the nuptial feast splendid, and welcome her with all
 honour; that I may confess myself satisfied with your observance of
 your promise, as you will be with my observance of mine.</q>  <milestone id="p00100013" />The
 worthy men, one and all, answered with alacrity that they were well
 content, and that, whoever she might be, they would entreat her as
 a lady, and pay her all due honour as such. After which, they all
 addressed them to make goodly and grand and gladsome celebration
 of the event, as did also Gualtieri.  <milestone id="p00100014" />He arranged for a wedding most
 stately and fair, and bade thereto a goodly number of his friends and
 kinsfolk, and great gentlemen, and others, of the neighbourhood;
 and therewithal he caused many a fine and costly robe to be cut and
 fashioned to the figure of a girl who seemed to him of the like proportions
 as the girl that he purposed to wed; and laid in store,
 besides, of girdles and rings, with a costly and beautiful crown, and
 all the other paraphernalia of a bride.</p><p><milestone id="p00100015" />The day that he had appointed for the wedding being come,
 about half tierce he got him to horse with as many as had come to
 do him honour, and having made all needful dispositions: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis time to go bring home the bride.</q> And so
 away he rode with his company to the village;  <milestone id="p00100016" />where, being come
 to the house of the girl's father, they found her returning from the
 spring with a bucket of water, making all the haste she could, that
 she might afterwards go with the other women to see Gualtieri's
 bride come by. Whom Gualtieri no sooner saw, than he called her
 by her name, to wit, Griselda, and asked her where her father was.
 To whom she modestly made answer: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, he is in the house.</q>
  <milestone id="p00100017" />Whereupon Gualtieri dismounted, and having bidden the rest await
 him without, entered the cottage alone; and meeting her father,
 whose name was Giannucolo: <q direct="unspecified">I am come,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">to wed
 Griselda, but first of all there are some matters I would learn from
 her own lips in thy presence.</q>  <milestone id="p00100018" />He then asked her, whether, if he
 took her to wife, she would study to comply with his wishes, and be
 not wroth, no matter what he might say or do, and be obedient,
 <pb n="390" />with not a few other questions of a like sort: to all which she
 answered, ay.  <milestone id="p00100019" />Whereupon Gualtieri took her by the hand, led her
 forth, and before the eyes of all his company, and as many other
 folk as were there, caused her to strip naked, and let bring the
 garments that he had had fashioned for her, and had her forthwith
 arrayed therein, and upon her unkempt head let set a crown;  <milestone id="p00100020" />and
 then, while all wondered: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">this is she
 whom I purpose to make my wife, so she be minded to have me for
 husband.</q> Then, she standing abashed and astonied, he turned to
 her, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Griselda, wilt thou have me for thy husband?</q>  <milestone id="p00100021" />To
 whom: <q direct="unspecified">Ay, my lord,</q> answered she.  <milestone id="p00100022" /><q direct="unspecified">And I will have thee to
 wife,</q> said he, and married her before them all. And having set her
 upon a palfrey, he brought her home with pomp.</p><p><milestone id="p00100023" />The wedding was fair and stately, and had he married a daughter
 of the King of France, the feast could not have been more splendid.
  <milestone id="p00100024" />It seemed as if, with the change of her garb, the bride had acquired
 a new dignity of mind and mien. She was, as we have said, fair of
 form and feature; and therewithal she was now grown so engaging
 and gracious and debonair, that she shewed no longer as the shepherdess,
 and the daughter of Giannucolo, but as the daughter of some noble
 lord, insomuch that she caused as many as had known her before to
 marvel. Moreover, she was so obedient and devoted to her husband,
 that he deemed himself the happiest and luckiest man in the world.
  <milestone id="p00100025" />And likewise so gracious and kindly was she to her husband's vassals,
 that there was none of them but loved her more dearly than himself,
 and was zealous to do her honour, and prayed for her welfare and
 prosperity and aggrandisement, and instead of, as erstwhile, saying
 that Gualtieri had done foolishly to take her to wife, now averred
 that he had not his like in the world for wisdom and discernment,
 for that, save to him, her noble qualities would ever have remained
 hidden under her sorry apparel and the garb of the peasant girl.
  <milestone id="p00100026" />And in short she so comported herself as in no long time to bring it
 to pass that, not only in the marquisate, but far and wide besides, her
 virtues and her admirable conversation were matter of common talk,
 and, if aught had been said to the disadvantage of her husband, when
 he married her, the judgment was now altogether to the contrary
 effect.</p><p><milestone id="p00100027" />She had not been long with Gualtieri before she conceived; and
 <pb n="391" />in due time she was delivered of a girl; whereat Gualtieri made great
 cheer. But, soon after, a strange humour took possession of him,
 to wit, to put her patience to the proof by prolonged and intolerable
 hard usage; wherefore he began by afflicting her with his gibes,
 putting on a vexed air, and telling her that his vassals were most
 sorely dissatisfied with her by reason of her base condition, and all
 the more so since they saw that she was a mother, and that they
 did nought but most ruefully murmur at the birth of a daughter.
  <milestone id="p00100028" />Whereto Griselda, without the least change of countenance or sign
 of discomposure, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, do with me as thou
 mayst deem best for thine own honour and comfort, for well I wot
 that I am of less account than they, and unworthy of this honourable
 estate to which of thy courtesy thou hast advanced me.</q>  <milestone id="p00100029" />By which
 answer Gualtieri was well pleased, witting that she was in no degree
 puffed up with pride by his, or any other's, honourable entreatment
 of her.  <milestone id="p00100030" />A while afterwards, having in general terms given his wife
 to understand that the vassals could not endure her daughter, he sent
 her a message by a servant. So the servant came, and: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q>
 quoth he with a most dolorous mien, <q direct="unspecified">so I value my life, I must
 needs do my lord's bidding. He has bidden me take your daughter
 and . . .</q>  <milestone id="p00100031" />He said no more, but the lady by what she heard, and
 read in his face, and remembered of her husband's words, understood
 that he was bidden to put the child to death. Whereupon she
 presently took the child from the cradle, and having kissed and blessed
 her, albeit she was very sore at heart, she changed not countenance,
 but placed it in the servant's arms, saying:  <milestone id="p00100032" /><q direct="unspecified">See that thou leave
 nought undone that my lord and thine has charged thee to do, but
 leave her not so that the beasts and the birds devour her, unless he
 have so bidden thee.</q>  <milestone id="p00100033" />So the servant took the child, and told
 Gualtieri what the lady had said; and Gualtieri, marvelling at her
 constancy, sent him with the child to Bologna, to one of his kinswomen,
 whom he besought to rear and educate the child with all
 care, but never to let it be known whose child she was.</p><p><milestone id="p00100034" />Soon after it befell that the lady again conceived, and in due
 time was delivered of a son, whereat Gualtieri was overjoyed. But,
 not content with what he had done, he now even more poignantly
 afflicted the lady; and one day with a ruffled mien:  <milestone id="p00100035" /><q direct="unspecified">Wife,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">since thou gavest birth to this boy, I may on no wise live
 <pb n="392" />in peace with my vassals, so bitterly do they reproach me that a
 grandson of Giannucolo is to succeed me as their lord; and therefore I
 fear that, so I be not minded to be sent a packing hence, I must even
 do herein as I did before, and in the end put thee away, and take
 another wife.</q>  <milestone id="p00100036" />The lady heard him patiently, and answered only:
 <q direct="unspecified">My lord, study how thou mayst content thee and best please thyself,
 and waste no thought upon me, for there is nought I desire save in so
 far as I know that 'tis thy pleasure.</q>  <milestone id="p00100037" />Not many days after, Gualtieri,
 in like manner as he had sent for the daughter, sent for the son, and
 having made a shew of putting him to death, provided for his, as for
 the girl's, nurture at Bologna.  <milestone id="p00100038" />Whereat the lady shewed no more
 discomposure of countenance or speech than at the loss of her
 daughter: which Gualtieri found passing strange, and inly affirmed
 that there was never another woman in the world that would have
 so done. And but that he had marked that she was most tenderly
 affectionate towards her children, while 'twas well pleasing to him, he
 had supposed that she was tired of them, whereas he knew that 'twas
 of her discretion that she so did.  <milestone id="p00100039" />His vassals, who believed that he had
 put the children to death, held him mightily to blame for his cruelty,
 and felt the utmost compassion for the lady. She, however, said
 never aught to the ladies that condoled with her on the death of her
 children, but that the pleasure of him that had begotten them was
 her pleasure likewise.</p><p><milestone id="p00100040" />Years not a few had passed since the girl's birth, when Gualtieri
 at length deemed the time come to put his wife's patience to the
 final proof. Accordingly, in the presence of a great company of his
 vassals he declared that on no wise might he longer brook to have
 Griselda to wife, that he confessed that in taking her he had done a
 sorry thing and the act of a stripling, and that he therefore meant to
 do what he could to procure the Pope's dispensation to put Griselda
 away, and take another wife: for which cause being much upbraided
 by many worthy men, he made no other answer but only that needs
 must it so be.  <milestone id="p00100041" />Whereof the lady being apprised, and now deeming
 that she must look to go back to her father's house, and perchance
 tend the sheep, as she had aforetime, and see him, to whom she
 was utterly devoted, engrossed by another woman, did inly bewail
 herself right sorely: but still with the same composed mien with
 which she had borne Fortune's former buffets, she set herself to endure
 <pb n="393" />this last outrage.  <milestone id="p00100042" />Nor was it long before Gualtieri by counterfeit
 letters, which he caused to be sent to him from Rome, made his
 vassals believe that the Pope had thereby given him a dispensation to
 put Griselda away, and take another wife. Wherefore, having caused
 her to be brought before him, he said to her in the presence of not a
 few:  <milestone id="p00100043" /><q direct="unspecified">Wife, by license granted me by the Pope, I am now free
 to put thee away, and take another wife; and, for that my forbears
 have always been great gentlemen and lords of these parts, whereas
 thine have ever been husbandmen, I purpose that thou go back
 to Giannucolo's house with the dowry that thou broughtest me;
 whereupon I shall bring home a lady that I have found, and who is
 meet to be my wife.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00100044" />'Twas not without travail most grievous that the lady, as she
 heard this announcement, got the better of her woman's nature, and
 suppressing her tears, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, I ever knew that
 my low degree was on no wise congruous with your nobility, and
 acknowledged that the rank I had with you was of your and God's
 bestowal, nor did I ever make as if it were mine by gift, or so esteem
 it, but still accounted it as a loan. 'Tis your pleasure to recall it,
 and therefore it should be, and is, my pleasure to render it up to you.
 So, here is your ring, with which you espoused me; take it back.
  <milestone id="p00100045" />You bid me take with me the dowry that I brought you; which to
 do will require neither paymaster on your part nor purse nor packhorse
 on mine; for I am not unmindful that naked was I when you
 first had me. And if you deem it seemly that that body in which I
 have borne children, by you begotten, be beheld of all, naked will I
 depart; but yet, I pray you, be pleased, in guerdon of the virginity
 that I brought you and take not away, to suffer me to bear hence
 upon my back a single shift--I crave no more--besides my dowry.</q>
  <milestone id="p00100046" />There was nought of which Gualtieri was so fain as to weep; but
 yet, setting his face as a flint, he made answer: <q direct="unspecified">I allow thee a
 shift to thy back; so get thee hence.</q>  <milestone id="p00100047" />All that stood by besought
 him to give her a robe, that she, who had been his wife for thirteen
 years and more, might not be seen to quit his house in so sorry and
 shameful a plight, having nought on her but a shift. But their
 entreaties went for nothing: the lady in her shift, and barefoot and
 bareheaded, having bade them adieu, departed the house, and went
 back to her father amid the tears and lamentations of all that saw
 <pb n="394" />her.  <milestone id="p00100048" />Giannucolo, who had ever deemed it a thing incredible
 that Gualtieri should keep his daughter to wife, and had looked
 for this to happen every day, and had kept the clothes that she
 had put off on the morning that Gualtieri had wedded her, now
 brought them to her; and she, having resumed them, applied herself
 to the petty drudgery of her father's house, as she had been wont,
 enduring with fortitude this cruel visitation of adverse Fortune.</p><p><milestone id="p00100049" />Now no sooner had Gualtieri dismissed Griselda, than he gave his
 vassals to understand that he had taken to wife a daughter of one of
 the Counts of Panago. He accordingly made great preparations as
 for the nuptials, during which he sent for Griselda. To whom,
 being come, quoth he:  <milestone id="p00100050" /><q direct="unspecified">I am bringing hither my new bride, and
 in this her first home-coming I purpose to shew her honour; and
 thou knowest that women I have none in the house that know
 how to set chambers in due order, or attend to the many other
 matters that so joyful an event requires; wherefore do thou, that
 understandest these things better than another, see to all that needs
 be done, and bid hither such ladies as thou mayst see fit, and
 receive them, as if thou wert the lady of the house, and then,
 when the nuptials are ended, thou mayst go back to thy cottage.</q>
  <milestone id="p00100051" />Albeit each of these words pierced Griselda's heart like a knife,
 for that, in resigning her good fortune, she had not been able to
 renounce the love she bore Gualtieri, nevertheless: <q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> she
 made answer, <q direct="unspecified">I am ready and prompt to do your pleasure.</q>  <milestone id="p00100052" />And
 so, clad in her sorry garments of coarse romagnole, she entered the
 house, which, but a little before, she had quitted in her shift, and
 addressed her to sweep the chambers, and arrange arras and cushions
 in the halls, and make ready the kitchen, and set her hand to everything,
 as if she had been a paltry serving-wench: nor did she rest
 until she had brought all into such meet and seemly trim as the
 occasion demanded.  <milestone id="p00100053" />This done, she invited in Gualtieri's name all
 the ladies of those parts to be present at his nuptials, and awaited the
 event. The day being come, still wearing her sorry weeds, but in
 heart and soul and mien the lady, she received the ladies as they
 came, and gave each a gladsome greeting.</p><p><milestone id="p00100054" />Now Gualtieri, as we said, had caused his children to be carefully
 nurtured and brought up by a kinswoman of his at Bologna, which
 kinswoman was married into the family of the Counts of Panago;
 <pb n="395" />and, the girl being now twelve years old, and the loveliest creature
 that ever was seen, and the boy being about six years old, he had
 sent word to his kinswoman's husband at Bologna, praying him to
 be pleased to come with this girl and boy of his to Saluzzo, and to
 see that he brought a goodly and honourable company with him,
 and to give all to understand that he brought the girl to him to
 wife, and on no wis&#232; to disclose to any, who she really was.  <milestone id="p00100055" />The
 gentleman did as the Marquis bade him, and within a few days of
 his setting forth arrived at Saluzzo about breakfast-time with the
 girl, and her brother, and a noble company, and found all the folk of
 those parts, and much people besides, gathered there in expectation
 of Gualtieri's new bride.  <milestone id="p00100056" />Who, being received by the ladies, was
 no sooner come into the hall, where the tables were set, than Griselda
 advanced to meet her, saying with hearty cheer: <q direct="unspecified">Welcome, my
 lady.</q> So the ladies, who had with much instance, but in vain, besought
 Gualtieri, either to let Griselda keep in another room, or at any
 rate to furnish her with one of the robes that had been hers, that she
 might not present herself in such a sorry guise before the strangers,
 sate down to table; and the service being begun,  <milestone id="p00100057" />the eyes of all were
 set on the girl, and every one said that Gualtieri had made a good
 exchange, and Griselda joined with the rest in greatly commending
 her, and also her little brother.  <milestone id="p00100058" />And now Gualtieri, sated at last
 with all that he had seen of his wife's patience, marking that this
 new and strange turn made not the least alteration in her demeanour,
 and being well assured that 'twas not due to apathy, for he knew her
 to be of excellent understanding, deemed it time to relieve her
 of the suffering which he judged her to dissemble under a resolute
 front; and so, having called her to him in presence of them all, he
 said with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">And what thinkst thou of our bride?</q>
  <milestone id="p00100059" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> replied Griselda, <q direct="unspecified">I think mighty well of her; and if
 she be but as discreet as she is fair--and so I deem her--I make no
 doubt but you may reckon to lead with her a life of incomparable
 felicity; but with all earnestness I entreat you, that you spare her
 those tribulations which you did once inflict upon another that was
 yours, for I scarce think she would be able to bear them, as well
 because she is younger, as for that she has been delicately nurtured,
 whereas that other had known no respite of hardship since she was
 but a little child.</q>  <milestone id="p00100060" />Marking that she made no doubt but that the
 <pb n="396" />girl was to be his wife, and yet spoke never a whit the less sweetly,
 Gualtieri caused her to sit down beside him, and:  <milestone id="p00100061" /><q direct="unspecified">Griselda,</q>
 said he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis now time that thou see the reward of thy long patience,
 and that those, who have deemed me cruel and unjust and insensate,
 should know that what I did was done of purpose aforethought, for
 that I was minded to give both thee and them a lesson, that thou
 mightst learn to be a wife, and they in like manner might learn how
 to take and keep a wife, and that I might beget me perpetual peace
 with thee for the rest of my life; whereof being in great fear, when
 I came to take a wife, lest I should be disappointed, I therefore, to
 put the matter to the proof, did, and how sorely thou knowest, harass
 and afflict thee.  <milestone id="p00100062" />And since I never knew thee either by deed or by
 word to deviate from my will, I now, deeming myself to have of
 thee that assurance of happiness which I desired, am minded to
 restore to thee at once all that, step by step, I took from thee, and
 by extremity of joy to compensate the tribulations that I inflicted
 on thee.  <milestone id="p00100063" />Receive, then, this girl, whom thou supposest to be my
 bride, and her brother, with glad heart, as thy children and mine.
 These are they, whom by thee and many another it has long been
 supposed that I did ruthlessly to death, and I am thy husband, that
 loves thee more dearly than aught else, deeming that other there is
 none that has the like good cause to be well content with his wife.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00100064" />Which said, he embraced and kissed her; and then, while she
 wept for joy, they rose and hied them there where sate the daughter,
 all astonied to hear the news, whom, as also her brother, they tenderly
 embraced, and explained to them, and many others that stood
 by, the whole mystery.  <milestone id="p00100065" />Whereat the ladies, transported with delight,
 rose from table and betook them with Griselda to a chamber,
 and, with better omen, divested her of her sorry garb, and arrayed
 her in one of her own robes of state; and so, in guise of a lady
 (howbeit in her rags she had shewed as no less) they led her back
 into the hall.  <milestone id="p00100066" />Wondrous was the cheer which there they made
 with the children; and, all overjoyed at the event, they revelled and
 made merry amain, and prolonged the festivities for several days;
 and very discreet they pronounced Gualtieri, albeit they censured as
 intolerably harsh the probation to which he had subjected Griselda,
 and most discreet beyond all compare they accounted Griselda.</p><p><milestone id="p00100067" />Some days after, the Count of Panago returned to Bologna, and
 <pb n="397" />Gualtieri took Giannucolo from his husbandry, and established him
 in honour as his father-in-law, wherein to his great solace he lived
 for the rest of his days. Gualtieri himself, having mated his daughter
 with a husband of high degree, lived long and happily thereafter with
 Griselda, to whom he ever paid all honour.</p><p><milestone id="p00100068" />Now what shall we say in this case but that even into the cots of
 the poor the heavens let fall at times spirits divine, as into the palaces
 of kings souls that are fitter to tend hogs than to exercise lordship over
 men? Who but Griselda had been able, with a countenance not only
 tearless, but cheerful, to endure the hard and unheard-of trials to which
 Gualtieri subjected her?  <milestone id="p00100069" />Who perhaps might have deemed himself
 to have made no bad investment, had he chanced upon one, who,
 having been turned out of his house in her shift, had found means so
 to dust the pelisse of another as to get herself thereby a fine robe.</p></div2><div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d10conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p00970001" />So ended Dioneo's story, whereof the ladies, diversely inclining,
 one to censure where another found matter for commendation, had
 discoursed not a little, when the king, having glanced at the sky,
 and marked that the sun was now low, insomuch that 'twas nigh the
 vesper hour, still keeping his seat, thus began:  <milestone id="p00970002" /><q direct="unspecified">Exquisite my
 ladies, as, methinks, you wot, 'tis not only in minding them of
 the past and apprehending the present that the wit of mortals
 consists; but by one means or the other to be able to foresee the
 future is by the sages accounted the height of wisdom.  <milestone id="p00970003" />Now,
 to-morrow, as you know, 'twill be fifteen days since, in quest of
 recreation and for the conservation of our health and life, we, shunning
 the dismal and dolorous and afflicting spectacles that have ceased
 not in our city since this season of pestilence began, took our departure
 from Florence.  <milestone id="p00970004" />Wherein, to my thinking, we have done
 nought that was not seemly; for, if I have duly used my powers of
 observation, albeit some gay stories, and of a kind to stimulate
 concupiscence,
 have here been told, and we have daily known no lack
 of dainty dishes and good wine, nor yet of music and song, things,
 one and all, apt to incite weak minds to that which is not seemly,
 neither on your part, nor on ours, have I marked deed or word, or
 aught of any kind, that called for reprehension;  <milestone id="p00970005" />but, by what I have
 seen and heard, seemliness and the sweet intimacy of brothers and
 sisters have ever reigned among us. Which, assuredly, for the honour
 and advantage which you and I have had thereof, is most grateful to
 <pb n="398" />me.  <milestone id="p00970006" />Wherefore, lest too long continuance in this way of life might
 beget some occasion of weariness, and that no man may be able to
 misconstrue our too long abidance here, and as we have all of us had
 our day's share of the honour which still remains in me, I should
 deem it meet, so you be of like mind, that we now go back whence
 we came:  <milestone id="p00970007" />and that the rather that our company, the bruit whereof
 has already reached divers others that are in our neighbourhood, might
 be so increased that all our pleasure would be destroyed. And so, if
 my counsel meet with your approval, I will keep the crown I have
 received of you until our departure, which, I purpose, shall be tomorrow
 morning. Should you decide otherwise, I have already
 determined whom to crown for the ensuing day.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00970008" />Much debate ensued among the ladies and young men; but in
 the end they approved the king's proposal as expedient and seemly;
 and resolved to do even as he had said. The king therefore
 summoned the seneschal; and having conferred with him of the
 order he was to observe on the morrow, he dismissed the company
 until supper-time.  <milestone id="p00970009" />So, the king being risen, the ladies and the rest
 likewise rose, and betook them, as they were wont, to their several
 diversions. Supper-time being come, they supped with exceeding
 great delight. Which done, they addressed them to song and music
 and dancing; and, while Lauretta was leading a dance, the king bade
 Fiammetta give them a song; whereupon Fiammetta right debonairly
 sang on this wise:</p><div3 who="fiammetta" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p00970010" /><l>So came but Love, and brought no jealousy,</l>
<l>So blithe, I wot, as I,</l>
<l>Dame were there none, be she whoe'er she be.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00970011" /><l>If youth's fresh, lusty pride</l>
<l>May lady of her lover well content,</l>
<l>Or valour's just renown,</l>
<l>Hardihood, prowess tried,</l>
<l>Wit, noble mien, discourse most excellent,</l>
<l>And of all grace the crown;</l>
<l>That she am I, who, fain for love to swoun,</l>
<l>There where my hope doth lie</l>
<l>These several virtues all conjoined do see.</l></lg><pb n="399" /><lg><milestone id="p00970012" /><l>But, for that I less wise</l>
<l>Than me no whit do other dames discern,</l>
<l>Trembling with sore dismay,</l>
<l>I still the worst surmise,</l>
<l>Deeming their hearts with the same flame to burn</l>
<l>That of mine maketh prey:</l>
<l>Wherefore of him that is my hope's one stay</l>
<l>Disconsolate I sigh,</l>
<l>Yea mightily, and daily do me dree.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00970013" /><l>If but my lord as true</l>
<l>As worthy to be loved I might approve,</l>
<l>I were not jealous then:</l>
<l>But, for that charmer new</l>
<l>Doth all too often gallant lure to love,</l>
<l>Forsworn I hold all men,</l>
<l>And sick at heart I am, of death full fain;</l>
<l>Nor lady doth him eye,</l>
<l>But I do quake, lest she him wrest from me.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00970014" /><l>'Fore God, then, let each she</l>
<l>List to my prayer, nor e'er in my despite</l>
<l>Such grievous wrong essay;</l>
<l>For should there any be</l>
<l>That by or speech or mien's allurements light</l>
<l>Of him to rob me may</l>
<l>Study or plot, I, witting, shall find way,</l>
<l>My beauty it aby!</l>
<l>To cause her sore lament such frenesie.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p00970015" />As soon as Fiammetta had ended her song, Dioneo, who was
 beside her, said with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, 'twould be a great courtesy
 on your part to do all ladies to wit, who he is, that he be not stolen
 from you in ignorance, seeing that you threaten such dire resentment.</q>
 Several other songs followed; and it being then nigh upon
 midnight, all, as the king was pleased to order, betook them to rest.
  <milestone id="p00970016" />With the first light of the new day they rose, and, the seneschal
 having already conveyed thence all their chattels, they, following the
 lead of their discreet king, hied them back to Florence; and in Santa
 Maria Novella, whence they had set forth, the three young men
 <pb n="400" />took leave of the seven ladies, and departed to find other diversions
 elsewhere, while the ladies in due time repaired to their homes.</p></div2></div1>