<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov0808"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08080001" />Two men keep with one another: the one
	lies with the other's
	wife: the other, being ware thereof, manages with the
	aid of his wife to have the one locked in a chest, upon
	which he then lies with the wife of him that is locked
	therein.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08080002" />Grievous and distressful was it to
      the ladies to hear how it fared
      with Elena; but as they accounted the retribution in a measure
      righteous, they were satisfied to expend upon her but a moderate
      degree of compassion, albeit they censured the scholar as severe,
      intemperately relentless, and indeed ruthless, in his vengeance.
      However, Pampinea having brought the story to a close, the queen
      bade Fiammetta follow suit; and prompt to obey, Fiammetta thus
      spoke:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08080003" />Debonair my ladies, as, methinks, your feelings must have
	been somewhat harrowed by the severity of the resentful scholar, I
	deem it meet to soothe your vexed spirits with something of a more
	cheerful order. Wherefore I am minded to tell you a little story of
	a young man who bore an affront in a milder temper, and avenged
	himself with more moderation. Whereby you may understand that
	one should be satisfied if the ass and the wall are quits, nor by
	indulging a vindictive spirit to excess turn the requital of a wrong
	into an occasion of wrong-doing.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08080004" />You are to know, then, that at Siena,
 as I have heard tell, there dwelt two young men of good substance,
 and, for plebeians, of good family, the one Spinelloccio Tanena, the
 other Zeppa di Mino, by name; who, their houses being contiguous
 in the Camollia,<note>A suburb of Siena.</note> <milestone id="p08080005" />kept ever together, and, by
 what appeared, loved
 each other as brothers, or even more so, and had each a very fine
 <pb n="231" />woman to wife. <milestone id="p08080006" />Now it so befell that Spinelloccio, being much in
 Zeppa's house, as well when Zeppa was not, as when he was there,
 grew so familiar with Zeppa's wife, that he sometimes lay with her;
 and on this wise they continued to forgather a great while before any
 one was ware of it. <milestone id="p08080007" />However, one of these days Zeppa being at
 home, though the lady wist it not, Spinelloccio came in quest of
 him; and, the lady sending word that he was not at home, he forthwith
 went upstairs and found the lady in the saloon, and seeing none
 else there, kissed her, as did she him.</p><p><milestone id="p08080008" />Zeppa saw all that passed, but said nothing and kept close, being
 minded to see how the game would end, and soon saw his wife and
 Spinelloccio, still in one another's arms, hie them to her chamber and
 lock themselves in: whereat he was mightily incensed. <milestone id="p08080009" />But, witting
 that to make a noise, or do aught else overt, would not lessen but
 rather increase his dishonour, he cast about how he might be avenged
 on such wise that, without the affair getting wind, he might content
 his soul; and having, after long pondering, hit, as he thought, upon
 the expedient, he budged not from his retreat, until Spinelloccio had
 parted from the lady. <milestone id="p08080010" />Whereupon he hied him into the chamber,
 and there finding the lady with her head-gear, which Spinelloccio in
 toying with her had disarranged, scarce yet readjusted: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,
 what dost thou?</q> quoth he. <milestone id="p08080011" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Why, dost not see?</q>
 returned the lady. 
<milestone id="p08080012" /><q direct="unspecified">Troth do I,</q> rejoined he, <q direct="unspecified">and somewhat else
 have I seen that I would I had not.</q> And so he questioned her of
 what had passed, and she, being mightily afraid, did after long parley
 confess that which she might not plausibly deny, to wit, her intimacy
 with Spinelloccio, and fell a beseeching him with tears to pardon her.
 <milestone id="p08080013" /><q direct="unspecified">Lo, now, wife,</q> quoth Zeppa, <q direct="unspecified">thou hast done wrong, and, so thou
 wouldst have me pardon thee, have a care to do exactly as I shall bid
 thee; to wit, on this wise: 
<milestone id="p08080014" />thou must tell Spinelloccio to find some
 occasion to part from me to-morrow morning about tierce, and come
 hither to thee; and while he is here I will come back, and when
 thou hearest me coming, thou wilt get him into this chest, and lock
 him in there; which when thou hast done, I will tell thee what else
 thou hast to do, which thou mayst do without the least misgiving,
 for I promise thee I will do him no harm.</q> The lady, to content
 him, promised to do as he bade, and she kept her word.</p><p><milestone id="p08080015" />The morrow came, and Zeppa and Spinelloccio being together
 <pb n="232" />about tierce, Spinelloccio, having promised the lady to come to see
 her at that hour, said to Zeppa: <q direct="unspecified">I must go breakfast with a
 friend, whom I had life not keep in waiting; therefore, adieu!</q>
 <milestone id="p08080016" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but,</q> quoth Zeppa, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not yet breakfast-time.</q> 
<milestone id="p08080017" /><q direct="unspecified">No
 matter,</q> returned Spinelloccio, <q direct="unspecified">I have business on which I must
 speak with him; so I must be in good time.</q> 
<milestone id="p08080018" />Whereupon Spinelloccio
 took his leave of Zeppa, and having reached Zeppa's house by
 a slightly circuitous route, and finding his wife there, was taken by
 her into the chamber, where they had not been long together when
 Zeppa returned. Hearing him come, the lady, feigning no small
 alarm, bundled Spinelloccio into the chest, as her husband had bidden
 her, and having locked him in, left him there. <milestone id="p08080019" />As Zeppa came
 upstairs: <q direct="unspecified">Wife,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">is it breakfast time?</q> 
<milestone id="p08080020" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, husband, 'tis so,</q> replied the lady. 
<milestone id="p08080021" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Spinelloccio is
 gone to breakfast with a friend to-day,</q> quoth Zeppa, <q direct="unspecified">leaving his
 wife at home: get thee to the window, and call her, and bid her
 come and breakfast with us.</q> 
<milestone id="p08080022" />The lady, whose fear for herself made
 her mighty obedient, did as her husband bade her; and after much
 pressing Spinelloccio's wife came to breakfast with them, though she
 was given to understand that her husband would not be of the company.
 So, she being come, Zeppa received her most affectionately,
 and taking her familiarly by the hand, bade his wife, in an undertone,
 get her to the kitchen; he then led Spinelloccio's wife into the
 chamber, and locked the door. 
<milestone id="p08080023" />Hearing the key turn in the lock:
 <q direct="unspecified">Alas!</q> quoth the lady, <q direct="unspecified">what means this, Zeppa? Is't for this you
 have brought me here? Is this the love you bear Spinelloccio? Is
 this your loyalty to him as your friend and comrade?</q> 
<milestone id="p08080024" />By the time
 she had done speaking, Zeppa, still keeping fast hold of her, was
 beside the chest, in which her husband was locked. Wherefore:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">spare me thy reproaches, until thou hast
 heard what I have to say to thee. I have loved, I yet love, Spinelloccio
 as a brother; and yesterday, though he knew it not, I discovered
 that the trust I reposed in him has for its guerdon that he
 lies with my wife, as with thee. Now, for that I love him, I purpose
 not to be avenged upon him save in the sort in which he
 offended. He has had my wife, and I intend to have thee. 
<milestone id="p08080025" />So thou
 wilt not grant me what I crave of thee, be sure I shall not fail to
 take it; and having no mind to let this affront pass unavenged, will
 <pb n="233" />make such play with him that neither thou nor he shall ever be
 happy again.</q> 
<milestone id="p08080026" />The lady hearkening, and by dint of his repeated
 asseverations coming at length to believe him: <q direct="unspecified">Zeppa mine,</q>
 quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">as this thy vengeance is to light upon me, well content
 am I; so only thou let not this which we are to do embroil me with
 thy wife, with whom, notwithstanding the evil turn she has done
 me, I am minded to remain at peace.</q> 
<milestone id="p08080027" /><q direct="unspecified">Have no fear on that
 score,</q> replied Zeppa; <q direct="unspecified">nay, I will give thee into the bargain a
 jewel so rare and fair that thou hast not the like.</q> Which said,
 he took her in his arms and fell a kissing her, and having laid her
 on the chest, in which her husband was safe under lock and key,
 did there disport himself with her to his heart's content, as she with
 him.</p><p><milestone id="p08080028" />Spinelloccio in the chest heard all that Zeppa had said, and how
 he was answered by the lady, and the Trevisan dance that afterwards
 went on over his head; whereat his mortification was such that for
 a great while he scarce hoped to live through it; and, but for the fear
 he had of Zeppa, he would have given his wife a sound rating, close
 prisoner though he was. <milestone id="p08080029" />But, as he bethought him that 'twas he
 that had given the first affront, and that Zeppa had good cause for
 acting as he did, and that he had dealt with him considerately and
 as a good fellow should, he resolved that if it were agreeable to
 Zeppa, they should be faster friends than ever before. 
<milestone id="p08080030" />However,
 Zeppa, having had his pleasure with the lady, got down from the
 chest, and being reminded by the lady of his promise of the jewel,
 opened the door of the chamber and brought his wife in. Quoth
 she with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, you have given me tit for tat,</q> and
 never a word more. <milestone id="p08080031" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Open the chest,</q> quoth
 Zeppa; and she obeying, he shewed the lady her Spinelloccio lying
 therein. <milestone id="p08080032" />'Twould be hard to say whether of the twain was the
 more shame-stricken, Spinelloccio to be confronted with Zeppa,
 knowing that Zeppa wist what he had done, or the lady to meet her
 husband's eyes, knowing that he had heard what went on above his
 head. <milestone id="p08080033" /><q direct="unspecified">Lo, here is the jewel I give thee,</q> quoth Zeppa to her,
 pointing to Spinelloccio, <milestone id="p08080034" />who, as he came forth of the chest, blurted
 out: <q direct="unspecified">Zeppa, we are quits, and so 'twere best, as thou saidst a while
 ago to my wife, that we still be friends as we were wont, and as we
 had nought separate, save our wives, that henceforth we have them
 <pb n="234" />also in common.</q> <milestone id="p08080035" /><q direct="unspecified">Content,</q> quoth Zeppa; and so in perfect
 peace and accord they all four breakfasted together. And thenceforth
 each of the ladies had two husbands, and each of the husbands two
 wives; nor was there ever the least dispute or contention between
 them on that score.</p></div2>