<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d04conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p04970001" />Heartsore as the gentle ladies had been made by the preceding
 stories, this last of Dioneo provoked them to such merriment, more
 especially the passage about the Stadic and the hook, that they lacked
 not relief of the piteous mood engendered by the others. 
<milestone id="p04970002" />But the
 king observing that the sun was now taking a yellowish tinge, and
 that the end of his sovereignty was come, in terms most courtly
 made his excuse to the fair ladies, that he had made so direful a
 theme as lovers' infelicity the topic of their discourse; after which,
 he rose, took the laurel wreath from his head, and, while the ladies
 watched to see to whom he would give it, set it graciously upon the
 blond head of Fiammetta, saying: 
<milestone id="p04970003" /><q direct="unspecified">Herewith I crown thee, as
 deeming that thou, better than any other, wilt know how to make
 to-morrow console our fair companions for the rude trials of to-day.</q>
 <milestone id="p04970004" />Fiammetta, whose wavy tresses fell in a flood of gold over her white
 and delicate shoulders, whose softly rounded face was all radiant
 with the very tints of the white lily blended with the red of the
 rose, who carried two eyes in her head that matched those of a
 peregrine falcon, while her tiny sweet mouth shewed a pair of lips
 that shone as rubies, replied with a smile: 
<milestone id="p04970005" /><q direct="unspecified">And gladly take I the
 wreath, Filostrato, and that thou mayst more truly understand what
 thou hast done, 'tis my present will and pleasure that each make
	ready to discourse to-morrow of <seg type="topic">good fortune befalling lovers after
 divers direful or disastrous adventures</seg>.</q> 
<milestone id="p04970006" />The theme propounded was
 approved by all; whereupon the queen called the seneschal, and
 having made with him all meet arrangements, rose and gaily dismissed
 all the company until the supper hour; <milestone id="p04970007" />wherefore, some
 straying about the garden, the beauties of which were not such
 as soon to pall, others bending their steps towards the mills that
 were grinding without, each, as and where it seemed best, they took
 meanwhile their several pleasures. <milestone id="p04970008" />The supper hour come, they all
 gathered, in their wonted order, by the fair fountain, and in the
 gayest of spirits and well served they supped. Then rising they
 addressed them, as was their wont, to dance and song, and while
 <pb n="331" />Filomena led the dance: 
<milestone id="p04970009" /><q direct="unspecified">Filostrato,</q> said the queen, <q direct="unspecified">being
 minded to follow in the footsteps of our predecessors, and that, as
 by their, so by our command a song be sung; and well witting that
 thy songs are even as thy stories, to the end that no day but this be
 vexed with thy misfortunes, we ordain that thou give us one of
 them, whichever thou mayst prefer.</q> 
<milestone id="p04970010" />Filostrato answered that he
 would gladly do so; and without delay began to sing on this wise:</p><div3 who="filostrato" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p04970011" />
	<l>Full well my tears attest,</l>
	<l>O traitor Love, with what just cause the heart,</l>
	<l>With which thou once hast broken faith, doth smart.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p04970012" />
	<l>Love, when thou first didst in my heart enshrine</l>
	<l>Her for whom still I sigh, alas! in vain,</l>
	<l>Nor any hope do know,</l>
	<l>A damsel so complete thou didst me shew,</l>
	<l>That light as air I counted every pain,</l>
	<l>Wherewith behest of thine</l>
	<l>Condemned my soul to pine.</l>
	<l>Ah! but I gravely erred; the which to know</l>
	<l>Too late, alas! doth but enhance my woe.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p04970013" />
	<l>The cheat I knew not ere she did me leave,</l>
	<l>She, she, in whom alone my hopes were placed:</l>
	<l>For 'twas when I did most</l>
	<l>Flatter myself with hope, and proudly boast</l>
	<l>Myself her vassal lowliest and most graced,</l>
	<l>Nor thought Love might bereave,</l>
	<l>Nor dreamed he e'er might grieve,</l>
	<l>'Twas then I found that she another's worth</l>
	<l>Into her heart had ta'en, and me cast forth.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p04970014" />
	<l>A plant of pain, alas! my heart did bear,</l>
	<l>What time my hapless self cast forth I knew;</l>
	<l>And there it doth remain;</l>
	<l>And day and hour I curse and curse again,</l>
	<l>When first that front of love shone on my view</l>
	<l>That front so queenly fair,</l>
	<l>And bright beyond compare!</l>
	<l>Wherefore at once my faith, my hope, my fire</l>
	<l>My soul doth imprecate, ere she expire.</l>
      </lg><pb n="332" /><lg><milestone id="p04970015" /><l>My lord, thou knowest how comfortless my woe,</l>
	<l>Thou, Love, my lord, whom thus I supplicate</l>
	<l>With many a piteous moan,</l>
	<l>Telling thee how in anguish sore I groan,</l>
	<l>Yearning for death my pain to mitigate.</l>
	<l>Come death, and with one blow</l>
	<l>Cut short my span, and so</l>
	<l>With my curst life me of my frenzy ease;</l>
	<l>For wheresoe'er I go, 'twill sure decrease.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p04970016" />
	<l>Save death no way of comfort doth remain:</l>
	<l>No anodyne beside for this sore smart.</l>
	<l>The boon, then, Love bestow;</l>
	<l>And presently by death annul my woe,</l>
	<l>And from this abject life release my heart.</l>
	<l>Since from me joy is ta'en,</l>
	<l>And every solace, deign</l>
	<l>My prayer to grant, and let my death the cheer</l>
	<l>Complete, that she now hath of her new fere.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p04970017" />
	<l>Song, it may be that no one shall thee learn:</l>
	<l>Nor do I care; for none I wot, so well</l>
	<l>As I may chant thee; so,</l>
	<l>This one behest I lay upon thee, go</l>
	<l>Hie thee to Love, and him in secret tell,</l>
	<l>How I my life do spurn,</l>
	<l>My bitter life, and yearn,</l>
	<l>That to a better harbourage he bring</l>
	<l>Me, of all might and grace that own him king.</l>
      </lg><lg><l>Full well my tears attest, etc.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p04970018" />Filostrato's mood and its cause were made abundantly manifest
      by the words of this song; and perchance they had been made still
      more so by the looks of a lady that was among the dancers, had not
      the shades of night, which had now overtaken them, concealed the
      blush that suffused her face. Other songs followed until the hour
      for slumber arrived: whereupon at the behest of the queen all the
      ladies sought their several chambers.</p></div2>