<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d07intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p07980002" />Fled was now each star from the eastern sky, save only that
which we call Lucifer, which still glowed in the whitening dawn, when uprose the
seneschal, and with a goodly baggage-train hied him to the Ladies' Vale, there to make all
things ready according to the ordinance and commandment of the king. <milestone id="p07980003" />Nor was it
long after his departure that the king rose, being awaked by the stir and bustle that the
servants made in lading the horses, and being risen he likewise roused all the ladies and
the other gallants; <milestone id="p07980004" />and so, when as yet 'twas scarce clear daybreak, they all
took the road; nor seemed it to them that the nightingales and the other birds had ever
chanted so blithely as that morning. By which choir they were attended to the Ladies'
Vale, where they were greeted by other warblers not a few, that seemed rejoiced at their
arrival. <milestone id="p07980005" />Roving about the vale, and surveying its beauties afresh, they rated
them higher than on the previous day, as indeed the hour was more apt to shew them
forth. <milestone id="p07980006" />Then with good wine and comfits they broke their fast, and, that they
might not lag behind the songsters, they fell a singing, whereto the vale responded, ever
echoing their strains; nor did the birds, as minded not to be beaten, fail to swell the
chorus with notes of unwonted sweetness. <milestone id="p07980007" />However, breakfast-time came, and
then, the tables being laid under a living canopy of trees, and beside other goodly trees
that fringed the little lake, they sat them down in order as to the king seemed meet. So
they took their meal, <pb n="113" />glancing from time to time at the lake, where the fish
darted to and fro in multitudinous shoals, which afforded not only delight to their eyes
but matter for converse. <milestone id="p07980008" />Breakfast ended, and the tables
removed, they fell a singing again more blithely than before. <milestone id="p07980009" />After which,
there being set, in divers places about the little vale, beds which the discreet seneschal
had duly furnished and equipped within and without with store of French coverlets, and
other bedgear, all, that were so minded, had leave of the king to go to sleep, and those
that cared not to sleep might betake them, as each might choose, to any of their wonted
diversions. <milestone id="p07980010" />But, all at length being risen, and the time for addressing them to
the story-telling being come, the king had carpets spread on the sward no great way from
the place where they had breakfasted; and, all having sat them down beside the lake, he
bade Emilia begin; which, blithe and smiling, Emilia did on this wise.</p></div2>