<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0805"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08050001" />Three young men pull down the breeches of a judge from
 the Marches, while he is administering justice on the
 bench.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08050002" />So ended Emilia her story; and when
	all had commended the
	widow lady: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis now thy turn to speak,</q> quoth the queen,
	fixing her gaze upon Filostrato, who answered that he was ready,
	and forthwith thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08050003" />Sweet my ladies, by what I remember
	of that young man, to wit, Maso del Saggio, whom Elisa named a
	while ago, I am prompted to lay aside a story that I had meant to
	tell you, and to tell you another, touching him and some of his
	comrades, which, notwithstanding there are in it certain words
	(albeit 'tis not unseemly) which your modesty forbears to use, is yet
	so laughable that I shall relate it.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08050004" />As you all may well have heard, there come not seldom to our
 city magistrates from the Marches, who for the most part are men
 of a mean spirit, and in circumstances so reduced and beggarly, that
 their whole life seems to be but a petty-foggery; and by reason of
 this their inbred sordidness and avarice they bring with them judges
 and notaries that have rather the air of men taken from the plough
 or the last than trained in the schools of law.<note>It was owing to their
 internal dissensions that the Florentines were
 from time to time fain to introduce these stranger Podest&#224;s.</note>
 <milestone id="p08050005" />Now one of these
 Marchers, being come hither as Podest&#224;, brought with him judges
 not a few, and among them one that called himself Messer Niccola
 da San Lepidio, and looked liker to a locksmith than aught else.
 However, this fellow was assigned with the rest of the judges to
 hear criminal causes. <milestone id="p08050006" />And as folk will often go to the court, though
 they have no concern whatever there, it so befell that Maso del <pb n="200" />Saggio
 went thither one morning in quest of one of his friends, and
 there chancing to set eyes on this Messer Niccola, where he sate,
 deemed him a fowl of no common feather, and surveyed him from
 head to foot, <milestone id="p08050007" />observing that the vair which he wore on his head was
 all begrimed, that he carried an ink-horn at his girdle, that his gown
 was longer than his robe, and many another detail quite foreign to
 the appearance of a man of birth and breeding, of which that which
 he deemed most notable was a pair of breeches, which, as he saw
 (for the judge's outer garments being none too ample were open in
 front, as he sate), reached half-way down his legs. <milestone id="p08050008" />By which sight his
 mind was presently diverted from the friend whom he came there to
 seek; and forth he hied him in quest of other two of his comrades,
 the one Ribi, the other Matteuzzo by name, fellows both of them
 not a whit less jolly than Maso himself; and having found them, he
 said to them: <q direct="unspecified">An you love me, come with me to the court, and
 I will shew you the queerest scarecrow that ever you saw.</q> 
<milestone id="p08050009" />So the
 two men hied them with him to the court; and there he pointed
 out to them the judge and his breeches. What they saw from a
 distance served to set them laughing: then drawing nearer to the
 da&#239;s on which Master Judge was seated, they observed that 'twas
 easy enough to get under the da&#239;s, and moreover that the plank, on
 which the judge's feet rested, was broken, so that there was plenty
 of room for the passage of a hand and arm. <milestone id="p08050010" />Whereupon quoth
 Maso to his comrades: <q direct="unspecified">'Twere a very easy matter to pull these
 breeches right down: wherefore I propose that we do so.</q> 
<milestone id="p08050011" />Each
 of the men had marked how it might be done; and so, having
 concerted both what they should do and what they should say, they
 came to the court again next morning; and, the court being
 crowded, Matteuzzo, observed by never a soul, slipped beneath the
 da&#239;s, and posted himself right under the spot where the judge's feet
 rested, <milestone id="p08050012" />while the other two men took their stand on either side of the
 judge, each laying hold of the hem of his robe. Then: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, sir, I
 pray you for God's sake,</q> began Maso, <q direct="unspecified">that, before the pilfering
 rascal
 that is there beside you can make off, you constrain him to give me
 back a pair of jack boots that he has stolen from me, which theft
 he still denies, though 'tis not a month since I saw him getting
 them resoled.</q> 
<milestone id="p08050013" />Meanwhile Ribi, at the top of his voice, shouted:
 <q direct="unspecified">Believe him not, Sir, the scurvy knave! 'Tis but that he knows <pb n="201" />that
 I am come to demand restitution of a valise that he has stolen
 from me that he now for the first time trumps up this story about
 a pair of jack boots that I have had in my house down to the last
 day or two; and if you doubt what I say, I can bring as witness
 Trecca, my neighbour, and Grassa, the tripe-woman, and one that
 goes about gathering the sweepings of Santa Maria a Verzaia, who
 saw him when he was on his way back from the farm.</q> <milestone id="p08050014" />But shout
 as he might, Maso was still even with him, nor for all that did Ribi
 bate a jot of his clamour. And while the judge stood, bending now
 towards the one, now towards the other, the better to hear them,
 Matteuzzo seized his opportunity, and thrusting his hand through
 the hole in the plank caught hold of the judge's breeches, and tugged
 at them amain. Whereby down they came straightway, for the
 judge was a lean man, and shrunk in the buttocks. <milestone id="p08050015" />The judge,
 being aware of the accident, but knowing not how it had come
 about, would have gathered his outer garments together in front, so
 as to cover the defect, but Maso on the one side, and Ribi on the
 other, held him fast, shouting amain and in chorus: 
<milestone id="p08050016" /><q direct="unspecified">You do me a
 grievous wrong, Sir, thus to deny me justice, nay, even a hearing,
 and to think of quitting the court: there needs no writ in this city
 for such a trifling matter as this.</q> And thus they held him by the
 clothes and in parley, until all that were in the court perceived that
 he had lost his breeches. However, after a while, Matteuzzo
 dropped the breeches, and slipped off, and out of the court, without
 being observed, <milestone id="p08050017" />and Ribi, deeming that the joke had gone far
 enough, exclaimed: <q direct="unspecified">By God, I vow, I will appeal to the Syndics;</q>
 <milestone id="p08050018" />while Maso, on the other side, let go the robe, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Nay,
 but for my part, I will come here again and again and again, until I
 find you less embarrassed than you seem to be to-day.</q> And so the
 one this way, the other that way, they made off with all speed.
 <milestone id="p08050019" />Whereupon Master Judge, disbreeched before all the world, was as
 one that awakens from sleep, albeit he was ware of his forlorn
 condition, and asked whither the parties in the case touching the
 jack boots and the valise were gone. However, as they were not
 to be found, he fell a swearing by the bowels of God, that 'twas
 meet and proper that he should know and wit, whether 'twas the
 custom at Florence to disbreech judges sitting in the seat of justice.</p><p><milestone id="p08050020" />When the affair reached the ears of the Podest&#224;, he made no
 <pb n="202" />little stir about it; but, being informed by some of his friends, that
 'twould not have happened, but that the Florentines were minded
 to shew him, that, in place of the judges he should have brought
 with him, he had brought but gowks, to save expense, he deemed it
 best to say no more about it, and so for that while the matter went
 no further.</p></div2>