<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0504"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05040001" /> Ricciardo Manardi is found by Messer Lizio da Valbona
 with his daughter, whom he marries, and remains at
 peace with her father.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05040002" />In silence Elisa received the praise bestowed on her story by
 her fair companions; and then the queen called for a story from
 Filostrato, who with a laugh began on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05040003" />Chidden have I
 been so often and by so many of you for the sore burden, which I
 laid upon you, of discourse harsh and meet for tears, that, as some
 compensation for such annoy, I deem myself bound to tell you somewhat
 that may cause you to laugh a little: wherefore my story,
 which will be of the briefest, shall be of a love, the course whereof,
 save for sighs and a brief passage of fear mingled with shame, ran
 smooth to a happy consummation.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p05040004" />Know then, noble ladies, that 'tis no long time since there dwelt
 in Romagna a right worthy and courteous knight, Messer Lizio da
 Valbona by name, who was already verging upon old age, when, as it
 happened, there was born to him of his wife, Madonna Giacomina,
  <milestone id="p05040005" />a daughter, who, as she grew up, became the fairest and most debonair
 of all the girls of those parts, and, for that she was the only daughter
 left to them, was most dearly loved and cherished by her father and
 mother, who guarded her with most jealous care, thinking to arrange
 some great match for her.  <milestone id="p05040006" />Now there was frequently in Messer
 Lizio's house, and much in his company, a fine, lusty young man,
 one Ricciardo de' Manardi da Brettinoro, whom Messer Lizio and
 his wife would as little have thought of mistrusting as if he had been
 their own son: who, now and again taking note of the damsel, that
 she was very fair and graceful, and in bearing and behaviour most
 <pb n="26" />commendable, and of marriageable age, fell vehemently in love with
 her, which love he was very careful to conceal.  <milestone id="p05040007" />The damsel detected
 it, however, and in like manner plunged headlong into love with
 him, to Ricciardo's no small satisfaction.  <milestone id="p05040008" />Again and again he was
 on the point of speaking to her, but refrained for fear; at length,
 however, he summoned up his courage, and seizing his opportunity,
 thus addressed her: <q direct="unspecified">Caterina, I implore thee, suffer me not to
 die for love of thee.</q>  <milestone id="p05040009" />Whereto the damsel forthwith responded:
 <q direct="unspecified">Nay, God grant that it be not rather that I die for love of thee.</q>
  <milestone id="p05040010" />Greatly exhilarated and encouraged, Ricciardo made answer:
 <q direct="unspecified">'Twill never be by default of mine that thou lackest aught that
 may pleasure thee; but it rests with thee to find the means to save
 thy life and mine.</q>  <milestone id="p05040011" />Then said the damsel: <q direct="unspecified">Thou seest, Ricciardo,
 how closely watched I am, insomuch that I see not how 'twere
 possible for thee to come to me; but if thou seest aught that I may
 do without dishonour, speak the word, and I will do it.</q>  <milestone id="p05040012" />Ricciardo
 was silent a while, pondering many matters: then, of a sudden, he
 said: <q direct="unspecified">Sweet my Caterina, there is but one way that I can see,
 to wit, that thou shouldst sleep either on or where thou mightst have
 access to the terrace by thy father's garden, where, so I but knew
 that thou wouldst be there at night, I would without fail contrive
 to meet thee, albeit 'tis very high.</q> <milestone id="p05040013" /><q direct="unspecified">As for my sleeping there,</q>
 replied Caterina, <q direct="unspecified">I doubt not that it may be managed, if thou art
 sure that thou canst join me.</q>  <milestone id="p05040014" />Ricciardo answered in the affirmative.
 Whereupon they exchanged a furtive kiss, and parted.</p><p><milestone id="p05040015" />On the morrow, it being now towards the close of May, the
 damsel began complaining to her mother that by reason of the
 excessive heat she had not been able to get any sleep during the
 night. <milestone id="p05040016" /><q direct="unspecified">Daughter,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">what heat was there? Nay,
 there was no heat at all.</q> <milestone id="p05040017" /><q direct="unspecified">Had you said, 'to my thinking,'
 mother,</q> rejoined Caterina, <q direct="unspecified">you would perhaps have said sooth;
 but you should bethink you how much more heat girls have in them
 than ladies that are advanced in years.</q> <milestone id="p05040018" /><q direct="unspecified">True, my daughter,</q>
 returned the lady, <q direct="unspecified">but I cannot order that it shall be hot and cold,
 as thou perchance wouldst like; we must take the weather as we
 find it, and as the seasons provide it: perchance to-night it will be
 cooler, and thou wilt sleep better.</q> <milestone id="p05040019" /><q direct="unspecified">God grant it be so,</q> said
 Caterina, <q direct="unspecified">but 'tis not wonted for the nights to grow cooler as the
 <pb n="27" />summer comes on.</q> <milestone id="p05040020" /><q direct="unspecified">What then,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">wouldst thou
 have me do?</q> <milestone id="p05040021" /><q direct="unspecified">With your leave and my father's,</q> answered
 Caterina, <q direct="unspecified">I should like to have a little bed made up on the terrace
 by his room and over his garden, where, hearing the nightingales
 sing, and being in a much cooler place, I should sleep much better
 than in your room.</q>  <milestone id="p05040022" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Daughter, be of good cheer,</q>
 said the mother; <q direct="unspecified">I will speak to thy father, and we will do as he
 shall decide.</q>  <milestone id="p05040023" />So the lady told Messer Lizio what had passed between
 her and the damsel; but he, being old and perhaps for that reason
 a little morose, said: <q direct="unspecified">What nightingale is this, to whose chant
 she would fain sleep? I will see to it that the cicalas shall yet lull
 her to sleep.</q>  <milestone id="p05040024" />Which speech, coming to Caterina's ears, gave her
 such offence, that for anger, rather than by reason of the heat, she
 not only slept not herself that night, but suffered not her mother to
 sleep, keeping up a perpetual complaint of the great heat.  <milestone id="p05040025" />Wherefore
 her mother hied her in the morning to Messer Lizio, and said
 to him: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, you hold your daughter none too dear; what difference
 can it make to you that she lie on the terrace? She has tossed
 about all night long by reason of the heat; and besides, can you
 wonder that she, girl that she is, loves to hear the nightingale sing?
 Young folk naturally affect their likes.</q>  <milestone id="p05040026" />Whereto Messer Lizio
 made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Go, make her a bed there to your liking, and set
 a curtain round it, and let her sleep there, and hear the nightingale
 sing to her heart's content.</q>  <milestone id="p05040027" />Which the damsel no sooner learned,
 than she had a bed made there with intent to sleep there that same
 night; wherefore she watched until she saw Ricciardo, whom by a
 concerted sign she gave to understand what he was to do.  <milestone id="p05040028" />Messer
 Lizio, as soon as he had heard the damsel go to bed, locked a door
 that led from his room to the terrace, and went to sleep himself.
  <milestone id="p05040029" />When all was quiet, Ricciardo with the help of a ladder got upon
 a wall, and standing thereon laid hold of certain toothings of another
 wall, and not without great exertion and risk, had he fallen, clambered
 up on to the terrace, where the damsel received him quietly with
 the heartiest of cheer. Many a kiss they exchanged; and then got
 them to bed, where well-nigh all night long they had solace and
 joyance of one another, and made the nightingale sing not a few
 times.  <milestone id="p05040030" />But, brief being the night and great their pleasure, towards
 dawn, albeit they wist it not, they fell asleep, Caterina's right arm
 <pb n="28" />encircling Ricciardo's neck, while with her left hand she held him
 by that part of his person which your modesty, my ladies, is most
 averse to name in the company of men.  <milestone id="p05040031" />So, peacefully they slept,
 and were still asleep when day broke and Messer Lizio rose; and
 calling to mind that his daughter slept on the terrace, softly opened
 the door, saying to himself: Let me see what sort of night's rest
 the nightingale has afforded our Caterina?  <milestone id="p05040032" />And having entered,
 he gently raised the curtain that screened the bed, and saw Ricciardo
 asleep with her and in her embrace as described, both being quite
 naked and uncovered;  <milestone id="p05040033" />and having taken note of Ricciardo, he went
 away, and hied him to his lady's room, and called her, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Up,
 up, wife, come and see; for thy daughter has fancied the nightingale
 to such purpose that she has caught him, and holds him in her hand.</q>
 <milestone id="p05040034" /><q direct="unspecified">How can this be?</q> said the lady. <q direct="unspecified"> <milestone id="p05040035" />Come quickly, and thou shalt
 see,</q> replied Messer Lizio.  <milestone id="p05040036" />So the lady huddled on her clothes, and
 silently followed Messer Lizio, and when they were come to the
 bed, and had raised the curtain, Madonna Giacomina saw plainly
 enough how her daughter had caught, and did hold the nightingale,
 whose song she had so longed to hear.  <milestone id="p05040037" />Whereat the lady, deeming
 that Ricciardo had played her a cruel trick, would have cried out
 and upbraided him; but Messer Lizio said to her: <q direct="unspecified">Wife, as thou
 valuest my love, say not a word; for in good sooth, seeing that she
 has caught him, he shall be hers.  <milestone id="p05040038" />Ricciardo is a gentleman and
 wealthy; an alliance with him cannot but be to our advantage: if
 he would part from me on good terms, he must first marry her, so
 that the nightingale shall prove to have been put in his own cage
 and not in that of another.</q>  <milestone id="p05040039" />Whereby the lady was reassured, seeing
 that her husband took the affair so quietly, and that her daughter had
 had a good night, and was rested, and had caught the nightingale.
 So she kept silence;  <milestone id="p05040040" />nor had they long to wait before Ricciardo
 awoke; and, seeing that 'twas broad day, deemed that 'twas as much
 as his life was worth, and aroused Caterina, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! my
 soul, what shall we do, now that day has come and surprised me
 here?</q>  <milestone id="p05040041" />Which question Messer Lizio answered by coming forward,
 and saying: <q direct="unspecified">We shall do well.</q>  <milestone id="p05040042" />At sight of him Ricciardo felt
 as if his heart were torn out of his body, and sate up in the bed, and
 said: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, I cry you mercy for God's sake. I wot that my
 disloyalty and delinquency have merited death; wherefore deal with
 <pb n="29" />me even as it may seem best to you: however, I pray you, if so it
 may be, to spare my life, that I die not.</q> <milestone id="p05040043" /><q direct="unspecified">Ricciardo,</q> replied
 Messer
 Lizio, <q direct="unspecified">the love I bore thee, and the faith I reposed in thee, merited
 a better return; but still, as so it is, and youth has seduced thee into
 such a transgression, redeem thy life, and preserve my honour, by
 making Caterina thy lawful spouse, that thine, as she has been for
 this past night, she may remain for the rest of her life. In this way
 thou mayst secure my peace and thy safety; otherwise commend thy
 soul to God.</q>  <milestone id="p05040044" />Pending this colloquy, Caterina let go the nightingale,
 and having covered herself, began with many a tear to implore her
 father to forgive Ricciardo, and Ricciardo to do as Messer Lizio
 required, that thereby they might securely count upon a long continuance
 of such nights of delight.  <milestone id="p05040045" />But there needed not much
 supplication; for, what with remorse for the wrong done, and the
 wish to make amends, and the fear of death, and the desire to escape
 it, and above all ardent love, and the craving to possess the beloved
 one, Ricciardo lost no time in making frank avowal of his readiness
 to do as Messer Lizio would have him.  <milestone id="p05040046" />Wherefore Messer Lizio,
 having borrowed a ring from Madonna Giacomina, Ricciardo did
 there and then in their presence wed Caterina.  <milestone id="p05040047" />Which done, Messer
 Lizio and the lady took their leave, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Now rest ye a while;
 for so perchance 'twere better for you than if ye rose.</q>  <milestone id="p05040048" />And so
 they left the young folks, who forthwith embraced, and not having
 travelled more than six miles during the night, went two miles
 further before they rose, and so concluded their first day.  <milestone id="p05040049" />When
 they were risen, Ricciardo and Messer Lizio discussed the matter
 with more formality; and some days afterwards Ricciardo, as was
 meet, married the damsel anew in presence of their friends and
 kinsfolk, and brought her home with great pomp, and celebrated his
 nuptials with due dignity and splendour. And so for many a year
 thereafter he lived with her in peace and happiness, and snared the
 nightingales day and night to his heart's content.</p></div2>