<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0107"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p01070001" />Bergamino, with a story of Primasso and the Abbot of
	Cluny, finely censures a sudden access of avarice in
	Messer Cane della Scala.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01070002" />Emilia's charming manner and her story drew laughter and
      commendation from the queen and all the company, who were much
      tickled by her new type of crusader. When the laughter had subsided,
      and all were again silent, Filostrato, on whom the narration
      now fell, began on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01070003" />A fine thing it is, noble ladies, to hit a fixed mark; but
      if, on the sudden appearance of some strange object, it be forthwith
      hit by the bowman, 'tis little short of a miracle. <milestone id="p01070004" />The
      corrupt and filthy life of the clergy offers on many sides a fixed
      mark of iniquity at which, whoever is so minded, may let fly, with
      little doubt that they will reach it, the winged words of reproof
      and reprehension. Wherefore, though the worthy man did well
      to censure in the person of the inquisitor the pretended charity of
      the friars who give to the poor what they ought rather to give to the
      pigs or throw away, higher indeed is the praise which I accord to
      him, of whom, taking my cue from the last story, I mean to speak;
      seeing that by a clever apologue he rebuked a sudden and unwonted
      access of avarice in Messer Cane della Scala, conveying in a figure
      what he had at heart to say touching Messer Cane and himself; which
      apologue is to follow.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p01070005" />Far and wide, almost to the ends of the earth, is borne the most
      illustrious renown of Messer Cane della Scala, in many ways the
      favoured child of fortune, a lord almost without a peer among the
      notables and magnificoes of Italy since the time of the Emperor
      <pb n="52" />Frederic II. <milestone id="p01070006" />Now Messer Cane, being minded to hold high
      festival at Verona, whereof fame should speak marvellous things, and
      many folk from divers parts, of whom the greater number were jesters
      of every order, being already arrived, Messer Cane did suddenly (for
      some cause or another) abandon his design, and dismissed them with
      a partial recompense. <milestone id="p01070007" />One only, Bergamino by name, a speaker
      ready and polished in a degree credible only to such as heard him,
      remained, having received no recompense or cong&#233;, still cherishing
      the hope that this omission might yet turn out to his advantage.
      But Messer Cane was possessed with the idea that whatever he
      might give Bergamino would be far more completely thrown away
      than if he had tossed it into the fire; so never a word of the sort
      said he or sent he to him. <milestone id="p01070008" />A few days thus passed, and then Bergamino,
      seeing that he was in no demand or request for aught that
      belonged to his office, and being also at heavy charges at his inn for
      the keep of his horses and servants, fell into a sort of melancholy;
      but still he waited a while, not deeming it expedient to leave. 
      <milestone id="p01070009" />He
      had brought with him three rich and goodly robes, given him by
      other lords, that he might make a brave show at the festival, and
      when his host began to press for payment he gave him one of the
      robes; afterwards, there being still much outstanding against him, he
      must needs, if he would tarry longer at the inn, give the host the
      second robe; after which he began to live on the third, being minded
      to remain there, as long as it would hold out, in expectation of better
      luck, and then to take his departure. 
      <milestone id="p01070010" />Now, while he was thus living
      on the third robe, it chanced that Messer Cane encountered him one
      day as he sate at breakfast with a very melancholy visage. Which
      Messer Cane observing, said, rather to tease him than expecting to
      elicit from him any pleasant retort: <q direct="unspecified">What ails thee, Bergamino,
	that thou art still so melancholy? Let me know the reason why.</q>
      <milestone id="p01070011" />Whereupon Bergamino, without a moment's reflection, told the
      following story, which could not have fitted his own case more
      exactly if it had been long premeditated.</p><p><q type="novella" direct="unspecified">My lord, you must know that Primasso was a grammarian of great
	eminence, and excellent and quick beyond all others in versifying;
	whereby he waxed so notable and famous that, albeit he was not
	everywhere known by sight, yet there were scarce any that did not
	at least by name and report know who Primasso was. 
	<milestone id="p01070012" />Now it so
	<pb n="53" />happened that, being once at Paris in straitened circumstances, as
	it was his lot to be most of his time by reason that virtue is little
	appreciated by the powerful, he heard speak of the Abbot of Cluny,
	who, except the Pope, is supposed to be the richest prelate, in regard
	of his vast revenues, that the Church of God can shew; and marvellous
	and magnificent things were told him of the perpetual court
	which the abbot kept, and how, wherever he was, he denied not to
	any that came there either meat or drink, so only that he preferred
	his request while the abbot was at table. <milestone id="p01070013" />Which when
	Primasso heard, he determined to go and see for himself what
	magnificent state this abbot kept, for he was one that took great
	delight in observing the ways of powerful and lordly men; wherefore
	he asked how far from Paris was the abbot then sojourning. He
	was informed that the abbot was then at one of his places distant
	perhaps six miles; which Primasso concluded he could reach in time
	for breakfast, if he started early in the morning. <milestone id="p01070014" />When he had
	learned the way, he found that no one else was travelling by it, and
	fearing lest by mischance he should lose it, and so find himself where
	it would not be easy for him to get food, he determined to obviate so
	disagreeable a contingency by taking with him three loaves of bread--as
	for drink, water, though not much to his taste, was, he supposed,
	to be found everywhere. So, having disposed the loaves in the fold of
	his tunic, he took the road and made such progress that he reached
	the abbot's place of sojourn before the breakfast-hour. 
	<milestone id="p01070015" />Having
	entered, he made the circuit of the entire place, observing everything,
	the vast array of tables, and the vast kitchen well-appointed with all
	things needful for the preparation and service of the breakfast, and
	saying to himself: <q type="internalmonologue" direct="unspecified" who="primasso">In very truth this
	  man is even such a magnifico
	  as he is reported to be.</q> <milestone id="p01070016" />While his attention was thus occupied,
	the abbot's seneschal, it being now breakfast-time, gave order to serve
	water for the hands, which being washen, they sat them all down to
	breakfast. Now it so happened that Primasso was placed immediately
	in front of the door by which the abbot must pass from his chamber
	into the hall; 
	<milestone id="p01070017" />in which, according to rule of his court, neither wine,
	nor bread, nor aught else drinkable or eatable was ever set on the
	tables before he made his appearance and was seated. The seneschal,
	therefore, having set the tables, sent word to the abbot, that all
	was now ready, and they waited only his pleasure. 
	<milestone id="p01070018" />So the abbot
	<pb n="54" />gave the word, the door of his chamber was thrown open, and he
	took a step or two forward towards the hall, gazing straight in front
	of him as he went. Thus it fell out that the first man on whom he
	set eyes was Primasso, who was in very sorry trim. The abbot, who
	knew him not by sight, no sooner saw him, than, surprised by a
	churlish mood to which he had hitherto been an entire stranger, he
	said to himself: 
	<milestone id="p01070019" /><q type="internalmonologue" direct="unspecified" who="abatecligni">So it is
	  to such as this man that I give my hospitality;</q>
	and going back into the chamber he bade lock the door, and
	asked of his attendants whether the vile fellow that sate at table
	directly opposite the door was known to any of them, <milestone id="p01070020" />who, one and all,
	answered in the negative. Primasso waited a little, but he was not
	used to fast, and his journey had whetted his appetite. So, as the abbot
	did not return, he drew out one of the loaves which he had brought
	with him, and began to eat. <milestone id="p01070021" />The abbot, after a while, bade one of
	his servants go see whether Primasso were gone. The servant
	returned with the answer: <q direct="unspecified">No, sir, and (what is more) he is
	  eating a loaf of bread, which he seems to have brought with him.</q>
	<q direct="unspecified" who="abatecligni">Be it so then,</q> said the abbot, <milestone id="p01070022" />who was
	vexed that he was not gone
	of his own accord, but was not disposed to turn him out; <q direct="unspecified">let him
	  eat his own bread, if he have any, for he shall have none of ours today.</q>
	By and by Primasso, having finished his first loaf, began, as
	the abbot did not make his appearance, to eat the second; which was
	likewise reported to the abbot, who had again sent to see if he were
	gone. <milestone id="p01070023" />Finally, as the abbot still delayed his coming, Primasso,
	having finished the second loaf, began upon the third; whereof, once
	more, word was carried to the abbot, who now began to commune
	with himself and say: <q direct="unspecified" who="abatecligni">Alas! my soul, what unwonted mood
	  harbourest thou to-day? What avarice? what scorn? and of whom?
	  I have given my hospitality, now for many a year, to whoso craved
	  it, without looking to see whether he were gentle or churl, poor or
	  rich, merchant or cheat, and mine eyes have seen it squandered on
	  vile fellows without number; and nought of that which I feel
	  towards this man ever entered my mind. <milestone id="p01070024" />Assuredly it cannot be that
	  he is a man of no consequence, who is the occasion of this access of
	  avarice in me. Though he seem to me a vile fellow, he must be some
	  great man, that my mind is thus obstinately averse to do him honour.</q>
	<milestone id="p01070025" />Of which musings the upshot was that he sent to inquire who the
	vile fellow was, and learning that he was Primasso, come to see if what
	<pb n="55" />he had heard of his magnificent state were true, he was stricken with
	shame, having heard of old Primasso's fame, and knowing him to be
	a great man. Wherefore, being zealous to make him the amend, he
	studied to do him honour in many ways; <milestone id="p01070026" />and after breakfast, that
	his garb might accord with his native dignity, he caused him to be
	nobly arrayed, and setting him upon a palfrey and filling his purse,
	left it to his own choice, whether to go or to stay. So Primasso, with
	a full heart, thanked him for his courtesy in terms the amplest that
	he could command, and, having left Paris afoot, returned thither on
	horseback.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01070027" />Messer Cane was shrewd enough to apprehend Bergamino's
	meaning perfectly well without a gloss, and said with a smile:
	<q direct="unspecified">Bergamino, thy parable is apt, and declares to me very plainly
	  thy losses, my avarice, and what thou desirest of me. And in good
	  sooth this access of avarice, of which thou art the occasion, is the
	  first that I have experienced. But I will expel the intruder with
	  the b&#226;ton which thou thyself hast furnished.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01070028" />So he paid Bergamino's
	reckoning, habited him nobly in one of his own robes, gave
	him money and a palfrey, and left it for the time at his discretion,
	whether to go or to stay.</p></div2>