<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0802"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08020001" />The priest of Varlungo lies with Monna Belcolore: he
 leaves with her his cloak by way of pledge, and
 receives from her a mortar. He returns the mortar,
 and demands of her the cloak that he had left in pledge,
	which the good lady returns him with a gibe.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08020002" />Ladies and men alike commended
	Gulfardo for the check that
	he gave to the greed of the Milanese lady; but before they had
	done, the queen turned to Pamfilo, and with a smile bade him follow
	suit: wherefore thus Pamfilo began:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08020003" />Fair my ladies, it occurs to
	me to tell you a short story, which reflects no credit on those by
	whom we are continually wronged without being able to retaliate, to
	wit, the priests, who have instituted a crusade against our wives, and
	deem that, when they have made conquest of one of them, they have
	done a work every whit as worthy of recompense by remission of sin
	and punishment as if they had brought the Soldan in chains to Avignon:
	<milestone id="p08020004" />in which respect 'tis not possible for the hapless laity to be
	even with them: howbeit they are as hot to make reprisals on the
	priests' mothers, sisters, mistresses, and daughters as the priests to
	attack their wives. <milestone id="p08020005" />Wherefore I am minded to give you, as I may
	do in few words, the history of a rustic amour, the conclusion whereof
	was not a little laughable, nor barren of moral, for you may also
	gather therefrom, that 'tis not always well to believe everything
	that a priest says.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08020006" />I say then, that at Varlungo, a village hard by here, as all of you,
 my ladies, should wot either of your own knowledge or by report,
 there dwelt a worthy priest, and doughty of body in the service of
 the ladies: who, albeit he was none too quick at his book, had no <pb n="181" />lack
 of precious and blessed solecisms to edify his flock withal of a
 Sunday under the elm. <milestone id="p08020007" />And when the men were out of doors, he
 would visit their wives as never a priest had done before him, bringing
 them feast-day gowns and holy water, and now and again a bit of
 candle, and giving them his blessing. <milestone id="p08020008" />Now it so befell that among
 those of his fair parishioners whom he most affected the first place
 was at length taken by one Monna Belcolore, the wife of a husbandman
 that called himself Bentivegna del Mazzo. <milestone id="p08020009" />And in good sooth
 she was a winsome and lusty country lass, brown as a berry and
 buxom enough, and fitter than e'er another for his mill. Moreover
 she had not her match in playing the tabret and singing: <title type="song">The
 borage is full sappy</title>,
      
      <note>For this folk-song see Cantilene e Ballate,
	Strambotti e Madrigali, ed.
	Carducci (1871), p. 60. The fragment there printed may be freely rendered
	as follows:
	<lg>	  <l>The borage is full sappy,</l>
	  <l>And clusters red we see,</l>
	  <l>And my love would make me happy;</l>
	  <l>So that maiden give to me.</l>
	</lg>
	<lg>	  <l>Ill set I find this dance,</l>
	  <l>And better might it be:</l>
	  <l>So, comrade mine, advance,</l>
	  <l>And, changing place with me,</l>
	  <l>Stand thou thy love beside.</l>
	</lg>
      </note> 
      
and in leading a brawl or a breakdown, no
 matter who might be next her, with a fair and dainty kerchief in her
 hand. <milestone id="p08020010" />Which spells so wrought upon Master Priest, that for love
 of her he grew distracted, and did nought all day long but loiter
 about the village on the chance of catching sight of her. And if of
 a Sunday morning he espied her in church, he strove might and main
 to acquit himself of his <title type="song">Kyrie</title> and <title type="song">Sanctus</title> in the style of a great
 singer, albeit his performance was liker to the braying of an ass:
 whereas, if he saw her not, he scarce exerted himself at all. However,
 he managed with such discretion that neither Bentivegna del
 Mazzo nor any of the neighbours wist aught of his love. 
      <milestone id="p08020011" />And
 hoping thereby to ingratiate himself with Monna Belcolore, he from
 time to time would send her presents, now a clove of fresh garlic, the
 best in all the country-side, from his own garden, which he tilled with
 his own hands, and anon a basket of beans or a bunch of chives or
 shallots; <milestone id="p08020012" />and, when he thought it might serve his turn, he would 
<pb n="182" />give
 her a sly glance, and follow it up with a little amorous mocking
 and mowing, which she, with rustic awkwardness, feigned not to
 understand, and ever maintained her reserve, so that Master Priest
 made no headway.</p><p><milestone id="p08020013" />Now it so befell that one day, when the priest at high noon was
 aimlessly gadding about the village, he encountered Bentivegna del
 Mazzo at the tail of a well laden ass, and greeted him, asking him
 whither he was going. 
<milestone id="p08020014" /><q direct="unspecified">I'faith, Sir,</q> quoth Bentivegna, <q direct="unspecified">for sure
 'tis to town I go, having an affair or two to attend to there; and I
 am taking these things to Ser Buonaccorri da Ginestreto, to get him
 to stand by me in I wot not what matter, whereof the justice
 o' th' coram has by his provoker served me with a pertrumpery
 summons to appear before him.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020015" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis well, my
 son,</q> quoth the priest, overjoyed, <q direct="unspecified">my blessing go with thee: good
 luck to thee and a speedy return; and harkye, shouldst thou see
 Lapuccio or Naldino, do not forget to tell them to send me those
 thongs for my flails.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020016" /><q direct="unspecified">It shall be done,</q> quoth Bentivegna, and
 jogged on towards Florence, while the priest, thinking that now was
 his time to hie him to Belcolore and try his fortune, put his best
 leg forward, and stayed not till he was at the house, which entering,
 he said: <q direct="unspecified">God be gracious to us! Who is within?</q> 
<milestone id="p08020017" />Belcolore,
 who was up in the loft, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Welcome, Sir; but what
 dost thou, gadding about in the heat?</q> 
<milestone id="p08020018" /><q direct="unspecified">Why, as I hope for
 God's blessing,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I am just come to stay with thee a
 while, having met thy husband on his way to town.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020019" />Whereupon
 down came Belcolore, took a seat, and began sifting cabbage-seed
 that her husband had lately threshed. By and by the priest began:
 <q direct="unspecified">So, Belcolore, wilt thou keep me ever a dying thus?</q> 
<milestone id="p08020020" />Whereat
 Belcolore tittered, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Why, what is't I do to you?</q>
 <milestone id="p08020021" /><q direct="unspecified">Truly, nothing at all,</q> replied the priest: <q direct="unspecified">but thou sufferest me
 not to do to thee that which I had lief, and which God commands.</q>
 <milestone id="p08020022" /><q direct="unspecified">Now away with you!</q> returned Belcolore, <q direct="unspecified">do priests do that
 sort of thing?</q> 
<milestone id="p08020023" /><q direct="unspecified">Indeed we do,</q> quoth the priest, <q direct="unspecified">and to better
 purpose than others: why not? I tell you our grinding is far
 better; and wouldst thou know why? 'tis because 'tis intermittent.
 And in truth 'twill be well worth thy while to keep thine own
 counsel, and let me do it.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020024" /><q direct="unspecified">Worth my while!</q> ejaculated
 Belcolore. <q direct="unspecified">How may that be? There is never a one of you but <pb n="183" />would
 overreach the very Devil.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020025" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis not for me to say,</q>
 returned the priest; <q direct="unspecified">say but what thou wouldst have: shall it be
 a pair of dainty shoes? Or wouldst thou prefer a fillet? Or
 perchance a gay riband? What's thy will?</q> 
<milestone id="p08020026" /><q direct="unspecified">Marry, no lack
 have I,</q> quoth Belcolore, <q direct="unspecified">of such things as these. But, if you
 wish me so well, why do me not a service? and I would then be
 at your command.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020027" /><q direct="unspecified">Name but the service,</q> returned the priest,
 <q direct="unspecified">and gladly will I do it.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020028" />Quoth then Belcolore: <q direct="unspecified">On Saturday
 I have to go to Florence to deliver some wool that I have spun,
 and to get my spinning-wheel put in order: lend me but five
 pounds--I know you have them--and I will redeem my perse
 petticoat from the pawnshop, and also the girdle that I wear on
 saints' days, and that I had when I was married--you see that
 without them I cannot go to church or anywhere else, and then I
 will do just as you wish thenceforth and forever.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020029" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">So God give me a good year,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">as I have not the
 money with me: but never fear that I will see that thou hast it
 before Saturday with all the pleasure in life.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020030" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, ay,</q> rejoined
 Belcolore, <q direct="unspecified">you all make great promises, but then you never keep
 them. Think you to serve me as you served Biliuzza, whom you
 left in the lurch at last? God's faith, you do not so. To think
 that she turned woman of the world just for that! If you have
 not the money with you, why, go and get it.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020031" /><q direct="unspecified">Prithee,</q> returned
 the priest, <q direct="unspecified">send me not home just now. For, seest thou, 'tis the
 very nick of time with me, and the coast is clear, and perchance it
 might not be so on my return, and in short I know not when it
 would be likely to go so well as now.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020032" />Whereto she did but
 rejoin: <q direct="unspecified">Good; if you are minded to go, get you gone; if not,
 stay where you are.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020033" />The priest, therefore, seeing that she was
 not disposed to give him what he wanted, as he was fain, to wit, on
 his own terms, but was bent upon having a quid pro quo, changed
 his tone; and: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">thou doubtest I will not
 bring thee the money; so to set thy mind at rest, I will leave thee
 this cloak--thou seest 'tis good sky-blue silk--in pledge.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020034" />So raising
 her head and glancing at the cloak: <q direct="unspecified">And what may the cloak be
 worth?</q> quoth Belcolore. 
<milestone id="p08020035" /><q direct="unspecified">Worth!</q> ejaculated the priest: <q direct="unspecified">I
 would have thee know that 'tis all Douai, not to say Trouai,
 make: nay, there are some of our folk here that say 'tis Quadrouai; <pb n="184" />and
 'tis not a fortnight since I bought it of Lotto, the secondhand
 dealer, for seven good pounds, and then had it five good soldi
 under value, by what I hear from Buglietto, who, thou knowest,
 is an excellent judge of these articles.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020036" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh! say you so?</q>
 exclaimed Belcolore. <q direct="unspecified">So help me God, I should not have thought
 it; however, let me look at it.</q> 
<milestone id="p08020037" />So Master Priest, being ready for
 action, doffed the cloak and handed it to her. And she, having
 put it in a safe place, said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Sir, we will away to
 the hut; there is never a soul goes there;</q> and so they did. 
<milestone id="p08020038" />And
 there Master Priest, giving her many a mighty buss and straining
 her to his sacred person, solaced himself with her no little while.</p><p><milestone id="p08020039" />Which done, he hied him away in his cassock, as if he were come
 from officiating at a wedding; but, when he was back in his holy
 quarters, he bethought him that not all the candles that he received
 by way of offering in the course of an entire year would amount to
 the half of five pounds, and saw that he had made a bad bargain,
 and repented him that he had left the cloak in pledge, and cast
 about how he might recover it without paying anything. 
<milestone id="p08020040" />And as
 he did not lack cunning, he hit upon an excellent expedient, by
 which he compassed his end. So on the morrow, being a saint's
 day, he sent a neighbour's lad to Monna Belcolore with a request
 that she would be so good as to lend him her stone mortar, for that
 Binguccio dal Poggio and Nuto Buglietti were to breakfast with
 him that morning, and he therefore wished to make a sauce.
 Belcolore having sent the mortar, 
<milestone id="p08020041" />the priest, about breakfast time,
 reckoning that Bentivegna del Mazzo and Belcolore would be at
 their meal, called his clerk, and said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Take the mortar
 back to Belcolore, and say: 'My master thanks you very kindly,
 and bids you return the cloak that the lad left with you in pledge.'</q>
 <milestone id="p08020042" />The clerk took the mortar to Belcolore's house, where, finding her
 at table with Bentivegna, he set the mortar down and delivered the
 priest's message. <milestone id="p08020043" />Whereto Belcolore would fain have demurred;
 but Bentivegna gave her a threatening glance, saying: <q direct="unspecified">So, then,
 thou takest a pledge from Master Priest? By Christ, I vow, I
 have half a mind to give thee a great clout o' the chin. Go, give
 it back at once, a murrain on thee! And look to it that whatever
 he may have a mind to, were it our very ass, he be never denied.</q>
 <milestone id="p08020044" />So, with a very bad grace, Belcolore got up, and went to the <pb n="185" />wardrobe,
 and took out the cloak, and gave it to the clerk, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">Tell thy master from me: Would to God he may never ply pestle
 in my mortar again, such honour has he done me for this turn!</q>
 <milestone id="p08020045" />So the clerk returned with the cloak, and delivered the message to
 Master Priest; who, laughing, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Tell her, when
 thou next seest her, that, so she lend us not the mortar, I will not
 lend her the pestle: be it tit for tat.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08020046" />Bentivegna made no account of his wife's words, deeming that
 'twas but his chiding that had provoked them. But Belcolore was
 not a little displeased with Master Priest, and had never a word to say
 to him till the vintage; after which, what with the salutary fear in
 which she stood of the mouth of Lucifer the Great, to which he
 threatened to consign her, and the must and roast chestnuts that he
 sent her, she made it up with him, and many a jolly time they had
 together. <milestone id="p08020047" />And though she got not the five pounds from him, he put
 a new skin on her tabret, and fitted it with a little bell, wherewith
 she was satisfied.</p></div2>