<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0410"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04100001" />The wife of a leech, deeming her lover, who has taken an
 opiate, to be dead, puts him in a chest, which, with
 him therein, two usurers carry off to their house.
 He comes to himself, and is taken for a thief; but,
 the lady's maid giving the Signory to understand that
 she had put him in the chest which the usurers stole,
 he escapes the gallows, and the usurers are mulcted
 in moneys for the theft of the chest.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04100002" />Now that the king had told his tale, it only
	remained for Dioneo
	to do his part, which he witting, and being thereto bidden by the
	king, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04100003" />Sore have I--to say nought of you, my ladies--been
	of eyne and heart to hear the woeful histories of ill-starred love,
	insomuch that I have desired of all things that they might have an
	end. Wherefore, now that, thank God, ended they are, unless indeed
	I were minded, which God forbid, to add to such pernicious stuff a
	supplement of the like evil quality, no such dolorous theme do I
	purpose to ensue, but to make a fresh start with somewhat of a
	better and more cheerful sort, which perchance may serve to suggest
	to-morrow's argument.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04100004" />You are to know, then, fairest my damsels, that 'tis not long
 since there dwelt at Salerno a leech most eminent in surgery, his
 name, Master Mazzeo della Montagna, who in his extreme old age
 took to wife a fair damsel of the same city, whom he kept in nobler
 and richer array of dresses and jewels, and all other finery that the
 sex affects, than any other lady in Salerno. Howbeit, she was none
 too warm most of her time, being ill covered abed by the doctor;
 <pb n="323" />
<milestone id="p04100005" />who gave her to understand--even as Messer Ricciardo di Chinzica,
 of whom we spoke a while since, taught his lady the feasts--that for
 once that a man lay with a woman he needed I know not how
 many days to recover, and the like nonsense: whereby she lived as
 ill content as might be; <milestone id="p04100006" />and, lacking neither sense nor spirit, she
 determined to economize at home, and taking to the street, to live
 at others' expense. So, having passed in review divers young men,
 she at last found one that was to her mind, on whom she set all her
 heart and hopes of happiness. Which the gallant perceiving was
 mightily flattered, and in like manner gave her all his love. 
<milestone id="p04100007" />Ruggieri
 da Jeroli--such was the gallant's name--was of noble birth, but of
 life and conversation so evil and reprehensible that kinsman or
 friend he had none left that wished him well, or cared to see him;
 and all Salerno knew him for a common thief and rogue of the vilest
 character. Whereof the lady took little heed, having a mind to him
 for another reason; and so with the help of her maid she arranged
 a meeting with him. <milestone id="p04100008" />But after they had solaced themselves a while,
 the lady began to censure his past life, and to implore him for love
 of her to depart from such evil ways; and to afford him the means
 thereto, she from time to time furnished him with money. 
<milestone id="p04100009" />While
 thus with all discretion they continued their intercourse, it chanced
 that a man halt of one of his legs was placed under the leech's care.
 The leech saw what was amiss with him, and told his kinsfolk, that,
 unless a gangrened bone that he had in his leg were taken out, he
 must die, or have the whole leg amputated; that if the bone were
 removed he might recover; but that otherwise he would not answer
 for his life: whereupon the relatives assented that the bone should
 be removed, and left the patient in the hands of the leech; 
<milestone id="p04100010" />who,
 deeming that by reason of the pain 'twas not possible for him to
 endure the treatment without an opiate, caused to be distilled in the
 morning a certain water of his own concoction, whereby the patient,
 drinking it, might be ensured sleep during such time as he deemed
 the operation, which he meant to perform about vespers, would
 occupy. In the meantime he had the water brought into his house,
 and set it in the window of his room, telling no one what it was.
 <milestone id="p04100011" />But when the vesper hour was come, and the leech was about to
 visit his patient, a messenger arrived from some very great friends of
 his at Amalfi, bearing tidings of a great riot there had been there, in
 <pb n="324" />which not a few had been wounded, and bidding him on no account
 omit to hie him thither forthwith. 
<milestone id="p04100012" />Wherefore the leech put off
 the treatment of the leg to the morrow, and took boat to Amalfi;
 and the lady, knowing that he would not return home that night,
 did as she was wont in such a case, to wit, brought Ruggieri in
 privily, and locked him in her chamber until certain other folk that
 were in the house were gone to sleep. <milestone id="p04100013" />Ruggieri, then, being thus in
 the chamber, awaiting the lady, and having--whether it were that
 he had had a fatiguing day, or eaten something salt, or, perchance,
 that 'twas his habit of body--a mighty thirst, glancing at the window,
 caught sight of the bottle containing the water which the leech had
 prepared for the patient, and taking it to be drinking water, set it
 to his lips and drank it all, and in no long time fell into a deep
 sleep.</p><p><milestone id="p04100014" />So soon as she was able the lady hied her to the room, and there
 finding Ruggieri asleep, touched him and softly told him to get up:
 to no purpose, however; he neither answered nor stirred a limb.
 Wherefore the lady, rather losing patience, applied somewhat more
 force, and gave him a push, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Get up, sleepy-head; if
 thou hadst a mind to sleep, thou shouldst have gone home, and not
 have come hither.</q> <milestone id="p04100015" />Thus pushed Ruggieri fell down from a box
 on which he lay, and, falling, shewed no more sign of animation
 than if he had been a corpse. The lady, now somewhat alarmed,
 essayed to lift him, and shook him roughly, and took him by the nose,
 and pulled him by the beard; again to no purpose: he had tethered
 his ass to a stout pin. <milestone id="p04100016" />So the lady began to fear he must be dead:
 however, she went on to pinch him shrewdly, and singe him with the
 flame of a candle; but when these methods also failed she, being, for
 all she was a leech's wife, no leech herself, believed for sure that he
 was dead; and as there was nought in the world that she loved so
 much, it boots not to ask if she was sore distressed; wherefore
 silently, for she dared not lament aloud, she began to weep over him
 and bewail such a misadventure. <milestone id="p04100017" />But, after a while, fearing lest her
 loss should not be without a sequel of shame, she bethought her that
 she must contrive without delay to get the body out of the house;
 and standing in need of another's advice, she quietly summoned her
 maid, shewed her the mishap that had befallen her, and craved her
 counsel. Whereat the maid marvelled not a little; and she too fell
 <pb n="325" />to pulling Ruggieri this way and that, and pinching him, and, as she
 found no sign of life in him, concurred with her mistress that he was
 verily dead, and advised her to remove him from the house. 
<milestone id="p04100018" /><q direct="unspecified">And
 where,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">shall we put him, that to-morrow, when he
 is discovered, it be not suspected that 'twas hence he was carried?</q>
 <milestone id="p04100019" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> answered the maid, <q direct="unspecified">late last evening I marked in front
 of our neighbour the carpenter's shop a chest, not too large, which,
 if he have not put it back in the house, will come in very handy
 for our purpose, for we will put him inside, and give him two or
 three cuts with a knife, and so leave him. When he is found, I
 know not why it should be thought that 'twas from this house rather
 than from any other that he was put there; nay, as he was an evilliver,
 'twill more likely be supposed, that, as he hied him on some
 evil errand, some enemy slew him, and then put him in the chest.</q>
 <milestone id="p04100020" />The lady said there was nought in the world she might so ill brook
 as that Ruggieri should receive any wound; but with that exception
 she approved her maid's proposal, and sent her to see if the chest
 were still where she had seen it. The maid, returning, reported
 that there it was, and, being young and strong, got Ruggieri, with
 the lady's help, upon her shoulders; and so the lady, going before
 to espy if any folk came that way, and the maid following, they
 came to the chest, and having laid Ruggieri therein, closed it and
 left him there.</p><p><milestone id="p04100021" />Now a few days before, two young men, that were usurers, had
 taken up their quarters in a house a little further on: they had seen
 the chest during the day, and being short of furniture, and having
 a mind to make great gain with little expenditure, they had resolved
 that, if it were still there at night, they would take it home with
 them. <milestone id="p04100022" />So at midnight forth they hied them, and finding the chest,
 were at no pains to examine it closely, but forthwith, though it
 seemed somewhat heavy, bore it off to their house, and set it down
 beside a room in which their women slept; and without being at
 pains to adjust it too securely they left it there for the time, and
 went to bed.</p><p><milestone id="p04100023" />Towards matins Ruggieri, having had a long sleep and digested
 the draught and exhausted its efficacy, awoke, but albeit his slumber
 was broken, and his senses had recovered their powers, yet his brain
 remained in a sort of torpor which kept him bemused for some days;
 <pb n="326" />and when he opened his eyes and saw nothing, and stretched his
 hands hither and thither and found himself in the chest, it was with
 difficulty that he collected his thoughts. 
<milestone id="p04100024" /><q direct="unspecified">How is this?</q> he said to
 himself. <q direct="unspecified">Where am I? Do I sleep or wake? I remember
 coming this evening to my lady's chamber; and now it seems I am
 in a chest. What means it? Can the leech have returned, or
 somewhat else have happened that caused the lady, while I slept, to
 hide me here? That was it, I suppose. Without a doubt it must
 have been so.</q> 
<milestone id="p04100025" />And having come to this conclusion, he composed
 himself to listen, if haply he might hear something, and being somewhat
 ill at ease in the chest, which was none too large, and the side
 on which he lay paining him, he must needs turn over to the other,
 and did so with such adroitness that, bringing his loins smartly
 against one of the sides of the chest, which was set on an uneven
 floor, he caused it to tilt and then fall; and such was the noise that
 it made as it fell that the women that slept there awoke, albeit for
 fear they kept silence. <milestone id="p04100026" />Ruggieri was not a little disconcerted by the
 fall, but, finding that thereby the chest was come open, he judged
 that, happen what might, he would be better out of it than in it;
 and not knowing where he was, and being otherwise at his wits' end,
 he began to grope about the house, if haply he might find a stair or
 door whereby he might take himself off. <milestone id="p04100027" />Hearing him thus groping
 his way, the alarmed women gave tongue with: <q direct="unspecified">Who is there?</q>
 Ruggieri, not knowing the voice, made no answer: wherefore the
 women fell to calling the two young men, who, having had a long
 day, were fast asleep, and heard nought of what went on. 
<milestone id="p04100028" />Which
 served to increase the fright of the women, who rose and got them
 to divers windows, and raised the cry: <q direct="unspecified">Take thief, take thief!</q>
 At which summons there came running from divers quarters not a
 few of the neighbours, who got into the house by the roof or otherwise
 as each best might: likewise the young men, aroused by the
 din, got up; <milestone id="p04100029" />and, Ruggieri being now all but beside himself for sheer
 amazement, and knowing not whither to turn him to escape them,
 they took him and delivered him to the officers of the Governor of
 the city, who, hearing the uproar, had hasted to the spot. And so
 he was brought before the Governor, who, knowing him to be held
 of all a most arrant evil-doer, put him forthwith to the torture, and,
 upon his confessing that he had entered the house of the usurers with
 <pb n="327" />intent to rob, was minded to make short work of it, and have him
 hanged by the neck.</p><p><milestone id="p04100030" />In the morning 'twas bruited throughout all Salerno that
 Ruggieri had been taken a thieving in the house of the usurers.
 Whereat the lady and her maid were all amazement and bewilderment,
 insomuch that they were within an ace of persuading themselves
 that what they had done the night before they had not done,
 but had only dreamed it; besides which, the peril in which Ruggieri
 stood caused the lady such anxiety as brought her to the verge
 of madness. <milestone id="p04100031" />Shortly after half tierce the leech, being returned
 from Amalfi, and minded now to treat his patient, called for his
 water, and finding the bottle empty made a great commotion, protesting
 that nought in his house could be let alone. <milestone id="p04100032" />The lady,
 having other cause of annoy, lost temper, and said: <q direct="unspecified">What would
 you say, Master, of an important matter, when you raise such a din
 because a bottle of water has been upset? Is there never another to
 be found in the world?</q> 
<milestone id="p04100033" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied the leech, <q direct="unspecified">thou takest
 this to have been mere water: 'twas no such thing, but an artificial
 water of a soporiferous virtue;</q> and he told her for what purpose he
 had made it. <milestone id="p04100034" />Which the lady no sooner heard, than, guessing that
 Ruggieri had drunk it, and so had seemed to them to be dead, she
 said: <q direct="unspecified">Master, we knew it not; wherefore make you another.</q>
 And so the leech, seeing that there was no help for it, had another
 made. <milestone id="p04100035" />Not long after, the maid, who by the lady's command had
 gone to find out what folk said of Ruggieri, returned, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam, of Ruggieri they say nought but evil, nor, by what I have
 been able to discover, has he friend or kinsman that has or will come
 to his aid; and 'tis held for certain that to-morrow the Stadic<note>The
 Neapolitan term for the chief of police.</note> will
 have him hanged. <milestone id="p04100036" />Besides which, I have that to tell you which will
 surprise you; for, methinks, I have found out how he came into the
 usurers' house. List, then, how it was: you know the carpenter in
 front of whose shop stood the chest we put Ruggieri into: he had
 to-day the most violent altercation in the world with one to whom
 it would seem the chest belongs, by whom he was required to make
 good the value of the chest, to which he made answer that he had
 not sold it, but that it had been stolen from him in the night. 
<milestone id="p04100037" />'Not
 <pb n="328" />so,' said the other; 'thou soldst it to the two young usurers, as they
 themselves told me last night, when I saw it in their house at the
 time Ruggieri was taken.' 'They lie,' replied the carpenter. 'I
 never sold it them, but they must have stolen it from me last night;
 go we to them.' <milestone id="p04100038" />So with one accord off they went to the usurers'
 house, and I came back here. And so, you see, I make out that
 'twas on such wise that Ruggieri was brought where he was found;
 but how he came to life again, I am at a loss to conjecture.</q> 
<milestone id="p04100039" />The lady
 now understood exactly how things were, and accordingly told the
 maid what she had learned from the leech, and besought her to aid
 her to get Ruggieri off, for so she might, if she would, and at the
 same time preserve her honour. <milestone id="p04100040" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> said the maid, <q direct="unspecified">do but
 shew me how; and glad shall I be to do just as you wish.</q> 
<milestone id="p04100041" />Whereupon
 the lady, to whom necessity taught invention, formed her plan
 on the spur of the moment, and expounded it in detail to the maid;
 <milestone id="p04100042" />who (as the first step) hied her to the leech, and, weeping, thus
 addressed him: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, it behoves me to ask your pardon of a great
 wrong that I have done you.</q> 
<milestone id="p04100043" /><q direct="unspecified">And what may that be?</q> inquired the leech. 
<milestone id="p04100044" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> said the maid, who ceased not to weep, <q direct="unspecified">you
 know what manner of man is Ruggieri da Jeroli. Now he took a
 fancy to me, and partly for fear, partly for love, I this year agreed to
 be his mistress; and knowing yestereve that you were from home,
 he coaxed me into bringing him into your house to sleep with me in
 my room. Now he was athirst, and I, having no mind to be seen
 by your lady, who was in the hall, and knowing not whither I might
 sooner betake me for wine or water, bethought me that I had seen a
 bottle of water in your room, and ran and fetched it, and gave it him
 to drink, and then put the bottle back in the place whence I had
 taken it; touching which I find that you have made a great stir in
 the house. <milestone id="p04100045" />Verily I confess that I did wrong; but who is there
 that does not wrong sometimes? Sorry indeed am I to have so done,
 but 'tis not for such a cause and that which ensued thereon that
 Ruggieri should lose his life. Wherefore, I do most earnestly
 beseech you, pardon me, and suffer me to go help him as best I may
 be able.</q> 
<milestone id="p04100046" />Wroth though he was at what he heard, the leech replied
 in a bantering tone: <q direct="unspecified">Thy pardon thou hast by thine own deed;
 for, whereas thou didst last night think to have with thee a gallant
 that would thoroughly dust thy pelisse for thee, he was but a
 sleepy<pb n="329" />head;
 wherefore get thee gone, and do what thou mayst for the
 deliverance of thy lover, and for the future look thou bring him not
 into the house; else I will pay thee for that turn and this to boot.</q>
 <milestone id="p04100047" />The maid, deeming that she had come off well in the first brush,
 hied her with all speed to the prison where Ruggieri lay, and by her
 cajoleries prevailed upon the warders to let her speak with him; and
 having told him how he must answer the Stadic if he would get off,
 she succeeded in obtaining preaudience of the Stadic; 
<milestone id="p04100048" />who, seeing
 that the baggage was lusty and mettlesome, was minded before he
 heard her to grapple her with the hook, to which she was by no
 means averse, knowing that such a preliminary would secure her a
 better hearing. When she had undergone the operation and was
 risen: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> said she, <q direct="unspecified">you have here Ruggieri da Jeroli,
 apprehended
 on a charge of theft; which charge is false.</q> 
<milestone id="p04100049" />Whereupon she
 told him the whole story from beginning to end, how she, being
 Ruggieri's mistress, had brought him into the leech's house and had
 given him the opiate, not knowing it for such, and taking him to be
 dead, had put him in the chest; and then recounting what she had
 heard pass between the carpenter and the owner of the chest, she
 shewed him how Ruggieri came into the house of the usurers.
 <milestone id="p04100050" />Seeing that 'twas easy enough to find out whether the story were
 true, the Stadic began by questioning the leech as to the water, and
 found that 'twas as she had said: he then summoned the carpenter,
 the owner of the chest and the usurers, and after much further
 parley ascertained that the usurers had stolen the chest during the
 night, and brought it into their house: <milestone id="p04100051" />finally he sent for Ruggieri,
 and asked him where he had lodged that night, to which Ruggieri
 answered that where he had lodged he knew not, but he well
 remembered going to pass the night with Master Mazzeo's maid, in
 whose room he had drunk some water by reason of a great thirst
 that he had; but what happened to him afterwards, except that, when
 he awoke, he found himself in a chest in the house of the usurers, he
 knew not. <milestone id="p04100052" />All which matters the Stadic heard with great interest,
 and caused the maid and Ruggieri and the carpenter and the
 usurers to rehearse them several times. <milestone id="p04100053" />In the end, seeing that
 Ruggieri was innocent, he released him, and mulcted the usurers in
 fifteen ounces for the theft of the chest. How glad Ruggieri was
 thus to escape, it boots not to ask; and glad beyond measure was his
 <pb n="330" />lady. And so, many a time did they laugh and make merry
 together over the affair, she and he and the dear maid that had
 proposed to give him a taste of the knife; and remaining constant in
 their love, they had ever better and better solace thereof. The like
 whereof befall me, sans the being put in the chest.</p></div2>