<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0710"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p07100001" />Two Sienese love a lady, one of them being
her gossip: the gossip dies, having promised his comrade to return to him from the other
world; which he does, and tells him what sort of life is led
there.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07100002" />None now was left to tell, save
	the king, who, as soon as the ladies had ceased mourning over the fall of the pear-tree,
	that had done no wrong, and were silent, began thus:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07100003" />Most manifest it is that
      'tis the prime duty of a just king to observe the laws that he has made; and, if he do not
      so, he is to be esteemed no king, but a slave that has merited punishment, into which
      fault, and under which condemnation, I, your king, must, as of necessity,
      fall. <milestone id="p07100004" />For, indeed, when yesterday I made the law which governs our discourse of
      to-day, I thought not to-day to avail myself of my privilege, but to submit to the law, no
      less than you, and to discourse of the same topic whereof you all have discoursed;
      <milestone id="p07100005" />but not only has the very story
      been told which I had intended to tell, but therewithal so many things else, and so very
      much goodlier have been said, that, search my memory as I may, I cannot mind me of aught,
      nor wot I that touching such a matter there is indeed aught, for me to say, that would be
      comparable with what has been said; <milestone id="p07100006" />wherefore, as infringe I must the law that
      I myself have made, I confess myself worthy of punishment, and instantly declaring my
      readiness to pay any forfeit that may be demanded of me, am minded to have recourse to my
      wonted privilege. <milestone id="p07100007" />And such, dearest ladies, is the potency of Elisa's story of
      the godfather and his gossip, and therewith of the simplicity of the Sienese, that I am
      prompted thereby to pass from this topic of the beguilement of foolish husbands by their
      cunning wives to a
      <pb n="170" />little story touching these same Sienese, which, albeit there is not a little
      therein which you were best not to believe, may yet be in
      some degree entertaining to hear.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p07100008" />Know, then, that at Siena there dwelt in Porta
Salaia two young men of the people, named, the one, Tingoccio Mini, the other Meuccio di
Tura, who, by what appeared, loved one another not a little, for they were scarce ever out
of one another's company; <milestone id="p07100009" />and being wont, like other folk, to go to church and
listen to sermons, they heard from time to time of the glory and the woe, which in the
other world are allotted, according to merit, to the souls of the dead.  Of which matters
craving, but being unable to come by, more certain assurance, they agreed together that,
whichever of them should die first, should, if he might, return to the survivor, and
certify him of that which he would fain know; and this agreement they confirmed with an
oath. <milestone id="p07100010" />Now, after they had made this engagement, and while they were still
constantly together, Tingoccio chanced to become sponsor to one Ambruogio Anselmini, that
dwelt in Campo Reggi, who had had a son by his wife, Monna Mita. <milestone id="p07100011" />The lady was
exceeding fair, and amorous withal, and Tingoccio being wont sometimes to visit her as his
gossip, and to take Meuccio with him, he,
notwithstanding his sponsorship, grew enamoured of her, as did also
Meuccio, for she pleased him not a little, and he heard her much commended by
Tingoccio. <milestone id="p07100012" />Which love each concealed from the other; but not for the same
reason. Tingoccio was averse to discover it to Meuccio, for that he deemed it an
ignominious thing to love his gossip, and was ashamed to let any one know it. Meuccio was
on his guard for a very different reason, to wit, that he was already ware that the lady
was in Tingoccio's good graces. <milestone id="p07100013" />Wherefore he said to himself: If I avow my love
to him, he will be jealous of me, and as, being her gossip, he can speak with her as
often as he pleases, he will do all he can to make her hate me, and so I shall never have
any favour of her.</p><p><milestone id="p07100014" />Now, the two young men being thus, as I have said, on terms of
most familiar friendship, it befell that Tingoccio, being the better able to open his
heart to the lady, did so order his demeanour and discourse that he had from her all that
he desired. Nor was his friend's success hidden from Meuccio; though, much as it vexed
him, yet still cherishing the hope of eventually attaining his end, and <pb n="171" />
fearing to give Tingoccio occasion to baulk or hamper him in some way, he feigned
to know nought of the matter. <milestone id="p07100015" />So Tingoccio, more fortunate than his comrade,
and rival in love, did with such assiduity till his gossip's good land that he got thereby
a malady, which in the course of some days waxed so grievous that he succumbed thereto,
and departed this life. <milestone id="p07100016" />And on the night of the third day after his
decease (perchance because earlier he might not) he made his appearance,
according to his promise, in Meuccio's chamber, and called Meuccio, who was fast asleep,
by his name. <milestone id="p07100017" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Who art thou?</q> quoth Meuccio, as he
awoke. <milestone id="p07100018" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis I, Tingoccio,</q> replied he, <q direct="unspecified">come back, in fulfilment of the
pledge I gave thee, to give thee tidings of the other world.</q> <milestone id="p07100019" />For a while
Meuccio saw him not without terror: then, his courage reviving: <q direct="unspecified">Welcome, my
brother,</q> quoth he: and proceeded to ask him if he were lost.  <milestone id="p07100020" /><q direct="unspecified">Nought is
lost but what is irrecoverable,</q> replied Tingoccio: <q direct="unspecified">how then should I be here, if I
were lost?</q> <milestone id="p07100021" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> quoth then Meuccio; <q direct="unspecified">I mean it not so: I would
know of thee, whether thou art of the number of the souls that are condemned to the penal
fire of hell.</q> <milestone id="p07100022" /><q direct="unspecified">Why no,</q> returned Tingoccio, <q direct="unspecified">not just that; but
still for the sins that I did I am in most sore and grievous torment.</q>
<milestone id="p07100023" />Meuccio then questioned Tingoccio in detail of the pains there meted out for
each of the sins done here; and Tingoccio enumerated them all.  Whereupon Meuccio asked if
there were aught he might do for him
here on earth. Tingoccio answered in the affirmative; to wit, that he might have masses
and prayers said and alms-deeds done for him, for that such things were of great service
to the souls there. <q direct="unspecified">That gladly will I,</q> replied Meuccio; <milestone id="p07100024" />and then, as
Tingoccio was about to take his leave, he bethought him of the gossip, and raising his
head a little, he said: <q direct="unspecified">I mind me, Tingoccio, of the gossip, with whom thou wast wont
to lie when thou wast here. Now what is thy punishment for that?</q> <milestone id="p07100025" /><q direct="unspecified">My
brother,</q> returned Tingoccio, <q direct="unspecified">as soon as I got down there, I met one that seemed to
know all my sins by heart, who bade me betake me to a place, where, while in direst
torment I bewept my sins, I found comrades not a few condemned to the same pains; and so,
standing there among them, and calling to mind what I had done with the gossip, and
foreboding in
requital thereof a much greater torment than had yet been allotted me, albeit I was in a
great and most vehement flame, I quaked for <pb n="172" />fear in every part of
me. <milestone id="p07100026" />Which one that was beside me observing:
'What,' quoth he, 'hast thou done more than the rest of us that are here, that thou
quakest thus as thou standest in the fire?' 'My friend,' quoth I, 'I am in mortal fear of
the doom that I expect for a great sin that I once committed.' <milestone id="p07100027" />He then asked
what sin it might be. ''Twas on this wise,' replied I: 'I lay with my gossip, and that so
much that I died thereof.'  <milestone id="p07100028" />Whereat, he did but laugh, saying: 'Go to, fool,
make thy mind easy; for here there is no account taken of gossips.' Which completely
revived my drooping spirits.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07100029" />'Twas now near daybreak: wherefore: <q direct="unspecified">Adieu! Meuccio,</q> quoth his friend: <q direct="unspecified">for
longer tarry with thee I may not;</q> and so he vanished. <milestone id="p07100030" />As for Meuccio,
having learned that no account was taken of gossips in the other world, he began to laugh
at his own folly in that he had already spared divers such; and so, being quit of his
ignorance, he in that respect in course of time waxed wise.  Which matters had Fra Rinaldo
but known, he would not have
needed to go about syllogizing in order to bring his fair gossip to
pleasure him.</p></div2>