<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov1008"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00080001" />Sophronia, albeit she deems herself wife to Gisippus, is
 wife to Titus Zuintius Fulvus, and goes with him to
 Rome, where Gisippus arrives in indigence, and deeming
 himself scorned by Titus, to compass his own death,
 avers that he has slain a man. Titus recognizes
 him, and to save his life, alleges that 'twas he that
 slew the man: whereof he that did the deed being
 witness, he discovers himself as the murderer. Whereby
 it comes to pass that they are all three liberated by
 Octavianus; and Titus gives Gisippus his sister to
 wife, and shares with him all his substance.</p></argument><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00080002" />So ceased Pampinea; and when all the ladies, and most of all
 the Ghibelline, had commended King Pedro, Filomena by command
 of the king thus began:</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00080003" />Magnificent my ladies, who wots not
 that there is nought so great but kings, when they have a mind, may
 accomplish it? As also that 'tis of them that magnificence is most
 especially demanded? Now whoso, being powerful, does that which
 it appertains to him to do, does well; but therein is no such matter of
 marvel, or occasion of extolling him to the skies, as in his deed, of
 whom, for that his power is slight, less is demanded.  <milestone id="p00080004" />Wherefore, as
 you are so profuse of your words in exaltation of the fine deeds, as
 you deem them, of monarchs, I make no manner of doubt, but that the
 doings of our peers must seem to you yet more delectable and commendable,
 when they equal or surpass those of kings. Accordingly
 'tis a transaction, laudable and magnificent, that passed between two
 <pb n="354" />citizens, who were friends, that I purpose to recount to you in my
 story.</p><p><milestone id="p00080005" />I say, then, that what time Octavianus Caesar, not as yet hight
 Augustus, but being in the office called Triumvirate, swayed the
 empire of Rome, there dwelt at Rome a gentleman, Publius Quintius
 Fulvus by name, who, having a son, Titus Quintius Fulvus, that
 was a very prodigy of wit, sent him to Athens to study philosophy,
 and to the best of his power commended him to a nobleman of that
 city, Chremes by name, who was his very old friend.  <milestone id="p00080006" />Chremes
 lodged Titus in his own house with his son Gisippus, and placed
 both Titus and Gisippus under a philosopher named Aristippus, to
 learn of him his doctrine.  <milestone id="p00080007" />And the two youths, thus keeping
 together, found each the other's conversation so congruous with his
 own, that there grew up between them a friendship so close and
 brotherly that 'twas never broken by aught but death; nor knew
 either rest or solace save when he was with the other.  <milestone id="p00080008" />So, gifted
 alike with pre-eminent subtlety of wit, they entered on their studies,
 and with even pace and prodigious applause scaled together the
 glorious heights of philosophy. In which way of life, to the exceeding
 great delight of Chremes, who entreated Titus as no less his son
 than Gisippus, they continued for full three years.  <milestone id="p00080009" />At the end
 whereof, it befell (after the common course of things mundane) that
 Chremes (being now aged) departed this life. Whom with equal
 grief they mourned as a common father; and the friends and kinsfolk
 of Chremes were alike at a loss to determine whether of the twain
 stood in need of the more consolation upon the bereavement.</p><p><milestone id="p00080010" />Some months afterward the friends and kinsfolk of Gisippus came
 to him and exhorted him, as did also Titus, to take a wife, and found
 him a maiden, wondrous fair, of one of the most noble houses of
 Athens, her name Sophronia, and her age about fifteen years.  <milestone id="p00080011" />So a
 time was appointed for their nuptials, and one day, when 'twas near
 at hand, Gisippus bade Titus come see the maiden, whom as yet he
 had not seen; and they being come into her house, and she sitting
 betwixt them, Titus, as he were fain to observe with care the several
 charms of his friend's wife that was to be, surveyed her with the
 closest attention, and being delighted beyond measure with all that
 he saw, grew, as inly he extolled her charms to the skies, enamoured
 of her with a love as ardent, albeit he gave no sign of it, as ever lover
 <pb n="355" />bore to lady. However, after they had tarried a while with her,
 they took their leave, and went home,  <milestone id="p00080012" />where Titus repaired to his
 chamber, and there gave himself over to solitary musing on the
 damsel's charms, and the longer he brooded, the more he burned for
 her. Whereon as he reflected, having heaved many a fervent sigh,
 thus he began to commune with himself:  <milestone id="p00080013" />Ah! woe worth thy
 life, Titus! Whom makest thou the mistress of thy soul, thy
 love, thy hope? Knowest thou not that by reason as well of thy
 honourable entreatment by Chremes and his kin as of the whole-hearted
 friendship that is between thee and Gisippus, it behoves thee
 to have his betrothed in even such pious regard as if she were thy
 sister? Whither art thou suffering beguiling love, delusive hope, to
 hurry thee?  <milestone id="p00080014" />Open the eyes of thine understanding, and see thyself,
 wretched man, as thou art; obey the dictates of thy reason, refrain thy
 carnal appetite, control thine inordinate desires, and give thy thoughts
 another bent; join battle with thy lust at the outset, and conquer
 thyself while there is yet time.  <milestone id="p00080015" />This which thou wouldst have is
 not meet, is not seemly: this which thou art minded to ensue, thou
 wouldst rather, though thou wert, as thou art not, sure of its attainment,
 eschew, hadst thou but the respect thou shouldst have, for the
 claims of true friendship. So, then, Titus, what wilt thou do?
 What but abandon this unseemly love, if thou wouldst do as it
 behoves thee?</p><p><milestone id="p00080016" />But then, as he remembered Sophronia, his thoughts took the
 contrary direction, and he recanted all he had said, musing on this
 wise: The laws of Love are of force above all others; they abrogate
 not only the law of human friendship, but the law Divine
 itself. How many times ere now has father loved daughter, brother
 sister, step-mother step-son? aberrations far more notable than that a
 friend should love his friend's wife, which has happened a thousand
 times.  <milestone id="p00080017" />Besides which, I am young, and youth is altogether subject
 to the laws of Love. Love's pleasure, then, should be mine. The
 seemly is for folk of riper years. 'Tis not in my power to will aught
 save that which Love wills.  <milestone id="p00080018" />So beauteous is this damsel that there
 is none but should love her; and if I love her, who am young, who
 can justly censure me? I love her not because she is the affianced
 of Gisippus; no matter whose she was, I should love her all the
 same.  <milestone id="p00080019" />Herein is Fortune to blame, that gave her to my friend,
 <pb n="356" />Gisippus, rather than to another. And if she is worthy of love, as
 for beauty she is, Gisippus, if he should come to know that I love
 her, ought to be less jealous than another.</p><p><milestone id="p00080020" />Then, scorning himself that he should indulge such thoughts, he
 relapsed into the opposing mood, albeit not to abide there, but ever
 veering to and fro, he spent not only the whole of that day and the
 ensuing night, but many others; insomuch that, being able neither
 to eat nor to sleep, he grew so weak that he was fain to take to his
 bed.  <milestone id="p00080021" />Gisippus, who had marked his moodiness for some days, and
 now saw that he was fairly sick, was much distressed; and with
 sedulous care, never quitting his side, he tended, and strove as best
 he might to comfort, him, not seldom and most earnestly demanding
 to know of him the cause of his melancholy and his sickness. Many
 were the subterfuges to which Titus resorted; but, as Gisippus was
 not to be put off with his fables, finding himself hard pressed by him,
 with sighs and sobs he made answer on this wise:  <milestone id="p00080022" /><q direct="unspecified">Gisippus, had
 such been the will of the Gods, I were fain rather to die than to
 live, seeing that Fortune has brought me to a strait in which needs
 must my virtue be put to the ordeal, and, to my most grievous
 shame, 'tis found wanting: whereof I confidently expect my due
 reward, to wit, death, which will be more welcome to me than to
 live, haunted ever by the memory of my baseness, which, as there is
 nought that from thee I either should or can conceal, I, not without
 burning shame, will discover to thee.</q>  <milestone id="p00080023" />And so he recounted the
 whole story from first to last, the occasion of his melancholy, its
 several moods, their conflict, and with which of them the victory
 rested, averring that he was dying of love for Sophronia, and that,
 knowing how ill such love beseemed him, he had, for penance, elected
 to die, and deemed the end was now not far off.  <milestone id="p00080024" />Gisippus, hearing
 his words and seeing his tears, for a while knew not what to say,
 being himself smitten with the damsel's charms, albeit in a less degree
 than Titus; but ere long he made up his mind that Sophronia must
 be less dear to him than his friend's life.</p><p>And so, moved to tears by his friend's tears:  <milestone id="p00080025" /><q direct="unspecified">Titus,</q> quoth
 he between his sobs, <q direct="unspecified">but that thou art in need of comfort, I should
 reproach thee, that thou hast offended against our friendship in that
 thou hast so long kept close from me this most distressful passion;
 and albeit thou didst deem it unseemly, yet unseemly things should
 <pb n="357" />no more than things seemly be withheld from a friend, for that, as a
 friend rejoices with his friend in things seemly, so he does his endeavour
 to wean his friend from things unseemly: but enough of this
 for the nonce: I pass to that which, I wot, is of greater moment.  <milestone id="p00080026" />If
 thou ardently lovest Sophronia, my affianced, so far from marvelling
 thereat, I should greatly marvel were it not so, knowing how fair
 she is, and how noble is thy soul, and thus the apter to be swayed by
 passion, the more excelling is she by whom thou art charmed.  <milestone id="p00080027" />And
 the juster the cause thou hast to love Sophronia, the greater is the
 injustice with which thou complainest of Fortune (albeit thou dost it
 not in so many words) for giving her to me, as if thy love of her had
 been seemly, had she belonged to any other but me;  <milestone id="p00080028" />whereas, if thou
 art still the wise man thou wast wont to be, thou must know that to
 none could Fortune have assigned her, with such good cause for thee
 to thank her, as to me. Had any other had her, albeit thy love had
 been seemly, he had loved her as his own, rather than as thine;
 which, if thou deem me even such a friend to thee as I am, thou wilt
 not apprehend from me, seeing that I mind me not that, since we
 were friends, I had ever aught that was not as much thine as mine.
  <milestone id="p00080029" />And so should I entreat thee herein as in all other matters, were the
 affair gone so far that nought else were possible; but as it is, I can
 make thee sole possessor of her; and so I mean to do; for I know
 not what cause thou shouldst have to prize my friendship, if, where
 in seemly sort it might be done, I knew not how to surrender my
 will to thine.  <milestone id="p00080030" />'Tis true that Sophronia is my betrothed, and that I
 loved her much, and had great cheer in expectation of the nuptials:
 but as thou, being much more discerning than I, dost more fervently
 affect this rare prize, rest assured that she will enter my chamber not
 mine but thine.  <milestone id="p00080031" />Wherefore, away with thy moodiness, banish thy
 melancholy, recover thy lost health, thy heartiness and jollity, and
 gladsomely, even from this very hour, anticipate the guerdon of thy
 love, a love worthier far than mine.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080032" />Delightful as was the prospect with which hope flattered Titus,
 as he heard Gisippus thus speak, no less was the shame with which
 right reason affected him, admonishing him that the greater was the
 liberality of Gisippus, the less it would become him to profit thereby.
 Wherefore, still weeping, he thus constrained himself to make
 answer:  <milestone id="p00080033" /><q direct="unspecified">Gisippus, thy generous and true friendship leaves me in
 <pb n="358" />no doubt as to the manner in which it becomes me to act. God forefend
 that her, whom, as to the more worthy, He has given to thee, I
 should ever accept of thee for mine. Had He seen fit that she should
 be mine, far be it from thee or any other to suppose that He would
 ever have awarded her to thee.  <milestone id="p00080034" />Renounce not, then, that which thy
 choice and wise counsel and His gift have made thine, and leave me,
 to whom, as unworthy, He has appointed no such happiness, to
 waste my life in tears; for either I shall conquer my grief, which
 will be grateful to thee, or it will conquer me, and so I shall be quit
 of my pain.</q>  <milestone id="p00080035" />Quoth then Gisippus: <q direct="unspecified">If our friendship, Titus, is
 of such a sort as may entitle me to enforce thee to ensue behests of
 mine, or as may induce thee of thine own free will to ensue the
 same, such is the use to which, most of all, I am minded to put it;
 and if thou lend not considerate ear unto my prayers, I shall by
 force, that force which is lawful in the interest of a friend, make
 Sophronia thine.  <milestone id="p00080036" />I know the might of Love, how redoubtable it is,
 and how, not once only, but oftentimes, it has brought ill-starred lovers
 to a miserable death; and thee I see so hard bested that turn back
 thou mightst not, nor get the better of thy grief, but holding on thy
 course, must succumb, and perish; and without doubt I should
 speedily follow thee.  <milestone id="p00080037" />And so, had I no other cause to love thee, thy
 life is precious to me in that my own is bound up with it. Sophronia,
 then, shall be thine; for thou wouldst not lightly find another so
 much to thy mind, and I shall readily find another to love, and so
 shall content both thee and me.  <milestone id="p00080038" />In which matter, peradventure, I
 might not be so liberal, were wives so scarce or hard to find as are
 friends; wherefore, as 'tis so easy a matter for me to find another
 wife, I had liefer--I say not lose her, for in giving her to thee lose
 her I shall not, but only transfer her to one that is my alter ego,
 and
 that to her advantage--I had liefer, I say, transfer her to thee than
 lose thee.  <milestone id="p00080039" />And so, if aught my prayers avail with thee, I entreat thee
 extricate thyself from this thy woeful plight, and comfort at once
 thyself and me, and in good hope, address thyself to pluck that boon
 which thy fervent love craves of her for whom thou yearnest.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080040" />Still scrupling, for shame, to consent that Sophronia should become
 his wife, Titus remained yet a while inexorable; but, yielding at
 last to the solicitations of Love, reinforced by the exhortations of
 Gisippus, thus he made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Lo now, Gisippus, I know not
 <pb n="359" />how to call it, whether 'tis more thy pleasure than mine, this which
 I do, seeing that 'tis as thy pleasure that thou so earnestly entreatest
 me to do it; but, as thy liberality is such that my shame, though
 becoming, may not withstand it, I will even do it.  <milestone id="p00080041" />But of this rest
 assured, that I do so, witting well that I receive from thee, not only
 the lady I love, but with her my very life. And, Fate permitting,
 may the Gods grant me to make thee such honourable and goodly
 requital as may shew thee how sensible I am of the boon, which
 thou, more compassionate of me than I am of myself, conferrest on
 me.</q>  <milestone id="p00080042" />Quoth then Gisippus: <q direct="unspecified">Now, for the giving effect to our
 purpose, methinks, Titus, we should proceed on this wise. Thou
 knowest that Sophronia, by treaty at length concluded between my
 family and hers, is become my betrothed: were I now to say that
 she should not be my wife, great indeed were the scandal that would
 come thereof, and I should affront both her family and mine own;
  <milestone id="p00080043" />whereof, indeed, I should make no account, so it gave me to see her
 become thine; but I fear that, were I to give her up at this juncture,
 her family would forthwith bestow her upon another, perchance,
 than thee, and so we should both be losers.  <milestone id="p00080044" />Wherefore
 methinks that, so thou approve, I were best to complete what I have
 begun, bring her home as my wife, and celebrate the nuptials, and
 thereafter we can arrange that thou lie with her, privily, as thy wife.
  <milestone id="p00080045" />Then, time and occasion serving, we will disclose the whole affair,
 and if they are satisfied, well and good; if not, 'twill be done all the
 same, and as it cannot be undone, they must perforce make the best
 of it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080046" />Which counsel being approved by Titus, Gisippus brought the
 lady home as his wife, Titus being now recovered, and quite himself
 again; and when they had made great cheer, and night was come,
 the ladies, having bedded the bride, took their departure.  <milestone id="p00080047" />Now the
 chambers of Titus and Gisippus were contiguous, and one might
 pass from one into the other: Gisippus, therefore, being come into
 his room, extinguished every ray of light, and stole into that of
 Titus, and bade him go get him to bed with his lady.  <milestone id="p00080048" />Whereat Titus
 gave way to shame, and would have changed his mind, and refused
 to go in; but Gisippus, no less zealous at heart than in words to
 serve his friend, after no small contention prevailed on him to go
 thither. Now no sooner was Titus abed with the lady, than, taking
 <pb n="360" />her in his arms, he, as if jestingly, asked in a low tone whether she
 were minded to be his wife.  <milestone id="p00080049" />She, taking him to be Gisippus,
 answered, yes; whereupon he set a fair and costly ring on her
 finger, saying: <q direct="unspecified">And I am minded to be thy husband.</q> And
 having presently consummated the marriage, he long and amorously
 disported him with her, neither she, nor any other, being ever aware
 that another than Gisippus lay with her.</p><p><milestone id="p00080050" />Now Titus and Sophronia being after this sort wedded, Publius,
 the father of Titus, departed this life. For which cause Titus was
 bidden by letter to return forthwith to Rome to see to his affairs;
 wherefore he took counsel with Gisippus how he might take
 Sophronia thither with him; which might not well be done without
 giving her to know how matters stood.  <milestone id="p00080051" />Whereof, accordingly, one
 day, having called her into the chamber, they fully apprised her,
 Titus for her better assurance bringing to her recollection not a little
 of what had passed between them.  <milestone id="p00080052" />Whereat she, after glancing from
 one to the other somewhat disdainfully, burst into a flood of tears,
 and reproached Gisippus that he had so deluded her; and forthwith,
 saying nought of the matter to any there, she hied her forth of
 Gisippus' house and home to her father, to whom and her mother
 she recounted the deceit which Gisippus had practised upon them as
 upon her, averring that she was the wife not of Gisippus, as they
 supposed, but of Titus.  <milestone id="p00080053" />Whereby her father was aggrieved exceedingly,
 and prolonged and grave complaint was made thereof by him
 and his own and Gisippus' families, and there was not a little parleying,
 and a world of pother. Gisippus earned the hatred of both his own and
 Sophronia's kin, and all agreed that he merited not only censure but
 severe punishment. He, however, averred that he had done a thing
 seemly, and that Sophronia's kinsfolk owed him thanks for giving her
 in marriage to one better than himself.</p><p><milestone id="p00080054" />All which Titus witnessed with great suffering, and witting that
 'twas the way of the Greeks to launch forth in high words and
 menaces, and refrain not until they should meet with one that
 answered them, whereupon they were wont to grow not only
 humble but even abject, was at length minded that their clavers
 should no longer pass unanswered;  <milestone id="p00080055" />and, as with his Roman temper he
 united Athenian subtlety, he cleverly contrived to bring the kinsfolk,
 as well of Gisippus as of Sophronia, together in a temple,
 <pb n="361" />where, being entered, attended only by Gisippus, thus (they being
 intent to hear) he harangued them:  <milestone id="p00080056" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis the opinion of not a
 few philosophers that whatsoever mortals do is ordained by the providence
 of the immortal Gods; for which cause some would have it
 that nought either is, or ever shall be, done, save of necessity, albeit
 others there are that restrict this necessity to that which is already
 done.  <milestone id="p00080057" />Regard we but these opinions with some little attention, and
 we shall very plainly perceive that to censure that which cannot be
 undone is nought else but to be minded to shew oneself wiser than
 the Gods; by whom we must suppose that we and our affairs are
 swayed and governed with uniform and unerring wisdom. Whereby
 you may very readily understand how vain and foolish a presumption
 it is to pass judgment on their doings, and what manner and might
 of chains they need who suffer themselves to be transported to such
 excess of daring.  <milestone id="p00080058" />Among whom, in my judgment, you must one
 and all be numbered, if 'tis true, what I hear, to wit, that you have
 complained and do continue to complain that Sophronia, albeit you
 gave her to Gisippus, is, nevertheless, become my wife; not considering
 that 'twas ordained from all eternity that she should become, not
 the wife of Gisippus, but mine, as the fact does now declare.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080059" /><q direct="unspecified">But, for that discourse of the secret providence and purposes of
 the Gods seems to many a matter hard and scarce to be understood,
 I am willing to assume that they meddle in no wise with our concerns,
 and to descend to the region of human counsels; in speaking
 whereof I must needs do two things quite at variance with my wont,
 to wit, in some degree praise myself and censure or vilify another.
  <milestone id="p00080060" />But, as in either case I mean not to deviate from the truth, and 'tis
 what the occasion demands, I shall not fail so to do.  <milestone id="p00080061" />With bitter
 upbraidings, animated rather by rage than by reason, you cease not
 to murmur, nay, to cry out, against Gisippus, and to harass him with
 your abuse, and hold him condemned, for that her, whom you saw
 fit to give him, he has seen fit to give me, to wife; wherein I deem
 him worthy of the highest commendation, and that for two reasons,
 first, because he has done the office of a friend, and secondly, because
 he has done more wisely than you did.  <milestone id="p00080062" />After what sort the sacred
 laws of friendship prescribe that friend shall entreat friend, 'tis not to
 my present purpose to declare; 'twill suffice to remind you that the
 tie of friendship should be more binding than that of blood, or
 <pb n="362" />kinship; seeing that our friends are of our own choosing, whereas our
 kinsfolk are appointed us by Fortune;  <milestone id="p00080063" />wherefore, if my life was more
 to Gisippus than your goodwill, since I am, as I hold myself, his
 friend, can any wonder thereat?</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080064" /><q direct="unspecified">But pass we to my second reason; in the exposition whereof I
 must needs with yet more cogency prove to you that he has been
 wiser than you, seeing that, methinks, you wot nought of the providence
 of the Gods, and still less of the consequences of friendship.  <milestone id="p00080065" />I
 say then, that, as 'twas your premeditated and deliberate choice that
 gave Sophronia to this young philosopher Gisippus, so 'twas his that
 gave her to another young philosopher. 'Twas your counsel that
 gave her to an Athenian; 'twas his that gave her to a Roman:
 'twas your counsel that gave her to a man of gentle birth; 'twas his
 that gave her to one of birth yet gentler: wealthy was he to whom
 your counsel gave her, most wealthy he to whom his counsel gave
 her. Not only did he to whom your counsel gave her, love her not,
 but he scarce knew her, whereas 'twas to one that loved her beyond
 all other blessings, nay, more dearly than his own life, that his
 counsel gave her.  <milestone id="p00080066" />And to the end that it may appear more plainly
 that 'tis even as I say, and Gisippus' counsel more to be commended
 than yours, let us examine it point by point. That I, like Gisippus,
 am young and a philosopher, my countenance and my pursuits may,
 without making more words about the matter, sufficiently attest.
 We are also of the same age, and have ever kept pace together in
 our studies.  <milestone id="p00080067" />Now true it is that he is an Athenian, and I am a
 Roman. But, as touching the comparative glory of the cities,
 should the matter be mooted, I say that I am of a free city, and he
 of a city tributary; that I am of a city that is mistress of all the
 world, and he of one that is subject to mine; that I am of a city
 that flourishes mightily in arms, in empire, and in arts; whereas he
 cannot boast his city as famous save in arts.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080068" /><q direct="unspecified">Moreover, albeit you see me here in the guise of a most humble
 scholar, I am not born of the dregs of the populace of Rome. My
 halls and the public places of Rome are full of the antique effigies of
 my forefathers, and the annals of Rome abound with the records of
 triumphs led by the Quintii to the Roman Capitol; and so far from
 age having withered it, to-day, yet more abundantly than ever of
 yore, flourishes the glory of our name.  <milestone id="p00080069" />Of my wealth I forbear, for
 <pb n="363" />shame, to speak, being mindful that honest poverty is the time-honoured
 and richest inheritance of the noble citizens of Rome;
 but, allowing for the nonce the opinion of the vulgar, which holds
 poverty in disrepute, and highly appraises wealth, I, albeit I never
 sought it, yet, as the favoured of Fortune, have abundant store
 thereof.  <milestone id="p00080070" />Now well I wot that, Gisippus being of your own city,
 you justly prized and prize an alliance with him; but not a whit
 less should you prize an alliance with me at Rome, considering that
 there you will have in me an excellent host, and a patron apt, zealous
 and potent to serve you as well in matters of public interest as in
 your private concerns.  <milestone id="p00080071" />Who, then, dismissing all bias from his
 mind, and judging with impartial reason, would deem your counsel
 more commendable than that of Gisippus? Assuredly none.
 Sophronia, then, being married to Titus Quintius Fulvus, a citizen
 of Rome, of an ancient and illustrious house, and wealthy, and a
 friend of Gisippus, whoso takes umbrage or offence thereat, does
 that which it behoves him not to do, and knows not what he does.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080072" /><q direct="unspecified">Perchance some will say that their complaint is not that
 Sophronia is the wife of Titus, but that she became his wife after
 such a sort, to wit, privily, by theft, neither friend nor any of her
 kin witting aught thereof; but herein is no matter of marvel, no
 prodigy as yet unheard-of.  <milestone id="p00080073" />I need not instance those who before
 now have taken to them husbands in defiance of their fathers' will,
 or have eloped with their lovers and been their mistresses before they
 were their wives, or of whose marriages no word has been spoken,
 until their pregnancy or parturition published them to the world,
 and necessity sanctioned the fact: nought of this has happened in
 the case of Sophronia; on the contrary, 'twas in proper form, and in
 meet and seemly sort, that Gisippus gave her to Titus.  <milestone id="p00080074" />And others,
 peradventure, will say that 'twas by one to whom such office belonged
 not that she was bestowed in marriage. Nay, but this is but
 vain and womanish querulousness, and comes of scant consideration.
 Know we not, then, that Fortune varies according to circumstances
 her methods and her means of disposing events to their predetermined
 ends?  <milestone id="p00080075" />What matters it to me, if it be a cobbler, rather than
 a philosopher, that Fortune has ordained to compass something for
 me, whether privily or overtly, so only the result is as it should be?
 I ought, indeed, to take order, if the cobbler be indiscreet, that he
 <pb n="364" />meddle no more in affairs of mine, but, at the same time, I ought to
 thank him for what he has done.  <milestone id="p00080076" />If Gisippus has duly bestowed
 Sophronia in marriage, it is gratuitous folly to find fault with the
 manner and the person. If you mistrust his judgment, have a care
 that it be not in his power to do the like again, but thank him
 for this turn.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080077" /><q direct="unspecified">Natheless, you are to know that I used no cunning practice or
 deceit to sully in any degree the fair fame of your house in the
 person of Sophronia;  <milestone id="p00080078" />and, albeit I took her privily to wife, I came
 not as a ravisher to despoil her of her virginity, nor in any hostile
 sort was I minded to make her mine on dishonourable terms, and
 spurn your alliance; but, being fervently enamoured of her bewitching
 beauty and her noble qualities, I wist well that, should I
 make suit for her with those formalities which you, perchance, will
 say were due, then, for the great love you bear her, and for fear lest I
 should take her away with me to Rome, I might not hope to have
 her.  <milestone id="p00080079" />Accordingly I made use of the secret practice which is now
 manifest to you, and brought Gisippus to consent in my interest to
 that whereto he was averse;  <milestone id="p00080080" />and thereafter, ardently though I loved
 her, I sought not to commingle with her as a lover, but as a husband,
 nor closed with her, until, as she herself by her true witness
 may assure you, I had with apt words and with the ring made her
 my lawful wife, asking her if she would have me to husband, whereto
 she answered, yes. Wherein if she seem to have been tricked, 'tis
 not I that am to blame, but she, for that she asked me not who I was.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080081" /><q direct="unspecified">This, then, is the great wrong, sin, crime, whereof for love and
 friendship's sake Gisippus and I are guilty, that Sophronia is privily
 become the wife of Titus Quintius: 'tis for this that you harass him
 with your menaces and hostile machinations.  <milestone id="p00080082" />What more would
 you do, had he given her to a villein, to a caitiff, to a slave? Where
 would you find fetters, dungeons, crosses adequate to your vengeance?
  <milestone id="p00080083" />But enough of this at present: an event, which I did not
 expect, has now happened; my father is dead; and I must needs
 return to Rome; wherefore, being fain to take Sophronia with me,
 I have discovered to you that which otherwise I had, perchance, still
 kept close. Whereto, if you are wise, you will gladly reconcile
 yourselves; for that, if I had been minded to play you false, or put
 an affront upon you, I might have scornfully abandoned her to you;
 <pb n="365" />but God forefend that such baseness be ever harboured in a Roman
 breast.  <milestone id="p00080084" />Sophronia, then, by the will of the Gods, by force of law,
 and by my own love-taught astuteness, is mine. The which it would
 seem that you, deeming yourselves, peradventure, wiser than the
 Gods, or the rest of mankind, do foolishly set at nought, and that in
 two ways alike most offensive to me; inasmuch as you both withhold
 from me Sophronia, in whom right, as against me, you have
 none, and also entreat as your enemy Gisippus, to whom you are
 rightfully bounden.  <milestone id="p00080085" />The folly whereof I purpose not at present
 fully to expound to you, but in friendly sort to counsel you to abate
 your wrath and abandon all your schemes of vengeance, and restore
 Sophronia to me, that I may part from you on terms of amity and
 alliance, and so abide:  <milestone id="p00080086" />but of this rest assured, that whether this,
 which is done, like you or not, if you are minded to contravene it, I
 shall take Gisippus hence with me, and once arrived in Rome, shall
 in your despite find means to recover her who is lawfully mine, and
 pursuing you with unremitting enmity, will apprise you by experience
 of the full measure and effect of a Roman's wrath.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080087" />Having so said, Titus started to his feet, his countenance distorted
 by anger, and took Gisippus by the hand, and with manifest
 contempt for all the rest, shaking his head at them and threatening
 them, led him out of the temple.  <milestone id="p00080088" />They that remained in the
 temple, being partly persuaded by his arguments to accept his
 alliance and friendship, partly terrified by his last words, resolved by
 common consent that 'twas better to have the alliance of Titus, as
 they had lost that of Gisippus, than to add to that loss the enmity of
 Titus.  <milestone id="p00080089" />Wherefore they followed Titus, and having come up with
 him, told him that they were well pleased that Sophronia should be
 his, and that they should prize his alliance and the friendship of dear
 Gisippus; and having ratified this treaty of amity and alliance with
 mutual cheer, they departed and sent Sophronia to Titus. Sophronia,
 discreetly making a virtue of necessity, transferred forthwith to Titus
 the love she had borne Gisippus, and being come with Titus to Rome,
 was there received with no small honour.  <milestone id="p00080090" />Gisippus tarried in Athens,
 held in little account by well-nigh all the citizens, and being involved
 in certain of their broils, was, not long afterwards, with all his
 household,
 banished the city, poor, nay, destitute, and condemned to perpetual
 exile.  <milestone id="p00080091" />Thus hard bested, and at length reduced to mendicancy,
 <pb n="366" />he made his way, so as least discomfortably he might, to Rome,
 being minded to see whether Titus would remember him: and
 there, learning that Titus lived, and was much affected by all the
 Romans, and having found out his house, he took his stand in front
 of it, and watched until Titus came by;  <milestone id="p00080092" />to whom, for shame of the
 sorry trim that he was in, he ventured no word, but did his endeavour
 that he might be seen of him, hoping that Titus might recognize
 him, and call him by his name: but Titus passing on, Gisippus
 deeming that he had seen and avoided him, and calling to mind that
 which aforetime he had done for him, went away wroth and
 desperate.  <milestone id="p00080093" />And fasting and penniless, and--for 'twas now night--knowing
 not whither he went, and yearning above all for death, he
 wandered by chance to a spot, which, albeit 'twas within the city,
 had much of the aspect of a wilderness, and espying a spacious
 grotto, he took shelter there for the night; and worn out at last with
 grief, on the bare ground, wretchedly clad as he was, he fell asleep.</p><p><milestone id="p00080094" />Now two men that had that night gone out a thieving, having
 committed the theft, came towards morning to the grotto, and there
 quarrelled, and the stronger slew the other, and took himself off.
  <milestone id="p00080095" />Aroused by the noise, Gisippus witnessed the murder, and deeming
 that he had now the means of compassing, without suicide, the death
 for which he so much longed, budged not a jot, but stayed there,
 until the serjeants of the court, which had already got wind of the
 affair, came on the scene, and laid violent hands upon him, and led
 him away.  <milestone id="p00080096" />Being examined, he confessed that he had slain the man,
 and had then been unable to make his escape from the grotto.
 Wherefore the praetor, Marcus Varro by name, sentenced him to
 death by crucifixion, as was then the custom.  <milestone id="p00080097" />But Titus, who
 happened at that moment to come into the praetorium, being told
 the crime for which he was condemned, and scanning the poor
 wretch's face, presently recognized him for Gisippus, and marvelled
 how he should come to be there, and in such a woeful plight. And
 most ardently desiring to succour him, nor seeing other way to save
 his life except to exonerate him by accusing himself, he straightway
 stepped forward, and said with a loud voice:  <milestone id="p00080098" /><q direct="unspecified">Marcus Varro, call
 back the poor man on whom thou hast passed sentence, for he is
 innocent. 'Tis enough that I have incurred the wrath of the Gods
 by one deed of violence, to wit, the murder of him whom your
 <pb n="367" />serjeants found dead this morning, without aggravating my offence
 by the death of another innocent man.</q>  <milestone id="p00080099" />Perplexed, and vexed that he
 should have been heard by all in the praetorium, but unable honourably
 to avoid compliance with that which the laws enjoined, Varro
 had Gisippus brought back, and in presence of Titus said to him:
  <milestone id="p00080100" /><q direct="unspecified">How camest thou to be so mad as, though no constraint was put
 upon thee, to confess a deed thou never didst, thy life being at stake?
 Thou saidst that 'twas thou by whom the man was slain last night,
 and now comes this other, and says that 'twas not thou but he that
 slew him.</q>  <milestone id="p00080101" />Gisippus looked, and seeing Titus, wist well that, being
 grateful for the service rendered by him in the past, Titus was now
 minded to save his life at the cost of his own: wherefore, affected to
 tears, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay but, Varro, in very sooth I slew him, and 'tis
 now too late, this tender solicitude of Titus for my deliverance.</q>
  <milestone id="p00080102" />But on his part: <q direct="unspecified">Praetor,</q> quoth Titus, <q direct="unspecified">thou seest this man is
 a stranger, and was found unarmed beside the murdered man; thou
 canst not doubt that he was fain of death for very wretchedness:
 wherefore discharge him, and let punishment light on me who have
 merited it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080103" />Marvelling at the importunity of both, Varro readily surmised
 that neither was guilty. And while he was casting about how he
 might acquit them, lo, in came a young man, one Publius Ambustus,
 a desperate character, and known to all the Romans for an arrant
 thief. He it was that had verily committed the murder,  <milestone id="p00080104" />and witting
 both the men to be innocent of that of which each accused himself, so
 sore at heart was he by reason of their innocence, that, overborne by
 an exceeding great compassion, he presented himself before Varro,
 and:  <milestone id="p00080105" /><q direct="unspecified">Praetor,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis destiny draws me hither to loose
 the knot of these men's contention; and some God within me leaves
 me no peace of his whips and stings, until I discover my offence:
 wherefore know that neither of these men is guilty of that of which
 each accuses himself.  <milestone id="p00080106" />'Tis verily I that slew the man this morning
 about daybreak; and before I slew him, while I was sharing our
 plunder with him, I espied this poor fellow asleep there. Nought
 need I say to clear Titus: the general bruit of his illustrious renown
 attests that he is not a man of such a sort. Discharge him, therefore,
 and exact from me the penalty prescribed by the laws.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080107" />The affair had by this time come to the ears of Octavianus, who
 <pb n="368" />caused all three to be brought before him, and demanded to know
 the causes by which they had been severally moved to accuse themselves;
 and, each having told his story, Octavianus released the two
 by reason of their innocence, and the third for love of them.  <milestone id="p00080108" />Titus
 took Gisippus home, having first chidden him not a little for his
 faint-heartedness and diffidence, and there, Sophronia receiving him as
 a brother, did him marvellous cheer;  <milestone id="p00080109" />and having comforted him a
 while, and arrayed him in apparel befitting his worth and birth, he
 first shared with him all his substance, and then gave him his sister,
 a young damsel named Fulvia, to wife, and said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Choose
 now, Gisippus, whether thou wilt tarry here with me, or go back
 to Achaia with all that I have given thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00080110" />Partly perforce of his banishment from his city, partly for that
 the sweet friendship of Titus was justly dear to him, Gisippus
 consented to become a Roman. And so, long and happily they
 lived together at Rome, Gisippus with his Fulvia, and Titus with
 his Sophronia, in the same house, growing, if possible, greater friends
 day by day.</p><p><milestone id="p00080111" />Exceeding sacred then, is friendship, and worthy not only to be
 had in veneration, but to be extolled with never-ending praise, as the
 most dutiful mother of magnificence and seemliness, sister of gratitude
 and charity, and foe to enmity and avarice; ever, without waiting
 to be asked, ready to do as generously by another as she would be
 done by herself.  <milestone id="p00080112" />Rarely indeed is it to-day that twain are found, in
 whom her most holy fruits are manifest; for which is most shamefully
 answerable the covetousness of mankind, which, regarding only
 private interest, has banished friendship beyond earth's farthest bourne,
 there to abide in perpetual exile.  <milestone id="p00080113" />How should love, or wealth, or
 kinship, how should aught but friendship have so quickened the soul
 of Gisippus that the tears and sighs of Titus should incline his heart
 to cede to him the fair and gracious lady that was his betrothed and
 his beloved?  <milestone id="p00080114" />Laws, menaces, terror! How should these, how should
 aught but friendship, have withheld Gisippus, in lonely places, in
 hidden retreats, in his own bed, from enfolding (not perchance unsolicited
 by her) the fair damsel within his youthful embrace?
  <milestone id="p00080115" />Honours, rewards, gains! Would Gisippus for these, would he for
 aught but friendship, have made nothing of the loss of kindred--his
 own and Sophronia's--have made nothing of the injurious murmurs
 <pb n="369" />of the populace, have made nothing of mocks and scorns, so only
 he might content his friend?  <milestone id="p00080116" />And on the other hand, for what
 other cause than friendship had Titus, when he might decently have
 feigned not to see, have striven with the utmost zeal to compass his
 own death, and set himself upon the cross in Gisippus' stead?  
[*** missing sentence: please see Italian <milestone id="p00080117" /> ***] 
<milestone id="p00080118" />And
 what but friendship had left no place for suspicion in the soul of
 Titus, and filled it with a most fervent desire to give his sister to
 Gisippus, albeit he saw him to be reduced to extreme penury
 and destitution?  <milestone id="p00080119" />But so it is that men covet hosts of acquaintance,
 troops of kinsfolk, offspring in plenty; and the number of their
 dependants increases with their wealth; and they reflect not that
 there is none of these, be he who he may, but will be more apprehensive
 of the least peril threatening himself than cumbered to avert
 a great peril from his lord or kinsman, whereas between friends we
 know 'tis quite contrariwise.</p></div2>