<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0907"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09070001" />Talano di Molese dreams that a wolf tears and rends all
 the neck and face of his wife: he gives her warning
 thereof, which she heeds not, and the dream comes
 true.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09070002" />When Pamfilo had brought his story to a close, and all had
 commended
 the good woman's quick perception, the queen bade Pampinea
 tell hers; and thus Pampinea began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09070003" />A while ago, debonair my
 ladies, we held discourse of the truths that dreams shew forth, which
 not a few of us deride; for which cause, albeit the topic has been
 handled before, I shall not spare to tell you that which not long ago
 befell a neighbour of mine, for that she disbelieved a dream that her
 husband had.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09070004" />I wot not if you knew Talano di Molese, a man right worthy to
 be had in honour; who, having married a young wife--Margarita
 by name--fair as e'er another, but without her match for whimsical,
 fractious, and perverse humours, insomuch that there was nought she
 would do at the instance of another, either for his or her own good,
 found her behaviour most grievous to bear, but was fain to endure
 what he might not cure.  <milestone id="p09070005" />Now it so befell that Talano and
 Margarita being together at an estate that Talano had in the contado,
 he, sleeping, saw in a dream a very beautiful wood that was on the
 estate at no great distance from the house, and his lady there walking.
  <milestone id="p09070006" />And as she went, there leapt forth upon her a huge and fierce wolf that
 griped her by the throat, and bore her down to the ground, and (she
 shrieking the while for succour) would have carried her off by main
 force; but she got quit of his jaws, albeit her neck and face shewed as
 quite disfigured.  <milestone id="p09070007" />On the morrow, as soon as he was risen, Talano said
 <pb n="296" />to
 his wife: <q direct="unspecified">Albeit for thy perversity I have not yet known a single
 good day with thee, yet I should be sorry, wife, that harm should
 befall thee; and therefore, if thou take my advice, thou wilt not stir
 out of doors to-day.</q> <q direct="unspecified">Wherefore?</q> quoth the lady; and thereupon
 he recounted to her all his dream.</p><p><milestone id="p09070008" />The lady shook her head, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Who means ill, dreams ill.
 Thou makest as if thou wast mighty tender of me, but thou bodest of
 me in thy dream that which thou wouldst fain see betide me. I
 warrant thee that to-day and all days I will have a care to avoid
 this or any other calamity that might gladden thy heart.</q>  <milestone id="p09070009" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Well wist I,</q> replied Talano, <q direct="unspecified">that thou wouldst so say,
 for such is ever the requital of those that comb scurfy heads; but
 whatever thou mayst be pleased to believe, I for my part speak to
 thee for thy good, and again I advise thee to keep indoors to-day, or
 at least not to walk in the wood.</q>  <milestone id="p09070010" /><q direct="unspecified">Good,</q> returned the lady, <q direct="unspecified">I
 will look to it,</q> and then she began communing with herself on this
 wise: Didst mark how artfully he thinks to have scared me from
 going into the wood to-day? Doubtless 'tis that he has an assignation
 there with some light o' love, with whom he had rather I did not
 find him. Ah! he would sup well with the blind, and what a fool
 were I to believe him! But I warrant he will be disappointed, and
 needs must I, though I stay there all day long, see what commerce it
 is that he will adventure in to-day.</p><p><milestone id="p09070011" />Having so said, she quitted the house on one side, while her
 husband did so on the other; and forthwith, shunning observation as
 best she might, she hied her to the wood, and hid her where 'twas
 most dense, and there waited on the alert, and glancing, now this
 way and now that, to see if any were coming.  <milestone id="p09070012" />And while thus she
 stood, nor ever a thought of a wolf crossed her mind, lo, forth of
 a close covert hard by came a wolf of monstrous size and appalling
 aspect, and scarce had she time to say, God help me! before he sprang
 upon her and griped her by the throat so tightly that she might not
 utter a cry, but, passive as any lambkin, was borne off by him,  <milestone id="p09070013" />and
 had certainly been strangled, had he not encountered some shepherds,
 who with shouts compelled him to let her go. The shepherds
 recognized the poor hapless woman, and bore her home, where the
 physicians by dint of long and careful treatment cured her; howbeit
 the whole of her throat and part of her face remained so disfigured
 <pb n="297" />that,
 fair as she had been before, she was ever thereafter most foul
 and hideous to look upon.  <milestone id="p09070014" />Wherefore, being ashamed to shew her
 face, she did many a time bitterly deplore her perversity, in that, when
 it would have cost her nothing, she would nevertheless pay no heed
 to the true dream of her husband.</p></div2>