<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0304"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03040001" />Dom Felice instructs Fra Puccio how to attain blessedness
 by doing a penance. Fra Puccio does the penance,
 and meanwhile Dom Felice has a good time with Fra
 Puccio's wife.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03040002" />When Filomena, having concluded her story, was silent, and
	Dioneo had added a few honeyed phrases in praise of the lady's wit and
	Filomena's closing prayer, the queen glanced with a smile to Pamfilo,
	and said: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Pamfilo, give us some pleasant trifle to speed our
	  delight.</q> <q direct="unspecified">That gladly will I,</q> returned forthwith Pamfilo, and
	then:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03040003" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> <seg type="authorialcomment">he began</seg>, 
	<q direct="unspecified">not a few there are that, while they
	  use their best endeavours to get themselves places in Paradise, do, by
	  inadvertence, send others thither: as did, not long ago, betide a fair
	  neighbour of ours, as you shall hear.</q></p></div3><p><milestone id="p03040004" />Hard by San Pancrazio there used to live, as I have heard tell,
 a worthy man and wealthy, Puccio di Rinieri by name, who in later
 life, under an overpowering sense of religion, became a tertiary of
 the order of St. Francis, and was thus known as Fra Puccio. In
 which spiritual life he was the better able to persevere that his
 household consisted but of a wife and a maid, and having no need to
 occupy himself with any craft, he spent no small part of his time at
 church; <milestone id="p03040005" />where, being a simple soul and slow of wit, he said his
 paternosters, heard sermons, assisted at the mass, never missed lauds
 (i. e. when chanted by the seculars), fasted and mortified his flesh;
 nay--so
 'twas whispered--he was of the Flagellants. <milestone id="p03040006" />His wife, Monna
 Isabetta by name, a woman of from twenty-eight to thirty summers,
 still young for her age, lusty, comely and plump as a casolan<note>Perhaps
 from Casoli, near Naples.</note> apple,
 <pb n="199" />had not unfrequently, by reason of her husband's devoutness, if not
 also of his age, more than she cared for, of abstinence; and when she
 was sleepy, or, maybe, riggish, he would repeat to her the life of Christ,
 and the sermons of Fra Nastagio, or the lament of the Magdalen, or
 the like. <milestone id="p03040007" />Now, while such was the tenor of her life, there returned
 from Paris a young monk, by name Dom Felice, of the convent of
 San Pancrazio, a well-favoured man and keen-witted, and profoundly
 learned, with whom Fra Puccio became very intimate; <milestone id="p03040008" />and as there
 was no question which he could put to him but Dom Felice could
 answer it, and moreover he made great shew of holiness, for well he
 knew Fra Puccio's bent, Fra Puccio took to bringing him home and
 entertaining him at breakfast and supper, as occasion served; and for
 love of her husband the lady also grew familiar with Dom Felice,
 and was zealous to do him honour. <milestone id="p03040009" />So the monk, being a constant
 visitor at Fra Puccio's house, and seeing the lady so lusty and plump,
 surmised that of which she must have most lack, and made up his
 mind to afford, if he could, at once relief to Fra Puccio and contentment
 to the lady. <milestone id="p03040010" />So cautiously, now and again, he cast an admiring
 glance in her direction with such effect that he kindled in her the
 same desire with which he burned, and marking his success, took the
 first opportunity to declare his passion to her. <milestone id="p03040011" />He found her fully
 disposed to gratify it; but how this might be, he was at a loss to
 discover, for she would not trust herself with him in any place whatever
 except her own house, and there it could not be, because Fra
 Puccio never travelled; whereby the monk was greatly dejected.
 Long he pondered the matter, and at length thought of an expedient,
 whereby he might be with the lady in her own house without
 incurring suspicion, notwithstanding that Fra Puccio was there.
 <milestone id="p03040012" />So, being with Fra Puccio one day, he said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Reasons
 many have I to know, Fra Puccio, that all thy desire is to become a
 saint; but it seems to me that thou farest by a circuitous route,
 whereas there is one very direct, which the Pope and the greater
 prelates that are about him know and use, but will have it remain a
 secret, because otherwise the clergy, who for the most part live by
 alms, and could not then expect alms or aught else from the laity,
 would be speedily ruined. <milestone id="p03040013" />However, as thou art my friend, and hast
 shewn me much honour, I would teach thee that way, if I were assured
 that thou wouldst follow it without letting another soul in the world
 <pb n="200" />hear of it.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040014" />Fra Puccio was now all agog to hear more of the matter,
 and began most earnestly entreating Dom Felice to teach him the
 way, swearing that without Dom Felice's leave none should ever
 hear of it from him, and averring that, if he found it practicable, he
 would certainly follow it. <q direct="unspecified"><milestone id="p03040015" />I am satisfied with thy promises,</q> said
 the monk, <q direct="unspecified">and I will shew thee the way. Know then that the
 holy doctors hold that whoso would achieve blessedness must do the
 penance of which I shall tell thee; but see thou take me judiciously.
 I do not say that after the penance thou wilt not be a sinner, as thou
 art; but the effect will be that the sins which thou hast committed
 up to the very hour of the penance will all be purged away and
 thereby remitted to thee, and the sins which thou shalt commit
 thereafter will not be written against thee to thy damnation, but will
 be quit by holy water, like venial sins. <milestone id="p03040016" />First of all then the penitent
 must with great exactitude confess his sins when he comes to begin
 the penance. Then follows a period of fasting and very strict
 abstinence which must last for forty days, during which time he is to
 touch no woman whomsoever, not even his wife. <milestone id="p03040017" />Moreover, thou
 must have in thy house some place whence thou mayst see the sky
 by night, whither thou must resort at compline; and there thou must
 have a beam, very broad, and placed in such a way, that, standing,
 thou canst rest thy nether part upon it, and so, not raising thy feet
 from the ground, thou must extend thy arms, so as to make a sort of
 crucifix, and if thou wouldst have pegs to rest them on thou mayst;
 and on this manner, thy gaze fixed on the sky, and never moving a
 jot, thou must stand until matins. <milestone id="p03040018" />And wert thou lettered, it were
 proper for thee to say meanwhile certain prayers that I would give
 thee; but as thou art not so, thou must say three hundred paternosters
 and as many avemarias in honour of the Trinity; and thus
 contemplating the sky, be ever mindful that God was the creator of
 the heaven and the earth, and being set even as Christ was upon the
 cross, meditate on His passion. <milestone id="p03040019" />Then, when the matin-bell sounds,
 thou mayst, if thou please, go to bed--but see that thou undress not--and
 sleep; but in the morning thou must go to church, and hear
 at least three masses, and say fifty paternosters and as many avemarias;
 after which thou mayst with a pure heart do aught that thou hast
 to do, and breakfast; but at vespers thou must be again at church,
 and say there certain prayers, which I shall give thee in writing and
 <pb n="201" />which are indispensable, and after compline thou must repeat thy
 former exercise. <milestone id="p03040020" />Do this, and I, who have done it before thee, have
 good hope that even before thou shalt have reached the end of the
 penance, thou wilt, if thou shalt do it in a devout spirit, have already
 a marvellous foretaste of the eternal blessedness.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040021" /><q direct="unspecified">This,</q> said Fra
 Puccio, <q direct="unspecified">is neither a very severe nor a very long penance, and can
 be very easily managed: wherefore in God's name I will begin on
 Sunday.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040022" />And so he took his leave of Dom Felice, and went home,
 and, by Dom Felice's permission, informed his wife of every particular
 of his intended penance.</p><p>The lady understood very well what the monk meant by enjoining
 him not to stir from his post until matins; and deeming it an
 excellent device, she said that she was well content that he should do
 this or aught else that he thought good for his soul; and to the end
 that his penance might be blest of God, she would herself fast with
 him, though she would go no further. 
<milestone id="p03040023" />So they did as they had
 agreed: when Sunday came Fra Puccio began his penance, and master
 monk, by understanding with the lady, came most evenings, at the
 hour when he was secure from discovery, to sup with her, always
 bringing
 with him abundance both of meat and of drink, and after slept
 with her till the matin hour, when he got up and left her, and Fra
 Puccio went to bed. <milestone id="p03040024" />The place which Fra Puccio had chosen for
 his penance was close to the room in which the lady slept, and only
 separated from it by the thinnest of partitions; so that, the monk and
 the lady disporting themselves with one another without stint or
 restraint, Fra Puccio thought he felt the floor of the house shake a
 little, and pausing at his hundredth paternoster, but without leaving
 his post, called out to the lady to know what she was about. <milestone id="p03040025" />The
 lady, who dearly loved a jest, and was just then riding the horse of
 St. Benedict or St. John Gualbert, answered: <q direct="unspecified">I'faith, husband, I am
 as restless as may be.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040026" /><q direct="unspecified">Restless,</q> said Fra Puccio, <q direct="unspecified">how so? What
 means this restlessness?</q> 
<milestone id="p03040027" />Whereto with a hearty laugh, for which
 she doubtless had good occasion, the bonny lady replied: <q direct="unspecified">What
 means it? How should you ask such a question? Why, I have
 heard you say a thousand times: 'Who fasting goes to bed, uneasy
 lies his head.'</q> 
<milestone id="p03040028" />Fra Puccio, supposing that her wakefulness and
 restlessness abed was due to want of food, said in good faith: <q direct="unspecified">Wife,
 I told thee I would have thee not fast; but as thou hast chosen to
 <pb n="202" />fast, think not of it, but think how thou mayst compose thyself to
 sleep; thou tossest about the bed in such sort that the shaking is felt
 here.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040029" /><q direct="unspecified">That need cause thee no alarm,</q> rejoined the lady. <q direct="unspecified">I
 know what I am about; I will manage as well as I can, and do thou
 likewise.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040030" />So Fra Puccio said no more to her, but resumed his
 paternosters; and thenceforth every night, while Fra Puccio's penance
 lasted, the lady and master monk, having had a bed made up for them
 in another part of the house, did there wanton it most gamesomely,
 the monk departing and the lady going back to her bed at one and
 the same time, being shortly before Fra Puccio's return from his
 nightly vigil. <milestone id="p03040031" />The friar thus persisting in his penance while the lady
 took her fill of pleasure with the monk, she would from time to time
 say jestingly to him: <q direct="unspecified">Thou layest a penance upon Fra Puccio
 whereby we are rewarded with Paradise.</q> 
<milestone id="p03040032" />So well indeed did she
 relish the dainties with which the monk regaled her, the more so by
 contrast with the abstemious life to which her husband had long
 accustomed her, that, when Fra Puccio's penance was done, she found
 means to enjoy them elsewhere, and ordered her indulgence with
 such discretion as to ensure its long continuance. <milestone id="p03040033" />Whereby (that my
 story may end as it began) it came to pass that Fra Puccio, hoping by
 his penance to win a place for himself in Paradise, did in fact translate
 thither the monk who had shewn him the way, and the wife who
 lived with him in great dearth of that of which the monk in his
 charity gave her superabundant largess.</p></div2>