<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0809"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08090001" />Bruno and Buffalmacco prevail upon Master Simone, a
 physician, to betake him by night to a certain place,
 there to be enrolled in a company that go the course.
 Buffalmacco throws him into a foul ditch, and there
 they leave him.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08090002" />When the ladies had made merry a while
	over the partnership in
	wives established by the two Sienese, the queen, who now, unless she
	were minded to infringe Dioneo's privilege, alone remained to tell,
	began on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08090003" />Fairly earned indeed, loving ladies, was the
 flout that Spinelloccio got from Zeppa. Wherefore my judgment jumps
 with that which Pampinea expressed a while ago, to wit, that
 he is not severely to be censured who bestows a flout on one that
 provokes it or deserves it; and as Spinelloccio deserved it, so 'tis my
 purpose to tell you of one that provoked it, for I deem that those
 from whom he received it, were rather to be commended than condemned.
 The man that got it was a physician, who, albeit he was
 but a blockhead, returned from Bologna to Florence in mantle and
 hood of vair.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08090004" />'Tis matter of daily experience that our citizens come back to us
 from Bologna, this man a judge, that a physician, and the other
 a notary, flaunting it in ample flowing robes, and adorned with the
 scarlet and the vair and other array most goodly to see; and how
 far their doings correspond with this fair seeming, is also matter of
 daily experience. <milestone id="p08090005" />Among whom 'tis not long since Master Simone
 da Villa, one whose patrimony was more ample than his knowledge,
 came back wearing the scarlet and a broad stripe<note>The distinguishing
 mark
 of a doctor in those days. Fanfani, Vocab. della Lingua Italiana,
 1891,
 <q direct="unspecified">Batolo.</q></note> on the shoulder, and
 <pb n="236" />a doctor, as he called himself, and took a house in the street that we
 now call Via del Cocomero. <milestone id="p08090006" />Now this Master Simone, being thus, as
 we said, come back, had this among other singular habits, that he could
 never see a soul pass along the street, but he must needs ask any that
 was by, who that man was; and he was as observant of all the doings
 of men, and as sedulous to store his memory with such matters, as
 if they were to serve him to compound the drugs that he was to give
 his patients. <milestone id="p08090007" />Now, of all that he saw, those that he eyed most observantly
 were two painters, of whom here to-day mention has twice
 been made, Bruno, to wit, and Buffalmacco, who were ever together,
 and were his neighbours. <milestone id="p08090008" />And as it struck him that they daffed the
 world aside and lived more lightheartedly than any others that he
 knew, as indeed they did, he enquired of not a few folk as to their
 rank. And learning on all hands that they were poor men and
 painters, he could not conceive it possible that they should live thus
 contentedly in poverty, but made his mind up that, being, as he was
 informed, clever fellows, they must have some secret source from
 which they drew immense gains; <milestone id="p08090009" />for which reason he grew all agog
 to get on friendly terms with them, or any rate with one of them,
 and did succeed in making friends with Bruno.</p><p><milestone id="p08090010" />Bruno, who had not needed to be much with him in order to
 discover that this physician was but a dolt, had never such a jolly
 time in palming off his strange stories upon him, while the physician,
 on his part, was marvellously delighted with Bruno; <milestone id="p08090011" />to whom, having
 bidden him to breakfast, and thinking that for that reason he might
 talk familiarly with him, he expressed the amazement with which
 he regarded both him and Buffalmacco, for that, being but poor men,
 they lived so lightheartedly, and asked him to tell him how they
 managed. <milestone id="p08090012" />At which fresh proof of the doctor's simplicity and
 fatuity Bruno was inclined to laugh; but, bethinking him that
 'twere best to answer him according to his folly, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Master,
 there are not many persons to whom I would disclose our manner
 of life, but, as you are my friend, and I know you will not let it go
 further, I do not mind telling you. <milestone id="p08090013" />The fact is that my comrade
 and I live not only as lightheartedly and jovially as you see, but
 much more so; and yet neither our art, nor any property that we
 possess, yields us enough to keep us in water: not that I would
 have you suppose that we go a thieving: no, 'tis that we go the
 <pb n="237" />course, and thereby without the least harm done to a soul we get all
 that we need, nay, all that we desire; and thus it is that we live so
 lightheartedly as you see.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090014" />Which explanation the doctor believing
 none the less readily that he knew not what it meant, was lost in
 wonder, and forthwith burned with a most vehement desire to know
 what going the course might be, and was instant with Bruno to
 expound it, assuring him that he would never tell a soul. 
<milestone id="p08090015" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas!
 Master,</q> said Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">what is this you ask of me? 'Tis a mighty
 great secret you would have me impart to you: 'twould be enough
 to undo me, to send me packing out of the world, nay, into the very
 jaws of Lucifer of San Gallo,<note>Perhaps an allusion to some frightful
 picture.</note> if it came to be known. But such is
 the respect in which I hold your quiditative pumpionship of Legnaia,
 and the trust I repose in you, that I am not able to deny you aught
 you ask of me; and so I will tell it you, on condition that you swear
 by the cross at Montesone that you will keep your promise, and
 never repeat it to a soul.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08090016" />The Master gave the required assurance. 
<milestone id="p08090017" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">You
 are then to know,</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">sweet my Master, that 'tis not
 long since there was in this city a great master in necromancy, hight
 Michael Scott, for that he was of Scotland, and great indeed was the
 honour in which he was held by not a few gentlemen, most of whom
 are now dead; and when the time came that he must needs depart
 from Florence, he at their instant entreaty left behind him two
 pupils, adepts both, whom he bade hold themselves ever ready to
 pleasure those gentlemen who had done him honour. <milestone id="p08090018" />And very
 handsomely they did serve the said gentlemen in certain of their love
 affairs and other little matters; and finding the city and the manners
 of the citizens agreeable to them, they made up their minds to stay
 here always, and grew friendly and very intimate with some of the
 citizens, making no distinction between gentle and simple, rich or
 poor, so only they were such as were conformable to their ways.
 <milestone id="p08090019" />And to gratify these their friends they formed a company of perhaps
 twenty-five men, to meet together at least twice a month in a place
 appointed by them; where, when they are met, each utters his
 desire, and forthwith that same night they accomplish it. Now
 Buffalmacco and I, being extraordinarily great and close friends with
 <pb n="238" />these two adepts, were by them enrolled in this company, and are
 still members of it. <milestone id="p08090020" />And I assure you that, as often as we are
 assembled together, the adornments of the saloon in which we eat
 are a marvel to see, ay, and the tables laid as for kings, and the
 multitudes of stately and handsome servants, as well women as men,
 at the beck and call of every member of the company, and the basins,
 and the ewers, the flasks and the cups, and all else that is there for
 our service in eating and drinking, of nought but gold and silver, and
 therewithal the abundance and variety of the viands, suited to the
 taste of each, that are set before us, each in due course, these too be
 marvels. <milestone id="p08090021" />'Twere vain for me to seek to describe to you the sweet
 concord that is there of innumerable instruments of music, and the
 tuneful songs that salute our ears; nor might I hope to tell you how
 much wax is burned at these banquets, or compute the quantity of the
 comfits that are eaten, or the value of the wines that are drunk.
 <milestone id="p08090022" />Nor, my pumpkin o' wit, would I have you suppose that, when we
 are there, we wear our common clothes, such as you now see me
 wear; nay, there is none there so humble but he shews as an
 emperor, so sumptuous are our garments, so splendid our trappings.
 <milestone id="p08090023" />But among all the delights of the place none may compare with the
 fair ladies, who, so one do but wish, are brought thither from every
 part of the world. Why, you might see there My Lady of the
 Barbanichs, the Queen of the Basques, the Consort of the Soldan,
 the Empress of Osbech, the Ciancianfera of Nornieca, the Semistante
 of Berlinzone, and the Scalpedra of Narsia. <milestone id="p08090024" />But why seek to enumerate
 them all? They include all the queens in the world, ay, even to
 the Schinchimurra of Prester John, who has the horns sprouting out
 of her nether end: so there's for you. Now when these ladies have
 done with the wine and the comfits, they tread a measure or two,
 each with the man at whose behest she is come, and then all go with
 their gallants to their chambers. <milestone id="p08090025" />And know that each of these
 chambers shews as a very Paradise, so fair is it, ay, and no less
 fragrant than the cases of aromatics in your shop when you are
 pounding the cumin: and therein are beds that you would find more
 goodly than that of the Doge of Venice, and 'tis in them we take
 our rest; <milestone id="p08090026" />and how busily they ply the treadle, and how lustily they
 tug at the frame to make the stuff close and compact, I leave you to
 imagine. <milestone id="p08090027" />However, among the luckiest of all I reckon Buffalmacco
 <pb n="239" />and myself; for that Buffalmacco for the most part fetches him the
 Queen of France, and I do the like with the Queen of England, who
 are just the finest women in the world, and we have known how to
 carry it with them so that we are the very eyes of their heads. 
<milestone id="p08090028" />So
 I leave it to your own judgment to determine whether we have not
 good cause to live and bear ourselves with a lighter heart than others,
 seeing that we are beloved of two such great queens, to say nothing
 of the thousand or two thousand florins that we have of them whenever
 we are so minded. <milestone id="p08090029" />Now this in the vulgar we call going the
 course, because, as the corsairs prey upon all the world, so do we;
 albeit with this difference, that, whereas they never restore their spoil,
 we do so as soon as we have done with it. <milestone id="p08090030" />So now, my worthy
 Master, you understand what we mean by going the course; but
 how close it behoves you to keep such a secret, you may see for
 yourself; so I spare you any further exhortations.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08090031" />The Master, whose skill did not reach, perhaps, beyond the treatment
 of children for the scurf, took all that Bruno said for gospel,
 and burned with so vehement a desire to be admitted into this company,
 that he could not have longed for the summum bonum itself
 with more ardour. <milestone id="p08090032" />So, after telling Bruno that indeed 'twas no
 wonder they bore them lightheartedly, he could scarce refrain from
 asking him there and then to have him enrolled, albeit he deemed it
 more prudent to defer his suit, until by lavishing honour upon him
 he had gained a right to urge it with more confidence. <milestone id="p08090033" />He therefore
 made more and more of him, had him to breakfast and sup with
 him, and treated him with extraordinary respect. In short, such and
 so constant was their intercourse that it seemed as though the Master
 wist not how to live without Bruno. <milestone id="p08090034" />As it went so well with him,
 Bruno, to mark his sense of the honour done him by the doctor,
 painted in his saloon a picture symbolical of Lent, and an Agnus
 Dei at the entrance of his chamber, and an alembic over his front
 door, that those who would fain consult him might know him from
 other physicians, besides a battle of rats and mice in his little gallery,
 which the doctor thought an extremely fine piece. <milestone id="p08090035" />And from time
 to time, when he had not supped with the Master, he would say to
 him: <q direct="unspecified">Last night I was with the company, and being a little tired
 of the Queen of England, I fetched me the Gumedra of the great
	Can of Tarisi.</q> <milestone id="p08090036" /><q direct="unspecified">Gumedra,</q> quoth the Master; <q direct="unspecified">what is she?
 <pb n="240" />I know not the meaning of these words.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090037" /><q direct="unspecified">Thereat, Master,</q>
 replied Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">I marvel not; for I have heard tell that neither
 Porcograsso nor Vannacena say aught thereof.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090038" /><q direct="unspecified">Thou wouldst say
 Ippocrasso and Avicenna,</q> returned the Master. 
<milestone id="p08090039" /><q direct="unspecified">I'faith I know
 not,</q> quoth Bruno. <q direct="unspecified">I as ill know the meaning of your words as
 you of mine. But Gumedra in the speech of the great Can signifies
 the same as Empress in ours. Ah! a fine woman you would find
 her, and plenty of her! I warrant she would make you forget your
 drugs and prescriptions and plasters.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090040" />And so, Bruno from time to
 time whetting the Master's appetite, and the Master at length thinking
 that by his honourable entreatment of him he had fairly made a
 conquest of Bruno, it befell that one evening, while he held the light
 for Bruno, who was at work on the battle of rats and mice, he
 determined to discover to him his desire; <milestone id="p08090041" />and as they were alone,
 thus he spoke: <q direct="unspecified">God knows, Bruno, that there lives not the man,
 for whom I would do as much as for thee: why, if thou wast to bid
 me go all the way from here to Peretola,<note>About four miles from
 Florence.</note> I almost think I would do
 so; wherefore I trust thou wilt not deem it strange if I talk to thee
 as an intimate friend and in confidence. <milestone id="p08090042" />Thou knowest 'tis not long
 since thou didst enlarge with me on thy gay company and their
 doings, which has engendered in me such a desire as never was to
 know more thereof. <milestone id="p08090043" />Nor without reason, as thou wilt discover,
 should I ever become a member of the said company, for I straightway
 give thee leave to make game of me, should I not then fetch
 me the fairest maid thou hast seen this many a day, whom I saw
 last year at Cacavincigli, and to whom I am entirely devoted; and by
 the body of Christ I offered her ten Bolognese groats, that she should
 pleasure me, and she would not. <milestone id="p08090044" />Wherefore I do most earnestly
 entreat thee to instruct me what I must do to fit myself for membership
 in the company; and never doubt that in me you will have a true
 and loyal comrade, and one that will do you honour. <milestone id="p08090045" />And above all
 thou seest how goodly I am of my person, and how well furnished
 with legs, and of face as fresh as a rose; and therewithal I am a
 doctor of medicine, and I scarce think you have any such among
 you; and not a little excellent lore I have, and many a good song by
 heart, of which I will sing thee one;</q> and forthwith he fell a
 singing.</p><pb n="241" /><p><milestone id="p08090046" />Bruno had such a mind to laugh, that he could scarce contain
 himself; but still he kept a grave countenance; and, when the
 Master had ended his song, and said: <q direct="unspecified">How likes it thee?</q> 
<milestone id="p08090047" />he answered: <q direct="unspecified">Verily, no lyre of straw could vie with you, so
 artargutically<note>In the Italian <q direct="unspecified">artagoticamente,</q> a word of
 Boccaccio's own minting.</note> you refine your strain.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090048" /><q direct="unspecified">I warrant
 thee,</q> returned the
 Master, <q direct="unspecified">thou hadst never believed it, hadst thou not heard me.</q>
      <milestone id="p08090049" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, indeed, sooth sayst thou,</q> quoth Bruno. 
      <milestone id="p08090050" /><q direct="unspecified">And I have other
 songs to boot,</q> said the Master; <q direct="unspecified">but enough of this at present. Thou
 must know that I, such as thou seest me, am a gentleman's son, albeit
 my father lived in the contado; and on my mother's side I come of
 the Vallecchio family. And as thou mayst have observed I have
 quite the finest library and wardrobe of all the physicians in Florence.
 <milestone id="p08090051" />God's faith! I have a robe that cost, all told, close upon a hundred
 pounds in bagattines<note>A Venetian coin of extremely low value, being
 reckoned as 1/4 of the Florentine quattrino.</note> more than ten years ago.
 Wherefore I make
 most instant suit to thee that thou get me enrolled, which if thou do,
 God's faith! be thou never so ill, thou shalt pay me not a stiver for
 my tendance of thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090052" />Whereupon Bruno, repeating to himself, as
 he had done many a time before, that the doctor was a very numskull:
 <q direct="unspecified">Master,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">shew a little more light here, and
 have patience until I have put the finishing touches to the tails of these
 rats, and then I will answer you.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090053" />So he finished the tails,
 and then, putting on an air as if he were not a little embarrassed by
 the request: <q direct="unspecified">Master mine,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I should have great
 things to expect from you; that I know: but yet what you ask of
 me, albeit to your great mind it seems but a little thing, is a weighty
 matter indeed for me; nor know I a soul in the world, to whom,
 though well able, I would grant such a request, save to you alone:
 and this I say not for friendship's sake alone, albeit I love you as I
 ought, but for that your discourse is so fraught with wisdom, that 'tis
 enough to make a beguine start out of her boots, much more, then, to
 incline me to change my purpose; and the more I have of your
 company, the wiser I repute you. <milestone id="p08090054" />Whereto I may add, that, if for
 no other cause, I should still be well disposed towards you for the
 love I see you bear to that fair piece of flesh of which you spoke but
 now. <milestone id="p08090055" />But this I must tell you: 'tis not in my power to do as you
 <pb n="242" />would have me in this matter; but, though I cannot myself do the
 needful in your behalf, if you will pledge your faith, whole and solid
 as may be, to keep my secret, I will shew you how to go about it
 for yourself, and I make no doubt that, having this fine library and
 the other matters you spoke of a while ago, you will compass your
 end.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090056" />Quoth then the Master: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but speak freely; I see
 thou dost yet scarce know me, and how well I can keep a secret.
 There were few things that Messer Guasparruolo da Saliceto did,
 when he was Podest&#224; of Forlinpopoli, that he did not confide to me,
 so safe he knew they would be in my keeping: and wouldst thou
 be satisfied that I say sooth? I assure you I was the first man whom
 he told that he was about to marry Bergamina: so there's for thee.</q>
 <milestone id="p08090057" /><q direct="unspecified">Well and good,</q> said Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">if such as he confided in you, well
 indeed may I do the like. Know, then, that you will have to proceed
 on this wise: Our company is governed by a captain and a
 council of two, who are changed every six months: and on the
 calends without fail Buffalmacco will be captain, and I councillor:
 'tis so fixed: and the captain has not a little power to promote the
 admission and enrolment of whomsoever he will: wherefore, methinks,
 you would do well to make friends with Buffalmacco and
 honourably entreat him: <milestone id="p08090058" />he is one that, marking your great wisdom,
 will take a mighty liking to you forthwith; and when you have just
 a little dazzled him with your wisdom and these fine things of yours,
 you may make your request to him; and he will not know how to
 say no--I have already talked with him of you, and he is as well
 disposed to you as may be--and having so done you will leave the
 rest to me.</q> <milestone id="p08090059" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Thy words are to me for an exceeding
 great joy,</q> quoth the Master: <q direct="unspecified">and if he be one that loves to
 converse with sages, he has but to exchange a word or two with
 me, and I will answer for it that he will be ever coming to see me;
 for so fraught with wisdom am I, that I could furnish a whole city
 therewith, and still remain a great sage.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08090060" />Having thus set matters in train, Bruno related the whole affair,
 point by point, to Buffalmacco, to whom it seemed a thousand years
 till he should be able to give Master Noodle that of which he was in
 quest. <milestone id="p08090061" />The doctor, now all agog to go the course, lost no time, and
 found no difficulty, in making friends with Buffalmacco, and fell to
 entertaining him, and Bruno likewise, at breakfast and supper in
 <pb n="243" />most magnificent style; while they fooled him to the top of his
 bent, for, being gentlemen that appreciated excellent wines and fat
 capons, besides other good cheer in plenty, they were inclined to be
 very neighbourly, and needed no second bidding, but, always letting
 him understand that there was none other whose company they
 relished so much, kept ever with him.</p><p><milestone id="p08090062" />However, in due time the Master asked of Buffalmacco that
 which he had before asked of Bruno. Whereat Buffalmacco feigned
 to be not a little agitated, and turning angrily to Bruno, made a
 great pother about his ears, saying: <q direct="unspecified">By the Most High God of
 Pasignano I vow I can scarce forbear to give thee that over the head
 that should make they nose fall about thy heels, traitor that thou art,
 for 'tis thou alone that canst have discovered these secrets to the
 Master.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090063" />Whereupon the Master interposed with no little vigour,
 averring with oaths that 'twas from another source that he had gotten
 his knowledge; and Buffalmacco at length allowed himself to be
 pacified by the sage's words. <milestone id="p08090064" />So turning to him: <q direct="unspecified">Master,</q> quoth
 he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis evident indeed that you have been at Bologna, and have
 come back hither with a mouth that blabs not, and that 'twas on no
 pippin, as many a dolt does, but on the good long pumpkin that you
 learned your A B C; and, if I mistake not, you were baptized on a
 Sunday;<note>I.e. without salt, that Florentine symbol of wit, not
 being so readily procurable on a holiday as on working-days.</note> 
	<milestone id="p08090065" />and
 though Bruno has told me that 'twas medicine you
studied there, 'tis my opinion that you there studied the art of
 catching men, of which, what with your wisdom and your startling
 revelations, you are the greatest master that ever I knew.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08090066" />He
 would have said more, but the doctor, turning to Bruno, broke in
 with: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! what it is to consort and converse with the wise!
 Who but this worthy man would thus have read my mind through
 and through? Less quick by far to rate me at my true worth wast
 thou. But what said I when thou toldst me that Buffalmacco
 delighted to converse with sages? Confess now; have I not kept
 my word?</q> 
<milestone id="p08090067" /><q direct="unspecified">Verily,</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">you have more than kept
 it.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090068" />Then, addressing Buffalmacco: <q direct="unspecified">Ah!</q> cried the Master,
 <q direct="unspecified">what hadst thou said, hadst thou seen me at Bologna, where there
 was none, great or small, doctor or scholar, but was devoted to me,
 so well wist I how to entertain them with my words of wisdom.
 <pb n="244" />
<milestone id="p08090069" />Nay more; let me tell thee that there was never a word I spoke but
 set every one a laughing, so great was the pleasure it gave them.
 And at my departure they all deplored it most bitterly, and would
 have had me remain, and by way of inducement went so far as to
 propose that I should be sole lecturer to all the students in medicine
 that were there; which offer I declined, for that I was minded to
 return hither, having vast estates here, that have ever belonged to
 my family; which, accordingly, I did.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090070" />Quoth then Bruno to
 Buffalmacco: <q direct="unspecified">How shews it, now, man? Thou didst not believe
 me when I told thee what he was. By the Gospels there is never a
 physician in this city that has the lore of ass's urine by heart as he
 has: verily, thou wouldst not find his like between here and the
 gates of Paris. Now see if thou canst help doing as he would have
 thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090071" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis even as Bruno says,</q> observed the doctor, <q direct="unspecified">but I am
 not understood here. You Florentines are somewhat slow of wit.
 Would you could see me in my proper element, among a company
 of doctors!</q> 
<milestone id="p08090072" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Of a truth, Master,</q> quoth Buffalmacco,
 <q direct="unspecified">your lore far exceeds any I should ever have imputed to
 you; wherefore, addressing you as 'tis meet to address a man of your
 wisdom, I give you disjointedly to understand that without fail I will
 procure your enrolment in our company.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08090073" />After this promise the honours lavished by the doctor upon the
 two men grew and multiplied; in return for which they diverted
 themselves by setting him a prancing upon every wildest chimera in
 the world; and promised, among other matters, to give him by way
 of mistress, the Countess of Civillari,<note>A public sink at
 Florence.</note>
 whom they averred to be the
 goodliest creature to be found in all the Netherlands of the human
 race; <milestone id="p08090074" />and the doctor asking who this Countess might be: <q direct="unspecified">Mature
 my gherkin,</q> quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">she is indeed a very great lady,
 and few houses are there in the world in which she has not some
 jurisdiction; nay, the very Friars Minors, to say nought of other
 folk, pay her tribute to the sound of the kettle-drum. 
<milestone id="p08090075" />And I may
 tell you that, when she goes abroad, she makes her presence very
 sensibly felt, albeit for the most part she keeps herself close: however,
 'tis no great while since she passed by your door one night on
 her way to the Arno to bathe her feet and get a breath of air; but
 <pb n="245" />most of her time she abides at Laterina.<note>In the contado of
 Arezzo:
 the &#233;quivoque is tolerably obvious.</note> 
<milestone id="p08090076" />Serjeants has she
 not
 a
 few that go their rounds at short intervals, bearing, one and all, the
 rod and the bucket in token of her sovereignty, and barons in plenty
 in all parts, as Tamagnino della Porta,<note>Slang for an ill-kept
 jakes.</note> Don Meta,<note>Also slang: signifying a pyramidal pile of
 ordure.</note> Manico di Scopa,<note>Broom-handle.</note>
 Squacchera,<note>The meaning of this term may perhaps be divined from the
 sound.</note> and others, with whom I doubt not you are intimately
 acquainted, though you may not just now bear them in mind. 
<milestone id="p08090077" />Such,
 then, is the great lady, in whose soft arms we, if we delude not ourselves,
 will certainly place you, in which case you may well dispense
 with her of Cacavincigli.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08090078" />The doctor, who had been born and bred at Bologna, and understood
 not their words, found the lady quite to his mind; and shortly
 afterwards the painters brought him tidings of his election into the
 company. <milestone id="p08090079" />Then came the day of the nocturnal gathering, and the
 doctor had the two men to breakfast; and when they had breakfasted,
 he asked them after what manner he was to join the company.
 <milestone id="p08090080" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now, Master,</q> quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">you have
 need of a stout heart; otherwise you may meet with some let, to
 our most grievous hurt; and for what cause you have need of this
 stout heart, you shall hear. <milestone id="p08090081" />You must contrive to be to-night about
 the hour of first sleep on one of the raised tombs that have been
 lately placed outside of Santa Maria Novella; and mind that you
 wear one of your best gowns, that your first appearance may impress
 the company with a proper sense of your dignity, and also because,
 as we are informed, for we were not present at the time, the
 Countess, by reason that you are a gentleman, is minded to make you
 a Knight of the Bath at her own charges. <milestone id="p08090082" />So you will wait there,
 until one, whom we shall send, come for you: who, that you may
 know exactly what you have to expect, will be a beast black and
 horned, of no great size; and he will go snorting and bounding
 amain about the piazza in front of you, with intent to terrify you;
 but, when he perceives that you are not afraid, he will draw nigh you
 quietly, and when he is close by you, then get you down from the
 <pb n="246" />tomb, fearing nothing; and, minding you neither of God nor of the
 saints, mount him, and when you are well set on his back, then fold
 your arms upon your breast, as in submission, and touch him no
 more. <milestone id="p08090083" />Then, going gently, he will bear you to us; but once mind
 you of God, or the saints, or give way to fear, and I warn you, he
 might give you a fall, or dash you against something that you would
 find scarce pleasant; wherefore, if your heart misgives you, you were
 best not to come, for you would assuredly do yourself a mischief, and
 us no good at all.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090084" />Quoth then the doctor: <q direct="unspecified">You know me not
 as yet; 'tis perchance because I wear the gloves and the long robe
 that you misdoubt me. Ah! did you but know what feats I have
 done in times past at Bologna, when I used to go after the women
 with my comrades, you would be lost in amazement. 
<milestone id="p08090085" />God's faith!
 on one of those nights there was one of them, a poor sickly creature
 she was too, and stood not a cubit in height, who would not come
 with us; so first I treated her to many a good cuff, and then I took
 her up by main force, and carried her well-nigh as far as a cross-bow
 will send a bolt, <milestone id="p08090086" />and so caused her, willy-nilly, come with us. And
 on another occasion I mind me that, having none other with me but
 my servant, a little after the hour of Ave Maria, I passed beside the
 cemetery of the Friars Minors, and, though that very day a woman
 had been there interred, I had no fear at all. So on this score you
 may make your minds easy; for indeed I am a man of exceeding
 great courage and prowess. <milestone id="p08090087" />And to appear before you with due
 dignity, I will don my scarlet gown, in which I took my doctor's
 degree, and it remains to be seen if the company will not give me a
 hearty welcome, and make me captain out of hand. <milestone id="p08090088" />Let me once
 be there, and you will see how things will go; else how is it that
 this countess, that has not yet seen me, is already so enamoured of
 me that she is minded to make me a Knight of the Bath? And
 whether I shall find knighthood agreeable, or know how to support
 the dignity well or ill, leave that to me.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090089" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Well
 said, excellent well said,</q> quoth Buffalmacco: <q direct="unspecified">but look to it you
 disappoint us not, either by not coming or by not being found, when
 we send for you; and this I say, because 'tis cold weather, and you
 medical gentlemen take great care of your health.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090090" /><q direct="unspecified">God forbid,</q>
 replied the doctor, <q direct="unspecified">I am none of your chilly folk; I fear not the
 cold: 'tis seldom indeed, when I leave my bed a nights, to answer
 <pb n="247" />the call of nature, as one must at times, that I do more than throw
 a pelisse over my doublet; so rest assured that I shall be there.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08090091" />So they parted; and towards nightfall the Master found a pretext
 for leaving his wife, and privily got out his fine gown, which in due
 time he donned, and so hied him to the tombs, and having perched
 himself on one of them, huddled himself together, for 'twas mighty
 cold, to await the coming of the beast. <milestone id="p08090092" />Meanwhile Buffalmacco,
 who was a tall man and strong, provided himself with one of those
 dominos that were wont to be worn in certain revels which are now
 gone out of fashion; and enveloped in a black pelisse turned inside
 out, shewed like a bear, save that the domino had the face of a devil,
 and was furnished with horns: <milestone id="p08090093" />in which guise, Bruno following
 close behind to see the sport, he hied him to the piazza of Santa
 Maria Novella. And no sooner wist he that the Master was on
 the tomb, than he fell a careering in a most wild and furious manner
 to and fro the piazza, and snorting and bellowing and gibbering like
 one demented, <milestone id="p08090094" />insomuch that, as soon as the Master was ware of him,
 each several hair on his head stood on end, and he fell a trembling
 in every limb, being in sooth more timid than a woman, and wished
 himself safe at home: but as there he was, he strove might and
 main to keep his spirits up, so overmastering was his desire to see the
 marvels of which Bruno and Buffalmacco had told him. <milestone id="p08090095" />However,
 after a while Buffalmacco allowed his fury to abate, and came quietly
 up to the tomb on which the Master was, and stood still. The
 Master, still all of a tremble with fear, could not at first make up his
 mind, whether to get on the beast's back, or no; <milestone id="p08090096" />but at length,
 doubting it might be the worse for him if he did not mount the
 beast, he overcame the one dread by the aid of the other, got down
 from the tomb, saying under his breath: <q direct="unspecified">God help me!</q> and
 seated himself very comfortably on the beast's back; and then, still
 quaking in every limb, he folded his arms as he had been bidden.</p><p><milestone id="p08090097" />Buffalmacco now started, going on all-fours, at a very slow pace,
 in the direction of Santa Maria della Scala, and so brought the
 Master within a short distance of the Convent of the Ladies of Ripoli.
 <milestone id="p08090098" />Now, in that quarter there were divers trenches, into which the
 husbandmen of those parts were wont to discharge the Countess of
 Civillari, that she might afterwards serve them to manure their land.
 <milestone id="p08090099" />Of one of which trenches, as he came by, Buffalmacco skirted the
 <pb n="248" />edge, and seizing his opportunity, raised a hand, and caught the
 doctor by one of his feet, and threw him off his back and head-foremost
 right into the trench, and then, making a terrific noise and
 frantic gestures as before, went bounding off by Santa Maria della
 Scala towards the field of Ognissanti, where he found Bruno, who
 had betaken him thither that he might laugh at his ease; and there
 the two men in high glee took their stand to observe from a distance
 how the bemired doctor would behave. <milestone id="p08090100" />Finding himself in so loathsome
 a place, the Master struggled might and main to raise himself
 and get out; and though again and again he slipped back, and
 swallowed some drams of the ordure, yet, bemired from head to foot,
 woebegone and crestfallen, he did at last get out, leaving his hood
 behind him. Then, removing as much of the filth as he might with
 his hands, knowing not what else to do, he got him home, where,
 by dint of much knocking, he at last gained admittance; <milestone id="p08090101" />and scarce
 was the door closed behind the malodorous Master, when Bruno and
 Buffalmacco were at it, all agog to hear after what manner he would
 be received by his wife. They were rewarded by hearing her give
 him the soundest rating that ever bad husband got. 
<milestone id="p08090102" /><q direct="unspecified">Ah!</q> quoth
 she, <q direct="unspecified">fine doings, these! Thou hast been with some other woman,
 and wast minded to make a brave shew in thy scarlet gown. So I
 was not enough for thee! not enough for thee forsooth, I that might
 content a crowd! Would they had choked thee with the filth in
 which they have soused thee; 'twas thy fit resting-place. Now, to
 think that a physician of repute, and a married man, should go by
 night after strange women!</q> 
<milestone id="p08090103" />Thus, and with much more to the
 like effect, while the doctor was busy washing himself, she ceased
 not to torment him until midnight.</p><p><milestone id="p08090104" />On the morrow, Bruno and Buffalmacco, having painted their
 bodies all over with livid patches to give them the appearance of
 having been thrashed, came to the doctor's house, and finding that
 he was already risen, went in, being saluted on all hands by a foul
 smell, for time had not yet served thoroughly to cleanse the house.
 <milestone id="p08090105" />The doctor, being informed that they were come to see him,
 advanced to meet them, and bade them good morning. Whereto
 Bruno and Buffalmacco, having prepared their answer, replied:
 
<milestone id="p08090106" /><q direct="unspecified">No good morning shall you have from us: rather we pray God to
 give you bad years enough to make an end of you, seeing that there
 <pb n="249" />lives no more arrant and faithless traitor. 'Tis no fault of yours, if
 we, that did our best to honour and pleasure you, have not come by
 a dog's death; 
<milestone id="p08090107" />your faithlessness has cost us to-night as many sound
 blows as would more than suffice to keep an ass a trotting all the
 way from here to Rome; besides which, we have been in peril of
 expulsion from the company in which we arranged for your enrolment.
 <milestone id="p08090108" />If you doubt our words, look but at our bodies, what a state
 they are in.</q> And so, baring their breasts they gave him a glimpse
 of the patches they had painted there, and forthwith covered them
 up again. <milestone id="p08090109" />The doctor would have made them his excuses, and
 recounted his misfortunes, and how he had been thrown into the
 trench. But Buffalmacco broke in with: <q direct="unspecified">Would he had thrown
 you from the bridge into the Arno! Why must you needs mind
 you of God and the saints? Did we not forewarn you?</q> 
<milestone id="p08090110" /><q direct="unspecified">God's
 faith,</q> returned the doctor, <q direct="unspecified">that did I not.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08090111" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> quoth
 Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">you did not? You do so above a little; for he that
 we sent for you told us that you trembled like an aspen, and knew not
 where you were. You have played us a sorry trick; but never
 another shall do so; and as for you, we will give you such requital
 thereof as you deserve.</q> 
<milestone id="p08090112" />The doctor now began to crave their
 pardon, and to implore them for God's sake not to expose him to
 shame, and used all the eloquence at his command to make his peace
 with them. And if he had honourably entreated them before, he
 thenceforth, for fear they should publish his disgrace, did so much
 more abundantly, and courted them both by entertaining them at his
 table and in other ways. And so you have heard how wisdom is
 imparted to those that get it not at Bologna.</p></div2>