<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0109"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p01090001" />The censure of a Gascon lady converts the King of
	Cyprus from a churlish to an honourable temper.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01090002" />Except Elisa none now remained to answer the call of the
      queen, and she without waiting for it, with gladsome alacrity thus
      began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01090003" />Bethink you, damsels, how often it has happened that men who
      have been obdurate to censures and chastisements have been reclaimed
      by some unpremeditated casual word. This is plainly manifest
      by the story told by Lauretta; and by mine, which will be of the
      briefest, I mean further to illustrate it; seeing that, good stories,
      being always pleasurable, are worth listening to with attention, no
      matter by whom they may be told.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p01090004" />'Twas, then, in the time of the first king of Cyprus, after the
      conquest made of the Holy Land by Godfrey de Bouillon, that a
      lady of Gascony made a pilgrimage to the Holy Sepulchre, and on
      her way home, having landed at Cyprus, met with brutal outrage
      at the hands of certain ruffians. <milestone id="p01090005" />Broken-hearted and disconsolate
      she determined to make her complaint to the king; but she was told
      that it would be all in vain, because so spiritless and
      fain&#232;ant
      was he that he not only neglected to avenge affronts put upon others, but
      endured with a reprehensible tameness those which were offered
      to himself, insomuch that whoso had any ill-humour to vent, took
      occasion to vex or mortify him. <milestone id="p01090006" />The lady, hearing this report,
      despaired of redress, and by way of alleviation of her grief determined
      to make the king sensible of his baseness. So in tears she presented
      herself before him and said: <q direct="unspecified">Sire, it is not to seek redress of the
	wrong done me that I come here before you: but only that, so please
	you, I may learn of you how it is that you suffer patiently the wrongs
	<pb n="60" />which, as I understand, are done you; that thus schooled by you in
	patience I may endure my own, which, God knows, I would gladly,
	were it possible, transfer to you, seeing that you are so well fitted to
	bear them.</q> <milestone id="p01090007" />These words aroused the hitherto sluggish and apathetic
      king as it were from sleep. He redressed the lady's wrong, and having
      thus made a beginning, thenceforth meted out the most rigorous
      justice to all that in any wise offended against the majesty of his
      crown.</p></div2>