<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov1006"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00060001" />King Charles the Old, being conqueror, falls in love with
 a young maiden, and afterward growing ashamed of
 his folly bestows her and her sister honourably in
 marriage.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00060002" />Who might fully recount with what diversity of argument the
 ladies debated which of the three, Giliberto, or Messer Ansaldo, or
 the necromancer, behaved with the most liberality in the affair of
 Madonna Dianora? Too long were it to tell. However, when the
 king had allowed them to dispute a while, he, with a glance at
 Fiammetta, bade her rescue them from their wrangling by telling her
 story. Fiammetta made no demur, but thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00060003" />Illustrious my
 ladies, I have ever been of opinion that in companies like ours one
 should speak so explicitly that the import of what is said should
 never by excessive circumscription afford matter for disputation;
 which is much more in place among students in the schools, than
 among us, whose powers are scarce adequate to the management of
 the distaff and the spindle.  <milestone id="p00060004" />Wherefore I, that had in mind a matter
 of, perchance, some nicety, now that I see you all at variance
 touching the matters last mooted, am minded to lay it aside, and
 tell you somewhat else, which concerns a man by no means of slight
 account, but a valiant king, being a chivalrous action that he did,
 albeit in no wise thereto actuated by his honour.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00060005" />There is none of you but may not seldom have heard tell of King
 Charles the Old, or the First, by whose magnificent emprise, and the
 ensuing victory gained over King Manfred, the Ghibellines were driven
 forth of Florence, and the Guelfs returned thither. For which cause a
 knight, Messer Neri degli Uberti by name, departing Florence with
 <pb n="341" />his household and not a little money, resolved to fix his abode under
 no
 other sway than that of King Charles.  <milestone id="p00060006" />And being fain of a lonely
 place in which to end his days in peace, he betook him to Castello
 da Mare di Stabia; and there, perchance a cross-bow-shot from the
 other houses of the place, amid the olives and hazels and chestnuts
 that abound in those parts, he bought an estate, on which he built a
 goodly house and commodious, with a pleasant garden beside it, in the
 midst of which, having no lack of running water, he set, after our
 Florentine fashion, a pond fair and clear, and speedily filled it with
 fish.  <milestone id="p00060007" />And while thus he lived, daily occupying himself with nought
 else but how to make his garden more fair, it befell that King
 Charles in the hot season betook him to Castello da Mare to refresh
 himself a while, and hearing of the beauty of Messer Neri's garden,
 was desirous to view it. And having learned to whom it belonged,
 he bethought him that, as the knight was an adherent of the party
 opposed to him, he would use more familiarity towards him than he
 would otherwise have done; and so he sent him word that he and
 four comrades would sup privily with him in his garden on the
 ensuing evening.  <milestone id="p00060008" />Messer Neri felt himself much honoured; and
 having made his preparations with magnificence, and arranged the
 order of the ceremonies with his household, did all he could and
 knew to make the King cordially welcome to his fair garden.</p><p><milestone id="p00060009" />When the King had viewed the garden throughout, as also Messer
 Neri's house, and commended them, he washed, and seated himself at
 one of the tables, which were set beside the pond, and bade Count
 Guy de Montfort, who was one of his companions, sit on one side
 of him, and Messer Neri on the other, and the other three to
 serve, as they should be directed by Messer Neri.  <milestone id="p00060010" />The dishes that
 were set before them were dainty, the wines excellent and rare, the
 order of the repast very fair and commendable, without the least
 noise or aught else that might distress; whereon the King bestowed
 no stinted praise.  <milestone id="p00060011" />As thus he gaily supped, well-pleased with the
 lovely spot, there came into the garden two young maidens, each
 perhaps fifteen years old, blonde both, their golden tresses falling all
 in ringlets about them, and crowned with a dainty garland of
 periwinkle-flowers; and so delicate and fair of face were they that
 they shewed liker to angels than aught else, each clad in a robe of
 finest linen, white as snow upon their flesh, close-fitting as might be
 <pb n="342" />from the waist up, but below the waist ample, like a pavilion to the
 feet.  <milestone id="p00060012" />She that was foremost bore on her shoulders a pair of nets,
 which she held with her left hand, carrying in her right a long pole.
 Her companion followed, bearing on her left shoulder a frying-pan,
 under her left arm a bundle of faggots, and in her left hand a tripod,
 while in the other hand she carried a cruse of oil and a lighted taper.
 At sight of whom the King marvelled, and gazed intent to learn
 what it might import.  <milestone id="p00060013" />The two young maidens came forward with
 becoming modesty, and did obeisance to the King; which done they
 hied them to the place of ingress to the pond, and she that had the
 frying-pan, having set it down, and afterward the other things, took
 the pole that the other carried, and so they both went down into the
 pond, being covered by its waters to their breasts.  <milestone id="p00060014" />Whereupon one
 of Messer Neri's servants, having forthwith lit a fire, and set the tripod
 on the faggots and oil therein, addressed himself to wait, until some
 fish should be thrown to him by the girls.  <milestone id="p00060015" />Who, the one searching
 with the pole in those parts where she knew the fish lay hid, while
 the other made ready the nets, did in a brief space of time, to the
 exceeding great delight of the King, who watched them attentively,
 catch fish not a few, which they tossed to the servant, who set them,
 before the life was well out of them, in the frying-pan. After
 which, the maidens, as pre-arranged, addressed them to catch some
 of the finest fish, and cast them on to the table before the King, and
 Count Guy, and their father.  <milestone id="p00060016" />The fish wriggled about the table to
 the prodigious delight of the King, who in like manner took some
 of them, and courteously returned them to the girls; with which
 sport they diverted them, until the servant had cooked the fish that
 had been given him: which, by Messer Neri's command, were set
 before the King rather as a side-dish than as aught very rare or
 delicious.</p><p><milestone id="p00060017" />When the girls saw that all the fish were cooked, and that there
 was no occasion for them to catch any more, they came forth of the
 pond, their fine white garments cleaving everywhere close to their
 flesh so as to hide scarce any part of their delicate persons, took up
 again the things that they had brought, and passing modestly before
 the King, returned to the house.  <milestone id="p00060018" />The King, and the Count, and
 the other gentlemen that waited, had regarded the maidens with no
 little attention, and had, one and all, inly bestowed on them no little
 <pb n="343" />praise, as being fair and shapely, and therewithal sweet and debonair;
 but 'twas in the King's eyes that they especially found favour.
 Indeed, as they came forth of the water, the King had scanned each
 part of their bodies so intently that, had one then pricked him, he
 would not have felt it,  <milestone id="p00060019" />and his thoughts afterwards dwelling upon
 them, though he knew not who they were, nor how they came to
 be there, he felt stir within his heart a most ardent desire to pleasure
 them, whereby he knew very well that, if he took not care, he
 would grow enamoured; howbeit he knew not whether of the
 twain pleased him the more, so like was each to the other.  <milestone id="p00060020" />Having
 thus brooded a while, he turned to Messer Neri, and asked who the
 two damsels were. Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Sire,</q> replied Messer Neri, <q direct="unspecified">they
 are my twin daughters, and they are called, the one, Ginevra the Fair,
 and the other, Isotta the Blonde.</q> Whereupon the King was loud
 in praise of them, and exhorted Messer Neri to bestow them in
 marriage. To which Messer Neri demurred, for that he no longer
 had the means.  <milestone id="p00060021" />And nought of the supper now remaining to serve,
 save the fruit, in came the two young damsels in gowns of taffeta
 very fine, bearing in their hands two vast silver salvers full of divers
 fruits, such as the season yielded, and set them on the table before
 the King.  <milestone id="p00060022" />Which done, they withdrew a little space and fell a
 singing to music a ditty, of which the opening words were as
 follows:</p><p> <q type="song" direct="unspecified"><l>Love, many words would not suffice</l>
<l>There where I am come to tell.</l></q></p><p>And so dulcet and delightsome was the strain that to the King,
 his eyes and ears alike charmed, it seemed as if all the nine orders
 of angels were descended there to sing. The song ended, they
 knelt and respectfully craved the King's leave to depart; which,
 though sorely against his will, he gave them with a forced gaiety.</p><p><milestone id="p00060023" />Supper ended, the King and his companions, having remounted
 their horses, took leave of Messer Neri, and conversing of divers
 matters, returned to the royal quarters;  <milestone id="p00060024" />where the King, still harbouring
 his secret passion, nor, despite affairs of state that supervened,
 being able to forget the beauty and sweetness of Ginevra the Fair,
 for whose sake he likewise loved her twin sister, was so limed by
 Love that he could scarce think of aught else. So, feigning other
 <pb n="344" />reasons, he consorted familiarly with Messer Neri, and did much
 frequent his garden, that he might see Ginevra.  <milestone id="p00060025" />And at length,
 being unable to endure his suffering any longer, and being minded,
 for that he could devise no other expedient, to despoil their father not
 only of the one but of the other damsel also, he discovered both his
 love and his project to Count Guy;  <milestone id="p00060026" />who, being a good man and true,
 thus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Sire, your tale causes me not a little astonishment,
 and that more especially because of your conversation from
 your childhood to this very day, I have, methinks, known more than
 any other man.  <milestone id="p00060027" />And as no such passion did I ever mark in you,
 even in your youth, when Love should more readily have fixed you
 with his fangs, as now I discern, when you are already on the
 verge of old age, 'tis to me so strange, so surprising that you
 should veritably love, that I deem it little short of a miracle.  <milestone id="p00060028" />And
 were it meet for me to reprove you, well wot I the language I should
 hold to you, considering that you are yet in arms in a realm but
 lately won, among a people as yet unknown to you, and wily and
 treacherous in the extreme, and that the gravest anxieties and
 matters of high policy engross your mind, so that you are not
 as yet able to sit you down, and nevertheless amid all these weighty
 concerns you have given harbourage to false, flattering Love.  <milestone id="p00060029" />This
 is not the wisdom of a great king, but the folly of a feather-pated
 boy. And moreover, what is far worse, you say that you are
 resolved to despoil this poor knight of his two daughters, whom,
 entertaining you in his house, and honouring you to the best of his
 power, he brought into your presence all but naked, testifying
 thereby, how great is his faith in you, and how assured he is that
 you are a king, and not a devouring wolf.  <milestone id="p00060030" />Have you so soon forgotten
 that 'twas Manfred's outrageous usage of his subjects that
 opened you the way into this realm? What treachery was he ever
 guilty of that better merited eternal torment, than 'twould be in you
 to wrest from one that honourably entreats you at once his hope and
 his consolation? What would be said of you if so you should do?
  <milestone id="p00060031" />Perchance you deem that 'twould suffice to say: 'I did it because
 he is a Ghibelline.' Is it then consistent with the justice of a king
 that those, be they who they may, who seek his protection, as this
 man has sought yours, should be entreated after this sort?  <milestone id="p00060032" />King, I
 bid you remember that exceeding great as is your glory to have
 <pb n="345" />vanquished Manfred, yet to conquer oneself is a still greater glory:
 wherefore you, to whom belongs the correction of others, see to it
 that you conquer yourself, and refrain this unruly passion; and let
 not such a blot mar the splendour of your achievements.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00060033" />Sore stricken at heart by the Count's words, and the more
 mortified that he acknowledged their truth, the King heaved a
 fervent sigh or two, and then: <q direct="unspecified">Count,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that enemy
 there is none, however mighty, but to the practised warrior is weak
 enough and easy to conquer in comparison of his own appetite, I
 make no doubt; but, great though the struggle will be and immeasurable
 the force that it demands, so shrewdly galled am I by
 your words, that not many days will have gone by before I shall
 without fail have done enough to shew you that I, that am the
 conqueror of others, am no less able to gain the victory over myself.</q>
  <milestone id="p00060034" />And indeed but a few days thereafter, the King, on his return to
 Naples, being minded at once to leave himself no excuse for dishonourable
 conduct, and to recompense the knight for his honourable
 entreatment of him, did, albeit 'twas hard for him to endow
 another with that which he had most ardently desired for himself,
 none the less resolve to bestow the two damsels in marriage, and that
 not as Messer Neri's daughters, but as his own.  <milestone id="p00060035" />Wherefore, Messer
 Neri consenting, he provided both with magnificent dowries, and
 gave Ginevra the Fair to Messer Maffeo da Palizzi, and Isotta the
 Blonde to Messer Guglielmo della Magna, noble knights and great
 barons both; which done, sad at heart beyond measure, he betook
 him to Apulia, and by incessant travail did so mortify his vehement
 appetite that he snapped and broke in pieces the fetters of Love, and
 for the rest of his days was no more vexed by such passion.</p><p><milestone id="p00060036" />Perchance there will be those who say that 'tis but a trifle for
 a king to bestow two girls in marriage; nor shall I dispute it: but
 say we that a king in love bestowed in marriage her whom he loved,
 neither having taken nor taking, of his love, leaf or flower or fruit;
 then this I say was a feat great indeed, nay, as great as might be.</p><p>After such a sort then did this magnificent King, at once
 generously rewarding the noble knight, commendably honouring
 the damsels that he loved, and stoutly subduing himself.</p></div2>