<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0307"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03070001" />Tedaldo, being in disfavour with his lady, departs from
 Florence. He returns thither after a while in the
 guise of a pilgrim, has speech of his lady, and makes
 her sensible of her fault. Her husband, convicted
 of slaying him, he delivers from peril of death,
 reconciles him with his brothers, and thereafter
 discreetly enjoys his lady.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03070002" />So ceased Fiammetta; and, when all had bestowed on her their
	meed of praise, the queen--to lose no time--forthwith bade Emilia
	resume the narration. So thus Emilia began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03070003" />I am minded to return to our city, whence my two last predecessors
	saw fit to depart, and to shew you how one of our citizens
	recovered the lady he had lost.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p03070004" />Know then that there was in
      Florence a young noble, his name Tedaldo Elisei, who being beyond
      measure enamoured of a lady hight Monna Ermellina, wife of one
      Aldobrandino Palermini, and by reason of his admirable qualities
      richly deserving to have his desire, <milestone id="p03070005" />found Fortune nevertheless adverse,
      as she is wont to be to the prosperous. Inasmuch as, for some reason
      or another, the lady, having shewn herself gracious towards Tedaldo
      for a while, completely altered her mien, and not only shewed him no
      further favour, but would not so much as receive a message from him
      or suffer him to see her face; whereby he fell a prey to a grievous
      and distressful melancholy; but so well had he concealed his love
      that the cause of his melancholy was surmised by none. <milestone id="p03070006" />He tried
      hard in divers ways to recover the love which he deemed himself to
      have lost for no fault of his, and finding all his efforts unavailing, he
      <pb n="218" />resolved to bid the world adieu, that he might not afford her
      who was the cause of his distress the satisfaction of seeing him
      languish. So he got together as much money as he might, and
      secretly, no word said to friend or kinsman except only a familiar
      gossip, who knew all, he took his departure for Ancona. Arrived
      there, he assumed the name of Filippo Santodeccio, and having
      forgathered with a rich merchant, entered his service. The merchant
      took him with him to Cyprus aboard one of his ships, <milestone id="p03070007" />and was so well
      pleased with his bearing and behaviour that he not only gave him a
      handsome salary but made him in a sort his companion, and entrusted
      him with the management of no small part of his affairs: wherein he
      proved himself so apt and assiduous, that in the course of a few years
      he was himself established in credit and wealth and great repute as a
      merchant. Seven years thus passed, during which, albeit his thoughts
      frequently reverted to his cruel mistress, and sorely love smote him,
      and much he yearned to see her again, yet such was his firmness that
      he came off conqueror, <milestone id="p03070008" />until one day in Cyprus it so befell that
      there was sung in his hearing a song that he had himself composed,
      and of which the theme was the mutual love that was between his
      lady and him, and the delight that he had of her; which as he heard,
      he found it incredible that she should have forgotten him, and burned
      with such a desire to see her once more, that, being able to hold out
      no longer, he made up his mind to return to Florence. <milestone id="p03070009" />So, having
      set all his affairs in order, he betook him, attended only by a single
      servant, to Ancona; whence he sent all his effects, as they arrived,
      forward to Florence, consigning them to a friend of his Ancontan
      partner, and followed with his servant in the disguise of a pilgrim
      returned from the Holy Sepulchre. Arrived at Florence, he put
      up at a little hostelry kept by two brothers hard by his lady's house,
      <milestone id="p03070010" />whither he forthwith hied him, hoping that, perchance, he might
      have sight of her from the street; but, finding all barred and
      bolted, doors, windows and all else, he doubted much, she must be
      dead, or have removed thence. So, with a very heavy heart, he
 returned to the house of the two brothers, and to his great surprise
      found his own four brothers standing in front of it, all in black. He
      knew that he was so changed from his former semblance, both in dress
      and in person, that he might not readily be recognized, and he had
      therefore no hesitation in going up to a shoemaker and asking him
      <pb n="219" />why these men were all dressed in black. <milestone id="p03070011" />The shoemaker answered:
      <q direct="unspecified">'Tis because 'tis not fifteen days since a brother of theirs, Tedaldo
	by name, that had been long abroad, was slain; and I understand
	that they have proved in court that one Aldobrandino Palermini,
	who is under arrest, did the deed, because Tedaldo, who loved his
	wife, was come back to Florence incognito to forgather with her.</q>
      <milestone id="p03070012" />Tedaldo found it passing strange that there should be any one so
      like him as to be mistaken for him, and deplored Aldobrandino's evil
      plight. He had learned, however, that the lady was alive and well.
      So, as 'twas now night, he hied him, much perplexed in mind, into
      the inn, and supped with his servant. The bedroom assigned him
      was almost at the top of the house, <milestone id="p03070013" />and the bed was none of the
      best. Thoughts many and disquieting haunted his mind, and his
      supper had been but light. Whereby it befell that midnight came and
      went, and Tedaldo was still awake. As thus he watched, he heard
      shortly after midnight, a noise as of persons descending from the roof
      into the house, and then through the chinks of the door of his room
      he caught the flicker of an ascending light. <milestone id="p03070014" />Wherefore he stole
      softly to the door, and peeping through a chink to make out what
      was afoot, he saw a very fine young woman bearing a light, and three
      men making towards her, being evidently those that had descended
      from the roof. The men exchanged friendly greetings with the
      young woman, and then one said to her: 
<milestone id="p03070015" /><q direct="unspecified">Now, God be praised,
 we may make our minds easy, for we are well assured that judgment
 for the death of Tedaldo Elisei is gotten by his brothers against
 Aldobrandino Palermini, and he has confessed, and the sentence is
 already drawn up; but still it behoves us to hold our peace; for,
 should it ever get abroad that we were guilty, we shall stand in the
 like jeopardy as Aldobrandino.</q> So saying, they took leave of the
 woman, who seemed much cheered, and went to bed. 
<milestone id="p03070016" />What he
 had heard set Tedaldo musing on the number and variety of the
 errors to which men are liable: as, first, how his brothers had
 mourned and interred a stranger in his stead, and then charged an
 innocent man upon false suspicion, and by false witness brought him
 into imminent peril of death: from which he passed to ponder the
 blind severity of laws and magistrates, who from misguided zeal to
 elicit the truth not unfrequently become ruthless, and, adjudging that
 which is false, forfeit the title which they claim of ministers of
 <pb n="220" />God and justice, and do but execute the mandates of iniquity and
 the Evil One. And so he came at last to consider the possibility
 of saving Aldobrandino, and formed a plan for the purpose. <milestone id="p03070017" />Accordingly,
 on the morrow, when he was risen, he left his servant at the
 inn, and hied him alone, at what he deemed a convenient time, to
 his lady's house, where, finding, by chance, the door open, he entered,
 and saw his lady sitting, all tears and lamentations, in a little parlour
 on the ground-floor. Whereat he all but wept for sympathy; and
 drawing near her, he said: 
<q direct="unspecified">Madam, be not troubled in spirit: your peace is nigh you.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070018" />Whereupon the lady raised her head, and said
 between her sobs: <q direct="unspecified">Good man, what dost thou, a pilgrim, if I
 mistake not, from distant parts, know either of my peace or of my
 affliction?</q> 
<milestone id="p03070019" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> returned the pilgrim, <q direct="unspecified">I am of Constantinople,
 and am but now come hither, at God's behest, that I may give
 you laughter for tears, and deliver your husband from death.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070020" /><q direct="unspecified">But,</q>
 said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">if thou art of Constantinople, and but now arrived,
 how is 't that thou knowest either who my husband is, or who I
 am?</q> 
<milestone id="p03070021" />Whereupon the pilgrim gave her the whole narrative, from
 the very beginning, of Aldobrandino's sufferings; he also told her,
 who she was, how long she had been married, and much besides that
 was known to him of her affairs: whereat the lady was lost in
 wonder, and, taking him to be a prophet, threw herself on her knees
 at his feet, and besought him for God's sake, if he were come to save
 Aldobrandino, to lose no time, for the matter brooked no delay. <milestone id="p03070022" />Thus
 adjured, the pilgrim assumed an air of great sanctity, as he said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Arise, Madam, weep not, but hearken diligently to what I shall
 say to you, and look to it that you impart it to none. I have it by
 revelation of God that the tribulation wherein you stand is come
 upon you in requital of a sin which you did once commit, of which
 God is minded that this suffering be a partial purgation, and that you
 make reparation in full, if you would not find yourself in a far
 more grievous plight.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070023" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> replied the lady, <q direct="unspecified">many sins have I
 committed, nor know I how among them all to single out that
 whereof, more than another, God requires reparation at my hands:
 wherefore, if you know it, tell it me, and what by way of reparation
 I may do, that will I do.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070024" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> returned the pilgrim, <q direct="unspecified">well
 wot I what it is, nor shall I question you thereof for my better
 instruction, but that the rehearsal may give you increase of remorse
 <pb n="221" />therefor. But pass we now to fact. Tell me, mind you ever to
 have had a lover?</q> 
<milestone id="p03070025" />Whereat the lady heaved a deep sigh; then,
 marvelling not a little, for she had thought 'twas known to none,
 albeit on the day when the man was slain, who was afterwards buried
 as Tedaldo, there had been some buzz about it, occasioned by some
 indiscreet words dropped by Tedaldo's gossip and confidant, she made
 answer: 
<milestone id="p03070026" /><q direct="unspecified">I see that there is nought that men keep secret but God
 reveals it to you; wherefore I shall not endeavour to hide my secrets
 from you. True it is that in my youth I was beyond measure
 enamoured of the unfortunate young man whose death is imputed to
 my husband; whom I mourned with grief unfeigned, for, albeit I
 shewed myself harsh and cruel towards him before his departure, yet
 neither thereby, nor by his long absence, nor yet by his calamitous
 death was my heart estranged from him.</q> <milestone id="p03070027" />Then said the pilgrim:
 <q direct="unspecified">'Twas not the unfortunate young man now dead that you did love,
 but Tedaldo Elisei. But let that pass; now tell me: wherefore lost
 he your good graces? Did he ever offend you?</q> 
<milestone id="p03070028" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay verily,</q>
 answered the lady, <q direct="unspecified">he never offended me at all. My harshness was
 prompted by an accursed friar, to whom I once confessed, and who,
 when I told him of the love I bore Tedaldo, and my intimacy with
 him, made my ears so tingle and sing that I still shudder to think of
 it, warning me that, if I gave it not up, I should fall into the jaws of
 the Devil in the abyss of hell, and be cast into the avenging fire.
 <milestone id="p03070029" />Whereby I was so terrified that I quite made my mind up to discontinue
 my intimacy with him, and, to trench the matter, I would
 thenceforth have none of his letters or messages; and so, I suppose,
 he went away in despair, though I doubt not, had he persevered a
 while longer, I should not have seen him wasting away like snow in
 sunshine without relenting of my harsh resolve; for in sooth there
 was nothing in the world I would so gladly have done.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070030" />Then said
 the pilgrim: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, 'tis this sin, and this only, that has brought
 upon you your present tribulation. I know positively that Tedaldo
 did never put force upon you: 'twas of your own free will, and for
 that he pleased you, that you became enamoured of him: your
 constant visitor, your intimate friend he became, because you yourself
 would have it so; and in the course of your intimacy you shewed
 him such favour by word and deed that, if he loved you first, you
 multiplied his love full a thousandfold. <milestone id="p03070031" />And if so it was, and well
 <pb n="222" />yourself from him? You should have considered the whole matter
 before the die was cast, and not have entered upon it, if you deemed
 you might have cause to repent you of it as a sin. As soon as he
 became yours, you became his. <milestone id="p03070032" />Had he not been yours, you might
 have acted as you had thought fit, at your own unfettered discretion;
 but, as you were his, 'twas robbery, 'twas conduct most disgraceful,
 to sever yourself from him against his will. <milestone id="p03070033" />Now you must know
 that I am a friar; and therefore all the ways of friars are familiar to
 me; nor does it misbecome me, as it might another, to speak for
 your behoof somewhat freely of them; as I am minded to do that
 you may have better understanding of them in the future than you
 would seem to have had in the past. <milestone id="p03070034" />Time was when the friars were
 most holy and worthy men, but those who to-day take the name and
 claim the reputation of friars have nought of the friar save only the
 habit: nay, they have not even that: for, whereas their founders
 ordained that their habits should be strait, of a sorry sort, and of
 coarse stuff, apt symbols of a soul that in arraying the body in so mean
 a garb did despite to all things temporal, our modern friars will have
 them full, and double, and resplendent, and of the finest stuff, and of
 a fashion goodly and pontifical, wherein without shame they flaunt it
 like peacocks in the church, in the piazza, even as do the laity in their
 robes. <milestone id="p03070035" />And as the fisherman casts his net into the stream with
 intent to take many fish at one throw: so 'tis the main solicitude and
 study, art and craft of these friars to embrace and entangle within
 the ample folds of their vast swelling skirts beguines, widows and
 other foolish women, ay, and men likewise in great number. Wherefore,
 to speak with more exactitude, the friars of to-day have nought
 of the habit of the friar save only the colour thereof. <milestone id="p03070036" />And, whereas
 the friars of old time sought to win men to their salvation, those of
 to-day seek to win their women and their wealth; wherefore they
 have made it and make it their sole concern by declamation and
 imagery to strike terror into the souls of fools, and to make believe
 that sins are purged by alms and masses; to the end that they, base
 wretches that have fled to friarage not to ensue holiness but to escape
 hardship, may receive from this man bread, from that man wine, and
 from the other man a donation for masses for the souls of his dead.
 <milestone id="p03070037" />True indeed it is that sins are purged by almsgiving and prayer; but,
 did they who give the alms know, did they but understand to whom
 <pb n="223" />or throw them to so many pigs. And, knowing that the fewer be
 they that share great riches, the greater their ease, 'tis the study of
 each how best by declamation and intimidation to oust others from
 that whereof he would fain be the sole owner. <milestone id="p03070038" />They censure lust in
 men, that, they turning therefrom, the sole use of their women may
 remain to the censors: they condemn usury and unlawful gains,
 that, being entrusted with the restitution thereof, they may be able
 to enlarge their habits, and to purchase bishoprics and other great
 preferments with the very money which they have made believe must
 bring its possessor to perdition. <milestone id="p03070039" />And when they are taxed with these
 and many other discreditable practices, they deem that there is no
 censure, however grave, of which they may not be quit by their glib
 formula: 'Follow our precepts, not our practice:' as if'twere possible
 that the sheep should be of a more austere and rigid virtue than the
 shepherds. And how many of these, whom they put off with this
 formula, understand it not in the way in which they enunciate it, not
 a few of them know. <milestone id="p03070040" />The friars of to-day would have you follow
 their precepts, that is to say, they would have you fill their purses
 with coin, confide to them your secrets, practise continence, be
 long-suffering,
 forgive those that trespass against you, keep yourselves from
 evil speaking; all which things are good, seemly, holy. But to what
 end? To the end that they may be able to do that which, if the
 laity do it, they will not be able to do. <milestone id="p03070041" />Who knows not that idleness
 cannot subsist without money? Spend thy money on thy pleasures,
 and the friar will not be able to live in sloth in his order. Go after
 women, and there will be no place for the friar. Be not long-suffering,
 pardon not the wrong-doer, and the friar will not dare to
 cross thy threshold to corrupt thy family. But wherefore pursue I
 the topic through every detail? <milestone id="p03070042" />They accuse themselves as often
 as they so excuse themselves in the hearing of all that have understanding.
 Why seclude they not themselves, if they misdoubt
 their power to lead continent and holy lives? Or if they must
 needs not live as recluses, why follow they not that other holy
 text of the Gospel: Christ began to do and to teach?<note>As pointed out by
 Mr. Payne, these words are not from any of the
 Gospels, but from the first verse of the Acts of the Apostles. Boccaccio
 doubtless used <q direct="unspecified">Evangelio</q> in a large sense for the whole of the New
 Testament.</note> 
<milestone id="p03070043" />Let
 <pb n="224" />them practise first, and school us with their precepts afterwards. A
 thousand such have I seen in my day, admirers, lovers, philanderers,
 not of ladies of the world alone, but of nuns; ay, and they too such as
 made the most noise in the pulpits. Is it such as they that we are to
 follow? He that does so, pleases himself; but God knows if he do
 wisely. <milestone id="p03070044" />But assume that herein we must allow that your censor, the
 friar, spoke truth, to wit, that none may break the marriage-vow
 without very grave sin. What then? to rob a man, to slay him, to
 make of him an exile and a wanderer on the face of the earth, are not
 these yet greater sins? <milestone id="p03070045" />None will deny that so they are. A woman
 that indulges herself in the intimate use with a man commits but a
 sin of nature; but if she rob him, or slay him, or drive him out into
 exile, her sin proceeds from depravity of spirit. That you did rob
 Tedaldo, I have already shewn you, in that, having of your own free
 will become his, you reft you from him. <milestone id="p03070046" />I now go further and say
 that, so far as in you lay, you slew him, seeing that, shewing yourself
 ever more and more cruel, you did your utmost to drive him to take
 his own life; and in the law's intent he that is the cause that wrong
 is done is as culpable as he that does it. <milestone id="p03070047" />Nor is it deniable that you
 were the cause that for seven years he has been an exile and a
 wanderer upon the face of the earth. Wherefore upon each of the
 said three articles you are found guilty of a greater crime than you
 committed by your intimacy with him. But consider we the matter
 more closely: perchance Tedaldo merited such treatment: nay, but
 assuredly 'twas not so. You have yourself so confessed: besides
 which I know that he loves you more dearly than himself. <milestone id="p03070048" />He
 would laud, he would extol, he would magnify you above all other
 ladies so as never was heard the like, wheresoever 'twas seemly for
 him to speak of you, and it might be done without exciting suspicion.
 All his bliss, all his honour, all his liberty he avowed was entirely in
 your disposal. <milestone id="p03070049" />Was he not of noble birth? And for beauty might
 he not compare with the rest of his townsfolk? Did he not excel in
 all the exercises and accomplishments proper to youth? Was he not
 beloved, held dear, well seen of all men? <milestone id="p03070050" />You will not deny it.
 How then could you at the behest of a paltry friar, silly, brutish and
 envious, bring yourself to deal with him in any harsh sort? <milestone id="p03070051" />I cannot
 estimate the error of those ladies who look askance on men and hold
 them cheap; whereas, bethinking them of what they are themselves,
 <pb n="225" />and what and how great is the nobility with which God has endowed
 man above all the other animals, they ought rather to glory in the
 love which men give them, and hold them most dear, and with all
 zeal study to please them, that so their love may never fail. <milestone id="p03070052" />In what
 sort you did so, instigated by the chatter of a friar, some broth-guzzling,
 pastry-gorging knave without a doubt, you know; and peradventure
 his purpose was but to instal himself in the place whence he sought
 to oust another. <milestone id="p03070053" />This then is the sin which the Divine justice,
 which, ever operative, suffers no perturbation of its even balance,
 or arrest of judgment, has decreed not to leave unpunished: wherefore,
 as without due cause you devised how you might despoil
 Tedaldo of yourself, so without due cause your husband has been
 placed and is in jeopardy of his life on Tedaldo's account, and to
 your sore affliction. <milestone id="p03070054" />Wherefrom if you would be delivered, there
 is that which you must promise, ay, and (much more) which you
 must perform: to wit, that, should it ever betide that Tedaldo return
 hither from his long exile, you will restore to him your favour, your
 love, your tender regard, your intimacy, and reinstate him in the
 position which he held before you foolishly hearkened to the half-witted
 friar.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03070055" />Thus ended the pilgrim; and the lady, who had followed him
 with the closest attention, deeming all that he advanced very sound,
 and doubting not that her tribulation was, as he said, in requital of her
 sin, spoke thus: 
<milestone id="p03070056" /><q direct="unspecified">Friend of God, well I wot that the matters
 which you discourse are true, and, thanks to your delineation, I now
 in great measure know what manner of men are the friars, whom
 I have hitherto regarded as all alike holy; nor doubt I that great
 was my fault in the course which I pursued towards Tedaldo; and
 gladly, were it in my power, would I make reparation in the manner
 which you have indicated. But how is this feasible? Tedaldo can
 never return to us. He is dead. Wherefore I know not why I
 must needs give you a promise which cannot be performed.</q>
 <milestone id="p03070057" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> returned the pilgrim, <q direct="unspecified">'tis revealed to me by God
 that Tedaldo is by no means dead, but alive and well and happy,
 so only he enjoyed your favour.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070058" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">speak
 advisedly; I saw his body done to death by more than one knife-wound;
 I folded it in these arms, and drenched the dead face with
 many a tear; whereby, perchance, I gave occasion for the bruit that
 <pb n="226" />has been made to my disadvantage.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070059" /><q direct="unspecified">Say what you may, Madam,</q>
 rejoined the pilgrim, <q direct="unspecified">I assure you that Tedaldo lives, and if you will
 but give the promise, then, for its fulfilment, I have good hope that
 you will soon see him.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070060" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">I give the promise,</q>
 said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">and right gladly will I make it good; nor is there
 aught that might happen that would yield me such delight as to see
 my husband free and scatheless, and Tedaldo alive.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070061" />Tedaldo now
 deemed it wise to make himself known, and establish the lady in a
 more sure hope of her husband's safety. Wherefore he said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam, to set your mind at ease in regard of your husband, I
 must first impart to you a secret, which be mindful to disclose to
 none so long as you live.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070062" />Then--for such was the confidence
 which the lady reposed in the pilgrim's apparent sanctity that they
 were by themselves in a place remote from observation--Tedaldo
 drew forth a ring which he had guarded with the most jealous care,
 since it had been given him by the lady on the last night when they
 were together, and said, as he shewed it to her: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, know
 you this?</q> 
<milestone id="p03070063" />The lady recognized it forthwith, and answered: <q direct="unspecified">I
 do, Sir; I gave it long ago to Tedaldo.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070064" />Then the pilgrim, rising
 and throwing off his sclavine<note>Schiavina, Low Lat.
 sclavina, the long coarse frock worn, among
 others, by palmers.</note> and hat, said with the Florentine
 accent: <q direct="unspecified">And know you me?</q> 
<milestone id="p03070065" />The lady recognizing forthwith
 the form and semblance of Tedaldo, was struck dumb with wonder
 and fear as of a corpse that is seen to go about as if alive, and was
 much rather disposed to turn and flee from Tedaldo returned from
 the tomb than to come forward and welcome Tedaldo arrived from
 Cyprus. 
<milestone id="p03070066" />But when Tedaldo said to her: <q direct="unspecified">Fear not, Madam, your
 Tedaldo am I, alive and well, nor was I ever dead, whatever you
 and my brothers may think,</q> 
<milestone id="p03070067" />the lady, partly awed, partly reassured
 by his voice, regarded him with rather more attention, and inly
 affirming that 'twas in very truth Tedaldo, threw herself upon his
 neck, and wept, and kissed him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Sweet my Tedaldo,
 welcome home.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070068" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied Tedaldo after he had kissed
 and embraced her, <q direct="unspecified">time serves not now for greetings more intimate.
 'Tis for me to be up and doing, that Aldobrandino may be restored
 to you safe and sound; touching which matter you will, I trust,
 before to-morrow at even hear tidings that will gladden your heart;
 <pb n="227" />indeed I expect to have good news to-night, and, if so, will come
 and tell it you, when I shall be less straitened than I am at present.</q>
 <milestone id="p03070069" />He then resumed his sclavine and that, and having kissed the lady
 again, and bade her be of good cheer, took his leave, and hied him to
 the prison, where Aldobrandino lay more occupied with apprehension
 of imminent death than hope of deliverance to come. As ministrant
 of consolation, he gained ready admittance of the warders, and, seating
 himself by Aldobrandino's side, he said: 
<milestone id="p03070070" /><q direct="unspecified">Aldobrandino, in me
 thou seest a friend sent thee by God, who is touched with pity of
 thee by reason of thy innocence; wherefore, if in reverent submission
 to Him thou wilt grant me a slight favour that I shall ask of thee,
 without fail, before to-morrow at even, thou shalt, in lieu of the
 doom of death that thou awaitest, hear thy acquittal pronounced.</q>
 <milestone id="p03070071" /><q direct="unspecified">Worthy man,</q> replied Aldobrandino, <q direct="unspecified">I know thee not, nor mind
 I ever to have seen thee; wherefore, as thou shewest thyself solicitous
 for my safety, my friend indeed thou must needs be, even as thou
 sayst. And in sooth the crime, for which they say I ought to be
 doomed to death, I never committed, though others enough I have
 committed, which perchance have brought me to this extremity.
 However, if so be that God has now pity on me, this I tell thee
 in reverent submission to Him, that, whereas 'tis but a little thing
 that thou cravest of me, there is nought, however great, but I would
 not only promise but gladly do it; wherefore, even ask what thou
 wilt, and, if so be that I escape, I will without fail keep my word to
 the letter.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070072" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> returned the pilgrim, <q direct="unspecified">I ask but this of thee,
 that thou pardon Tedaldo's four brothers, that in the belief that thou
 wast guilty of their brother's death they brought thee to this strait, and,
 so they ask thy forgiveness, account them as thy brothers and friends.</q>
 <milestone id="p03070073" /><q direct="unspecified">How sweet,</q> replied Aldobrandino, <q direct="unspecified">is the savour, how ardent the
 desire, of vengeance, none knows but he that is wronged; but yet, so
 God may take thought for my deliverance, I will gladly pardon, nay,
 I do now pardon them, and if I go hence alive and free, I will thenceforth
 have them in such regard as shall content thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070074" />Satisfied with
 this answer, the pilgrim, without further parley, heartily exhorted
 Aldobrandino to be of good cheer; assuring him that, before the next
 day was done, he should be certified beyond all manner of doubt of
 his deliverance; <milestone id="p03070075" />and so he left him.</p><p>On quitting the prison the pilgrim hied him forthwith to the
 <pb n="228" />signory, and being closeted with a knight that was in charge, thus
 spoke: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, 'tis the duty of all, and most especially of those
 who hold your place, zealously to bestir themselves that the truth be
 brought to light, in order as well that those bear not the penalty
 who have not committed the crime, as that the guilty be punished.
 And that this may come to pass to your honour and the undoing
 of the delinquent, I am come hither to you. <milestone id="p03070076" />You wot that you
 have dealt rigorously with Aldobrandino Palermini, and have found,
 as you think, that 'twas he that slew Tedaldo Elisei, and you are
 about to condemn him; wherein you are most certainly in error, as
 I doubt not before midnight to prove to you, delivering the murderers
 into your hands.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070077" />The worthy knight, who was not without pity
 for Aldobrandino, readily gave ear to the pilgrim's words. He
 conversed at large with him, and availing himself of his guidance,
 made an easy capture of the two brothers that kept the inn and their
 servant in their first sleep. He was about to put them the torture, to
 elicit the true state of the case, when, their courage failing, they
 confessed without the least reserve, severally at first, and then jointly,
 that 'twas they that had slain Tedaldo Elisei, not knowing who he
 was. Asked for why, they answered that 'twas because he had
 sorely harassed the wife of one of them, and would have constrained
 her to do his pleasure, while they were out of doors. <milestone id="p03070078" />Whereof the
 pilgrim was no sooner apprised, than by leave of the knight he withdrew,
 and hied him privily to the house of Madonna Ermellina, whom
 (the rest of the household being gone to bed) he found awaiting him
 alone, and equally anxious for good news of her husband and a
 complete reconciliation with her Tedaldo. On entering, he blithely
 exclaimed: <q direct="unspecified">Rejoice, dearest my lady, for thou mayst rest assured
 that to-morrow thou shalt have thy Aldobrandino back here safe and
 sound;</q> and to confirm her faith in his words, he told her all that
 he had done. <milestone id="p03070079" />Greater joy was never woman's than hers of two such
 glad surprises; to wit, to have Tedaldo with her alive again, whom
 she had wailed for verily dead, and to know Aldobrandino, whom she
 had thought in no long time to wail for dead, now out of jeopardy.
 Wherefore, when she had affectionately embraced and kissed her
 Tedaldo, they hied them to bed together, and with hearty goodwill
 made gracious and gladsome consummation of their peace by
 interchange of sweet solace.</p><pb n="229" /><p><milestone id="p03070080" />With the approach of day Tedaldo rose, and having first apprised
 the lady of his purpose and enjoined her, as before, to keep it most
 secret, resumed his pilgrim's habit, and sallied forth of her house,
 to be ready, as occasion should serve, to act in Aldobrandino's interest.
 <milestone id="p03070081" />As soon as 'twas day, the signory, deeming themselves amply conversant
 with the affair, set Aldobrandino at large; and a few days
 later they caused the malefactors to be beheaded in the place where
 they had done the murder.</p><p><milestone id="p03070082" />Great was Aldobrandino's joy to find himself free, nor less great
 was that of his lady and all his friends and kinsfolk; and as 'twas
 through the pilgrim that it had come about, they brought him to
 their house, there to reside as long as he cared to tarry in the city;
 nor could they do him honour and cheer enough, and most of all the
 lady, who knew her man. <milestone id="p03070083" />But after a while, seeing that his brothers
 were not only become a common laughing-stock by reason of Aldobrandino's
 acquittal, but had armed themselves for very fear, he felt
 that their reconciliation with him brooked no delay, and accordingly
 craved of him performance of his promise. <milestone id="p03070084" />Aldobrandino replied
 handsomely that it should be had at once. The pilgrim then bade
 him arrange for the following day a grand banquet, at which he and his
 kinsfolk and their ladies were to entertain the four brothers and their
 ladies, adding that he would himself go forthwith as Aldobrandino's
 envoy, and bid them welcome to his peace and banquet. <milestone id="p03070085" />All which
 being approved by Aldobrandino, the pilgrim hied him with all speed
 to the four brothers, whom by ample, apt and unanswerable argument
 he readily induced to reinstate themselves in Aldobrandino's friendship
 by suing for his forgiveness: which done, he bade them and their
 ladies to breakfast with Aldobrandino on the morrow, and they, being
 assured of his good faith, were consenting to come. <milestone id="p03070086" />So, on the
 morrow, at the breakfast hour, Tedaldo's four brothers, still wearing
 their black, came with certain of their friends to Aldobrandino's house,
 where he awaited them; and, in presence of the company that had
 been bidden to meet them, laid down their arms, and made surrender
 to Aldobrandino, asking his pardon of that which they had done
 against him. <milestone id="p03070087" />Aldobrandino received them compassionately, wept,
 kissed each on the mouth, and let few words suffice to remit each
 offence. After them came their sisters and their wives, all habited
 sadly, and were graciously received by Madonna Ermellina and the
 <pb n="230" />other ladies. <milestone id="p03070088" />The guests, men and women alike, found all things
 ordered at the banquet with magnificence, nor aught unmeet for
 commendation save the restraint which the yet recent grief, betokened
 by the sombre garb of Tedaldo's kinsfolk, laid upon speech (wherein
 some had found matter to except against the banquet and the pilgrim
 for devising it, as he well knew), but, as he had premeditated, in due
 time, he stood up, the others being occupied with their dessert, and
 spoke thus: 
<milestone id="p03070089" /><q direct="unspecified">Nothing is wanting to complete the gaiety of this
 banquet except the presence of Tedaldo; whom, as you have been
 long time with him and have not known him, I will point out to
 you.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070090" />So, having divested himself of his sclavine and whatever else
 in his garb denoted the pilgrim, he remained habited in a tunic of
 green taffeta, in which guise, so great was the wonder with which all
 regarded him that, though they recognized him, 'twas long before
 any dared to believe that 'twas actually Tedaldo. 
<milestone id="p03070091" />Marking their
 surprise, Tedaldo told them not a little about themselves, their family
 connexions, their recent history, and his own adventures. Whereat
 his brothers and the rest of the men, all weeping for joy, hasted to
 embrace him, followed by the women, as well those that were not, as
 those that were, of kin to him, save only Madonna Ermellina. <milestone id="p03070092" />Which
 Aldobrandino observing, said: <q direct="unspecified">What is this, Ermellina? How
 comes it that, unlike the other ladies, thou alone dost Tedaldo no
 cheer?</q>
 <milestone id="p03070093" /><q direct="unspecified">Cheer,</q> replied the lady in the hearing of all, <q direct="unspecified">would I
 gladly do him such as no other woman has done or could do, seeing
 that I am more beholden to him than any other woman, in that to
 him I owe it that I have thee with me again; 'tis but the words
 spoken to my disadvantage, while we mourned him that we deemed
 Tedaldo, that give me pause.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070094" /><q direct="unspecified">Now out upon thee,</q> said
 Aldobrandino,
 <q direct="unspecified">thinkest thou that I heed the yelping of these curs?
 His zeal for my deliverance has abundantly disproved it, besides which
 I never believed it. Quick, get thee up, and go and embrace him.</q>
 <milestone id="p03070095" />The lady, who desired nothing better, was in this not slow to obey
 her husband; she rose forthwith, and embraced Tedaldo as the other
 ladies had done, and did him gladsome cheer. Tedaldo's brothers
 and all the company, men and women alike, heartily approved Aldobrandino's
 handsomeness; and so whatever of despite the rumour had
 engendered in the minds of any was done away. <milestone id="p03070096" />And, now that all
 had done him cheer, Tedaldo with his own hands rent his brothers'
 <pb n="231" />suits of black upon their backs, as also the sad-hued garments which
 his sisters and sisters-in-law wore, and bade bring other apparel. Which
 when they had donned, there was no lack of singing, dancing and
 other sorts of merry-making; whereby the banquet, for all its subdued
 beginning, had a sonorous close. Then, just as they were, in the
 blithest of spirits, they hied them all to Tedaldo's house, where in
 the evening they supped; and in this manner they held festival for
 several days.</p><p><milestone id="p03070097" />'Twas some time before the Florentines ceased to look on Tedaldo
 as a portent, as if he were risen from the dead; and a shadow of doubt
 whether he were really Tedaldo or no continued to lurk in the minds
 of not a few, including even his brothers: they had no assured belief;
 and in that frame had perchance long continued, but for a casual
 occurrence that shewed them who the murdered man was. <milestone id="p03070098" />It so
 befell that one day some men-at-arms from Lunigiana passed by their
 house, and seeing Tedaldo accosted him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Good-morrow to
 thee, Faziuolo.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070099" />To whom Tedaldo, in the presence of his brothers,
 answered: <q direct="unspecified">You take me for another.</q> Whereat they were abashed,
 and asked his pardon, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Sooth to tell, you are liker than we
 ever knew any man like to another to a comrade of ours, Faziuolo da
 Pontremoli by name, who came hither a fortnight ago, or perhaps a
 little more, since when we have not been able to learn what became
 of him. Most true it is that your dress surprised us, because he, like
 ourselves, was a soldier.</q> 
<milestone id="p03070100" />Whereupon Tedaldo's eldest brother came
 forward, and asked how their comrade had been accoutred. They
 told him, and 'twas found to have been exactly as they said: by which
 and other evidence 'twas established that 'twas Faziuolo that had been
 murdered, and not Tedaldo; of whom thenceforth no suspicion
 lurked in the minds of his brothers or any one else.</p><p><milestone id="p03070101" />So, then, Tedaldo returned home very rich, and remained constant
 in his love; nor did the lady again treat him harshly; but, using
 discretion, they long had mutual solace of their love. God grant us
 solace of ours.</p></div2>