<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov0905"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09050001" />Calandrino being enamoured of a damsel, Bruno gives
 him a scroll, averring that, if he but touch her therewith,
 she will go with him: he is found with her by his
 wife, who subjects him to a most severe and vexatious
 examination.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09050002" />So, at no great length, ended Neifile her story, which the
 company
 allowed to pass with none too much laughter or remark:
 whereupon the queen, turning to Fiammetta, bade her follow suit.
 Fiammetta, with mien most gladsome, made answer that she willingly
 obeyed, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09050003" />As I doubt not, ye know, ladies most
 debonair, be the topic of discourse never so well worn, it will still
 continue to please, if the speaker knows how to make due choice of
 time and occasion meet.  <milestone id="p09050004" />Wherefore, considering the reason for
 which we are here (how that 'tis to make merry and speed the time
 gaily, and that merely) I deem that there is nought that may afford
 us mirth and solace but here may find time and occasion meet, and,
 after serving a thousand turns of discourse, should still prove not
 unpleasing
 for another thousand.  <milestone id="p09050005" />Wherefore, notwithstanding that of
 Calandrino and his doings not a little has from time to time been
 said among us, yet, considering that, as a while ago Filostrato
 observed, there is nought that concerns him that is not entertaining,
 I will make bold to add to the preceding stories another, which I
 might well, had I been minded to deviate from the truth, have disguised,
 and so recounted it to you, under other names; but as whoso
 in telling a story diverges from the truth does thereby in no small
 measure diminish the delight of his hearers, I purpose for the reason
 aforesaid to give you the narrative in proper form.</p></div3><pb n="283" /><p><milestone id="p09050006" />Niccol&#242; Cornacchini, one of our citizens, and a man of wealth,
 had among other estates a fine one at Camerata, on which he had
 a grand house built, and engaged Bruno and Buffalmacco to paint it
 throughout; in which task, for that 'twas by no means light, they associated
 with them Nello and Calandrino, and so set to work.  <milestone id="p09050007" />There
 were a few rooms in the house provided with beds and other furniture,
 and an old female servant lived there as caretaker, but otherwise
 the house was unoccupied, for which cause Niccol&#242;'s son, Filippo,
 being
 a young man and a bachelor, was wont sometimes to bring thither a
 woman for his pleasure, and after keeping her there for a few days to
 escort her thence again.  <milestone id="p09050008" />Now on one of these occasions it befell
 that he brought thither one Niccolosa, whom a vile fellow, named
 Mangione, kept in a house at Camaldoli as a common prostitute.
  <milestone id="p09050009" />And a fine piece of flesh she was, and wore fine clothes, and, for
 one of her sort, knew how to comport herself becomingly and talk
 agreeably.</p><p>Now one day at high noon forth tripped the damsel from her
 chamber in a white gown, her locks braided about her head, to
 wash her hands and face at a well that was in the courtyard of the
 house, and, while she was so engaged, it befell that Calandrino came
 there for water, and greeted her familiarly.  <milestone id="p09050010" />Having returned his
 salutation, she, rather because Calandrino struck her as something
 out of the common, than for any other interest she felt in him,
 regarded him attentively. Calandrino did the like by her, and being
 smitten by her beauty, found reasons enough why he should not go
 back to his comrades with the water; but, as he knew not who she
 was, he made not bold to address her.  <milestone id="p09050011" />She, upon whom his gaze
 was not lost, being minded to amuse herself at his expense, let her
 glance from time to time rest upon him, while she heaved a slight
 sigh or two. Whereby Calandrino was forthwith captivated, and
 tarried in the courtyard, until Filippo called her back into the chamber.
  <milestone id="p09050012" />Returned to his work, Calandrino sighed like a furnace: which
 Bruno, who was ever regardful of his doings for the diversion they
 afforded him, failed not to mark, and by and by: <q direct="unspecified">What the
 Devil is amiss with thee, comrade Calandrino?</q> quoth he. <q direct="unspecified">Thou
 dost nought but puff and blow.</q>  <milestone id="p09050013" /><q direct="unspecified">Comrade,</q> replied Calandrino,
 <q direct="unspecified">I should be in luck, had I but one to help me.</q> <milestone id="p09050014" /><q direct="unspecified">How so?</q>
 quoth Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050015" /><q direct="unspecified">Why,</q> returned Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not to go farther,
 <pb n="284" />but there is a damsel below, fairer than a lamia, and so mightily in
 love with me that 'twould astonish thee. I observed it but now,
 when I went to fetch the water.</q>  <milestone id="p09050016" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but, Calandrino, make
 sure she be not Filippo's wife,</q> quoth Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050017" /><q direct="unspecified">I doubt 'tis even
 so,</q> replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">for he called her and she joined him in the
 chamber; but what signifies it? I would circumvent Christ Himself
 in such case, not to say Filippo. Of a truth, comrade, I tell thee
 she pleases me I could not say how.</q>  <milestone id="p09050018" /><q direct="unspecified">Comrade,</q> returned Bruno,
 <q direct="unspecified">I will find out for thee who she is, and if she be Filippo's wife, two
 words from me will make it all straight for thee, for she is much my
 friend. But how shall we prevent Buffalmacco knowing it? I can
 never have a word with her, but he is with me.</q>  <milestone id="p09050019" /><q direct="unspecified">As to Buffalmacco,</q>
 replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">I care not if he do know it; but let
 us make sure that it come not to Nello's ears, for he is of kin to
 Monna Tessa, and would spoil it all.</q>  <milestone id="p09050020" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Thou art in
 the right,</q> returned Bruno.</p><p><milestone id="p09050021" />Now Bruno knew what the damsel was, for he had seen her
 arrive, and moreover Filippo had told him. So, Calandrino having
 given over working for a while, and betaken him to her, Bruno
 acquainted Nello and Buffalmacco with the whole story; and thereupon
 they privily concerted how to entreat him in regard of this love
 affair.  <milestone id="p09050022" />Wherefore, upon his return, quoth Bruno softly: <q direct="unspecified">Didst
 see her?</q>  <milestone id="p09050023" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, woe's me!</q> replied Calandrino: <q direct="unspecified">she has
 stricken me to the death.</q>  <milestone id="p09050024" />Quoth Bruno: <q direct="unspecified">I will go see if she
 be the lady I take her to be, and if I find that 'tis so, leave the
 rest to me.</q>  <milestone id="p09050025" />Whereupon down went Bruno, and found Filippo and
 the damsel, and fully apprised them what sort of fellow Calandrino
 was, and what he had told them, and concerted with them what
 each should do and say, that they might have a merry time together
	over Calandrino's love affair. <milestone id="p09050026" />He then rejoined Calandrino, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">'Tis the very same; and therefore the affair needs very delicate
 handling, for, if Filippo were but ware thereof, not all Arno's waters
 would suffice to cleanse us. However, what should I say to her
 from thee, if by chance I should get speech of her?</q>  <milestone id="p09050027" /><q direct="unspecified">I' faith,</q>
 replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">why, first, first of all, thou wilt tell her that I
 wish her a thousand bushels of the good seed of generation, and then
 that I am her servant, and if she is fain of--aught--thou tak'st
 me?</q>  <milestone id="p09050028" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay,</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">leave it to me.</q></p><pb n="285" /><p><milestone id="p09050029" />Supper-time came; and, the day's work done, they went down
 into the courtyard, Filippo and Niccolosa being there, and there
 they tarried a while to advance Calandrino's suit. Calandrino's gaze
 was soon riveted on Niccolosa, and such and so strange and startling
 were the gestures that he made that they would have given sight to
 the blind.  <milestone id="p09050030" />She on her part used all her arts to inflame his passion,
 primed as she had been by Bruno, and diverted beyond measure as
 she was by Calandrino's antics, while Filippo, Buffalmacco and the
 rest feigned to be occupied in converse, and to see nought of what
 passed.  <milestone id="p09050031" />However, after a while, to Calandrino's extreme disgust, they
 took their leave; and as they bent their steps towards Florence:
 <q direct="unspecified">I warrant thee,</q> quoth Bruno to Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">she wastes away
 for thee like ice in the sunlight; by the body o' God, if thou
 wert to bring thy rebeck, and sing her one or two of thy love-songs,
 she'd throw herself out of window to be with thee.</q>  <milestone id="p09050032" />Quoth Calandrino:
 <q direct="unspecified">Think'st thou, comrade, think'st thou, 'twere well I
 brought it?</q>  <milestone id="p09050033" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, indeed,</q> returned Bruno. 
 <milestone id="p09050034" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Ah! comrade,</q> quoth Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">so thou wouldst not believe
 me when I told thee to-day? Of a truth I perceive there's ne'er
 another knows so well what he would be at as I.  <milestone id="p09050035" />Who but I
 would have known how so soon to win the love of a lady like that?
 Lucky indeed might they deem themselves, if they did it, those
 young gallants that go about, day and night, up and down, a strumming
 on the one-stringed viol, and would not know how to gather
 a handful of nuts once in a millennium. Mayst thou be by to see
 when I bring her the rebeck! thou wilt see fine sport.  <milestone id="p09050036" />List well
 what I say: I am not so old as I look; and she knows it right well:
 ay, and anyhow I will soon let her know it, when I come to grapple
 her. By the very body of Christ I will have such sport with her,
 that she will follow me as any love-sick maid follows her swain.</q>
  <milestone id="p09050037" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">I doubt not thou wilt make her thy prey:
 and I seem to see thee bite her dainty vermeil mouth and her cheeks,
 that shew as twin roses, with thy teeth, that are as so many lute-pegs,
 and afterwards devour her bodily.</q>  <milestone id="p09050038" />So encouraged, Calandrino
 fancied himself already in action, and went about singing and capering
 in such high glee that 'twas as if he would burst his skin.  <milestone id="p09050039" />And so
 next day he brought the rebeck, and to the no small amusement
 of all the company sang several songs to her. And, in short, by
 <pb n="286" />frequently seeing her, he waxed so mad with passion that he gave
 over working; and a thousand times a day he would run now to the
 window, now to the door, and anon to the courtyard on the chance
 of catching sight of her; nor did she, astutely following Bruno's
 instructions, fail to afford him abundance of opportunity.  <milestone id="p09050040" />Bruno
 played the go-between, bearing him her answers to all his messages,
 and sometimes bringing him messages from her. When she was not
 at home, which was most frequently the case, he would send him
 letters from her, in which she gave great encouragement to his hopes,
 at the same time giving him to understand that she was at the house
 of her kinsfolk, where as yet he might not visit her.</p><p><milestone id="p09050041" />On this wise Bruno and Buffalmacco so managed the affair as to
 divert themselves inordinately, causing him to send her, as at her
 request, now an ivory comb, now a purse, now a little knife, and
 other such dainty trifles; in return for which they brought him, now
 and again, a counterfeit ring of no value, with which Calandrino was
 marvellously pleased. And Calandrino, to stimulate their zeal in his
 interest, would entertain them hospitably at table, and otherwise
 flatter them.  <milestone id="p09050042" />Now, when they had thus kept him in play for two
 good months, and the affair was just where it had been, Calandrino,
 seeing that the work was coming to an end, and bethinking him that,
 if it did so before he had brought his love affair to a successful issue,
 he must give up all hopes of ever so doing, began to be very instant
 and importunate with Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050043" />So, in the presence of the damsel, and
 by preconcert with her and Filippo, quoth Bruno to Calandrino:
 <q direct="unspecified">Harkye, comrade, this lady has vowed to me a thousand times that
 she will do as thou wouldst have her, and as, for all that, she does
 nought to pleasure thee, I am of opinion that she leads thee by the
 nose: wherefore, as she keeps not her promises, we will make her
 do so, willy-nilly, if thou art so minded.</q>  <milestone id="p09050044" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but, for the love
 of God, so be it,</q> replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">and that speedily.</q>
	<milestone id="p09050045" /><q direct="unspecified">Darest
 thou touch her, then, with a scroll that I shall give thee?</q> quoth
 Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050046" /><q direct="unspecified">I dare,</q> replied Calandrino. 
 <milestone id="p09050047" /><q direct="unspecified">Fetch me, then,</q> quoth
 Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">a bit of the skin of an unborn lamb, a live bat, three grains of
 incense, and a blessed candle; and leave the rest to me.</q>  <milestone id="p09050048" />To catch
 the bat taxed all Calandrino's art and craft for the whole of the evening;
 but having at length taken him, he brought him with the other
 matters to Bruno: who, having withdrawn into a room by himself,
 <pb n="287" />wrote on the skin some cabalistic jargon, and handed it to him,
 saying:  <milestone id="p09050049" /><q direct="unspecified">Know, Calandrino, that, if thou touch her with this
 scroll, she will follow thee forthwith, and do whatever thou shalt
 wish. Wherefore, should Filippo go abroad to-day, get thee somehow
 up to her, and touch her; and then go into the barn that is
 hereby--'tis the best place we have, for never a soul goes there--and
 thou wilt see that she will come there too. When she is there, thou
 wottest well what to do.</q>  <milestone id="p09050050" />Calandrino, overjoyed as ne'er another,
 took the scroll, saying only: <q direct="unspecified">Comrade, leave that to me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09050051" />Now Nello, whom Calandrino mistrusted, entered with no less
 zest than the others into the affair, and was their confederate for
 Calandrino's discomfiture; accordingly by Bruno's direction he hied
 to Florence, and finding Monna Tessa:  <milestone id="p09050052" /><q direct="unspecified">Thou hast scarce forgotten,
 Tessa,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what a beating Calandrino gave thee,
 without the least cause, that day when he came home with the stones
 from Mugnone; for which I would have thee be avenged, and, so
 thou wilt not, call me no more kinsman or friend. He is fallen in
 love with a lady up there, who is abandoned enough to go closeting
 herself not seldom with him, and 'tis but a short while since they
 made assignation to forgather forthwith: so I would have thee go
 there, and surprise him in the act, and give him a sound trouncing.</q>
  <milestone id="p09050053" />Which when the lady heard, she deemed it no laughing matter; but
 started up and broke out with: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, the arrant knave! is't thus
 he treats me? By the Holy Rood, never fear but I will pay him
 out!</q>  <milestone id="p09050054" />And wrapping herself in her cloak, and taking a young woman
 with her for companion, she sped more at a run than at a walk, escorted
 by Nello, up to Camerata. Bruno, espying her from afar, said to
 Filippo: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, here comes our friend.</q>  <milestone id="p09050055" />Whereupon Filippo went
 to the place where Calandrino and the others were at work, and
 said: <q direct="unspecified">My masters, I must needs go at once to Florence; slacken
 not on that account.</q> And so off he went, and hid himself where,
 unobserved, he might see what Calandrino would do.  <milestone id="p09050056" />Calandrino
 waited only until he saw that Filippo was at some distance, and then
 he went down into the courtyard, where he found Niccolosa alone,
 and fell a talking with her. She, knowing well what she had to do,
 drew close to him, and shewed him a little more familiarity than she
 was wont: whereupon Calandrino touched her with the scroll,  <milestone id="p09050057" />and
 having so done, saying never a word, bent his steps towards the
 <pb n="288" />barn, whither Niccolosa followed him, and being entered, shut the
 door, and forthwith embraced him, threw him down on the straw
 that lay there, and got astride of him, and holding him fast by the
 arms about the shoulders, suffered him not to approach his face to
 hers, but gazing upon him, as if he were the delight of her heart:
  <milestone id="p09050058" /><q direct="unspecified">O Calandrino, sweet my Calandrino,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">heart of my
 body, my very soul, my bliss, my consolation, ah! how long have I
 yearned to hold thee in my arms and have thee all my own! Thy
 endearing ways have utterly disarmed me; thou hast made prize of
 my heart with thy rebeck. Do I indeed hold thee in mine embrace?</q>
  <milestone id="p09050059" />Calandrino, scarce able to move, murmured: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! sweet
 my soul, suffer me to kiss thee.</q>  <milestone id="p09050060" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but thou art
 too hasty,</q> replied Niccolosa. <q direct="unspecified">Let me first feast mine eyes on
 thee; let me but sate them with this sweet face of thine.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09050061" />Meanwhile Bruno and Buffalmacco had joined Filippo, so that
 what passed was seen and heard by all three. And while Calandrino
 was thus intent to kiss Niccolosa, lo, up came Nello with Monna
 Tessa. <q direct="unspecified">By God, I swear they are both there,</q> ejaculated Nello,  <milestone id="p09050062" />as
 they entered the doorway; but the lady, now fairly furious, laid hold
 of him and thrust him aside, and rushing in, espied Niccolosa astride
 of Calandrino. Niccolosa no sooner caught sight of the lady, than
 up she jumped, and in a trice was beside Filippo.  <milestone id="p09050063" />Monna Tessa fell
 upon Calandrino, who was still on the floor, planted her nails in his
 face, and scratched it all over: she then seized him by the hair, and
 haling him to and fro about the barn: <q direct="unspecified">Foul, pestilent cur,</q> quoth
 she, <q direct="unspecified">is this the way thou treatest me? Thou old fool! A murrain
 on the love I have borne thee! Hast thou not enough to do at
 home, that thou must needs go falling in love with strange women?
  <milestone id="p09050064" />And a fine lover thou wouldst make! Dost not know thyself,
 knave? Dost not know thyself, wretch? Thou, from whose whole
 body 'twere not possible to wring enough sap for a sauce! God's
 faith, 'twas not Tessa that got thee with child: God's curse on her,
 whoever she was: verily she must be a poor creature to be enamoured
 of a jewel of thy rare quality.</q>  <milestone id="p09050065" />At sight of his wife, Calandrino,
 suspended, as it were, between life and death, ventured no defence; but,
 his face torn to shreds, his hair and clothes all disordered, fumbled about
 for his capuche, which having found, up he got, and humbly besought
 his wife not to publish the matter, unless she were minded that he
 <pb n="289" />should be cut to pieces, for that she that was with him was the wife
 of the master of the house. <q direct="unspecified">Then God give her a bad year,</q>
 replied the lady.  <milestone id="p09050066" />Whereupon Bruno and Buffalmacco, who by this
 time had laughed their fill with Filippo and Niccolosa, came up as if
 attracted by the noise; and after not a little ado pacified the lady,
 and counselled Calandrino to go back to Florence, and stay there,
 lest Filippo should get wind of the affair, and do him a mischief.
  <milestone id="p09050067" />So Calandrino, crestfallen and woebegone, got him back to Florence
 with his face torn to shreds; where, daring not to shew himself at
 Camerata again, he endured day and night the grievous torment of
 his wife's vituperation. Such was the issue, to which, after ministering
 not a little mirth to his comrades, as also to Niccolosa and Filippo,
 this ardent lover brought his amour.</p></div2>