<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov1002"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00020001" />Ghino di Tacco captures the Abbot of Cluny, cures him of
 a disorder of the stomach, and releases him. The
 abbot, on his return to the court of Rome, reconciles
 Ghino with Pope Boniface, and makes him prior of
 the Hospital.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00020002" />When an end was made of extolling the magnificence shewn by
 King Alfonso towards the Florentine knight, the king, who had
 listened to the story with no small pleasure, bade Elisa follow suit;
 and forthwith Elisa began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00020003" />Dainty my ladies, undeniable it is that
 for a king to be magnificent, and to entreat magnificently one that
 has done him service, is a great matter, and meet for commendation.
 What then shall we say when the tale is of a dignitary of the Church
 that shewed wondrous magnificence towards one whom he might
 well have entreated as an enemy, and not have been blamed by a
 soul?  <milestone id="p00020004" />Assuredly nought else than that what in the king was virtue
 was in the prelate nothing less than a miracle, seeing that for superlative
 greed the clergy, one and all, outdo us women, and wage war
 to the knife upon every form of liberality. And albeit all men are
 by nature prone to avenge their wrongs, 'tis notorious that the clergy,
 however they may preach longsuffering, and commend of all things
 the forgiving of trespasses, are more quick and hot to be avenged
 than the rest of mankind. Now this, to wit, after what manner a
 prelate shewed magnificence, will be made manifest to you in my
 story.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00020005" />Ghino di Tacco, a man redoubtable by reason of his truculence
 and his high-handed deeds, being banished from Siena, and at enmity
 with the Counts of Santa Fiore, raised Radicofani in revolt against
 <pb n="318" />the Church of Rome, and there abiding, harried all the surrounding
 country with his soldiers, plundering all wayfarers.  <milestone id="p00020006" />Now Pope
 Boniface VIII. being at Rome, there came to court the Abbot
 of Cluny, who is reputed one of the wealthiest prelates in the
 world; and having there gotten a disorder of the stomach, he was
 advised by the physicians to go to the baths of Siena, where (they
 averred) he would certainly be cured. So, having obtained the
 Pope's leave, reckless of the bruit of Ghino's exploits, he took the
 road, being attended by a great and well-equipped train of sumpter-horses
 and servants.  <milestone id="p00020007" />Ghino di Tacco, getting wind of his approach,
 spread his nets to such purpose as without the loss of so much as a
 boy to surround the abbot, with all his servants and effects, in a
 strait pass, from which there was no exit. Which done, he sent
 one of his men, the cunningest of them all, with a sufficient retinue to
 the abbot, who most lovingly on Ghino's part besought the abbot to
 come and visit Ghino at the castle.  <milestone id="p00020008" />Whereto the abbot, very wroth,
 made answer that he would none of it, for that nought had he to do
 with Ghino; but that he purposed to continue his journey, and
 would fain see who would hinder him.  <milestone id="p00020009" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> returned the envoy,
 assuming a humble tone, <q direct="unspecified">you are come to a part of the country
 where we have no fear of aught save the might of God, and where
 excommunications and interdicts are one and all under the ban;
 wherefore you were best be pleased to shew yourself agreeable to
 Ghino in this particular.</q>  <milestone id="p00020010" />As they thus spoke, Ghino's soldiers
 shewed themselves on every side, and it being thus manifest to the
 abbot that he and his company were taken prisoners, he, albeit
 mightily incensed, suffered himself with all his train and effects to be
 conducted by the envoy to the castle; where the abbot, being
 alighted, was lodged in a small and very dark and discomfortable
 room, while his retinue, according to their several conditions, were
 provided with comfortable quarters in divers parts of the castle, the
 horses well stabled and all the effects secured, none being in any
 wise tampered with.  <milestone id="p00020011" />Which done, Ghino hied him to the abbot,
 and: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">Ghino, whose guest you are, sends me to
 entreat you to be pleased to inform him of your destination, and the
 purpose of your journey.</q>  <milestone id="p00020012" />The abbot, vailing his pride like a wise
 man, told whither he was bound and for what purpose. Whereupon
 Ghino left him, casting about how he might cure him without a
 <pb n="319" />bath. To which end he kept a great fire ever burning in the little
 chamber, and had it closely guarded, and returned not to the abbot
 until the ensuing morning, when he brought him in a spotless napkin
 two slices of toast and a great beaker of vernaccia of Corniglia, being
 of the abbot's own vintage;  <milestone id="p00020013" />and: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he to the abbot,
 <q direct="unspecified">Ghino, as a young man, made his studies in medicine, and avers that
 he then learned that there is no better treatment for disorder of the
 stomach than that which he will afford you, whereof the matters
 that I bring you are the beginning; wherefore take them and be of
 good cheer.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00020014" />The abbot, being far too hungry to make many words about the
 matter, ate (albeit in high dudgeon) the toast, and drank the vernaccia;
 which done, he enlarged on his wrongs in a high tone, with
 much questioning and perpending; and above all he demanded to see
 Ghino.  <milestone id="p00020015" />Part of what the abbot said Ghino disregarded as of no
 substance, to other part he replied courteously enough; and having
 assured him that Ghino would visit him as soon as might be, he took
 his leave of him; nor did he return until the morrow, when he
 brought him toast and vernaccia in the same quantity as before;
 and so he kept him several days: then, having marked that the
 abbot had eaten some dried beans that he had secretly brought and
 left there of set purpose,  <milestone id="p00020016" />he asked him in Ghino's name how he
 felt in the stomach. <q direct="unspecified">Were I but out of Ghino's hands,</q> replied the
 abbot, <q direct="unspecified">I should feel myself well, indeed: next to which, I desire
 most of all a good breakfast, so excellent a cure have his medicines
 wrought on me.</q>  <milestone id="p00020017" />Whereupon Ghino caused the abbot's servants to
 furnish a goodly chamber with the abbot's own effects, and there
 on the morrow make ready a grand banquet, at which all the abbot's
 suite and not a few of the garrison being assembled, he hied him to
 the abbot, and: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis time you left the infirmary,
 seeing that you now feel yourself well;</q> and so saying, he took him
 by the hand, and led him into the chamber made ready for him, and
 having left him there with his own people, made it his chief concern
 that the banquet should be magnificent.  <milestone id="p00020018" />The abbot's spirits revived
 as he found himself again among his men, with whom he talked a
 while, telling them how he had been entreated, wherewith they
 contrasted the signal honour which they, on the other hand, had,
 one and all, received from Ghino.</p><pb n="320" /><p>Breakfast-time came, and with order meet the abbot and the
 rest were regaled with good viands and good wines, Ghino still
 suffering not the abbot to know who he was.  <milestone id="p00020019" />But when the abbot
 had thus passed several days, Ghino, having first had all his effects
 collected in a saloon, and all his horses, to the poorest jade, in the
 courtyard below, hied him to the abbot and asked him how he felt,
 and if he deemed himself strong enough to ride. The abbot replied
 that he was quite strong enough, and that 'twould be well indeed
 with him, were he once out of Ghino's hands.  <milestone id="p00020020" />Ghino then led him
 into the saloon in which were his effects and all his retinue, and
 having brought him to a window, whence he might see all his horses:
  <milestone id="p00020021" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir Abbot,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">you must know that 'tis not for that he
 has an evil heart, but because, being a gentleman, he is banished from
 his home, and reduced to poverty, and has not a few powerful enemies,
 that in defence of his life and honour, Ghino di Tacco, whom you see
 before you, has become a robber of highways and an enemy to the
 court of Rome.  <milestone id="p00020022" />But such as I am, I have cured you of your malady
 of the stomach, and taking you to be a worthy lord, I purpose not to
 treat you as I would another, from whom, were he in my hands, as
 you are, I should take such part of his goods as I should think fit;
 but I shall leave it to you, upon consideration of my need, to assign
 to me such portion of your goods as you yourself shall determine.
  <milestone id="p00020023" />Here are they before you undiminished and unimpaired, and from
 this window you may see your horses below in the courtyard;
 wherefore take the part or take the whole, as you may see fit, and
 be it at your option to tarry here, or go hence, from this hour
 forth.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00020024" />The abbot marvelled to hear a highway robber speak thus
 liberally, and such was his gratification that his wrath and fierce
 resentment departed from him, nay, were transformed into kindness,
 insomuch that in all cordial amity he hasted to embrace Ghino,
 saying:  <milestone id="p00020025" /><q direct="unspecified">By God I swear, that to gain the friendship of a man such
 I now deem thee to be, I would be content to suffer much greater
 wrong than that which until now, meseemed, thou hadst done me.
 Cursed be Fortune that constrains thee to ply so censurable a trade.</q>
  <milestone id="p00020026" />Which said, he selected a very few things, and none superfluous,
 from his ample store, and having done likewise with the horses, ceded
 all else to Ghino, and hied him back to Rome;  <milestone id="p00020027" />where, seeing him,
 the Pope, who to his great grief had heard of his capture, asked him
 <pb n="321" />what benefit he had gotten from the baths. Whereto the abbot
 made answer with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">Holy Father, I found nearer here than
 the baths a worthy physician who has wrought a most excellent cure
 on me:</q> he then recounted all the circumstances, whereat the Pope
 laughed. Afterwards, still pursuing the topic, the abbot, yielding to
 the promptings of magnificence, asked a favour of the Pope;  <milestone id="p00020028" />who,
 expecting that he would ask somewhat else than he did, liberally
 promised to give him whatever he should demand. Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Holy Father,</q> quoth the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">that which I would crave of you
 is that you restore Ghino di Tacco, my physician, to your favour;
 seeing that among the good men and true and meritorious that I have
 known, he is by no means of the least account. And for the evil life
 that he leads, I impute it to Fortune rather than to him:  <milestone id="p00020029" />change then
 his fortune, by giving him the means whereby he may live in manner
 befitting his rank, and I doubt not that in a little while your
 judgment of him will jump with mine.</q> 
	<milestone id="p00020030" />Whereto the Pope, being
 magnanimous, and an admirer of good men and true, made answer
 that so he would gladly do, if Ghino should prove to be such as the
 abbot said; and that he would have him brought under safe conduct
 to Rome.  <milestone id="p00020031" />Thither accordingly under safe conduct came Ghino, to
 the abbot's great delight; nor had he been long at court before the
 Pope approved his worth, and restored him to his favour, granting
 him a great office, to wit, that of prior of the Hospital, whereof he
 made him knight. Which office he held for the rest of his life,
 being ever a friend and vassal of Holy Church and the Abbot of
 Cluny.</p></div2>