<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0605"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06050001" />Messer Forese da Rabatta and Master Giotto, the
painter, journeying together from Mugello, deride one another's scurvy
appearance.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06050002" />Neifile being silent, and the ladies having made
	very merry over Chichibio's retort, Pamfilo at the queen's command thus spoke:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06050003" />Dearest ladies, if Fortune, as Pampinea has shewn us, does sometimes
	hide treasures most rich of native worth in the obscurity of base occupations, so in like
	manner 'tis not seldom found that Nature has enshrined prodigies of wit in the most
	ignoble of human forms.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06050004" />Whereof a notable example is afforded by two of our citizens,
 of whom I purpose for a brief while to discourse. The one, Messer Forese da Rabatta by
 name, was short and deformed of person and withal flat-cheeked and flat-nosed, insomuch
 that never a Baroncio<note>The name of a Florentine family famous for the extraordinary
 ugliness of its men: whereby it came to pass that any grotesque or extremely ugly man was
 called a Baroncio. Fanfani, Vocab. della Lingua Italiana,
 1891.</note> had a visage so misshapen but his would have shewed as hideous beside it;
 yet so conversant was this man with the laws, that by not a few of those well able to
 form an opinion he was reputed a veritable storehouse of civil jurisprudence. 
<milestone id="p06050005" />The other, whose name was Giotto, was of so excellent a wit that, let
 Nature, mother of all, operant ever by continual revolution of the heavens, fashion what
 she would, he with his style and pen and pencil would depict its like on such wise that
 it shewed not as its like, but rather as the thing itself, insomuch that the visual sense
 of men did often err in regard thereof, mistaking for real that which was but
 painted. <milestone id="p06050006" />Wherefore, having brought back to light that art which
 had for many ages lain buried beneath the blunders of those who painted rather to delight
 the eyes of the ignorant than to satisfy the intelligence of the wise, he may deservedly
 be called one of the lights that compose the glory of <pb n="86" />Florence, and the more
 so, the more lowly was the spirit in which he won that glory, who, albeit he was, while
 he yet lived, the master of others, yet did ever refuse to be called their
 master. <milestone id="p06050007" />And this title that he rejected adorned him with a
 lustre the more splendid in proportion to the avidity with which it was usurped by those
 who were less knowing than he, or were his pupils. <milestone id="p06050008" />But for all
 the exceeding greatness of his art, yet in no particular had he the advantage of Messer
 Forese either in form or in feature. But to come to the story: 
<milestone id="p06050009" />'Twas in Mugello that Messer Forese, as likewise Giotto, had his
 country-seat, whence returning from a sojourn that he had made there during the summer
 vacation of the courts, and being, as it chanced, mounted on a poor jade of a draught
 horse, he fell in with the said Giotto, who was also on his way back to Florence after a
 like sojourn on his own estate, and was neither better mounted, nor in any other wise
 better equipped, than Messer Forese. And so, being both old men, they jogged on together
 at a slow pace: <milestone id="p06050010" />and being surprised by a sudden shower, such as
 we frequently see fall in summer, they presently sought shelter in the house of a
 husbandman that was known to each of them, and was their friend. 
    <milestone id="p06050011" />But after a while, as the rain gave no sign of ceasing, and they had a
 mind to be at Florence that same day, they borrowed of the husbandman two old cloaks of
 Romagnole cloth, and two hats much the worse for age (there being no better to be had),
 and resumed their journey.  <milestone id="p06050012" />Whereon they had not proceeded far,
 when, taking note that they were soaked through and through, and liberally splashed with
 the mud cast up by their nags' hooves (circumstances which are not of a kind to add to
 one's dignity), they, after long silence, the sky beginning to brighten a little, began
 to converse. <milestone id="p06050013" />And Messer Forese, as he rode and hearkened to
 Giotto, who was an excellent talker, surveyed him sideways, and from head to foot, and
 all over, and seeing him in all points in so sorry and scurvy a trim, and recking nought
 of his own appearance, broke into a laugh and said: <milestone id="p06050014" /><q direct="unspecified">Giotto,
 would e'er a stranger that met us, and had not seen thee before, believe, thinkst thou,
 that thou wert, as thou art, the greatest painter in the world.</q> 
<milestone id="p06050015" />Whereto Giotto answered promptly: <q direct="unspecified">Methinks, Sir, he might, if, scanning
 you, he gave you credit for knowing the A B C.</q> <milestone id="p06050016" />Which
 hearing, Messer Forese recognized his error, and perceived that he had gotten as good as
 he brought.</p></div2>