<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov1005"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00050001" />Madonna Dianora craves of Messer Ansaldo a garden
 that shall be as fair in January as in May. Messer
 Ansaldo binds himself to a necromancer, and thereby
 gives her the garden. Her husband gives her leave
 to do Messer Ansaldo's pleasure: he, being apprised
 of her husband's liberality, releases her from her
 promise; and the necromancer releases Messer Ansaldo
 from his bond, and will take nought of his.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00050002" />Each of the gay company had with superlative commendation
 extolled Messer Gentile to the skies, when the king bade Emilia
 follow suit; and with a good courage, as burning to speak, thus
 Emilia began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00050003" />Delicate my ladies, none can justly say that 'twas
 not magnificently done of Messer Gentile; but if it be alleged that
 'twas the last degree of magnificence, 'twill perchance not be
 difficult to shew that more was possible, as is my purpose in the little
 story that I shall tell you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00050004" />In Friuli, a country which, though its air is shrewd, is pleasantly
 diversified by fine mountains and not a few rivers and clear
 fountains, is a city called Udine, where dwelt of yore a fair and
 noble lady, Madonna Dianora by name, wife of a wealthy grandee
 named Giliberto, a very pleasant gentleman, and debonair. Now
 this lady, for her high qualities, was in the last degree beloved by
 a great and noble baron, Messer Ansaldo Gradense by name, a
 man of no little consequence, and whose fame for feats of arms and
 courtesy was spread far and wide.  <milestone id="p00050005" />But, though with all a lover's
 ardour he left nought undone that he might do to win her love, and
 to that end frequently plied her with his ambassages, 'twas all in
 <pb n="336" />vain. And the lady being distressed by his importunity, and chat,
 refuse as she might all that he asked of her, he none the less
 continued to love her and press his suit upon her, bethought her how
 she might rid herself of him by requiring of him an extraordinary
 and, as she deemed, impossible feat.  <milestone id="p00050006" />So one day, a woman that came
 oftentimes from him to her being with her: <q direct="unspecified">Good woman,</q>
 quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">thou hast many a time affirmed that Messer Ansaldo
 loves me above all else; and thou hast made proffer to me on his
 part of wondrous rich gifts which I am minded he keep to himself,
 for that I could never bring myself to love him or pleasure him for
 their sake; but, if I might be certified that he loves me as
 much as thou sayst, then without a doubt I should not fail to love
 him, and do his pleasure; wherefore, so he give me the assurance
 that I shall require, I shall be at his command.</q>  <milestone id="p00050007" /><q direct="unspecified">What is it,
 Madam,</q> returned the good woman, <q direct="unspecified">that you would have him do?</q>
  <milestone id="p00050008" /><q direct="unspecified">This,</q> replied the lady; <q direct="unspecified">I would have this next ensuing January,
 hard by this city, a garden full of green grass and flowers and
 flowering trees, just as if it were May; and if he cannot provide me
 with this garden, bid him never again send either thee or any other
 to me, for that, should he harass me any further, I shall no longer
 keep silence, as I have hitherto done, but shall make my complaint
 to my husband and all my kinsmen, and it shall go hard but I will be
 quit of him.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00050009" />The gentleman being apprised of his lady's stipulation and
 promise, notwithstanding that he deemed it no easy matter, nay, a
 thing almost impossible, to satisfy her, and knew besides that 'twas
 but to deprive him of all hope that she made the demand, did nevertheless
 resolve to do his endeavour to comply with it, and causing
 search to be made in divers parts of the world, if any he might find
 to afford him counsel or aid, he lit upon one, who for a substantial
 reward offered to do the thing by necromancy.  <milestone id="p00050010" />So Messer Ansaldo,
 having struck the bargain with him for an exceeding great sum of
 money, gleefully expected the appointed time. Which being come
 with extreme cold, insomuch that there was nought but snow and
 ice, the adept on the night before the calends of January wrought
 with his spells to such purpose that on the morrow, as was averred by
 eye-witnesses, there appeared in a meadow hard by the city one of
 the most beautiful gardens that was ever seen, with no lack of grass
 <pb n="337" />and trees and fruits of all sorts.  <milestone id="p00050011" />At sight whereof Messer Ansaldo
 was overjoyed, and caused some of the finest fruits and flowers that
 it contained to be gathered, and privily presented to his lady, whom
 he bade come and see the garden that she had craved, that thereby
 she might have assurance of his love, and mind her of the promise
 that she had given him and confirmed with an oath, and, as a loyal
 lady, take thought for its performance.  <milestone id="p00050012" />When she saw the flowers
 and fruits, the lady, who had already heard not a few folk speak of
 the wondrous garden, began to repent her of her promise. But for
 all that, being fond of strange sights, she hied her with many other
 ladies of the city to see the garden, and having gazed on it with
 wonderment, and commended it not a little, she went home the
 saddest woman alive, bethinking her to what it bound her:  <milestone id="p00050013" />and so
 great was her distress that she might not well conceal it; but, being
 written on her face, 'twas marked by her husband, who was minded
 by all means to know the cause thereof.</p><p>The lady long time kept silence: but at last she yielded to his
 urgency, and discovered to him the whole matter from first to last.
  <milestone id="p00050014" />Whereat Giliberto was at first very wroth; but on second thoughts,
 considering the purity of the lady's purpose, he was better advised,
 and dismissing his anger: <q direct="unspecified">Dianora,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not the act
 of a discreet or virtuous lady to give ear to messages of such a sort,
 nor to enter into any compact touching her chastity with any man
 on any terms. Words that the ears convey to the heart have a
 potency greater than is commonly supposed, and there is scarce
 aught that lovers will not find possible.  <milestone id="p00050015" />'Twas then ill done of thee
 in the first instance to hearken, as afterwards to make the compact;
 but, for that I know the purity of thy soul, that thou mayst be quit
 of thy promise, I will grant thee that which, perchance, no other man
 would grant, being also swayed thereto by fear of the necromancer,
 whom Messer Ansaldo, shouldst thou play him false, might, peradventure,
 cause to do us a mischief.  <milestone id="p00050016" />I am minded, then, that thou
 go to him, and contrive, if on any wise thou canst, to get thee quit of
 this promise without loss of virtue; but if otherwise it may not be,
 then for the nonce thou mayst yield him thy body, but not thy soul.</q>
  <milestone id="p00050017" />Whereat the lady, weeping, would none of such a favour at her
 husband's hands. But Giliberto, for all the lady's protestations, was
 minded that so it should be.</p><pb n="338" /><p>Accordingly, on the morrow about dawn, apparelled none too
 ornately, preceded by two servants and followed by a chambermaid,
 the lady hied her to Messer Ansaldo's house.  <milestone id="p00050018" />Apprised that his lady
 was come to see him, Messer Ansaldo, marvelling not a little, rose,
 and having called the necromancer: <q direct="unspecified">I am minded,</q> quoth he,
 <q direct="unspecified">that thou see what goodly gain I have gotten by thine art.</q> And
 the twain having met the lady, Ansaldo gave way to no unruly
 appetite, but received her with a seemly obeisance; and then the
 three repaired to a goodly chamber, where there was a great fire, and
 having caused the lady to be seated, thus spoke Ansaldo:  <milestone id="p00050019" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,
 if the love that I have so long borne you merit any guerdon, I pray
 you that it be not grievous to you to discover to me the true occasion
 of your coming to me at this hour, and thus accompanied.</q>  <milestone id="p00050020" />Shamefast,
 and the tears all but standing in her eyes, the lady made
 answer: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, 'tis neither love that I bear you, nor faith that I
 pledged you, that brings me hither, but the command of my husband,
 who, regarding rather the pains you have had of your unbridled
 passion than his own or my honour, has sent me hither; and for that
 he commands it, I, for the nonce, am entirely at your pleasure.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00050021" />If Messer Ansaldo had marvelled to hear of the lady's coming,
 he now marvelled much more, and touched by Giliberto's liberality,
 and passing from passion to compassion:  <milestone id="p00050022" /><q direct="unspecified">Now, God forbid,
 Madam,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that, it being as you say, I should wound the
 honour of him that has compassion on my love; wherefore, no
 otherwise than as if you were my sister shall you abide here, while
 you are so minded, and be free to depart at your pleasure; nor crave
 I aught of you but that you shall convey from me to your husband
 such thanks as you shall deem meet for courtesy such as his has been,
 and entreat me ever henceforth as your brother and servant.</q>
  <milestone id="p00050023" />Whereat overjoyed in the last degree: <q direct="unspecified">Nought,</q> quoth the lady,
 <q direct="unspecified">by what I noted of your behaviour, could ever have caused me to
 anticipate other sequel of my coming hither than this which I see is
 your will, and for which I shall ever be your debtor.</q> She then
 took her leave, and, attended by a guard of honour, returned to
 Giliberto, and told him what had passed; between whom and Messer
 Ansaldo there was thenceforth a most close and loyal friendship.</p><p><milestone id="p00050024" />Now the liberality shewn by Giliberto towards Messer Ansaldo,
 and by Messer Ansaldo towards the lady, having been marked by
 <pb n="339" />the necromancer, when Messer Ansaldo made ready to give him the
 promised reward: <q direct="unspecified">Now God forbid,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that, as I have
 seen Giliberto liberal in regard of his honour, and you liberal in
 regard of your love, I be not in like manner liberal in regard of my
 reward, which accordingly, witting that 'tis in good hands, I am
 minded that you keep.</q>  <milestone id="p00050025" />The knight was abashed, and strove hard
 to induce him to take, if not the whole, at least a part of the money;
 but finding that his labour was in vain, and that the necromancer,
 having caused his garden to vanish after the third day, was minded
 to depart, he bade him adieu. And the carnal love he had borne
 the lady being spent, he burned for her thereafter with a flame of
 honourable affection.  <milestone id="p00050026" />Now what shall be our verdict in this case,
 lovesome ladies? A lady, as it were dead, and a love grown lukewarm
 for utter hopelessness! Shall we set a liberality shewn in such
 a case above this liberality of Messer Ansaldo, loving yet as ardently,
 and hoping, perchance, yet more ardently than ever, and holding
 in his hands the prize that he had so long pursued? Folly indeed
 should I deem it to compare that liberality with this.</p></div2>