<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d05conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p05970001" />Dioneo's story, whereat the ladies laughed the less for shamefastness
 rather than for disrelish, being ended, the queen, taking
 note that the term of her sovereignty was come, rose to her feet,
 and took off the laurel wreath and set it graciously upon Elisa's
 head, saying: <q direct="unspecified"> Madam, 'tis now your turn to bear sway.</q>  <milestone id="p05970002" />The
 dignity accepted, Elisa followed in all respects the example of her
 predecessors: she first conferred with the seneschal, and directed him
 how meetly to order all things during the time of her sovereignty;
 which done to the satisfaction of the company: <milestone id="p05970003" /><q direct="unspecified">Ofttimes,</q> quoth
 <pb n="69" />she, <q direct="unspecified">have we heard how with bright sallies, and ready retorts, and
 sudden devices, not a few have known how to repugn with apt checks
 the bites of others, or to avert imminent perils; and because 'tis an
 excellent argument, and may be profitable, I ordain that to-morrow,
 God helping us, the following be the rule of our discourse; to wit,
 that it be of such as by some sprightly sally have repulsed an attack,
 or by some ready retort or device have avoided loss, peril or scorn.</q>
  <milestone id="p05970004" />The rule being heartily approved by all, the queen rose and dismissed
 them till supper-time.  <milestone id="p05970005" />So the honourable company, seeing the queen
 risen, rose all likewise, and as their wont was, betook them to their
 diversions as to each seemed best.  <milestone id="p05970006" />But when the cicalas had hushed
 their chirping, all were mustered again for supper; and having blithely
 feasted, they all addressed them to song and dance.  <milestone id="p05970007" />And the queen,
 while Emilia led a dance, called for a song from Dioneo, who at once
 came out with: <title type="song">Monna Aldruda, come perk up thy mood, a piece
      of glad tidings I bring thee</title>.  <milestone id="p05970008" />Whereat all the ladies fell a laughing,
 and most of all the queen, who bade him give them no more of that,
 but sing another.  <milestone id="p05970009" />Quoth Dioneo: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, had I a tabret, I
	would sing: <title type="song">Up with your smock, Monna Lapa!</title> or: <title type="song">Oh!
 the greensward under the olive!</title> Or perchance you had liefer I
	should give you: <title type="song">Woe is me, the wave of the sea!</title> But no tabret
 have I: wherefore choose which of these others you will have.
	Perchance you would like: <title type="song">Now hie thee to us forth, that so it
 may be cut, as May the fields about</title>.</q> <milestone id="p05970010" /><q direct="unspecified">No,</q> returned the queen,
      <q direct="unspecified">give us another.</q> <milestone id="p05970011" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said Dioneo, <q direct="unspecified">I will sing: <title type="song">Monna
 Simona, embarrel, embarrel. Why, 'tis not the month of October</title>.</q>
      <note>The
	song is evidently amoebean.</note>
      <milestone id="p05970012" /><q direct="unspecified">Now a plague upon thee,</q> said the queen, with a laugh; <q direct="unspecified">give us
	a proper song, wilt thou? for we will have none of these.</q> <milestone id="p05970013" /><q direct="unspecified">Never
	fear, Madam,</q> replied Dioneo; <q direct="unspecified">only say which you prefer. I have
	more than a thousand songs by heart. Perhaps you would like:
	<title type="song">This my little covert, make I ne'er it overt</title>; or: 
	<title type="song">Gently, gently,
	  husband mine</title>; or: <title type="song">A hundred pounds were none too high a
	price for me a cock to buy</title>.</q>  <milestone id="p05970014" />The queen now shewed some offence,
      though the other ladies laughed, and: <q direct="unspecified">A truce to thy jesting,
	Dioneo,</q> said she, <q direct="unspecified">and give us a proper song: else thou mayst prove
	the quality of my ire.</q>  <milestone id="p05970015" />Whereupon Dioneo forthwith ceased his
      fooling, and sang on this wise:</p><pb n="70" /><div3 who="dioneo" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p05970016" /><l>So ravishing a light</l>
<l>Doth from the fair eyes of my mistress move</l>
<l>As keeps me slave to her and thee, O Love.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p05970017" /><l>A beam from those bright orbs did radiate</l>
<l>That flame that through mine own eyes to my breast</l>
<l>Did whilom entrance gain.</l>
<l>Thy majesty, O Love, thy might, how great</l>
<l>They be, 'twas her fair face did manifest:</l>
<l>Whereon to brood still fain,</l>
<l>I felt thee take and chain</l>
<l>Each sense, my soul enthralling on such wise</l>
<l>That she alone henceforth evokes my sighs.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p05970018" /><l>Wherefore, O dear my Lord, myself I own</l>
<l>Thy slave, and, all obedience, wait and yearn,</l>
<l>Till thy might me console.</l>
<l>Yet wot I not if it be throughly known</l>
<l>How noble is the flame wherewith I burn,</l>
<l>My loyalty how whole</l>
<l>To her that doth control</l>
<l>Ev'n in such sort my mind that shall I none,</l>
<l>Nor would I, peace receive, save hers alone.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p05970019" /><l>And so I pray thee, sweet my Lord, that thou</l>
<l>Give her to feel thy fire, and shew her plain</l>
<l>How grievous my disease.</l>
<l>This service deign to render; for that now</l>
<l>Thou seest me waste for love, and in the pain</l>
<l>Dissolve me by degrees:</l>
<l>And then the apt moment seize</l>
<l>My cause to plead with her, as is but due</l>
<l>From thee to me, who fain with thee would sue.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p05970020" />When Dioneo's silence shewed that his song was ended, the
 queen accorded it no stinted meed of praise; after which she
 caused not a few other songs to be sung.  <milestone id="p05970021" />Thus passed some part
 of the night; and then the queen, taking note that its freshness had
 vanquished the heat of the day, bade all go rest them, if they would,
 till the morning.</p></div2>