<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0201"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02010001" />Martellino pretends to be a paralytic, and makes it appear
 as if he were cured by being placed upon the body of
 St. Arrigo. His trick is detected; he is beaten and
 arrested, and is in peril of hanging, but finally escapes.</p></argument><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02010002" />Often has it happened, dearest ladies, that one who has studied
 to raise a laugh at others' expense, especially in regard of things
 worthy to be had in reverence, has found the laugh turn against himself,
 and sometimes to his loss: as, in obedience to the queen's
 command, and by way of introducing our theme, I am about to shew
 you, by the narrative of an adventure which befell one of our own
 citizens, and after a course of evil fortune had an entirely unexpected
 and very felicitous issue.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02010003" />Not long ago there was at Treviso a German, named Arrigo, a
 poor man who got his living as a common hired porter, but, though
 of so humble a condition, was respected by all, being accounted not
      only an honest but a most holy man; <milestone id="p02010004" />insomuch that, whether truly
 or falsely I know not, the Trevisans affirm, that on his decease all
 the bells of the cathedral of Treviso began to toll of their own accord.
 <milestone id="p02010005" />Which being accounted a miracle, this Arrigo was generally reputed
 a saint; and all the people of the city gathered before the house where
 his body lay, and bore it, with a saint's honours, into the cathedral,
 and brought thither the halt and paralytic and blind, and others
 afflicted with disease or bodily defects, as hoping that by contact with
 this holy body they would all be healed. <milestone id="p02010006" />The people thus tumultuously
 thronging the church, it so chanced that there arrived in
 Treviso three of our own citizens, of whom one was named Stecchi,
 another Martellino, and the third Marchese; all three being men
 <pb n="69" />whose habit it was to frequent the courts of the nobles and afford
 spectators amusement by assuming disguises and personating other
 men. Being entire strangers to the place, and seeing everybody
 running to and fro, they were much astonished, and having learned
 the why and wherefore, were curious to go see what was to be seen.
 <milestone id="p02010007" />So at the inn, where they put up, Marchese began: <q direct="unspecified">We would
 fain go see this saint; but for my part I know not how we are to
 reach the spot, for I hear the piazza is full of Germans and other
 armed men, posted there by the Lord who rules here to prevent an
 uproar, and moreover the church, so far as one may learn, is so full
 of folk that scarce another soul may enter it.</q> 
<milestone id="p02010008" />Whereupon Martellino,
 who was bent on seeing what was to be seen, said: <q direct="unspecified">Let not
 this deter us; I will assuredly find a way of getting to the saint's
 body.</q>
 <milestone id="p02010009" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> rejoined Marchese. 
<milestone id="p02010010" /><q direct="unspecified">I will tell you,</q> replied Martellino;
 <q direct="unspecified">I will counterfeit a paralytic, and thou wilt support me on one side
 and Stecchi on the other, as if I were not able to go alone, and so
 you will enter the church, making it appear as if you were leading
 me up to the body of the saint that he may heal me, and all that see
 will make way and give us free passage.</q> 
<milestone id="p02010011" />Marchese and Stecchi
 approved the plan; so all three forthwith left the inn and repaired to
 a lonely place, where Martellino distorted his hands, his fingers, his
 arms, his legs, and also his mouth and eyes and his entire face in a
 manner horrible to contemplate; so that no stranger that saw him
 could have doubted that he was impotent and paralysed in every part
 of his body. <milestone id="p02010012" />In this guise Marchese and Stecchi laid hold of him,
 and led him towards the church, assuming a most piteous air, and
 humbly beseeching everybody for God's sake to make way for them.
 Their request was readily granted; and, in short, observed by all,
 and crying out at almost every step, <q direct="unspecified">make way, make way,</q> they
 reached the place where St. Arrigo's body was laid. Whereupon
 some gentlemen who stood by hoisted Martellino on to the saint's
 body, that thereby he might receive the boon of health. <milestone id="p02010013" />There he
 lay still for a while, the eyes of all in the church being riveted upon
 him in expectation of the result; then, being a very practised performer,
 he stretched, first, one of his fingers, next a hand, afterwards
 an arm, and so forth, making as if he gradually recovered the use of
 all his natural powers. Which the people observing raised such a
 clamour in honour of St. Arrigo that even thunder would have been
 <pb n="70" />inaudible.
 <milestone id="p02010014" />Now it chanced that hard by stood a Florentine, who
 knew Martellino well, though he had failed to recognise him, when,
 in such strange guise, he was led into the church; but now, seeing
 him resume his natural shape, the Florentine recognised him, and at
 once said with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">God's curse upon him. Who that saw
 him come but would have believed that he was really paralysed?</q>
 <milestone id="p02010015" />These words were overheard by some of the Trevisans, who began
 forthwith to question the Florentine. <q direct="unspecified">How?</q> said they; <q direct="unspecified">was
 he then not paralysed?</q> 
<milestone id="p02010016" /><q direct="unspecified">No, by God!</q> returned the Florentine;
 <q direct="unspecified">he has always been as straight as any of us; he has merely
 shewn you that he knows better than any man alive how to play
 this trick of putting on any counterfeit semblance that he chooses.</q>
 <milestone id="p02010017" />Thereupon the Trevisans, without further parley, made a rush, clearing
 the way and crying out as they went: <q direct="unspecified">Seize this traitor who
 mocks at God and His saints; who, being no paralytic, has come
 hither in the guise of a paralytic to deride our patron saint and us.</q>
 <milestone id="p02010018" />So saying, they laid hands on him, dragged him down from where
 he stood, seized him by the hair, tore the clothes from his back, and
 fell to beating and kicking him, so that it seemed to him as if all the
 world were upon him. <milestone id="p02010019" />He cried out: <q direct="unspecified">Pity, for God's sake,</q> and
 defended himself as best he could: all in vain, however; the press
 became thicker and thicker moment by moment. <milestone id="p02010020" />Which Stecchi and
 Marchese observing began to say one to the other that 'twas a bad
 business; yet, being apprehensive on their own account, they did not
 venture to come to his assistance, but cried out with the rest that he
 ought to die, at the same time, however, casting about how they
 might find the means to rescue him from the hands of the people,
 who would certainly have killed him, but for a diversion which
 Marchese hastily effected. <milestone id="p02010021" />The entire posse of the signory being just
 outside, he ran off at full speed to the Podest&#224;'s lieutenant, and
 said
 to him: <q direct="unspecified">Help, for God's sake; there is a villain here that has cut
 my purse with full a hundred florins of gold in it; prithee have him
 arrested that I may have my own again.</q> <milestone id="p02010022" />Whereupon, twelve
 sergeants or more ran forthwith to the place where hapless Martellino
 was being carded without a comb, and, forcing their way with the
 utmost difficulty through the throng, rescued him all bruised and
 battered from their hands, and led him to the palace; whither he was
 followed by many who, resenting what he had done, and hearing that
 <pb n="71" />he was arrested as a cutpurse, and lacking better pretext for harassing
 him, began one and all to charge him with having cut their purses.
 <milestone id="p02010023" />All which the deputy of the Podest&#224; had no sooner heard, than, being
 a harsh man, he straightway took Martellino aside and began to
 examine him. <milestone id="p02010024" />Martellino answered his questions in a bantering tone,
 making light of the arrest; whereat the deputy, losing patience, had
 him bound to the strappado, and caused him to receive a few hints of
 the cord with intent to extort from him a confession of his guilt, by
 way of preliminary to hanging him. <milestone id="p02010025" />Taken down from the strappado,
 and questioned by the deputy if what his accusers said were
 true, Martellino, as nothing was to be gained by denial, answered:
 <q direct="unspecified">My lord, I am ready to confess the truth; let but my accusers say,
 each of them, when and where I cut his purse, and I will tell you
 what I have and what I have not done.</q> 
<milestone id="p02010026" /><q direct="unspecified">So be it,</q> said the deputy,
 and caused a few of them to be summoned. Whereupon Martellino,
 being charged with having cut this, that or the other man's purse
 eight, six or four days ago, while others averred that he had cut their
 purses that very day, <milestone id="p02010027" />answered thus: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, these men lie in
 the throat, and for token that I speak true, I tell you that, so far from
 having been here as long as they make out, it is but very lately that
 I came into these parts, where I never was before; and no sooner was
 I come, than, as my ill-luck would have it, I went to see the body of
 this saint, and so have been carded as you see; and that what I say
 is true, his Lordship's intendant of arrivals, and his book, and also my
 host may certify. <milestone id="p02010028" />Wherefore, if you find that even so it is as I say,
 hearken not to these wicked men, and spare me the torture and death
 which they would have you inflict.</q> 
<milestone id="p02010029" />In this posture of affairs
 Marchese and Stecchi, learning that the Podest&#224;'s deputy was dealing
 rigorously with Martellino, and had already put him to the strappado,
 grew mightily alarmed. <q direct="unspecified">We have made a mess of it,</q> they said to
 themselves; <q direct="unspecified">we have only taken him out of the frying-pan to toss
 him into the fire.</q> 
<milestone id="p02010030" />So, hurrying hither and thither with the utmost
 zeal, they made diligent search until they found their host, and told
 him how matters stood. The host had his laugh over the affair, and
 then brought them to one Sandro Agolanti, who dwelt in Treviso
 and had great interest with the Lord of the place. The host laid the
 whole matter before Sandro, and, backed by Marchese and Stecchi,
 besought him to undertake Martellino's cause. <milestone id="p02010031" />Sandro, after many
 <pb n="72" />a hearty laugh, hied him to the Lord, who at his instance sent for
 Martellino. The messengers found Martellino still in his shirt before
 the deputy, at his wits' end, and all but beside himself with fear,
 because the deputy would hear nothing that he said in his defence.
 Indeed, the deputy, having a spite against Florentines, had quite
 made up his mind to have him hanged; he was therefore in the last
 degree reluctant to surrender him to the Lord, and only did so upon
 compulsion. <milestone id="p02010032" />Brought at length before the Lord, Martellino detailed
 to him the whole affair, and prayed him as the greatest of favours to
 let him depart in peace. <milestone id="p02010033" />The Lord had a hearty laugh over the
 adventure, and bestowed a tunic on each of the three. So, congratulating
 themselves on their unexpected deliverance from so great
 a peril, they returned home safe and sound.</p></div2>