<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0604"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06040001" />Chichibio, cook to Currado Gianfigliazzi, owes his
	safety to a ready answer, whereby he converts Currado's wrath into laughter, and evades
	the evil fate with which Currado had threatened him.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06040002" />Lauretta being now silent, all lauded Nonna to
	the skies; after which Neifile received the queen's command to follow suit, and thus
	began:</p></div3><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06040003" />Albeit, loving ladies, ready wit not seldom ministers words apt and
	excellent and congruous with the circumstances of the speakers, 'tis also true that
	Fortune at times comes to the aid of the timid, and unexpectedly sets words upon the
	tongue, which in a quiet hour the speaker could never have found for himself: the which
	'tis my purpose to shew you by my story.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06040004" />Currado Gianfigliazzi, as the eyes and ears of each of you
may
 bear witness, has ever been a noble citizen of our city, open-handed
and magnificent, and one that lived as a gentleman should with
 hounds and
hawks, in which, to say nothing at present of more
 important matters, he
found unfailing delight. <milestone id="p06040005" />Now, having one
 day hard by Peretola despatched a
crane with one of his falcons,
 finding it young and plump, he sent it to
his excellent cook, a
 Venetian, Chichibio by name, bidding him roast it
for supper and
 make a dainty dish of it. <milestone id="p06040006" />Chichibio, who looked, as he was,
a
 very green-head, had dressed the crane, and set it to the fire and was

cooking it carefully, <milestone id="p06040007" />when, the bird being all but roasted, and the
 fumes
of the cooking very strong, it so chanced that a girl, Brunetta
 by name,
that lived in the same street, and of whom Chichibio was
 greatly
enamoured, came into the kitchen, and perceiving the smell
 <pb n="83" />and
seeing the bird, began coaxing Chichibio to give her a thigh.
 <milestone id="p06040008" />By way of
answer Chichibio fell a singing: <q direct="unspecified">You get it not from
 me, Madam
Brunetta, you get it not from me.</q> <milestone id="p06040009" />Whereat Madam
 Brunetta was offended,
and said to him: <q direct="unspecified">By God, if thou givest
 it me not, thou shalt never
have aught from me to pleasure thee.</q>
 In short there was not a little
altercation; and in the end Chichibio,
 fain not to vex his mistress, cut
off one of the crane's thighs, and
 gave it to her. <milestone id="p06040010" />So the bird was set
before Currado and some strangers
 that he had at table with him, and
Currado, observing that it had but
 one thigh, was surprised, and sent for
Chichibio, and demanded of
 him what was become of the missing thigh.
Whereto the mendacious
 Venetian answered readily: <q direct="unspecified">The crane, Sir, has
but one thigh and
 one leg.</q> <milestone id="p06040011" /><q direct="unspecified">What the devil?</q> rejoined Currado in
a rage: <q direct="unspecified">so the
 crane has but one thigh and one leg? thinkst thou I
never saw crane
 before this?</q> <milestone id="p06040012" />But Chichibio continued: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis even so
as I say,
 Sir; and, so please you, I will shew you that so it is in the
living
 bird.</q> <milestone id="p06040013" />Currado had too much respect for his guests to pursue
the
 topic; he only said: <q direct="unspecified">Since thou promisest to shew me in the
 living
bird what I have never seen or heard tell of, I bid thee do so
 to-morrow,
and I shall be satisfied, but if thou fail, I swear to thee
 by the body of
Christ that I will serve thee so that thou shalt ruefully
 remember my name
for the rest of thy days.</q></p><p><milestone id="p06040014" />No more was said of the matter that
evening, but on the morrow,
 at daybreak, Currado, who had by no means
slept off his wrath, got
 up still swelling therewith, and ordered his
horses, mounted Chichibio
 on a hackney, and saying to him: <q direct="unspecified">We shall
soon see which of us
 lied yesternight, thou or I,</q> set off with him for
a place where there
 was much water, beside which there were always cranes
to be seen
 about dawn. <milestone id="p06040015" />Chichibio, observing that Currado's ire was
unabated,
 and knowing not how to bolster up his lie, rode by Currado's
side
 in a state of the utmost trepidation, and would gladly, had he been
able, have taken to flight; but, as hemight not, he glanced, now
 ahead,
now aback, now aside, and saw everywhere nought but cranes
 standing on two
feet. <milestone id="p06040016" />However, as they approached the river, the
 very first thing they saw
upon the bank was a round dozen of cranes
 standing each and all on one
foot, as is their wont, when asleep.
 Which Chichibio presently pointed out
to Currado, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Now
 may you see well enough, Sir, that 'tis true as
I said yesternight, that
 <pb n="84" />the crane has but one thigh and one
leg; mark but how they stand
 over there.</q> <milestone id="p06040017" />Whereupon Currado:
<q direct="unspecified">Wait,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">and I
 will shew thee that they have each thighs
and legs twain.</q> So,
 having drawn a little nigher to them, he
ejaculated, <q direct="unspecified">Ohio!</q> Which
 caused the cranes to bring each the other
foot to the ground, and,
 after hopping a step or two, to take to flight.
Currado then turned
 to Chichibio, saying: <q direct="unspecified">How now, rogue? art satisfied
that the
 bird has thighs and legs twain?</q> <milestone id="p06040018" />Whereto Chichibio, all but
beside
 himself with fear, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Ay, Sir; but you cried not,
oho! to our crane of yestereve: had you done so, it would have
 popped its
other thigh and foot forth, as these have done.</q> <milestone id="p06040019" />Which
 answer Currado
so much relished, that, all his wrath changed to jollity
 and laughter:
<q direct="unspecified">Chichibio,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">thou art right, indeed I
 ought to have so
done.</q></p><p><milestone id="p06040020" />Thus did Chichibio by his ready and jocund retort arrest
impending
 evil, and make his peace with his master.</p></div2>