<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0702"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p07020001" />Her husband returning home, Peronella bestows her lover in a tun;
which, being sold by her husband, she avers
to have been already sold by herself to one that is inside examining it to see if it be
sound. Whereupon the lover jumps out, and causes the husband to scour the tun for him, and
afterwards to carry it to his house.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07020002" />Great indeed was the laughter with which Emilia's story was
	received; which being ended, and her orison commended by all as good and salutary, the
	king bade Filostrato follow suit; and thus Filostrato began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07020003" />Dearest my ladies,
	so many are the tricks that men play you, and most of all your husbands, that, when from
	time to time it so befalls that some lady plays her husband a trick, the circumstance,
	whether it come within your own cognizance or be told you by another, should not only give
	you joy but should incite you to publish it on all hands, that men may be ware, that,
	knowing as they are, their ladies also, on their part, know somewhat: <milestone id="p07020004" />which
	cannot but be serviceable to you, for that one does not rashly essay to take another with
	guile whom one wots not to lack that quality.
	<milestone id="p07020005" />Can we doubt, then, that, should but the converse that we shall hold
	to-day touching this matter come to be bruited among men, 'twould serve to put a most
	notable check upon the tricks they play you, by doing them to wit of the tricks, which
	you, in like manner, when you are so minded, may play them? <milestone id="p07020006" />Wherefore 'tis my
	intention to tell you in what manner a young girl, albeit she was but of low rank, did, on
	the spur of the moment, beguile her husband to her own deliverance.</p></div3><pb n="120" /><p><milestone id="p07020007" />'Tis no long time since at Naples a poor man, a mason by craft, took to wife a fair and
amorous maiden--Peronella was her name--who eked out by spinning what her husband made by
his craft; and so the pair managed as best they might on very slender
means. <milestone id="p07020008" />And as chance would have it, one of the gallants of the city, taking
note of this Peronella one day, and being mightily pleased with her, fell in love with
her, and by this means and that so prevailed that he won her to accord him her
intimacy. <milestone id="p07020009" />Their times of forgathering they concerted as follows: to wit, that,
her husband being wont to rise betimes of a morning to go to work or seek for work, the
gallant was to be where he might see him go forth, and, the street where she dwelt, which
is called Avorio, being scarce inhabited, was to come
into the house as soon as her husband was well out of it; and so times not a few they
did. <milestone id="p07020010" />But on one of these occasions it befell that, the good man being gone
forth, and Giannello Sirignario--such was the gallant's name--being come into the house,
and being with Peronella, after a while, back came the good man, though 'twas not his wont
to return until the day was done; and finding the door locked, he knocked, and after
knocking, he fell a saying to himself: <milestone id="p07020011" />O God, praised be Thy name forever; for
that, albeit Thou hast ordained that I be poor, at least Thou hast accorded me the
consolation of a good and honest girl for wife. Mark what haste she made to shut the door
when I was gone forth, that none else might enter to give her trouble.</p><p><milestone id="p07020012" />Now
Peronella knew by his knock that 'twas her husband; wherefore: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, Giannello
mine,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">I am a dead woman, for lo, here is my husband, foul fall him! come
back! What it may import, I know not, for he is never wont to come back at this hour;
perchance he caught sight of thee as thou camest in. <milestone id="p07020013" />However, for the love of
God, be it as it may, get thee into this tun that thou seest here, and I will go open to
him, and we shall see what is the occasion of this sudden return this morning.</q>
<milestone id="p07020014" />So Giannello forthwith got into the tun, and Peronella went to the door, and
let in her husband, and gave him black looks, saying: <q direct="unspecified">This is indeed a surprise that
thou art back so soon this morning! By what I see thou hast a mind to make this a holiday,
that thou returnest tools in hand; if so, what are we to live on? whence shall we get
bread to eat? Thinkest thou I will let thee pawn my gown and other bits <pb n="121" />of
clothes? Day and night I do nought else but spin, insomuch that the flesh is fallen away
from my nails, that at least I may have oil enough to keep our lamp
alight. <milestone id="p07020015" />Husband, husband, there is never a woman in the neighbourhood but
marvels and mocks at me, that I am at such labour and pains; and thou comest home to me
with thy hands hanging idle, when thou shouldst be at work.</q> <milestone id="p07020016" />Which said, she
fell a weeping and repeating: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, alas, woe's me, in what evil hour was I born? in
what luckless moment came I hither, I, that might have had so goodly a young man, and I
would not, to take up with one that bestows never a thought on her whom he has made his
wife? <milestone id="p07020017" />Other women have a good time with their lovers, and never a one have we
here but has two or three; they take their pleasure, and make their husbands believe that
the moon is the sun; and I, alas! for that I am an honest woman, and have no such casual
amours, I suffer, and am hard bested: I know not why I provide not myself with one of
these lovers, as others do. <milestone id="p07020018" />Give good heed, husband, to what I say: were I
disposed to dishonour thee, I were at no loss to find the man: for here are gallants
enough, that love me, and court me, and have sent me many an offer of money--no stint--or
dresses or jewels, should I prefer them; but my pride would never suffer it, because I was
not born of a woman of that sort: and now thou comest home to me when thou oughtest to be
at work.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07020019" />Whereto the husband: <q direct="unspecified">Wife, wife, for God's sake distress not
thyself: thou shouldst give me credit for knowing what manner of woman thou art, as indeed
I have partly seen this morning. True it is that I went out to work; but 'tis plain that
thou knowest not, as indeed I knew not, <milestone id="p07020020" />that to-day 'tis the feast of San
Galeone, and a holiday, and that is why I am come home at this hour; but nevertheless I
have found means to provide us with bread for more than a month; for I have sold to this
gentleman, whom thou seest with me, the tun, thou wottest of, seeing that it has
encumbered the house so long, and he will give me five gigliats for it.</q>
<milestone id="p07020021" />Quoth then Peronella: <q direct="unspecified">And all this but adds to my trouble: thou, that art a
man, and goest abroad, and shouldst know affairs, hast sold for five gigliats a tun, which
I, that am but a woman, and was scarce ever out of doors, have, for that it took up so
much room in the house, sold for seven gigliats to a good man, that but now, as thou
cam'st back, got therein, to see if 'twere sound.</q> <milestone id="p07020022" />So hearing, the husband
was over<pb n="122" />joyed, and said to the man that was come to take it away; <q direct="unspecified">Good man,
I wish thee Godspeed; for, as thou hearest, my wife has sold the tun for seven gigliats,
whereas thou gavest me only five.</q> <milestone id="p07020023" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">So be it,</q> said the good
man, and took himself off.  <milestone id="p07020024" />Then said Peronella to her husband: <q direct="unspecified">Now, as thou
art here, come
up, and arrange the matter with the good man.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07020025" />Now Giannello, who, meanwhile,
had been all on the alert to discover if there were aught he had to fear or be on his
guard against, no sooner heard Peronella's last words, than he sprang out of the tun, and
feigning to know nought of her husband's return, began thus: <q direct="unspecified">Where art thou, good
dame?</q> <milestone id="p07020026" />Whereto the husband, coming up, answered: <q direct="unspecified">Here am I: what wouldst
thou of me?</q> <milestone id="p07020027" />Quoth Giannello: <q direct="unspecified">And who art thou? I would speak with the
lady with whom I struck the bargain for this tun.</q> <milestone id="p07020028" />Then said the good
man: <q direct="unspecified">Have no fear, you can deal with me; for I am her husband.</q>
<milestone id="p07020029" />Quoth then Giannello: <q direct="unspecified">The tun seems to me sound enough; but I think you must
have let the lees remain in it; for 'tis all encrusted with I know not what that is so
dry, that I cannot raise it with the nail; wherefore I am not minded to take it unless I
first see it scoured.</q> <milestone id="p07020030" />Whereupon Peronella: <q direct="unspecified">To be sure: that shall not
hinder the bargain; my husband will scour it clean.</q> <milestone id="p07020031" />And: <q direct="unspecified">Well and
good,</q> said the husband.</p><p>So he laid down his tools, stripped himself to his
vest, sent for a light and a rasp, and was in the tun, and scraping away, in a trice.
<milestone id="p07020032" />Whereupon Peronella, as if she were curious to see what he did, thrust her head
into the vent of the tun, which was of no great size, and
therewithal one of her arms up to the shoulder, and fell a saying:
<q direct="unspecified">Scrape here, and here, and there too, and look, there is a bit left
here.</q> <milestone id="p07020033" />So, she being in this posture, directing and admonishing her
husband, Giannello, who had not, that morning, fully satisfied his desire, when the
husband arrived, now seeing that as he would, he might not, brought his mind to his
circumstances, and resolved to take his pleasure as he might: <milestone id="p07020034" />wherefore he made
up to the lady, who completely blocked the vent of the tun; and even on such wise as on
the open champaign the wild and lusty horses do amorously assail the mares of Parthia, he
sated his youthful appetite; and so it was that almost at the same moment that he did so,
and was off, the tun was scoured, the husband came forth of it, and <pb n="123" />Peronella
withdrew her head from the vent, <milestone id="p07020035" />and turning to
Giannello, said: <q direct="unspecified">Take this light, good man, and see if 'tis scoured to thy mind.</q>
<milestone id="p07020036" />Whereupon Giannello, looking into the tun, said that 'twas in good trim, and
that he was well content, and paid the husband the seven gigliats, and caused him carry
the tun to his house.</p></div2>