<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0407"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04070001" />Simona loves Pasquino; they are together in a garden;
 Pasquino rubs a leaf of sage against his teeth, and
 dies; Simona is arrested, and, with intent to shew
 the judge how Pasquino died, rubs one of the leaves of
 the same plant against her teeth, and likewise dies.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04070002" />When Pamfilo had done with his story, the king, betraying no
 compassion for Andreuola, glancing at Emilia, signified to her his
 desire that she should now continue the sequence of narration.
 Emilia made no demur, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04070003" />Dear gossips, Pamfilo's story puts me upon telling you another in
	no wise like thereto, save in this, that as Andreuola lost her lover in
	a garden, so also did she of whom I am to speak, and, being arrested
	like Andreuola, did also deliver herself from the court, albeit 'twas
	not by any vigour or firmness of mind, but by a sudden death. 
	<milestone id="p04070004" />And,
	as 'twas said among us a while ago, albeit Love affects the mansions
	of the noble, he does not, therefore, disdain the dominion of the
	dwellings of the poor, nay, does there at times give proof of his might
	no less signal than when he makes him feared of the wealthiest as a
	most potent lord. <milestone id="p04070005" />Which, though not fully, will in some degree
	appear in my story, wherewith I am minded to return to our city,
	from which to-day's discourse, roving from matter to matter, and
	one part of the world to another, has carried us so far.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04070006" />Know then that no great while ago there dwelt in Florence a
 maid most fair, and, for her rank, debonair--she was but a poor
 man's daughter--whose name was Simona; and though she must
 needs win with her own hands the bread she ate, and maintain
 herself by spinning wool; yet was she not, therefore, of so poor a
 <pb n="310" />spirit, but that she dared to give harbourage in her mind to Love,
 who for some time had sought to gain entrance there by means of
 the gracious deeds and words of a young man of her own order that
 went about distributing wool to spin for his master, a wool-monger.
 <milestone id="p04070007" />Love being thus, with the pleasant image of her beloved Pasquino,
 admitted into her soul, mightily did she yearn, albeit she hazarded no
 advance, and heaved a thousand sighs fiercer than fire with every
 skein of yarn that she wound upon her spindle, while she called to
 mind who he was that had given her that wool to spin. 
<milestone id="p04070008" />Pasquino
 on his part became, meanwhile, very anxious that his master's wool
 should be well spun, and most particularly about that which Simona
 span, as if, indeed, it and it alone was to furnish forth the whole of
 the cloth. <milestone id="p04070009" />And so, what with the anxiety which the one evinced,
 and the gratification that it afforded to the other, it befell that, the
 one waxing unusually bold, and the other casting off not a little
 of her wonted shyness and reserve, they came to an understanding
 for their mutual solace; which proved so delightful to both, that
 neither waited to be bidden by the other, but 'twas rather which
 should be the first to make the overture.</p><p><milestone id="p04070010" />While thus they sped their days in an even tenor of delight, and
 ever grew more ardently enamoured of one another, Pasquino
 chanced to say to Simona that he wished of all things she would
 contrive how she might betake her to a garden, whither he would
 bring her, that there they might be more at their ease, and in greater
 security. <milestone id="p04070011" />Simona said that she was agreeable; and, having given her
 father to understand that she was minded to go to San Gallo for the
 pardoning, she hied her with one of her gossips, Lagina by name, to
 the garden of which Pasquino had told her. Here she found
 Pasquino awaiting her with a friend, one Puccino, otherwise Stramba;
 and Stramba and Lagina falling at once to love-making, Pasquino
 and Simona left a part of the garden to them, and withdrew to
 another part for their own solace.</p><p><milestone id="p04070012" />Now there was in their part of the garden a very fine and lovely
 sage-bush, at foot of which they sat them down and made merry
 together a great while, and talked much of a junketing they meant
 to have in the garden quite at their ease. By and by Pasquino,
 turning to the great sage-bush, plucked therefrom a leaf, and fell to
 rubbing his teeth and gums therewith, saying that sage was an
 <pb n="311" />excellent detergent of aught that remained upon them after a meal.
 <milestone id="p04070013" />Having done so, he returned to the topic of the junketing of which
 he had spoken before. But he had not pursued it far before his
 countenance entirely changed, and forthwith he lost sight and speech,
 and shortly after died. <milestone id="p04070014" />Whereupon Simona fell a weeping and
 shrieking and calling Stramba and Lagina; who, notwithstanding
 they came up with all speed, found Pasquino not only dead but
 already swollen from head to foot, and covered with black spots both
 on the face and on the body; whereupon Stramba broke forth
 with: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! wicked woman! thou hast poisoned him;</q> 
<milestone id="p04070015" />and made
 such a din that 'twas heard by not a few that dwelt hard by the
 garden; who also hasted to the spot, and seeing Pasquino dead and
 swollen, and hearing Stramba bewail himself and accuse Simona of
 having maliciously poisoned him, while she, all but beside herself for
 grief to be thus suddenly bereft of her lover, knew not how to defend
 herself, did all with one accord surmise that 'twas even as Stramba
 said. <milestone id="p04070016" />Wherefore they laid hands on her, and brought her, still
 weeping bitterly, to the palace of the Podest&#224;: where at the instant
 suit of Stramba, backed by Atticciato and Malagevole, two other
 newly-arrived friends of Pasquino, a judge forthwith addressed himself
 to question her of the matter; and being unable to discover
 that she had used any wicked practice, or was guilty, he resolved to
 take her with him and go see the corpse, and the place, and the
 manner of the death, as she had recounted it to him; for by her
 words he could not well understand it. <milestone id="p04070017" />So, taking care that there
 should be no disturbance, he had her brought to the place where
 Pasquino's corpse lay swollen like a tun, whither he himself presently
 came, and marvelling as he examined the corpse, asked her
 how the death had come about. <milestone id="p04070018" />Whereupon, standing by the sagebush,
 she told him all that had happened, and that he might perfectly
 apprehend the occasion of the death, she did as Pasquino had
 done, plucked one of the leaves from the bush, and rubbed her teeth
 with it. Whereupon Stramba and Atticciato, and the rest of the
 friends and comrades of Pasquino, making in the presence of the
 judge open mock of what she did, as an idle and vain thing, and
 being more than ever instant to affirm her guilt, and to demand the
 fire as the sole condign penalty, the poor creature, that, between
 grief for her lost lover and dread of the doom demanded by Stramba,
 <pb n="312" />stood mute and helpless, was stricken no less suddenly, and in the
 same manner, and for the same cause (to wit, that she had rubbed
 her teeth with the sage leaf) as Pasquino, to the no small amazement
 of all that were present.</p><p><milestone id="p04070019" />Oh! happy souls for whom one and the same day was the
 term of ardent love and earthly life! Happier still, if to the
 same bourn ye fared! Ay, and even yet more happy, if love
 there be in the other world, and there, even as here, ye love!
 <milestone id="p04070020" />But happiest above all Simona, so far as we, whom she has left
 behind, may judge, in that Fortune brooked not that the witness of
 Stramba, Atticciato and Malagevole, carders, perchance, or yet viler
 fellows, should bear down her innocence, but found a more seemly
 issue, and, appointing her a like lot with her lover, gave her at once
 to clear herself from their foul accusation, and to follow whither the
 soul, that she so loved, of her Pasquino had preceded her!</p><p><milestone id="p04070021" />The judge, and all else that witnessed the event, remained long
 time in a sort of stupefaction, knowing not what to say of it; but at
 length recovering his wits, the judge said: <q direct="unspecified">'Twould seem that
 this sage is poisonous, which the sage is not used to be. Let it be
 cut down to the roots and burned, lest another suffer by it in like
 sort.</q>
 <milestone id="p04070022" />Which the gardener proceeding to do in the judge's presence, no sooner
 had he brought the great bush down, than the cause of the deaths of
 the two lovers plainly appeared: <milestone id="p04070023" />for underneath it was a toad of prodigious
 dimensions, from whose venomous breath, as they conjectured,
 the whole of the bush had contracted a poisonous quality. Around
 which toad, none venturing to approach it, they set a stout ring-fence
 of faggots, and burned it together with the sage. So ended Master
 Judge's inquest on the death of hapless Pasquino, 
<milestone id="p04070024" />who with his
 Simona, swollen as they were, were buried by Stramba, Atticciato,
 Guccio Imbratta, and Malagevole in the church of San Paolo, of
 which, as it so happened, they were parishioners.</p></div2>