<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov1009"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00090001" />Saladin, in guise of a merchant, is honourably entreated
 by Messer Torello. The Crusade ensuing, Messer
 Torello appoints a date, after which his wife may
 marry again: he is taken prisoner, and by training
 hawks comes under the Soldan's notice. The Soldan
 recognizes him, makes himself known to him, and
 entreats him with all honour. Messer Torello falls
 sick, and by magic arts is transported in a single night
 to Pavia, where his wife's second marriage is then to be
 solemnized, and being present thereat, is recognized by
 her, and returns with her to his house.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00090002" />So ended Filomena her story, and when all alike had commended
 the magnificence shewn by Titus in his gratitude, the king, reserving
 the last place for Dioneo, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00090003" />Lovesome my ladies, true
 beyond all question is what Filomena reports of friendship, and with
 justice did she deplore in her closing words the little account in
 which 'tis held to-day among mortals.  <milestone id="p00090004" />And were we here for the
 purpose of correcting, or even of censuring, the vices of the age, I
 should add a copious sequel to her discourse; but as we have another
 end in view, it has occurred to me to set before you in a narrative,
 which will be of considerable length, but entertaining throughout,
 an instance of Saladin's magnificence, to the end that, albeit, by reason
 of our vices, it may not be possible for us to gain to the full the
 friendship of any, yet by the matters whereof you shall hear in my
 story we may at least be incited to take delight in doing good offices,
 <pb n="371" />in the hope that sooner or later we may come by our reward
 thereof.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00090005" />I say, then, that in the time of the Emperor Frederic I., as
 certain writers affirm, the Christians made common emprise for the
 recovery of the Holy Land. Whereof that most valiant prince,
 Saladin, then Soldan of Babylonia, being in good time apprised,
 resolved to see for himself the preparations made by the Christian
 potentates for the said emprise, that he might put himself in better
 trim to meet them.  <milestone id="p00090006" />So, having ordered all things to his mind in
 Egypt, he made as if he were bound on a pilgrimage, and attended
 only by two of his chiefest and sagest lords, and three servants, took
 the road in the guise of a merchant.  <milestone id="p00090007" />And having surveyed many
 provinces of Christendom, as they rode through Lombardy with
 intent to cross the Alps, they chanced, between Milan and Pavia, to
 fall in with a gentleman, one Messer Torello d'Istria da Pavia, who
 with his servants and his dogs and falcons was betaking him to a fine
 estate that he had on the Ticino, there to tarry a while.  <milestone id="p00090008" />Now
 Messer Torello no sooner espied Saladin and his lords than he
 guessed them to be gentlemen and foreigners; and, being zealous to
 do them honour, when Saladin asked one of his servants how far
 off Pavia might still be, and if he might win there in time to enter
 the town, he suffered not the servant to make answer, but: <q direct="unspecified">No,
 gentlemen,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">by the time you reach Pavia 'twill be too
 late for you to enter.</q>  <milestone id="p00090009" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> replied Saladin, <q direct="unspecified">then might you
 be pleased to direct us, as we are strangers, where we may best be
 lodged?</q> <q direct="unspecified"> <milestone id="p00090010" />That gladly will I,</q> returned Messer Torello. <q direct="unspecified">I
 was but now thinking to send one of these my men on an errand to
 Pavia; I will send him with you, and he will guide you to a place
 where you will find very comfortable quarters.</q>  <milestone id="p00090011" />Then, turning to
 one of his most trusty servants, he gave him his instructions, and
 despatched him with them: after which, he repaired to his estate,
 and forthwith, as best he might, caused a goodly supper to be made
 ready, and the tables set in his garden; which done, he stationed
 himself at the gate on the look-out for his guests.</p><p>The servant, conversing with the gentlemen of divers matters,
 brought them by devious roads to his lord's estate without their being
 ware of it.  <milestone id="p00090012" />Whom as soon as Messer Torello espied, he came forth
 afoot to meet them, and said with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">A hearty welcome to
 <pb n="372" />you, gentlemen.</q>  <milestone id="p00090013" />Now Saladin, being very quick of apprehension,
 perceived that the knight had doubted, when he met them, that, were
 he to bid them to his house, they might not accept his hospitality;
 and accordingly, that it might not be in their power to decline it, had
 brought them to his house by a ruse. And so, returning his greeting:
 <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">were it meet to find fault with those that shew
 courtesy, we should have a grievance against you, for that, to say
 nought of somewhat delaying our journey, you have in guerdon of
 a single greeting constrained us to accept so noble a courtesy as
 yours.</q>  <milestone id="p00090014" />Whereto the knight, who was of good understanding and
 well-spoken, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, such courtesy as we
 shew you will, in comparison of that which, by what I gather from
 your aspect, were meet for you, prove but a sorry thing; but in sooth
 this side of Pavia you might not anywhere have been well lodged;
 wherefore take it not amiss that you have come somewhat out of
 your way to find less discomfortable quarters.</q>  <milestone id="p00090015" />And as he spoke,
 about them flocked the servants, who, having helped them to dismount,
 saw to their horses; whereupon Messer Torello conducted them to
 the chambers that were made ready for them, where, having caused
 them to be relieved of their boots, and refreshed with the coolest of
 wines, he held pleasant converse with them until supper-time.
  <milestone id="p00090016" />Saladin and his lords and servants all knew Latin, so that they both
 understood and made themselves understood very well, and there
 was none of them but adjudged this knight to be the most agreeable
 and debonair man, and therewithal the best talker, that he had ever
 seen;  <milestone id="p00090017" />while to Messer Torello, on the other hand, they shewed as
 far greater magnificoes than he had at first supposed, whereby he was
 inly vexed that he had not been able that evening to do them the
 honours of company, and a more ceremonious banquet. For which
 default he resolved to make amends on the ensuing morning: wherefore,
 having imparted to one of his servants that which he would have
 done, he sent him to his most judicious and highminded lady at
 Pavia, which was close by, and where never a gate was locked.
  <milestone id="p00090018" />Which done, he brought the gentlemen into the garden, and courteously
 asked them who they were. <q direct="unspecified">We are Cypriote merchants,</q>
 replied Saladin, <q direct="unspecified">and 'tis from Cyprus we come, and we are on our
 way to Paris on business.</q> Quoth then Messer Torello: <q direct="unspecified">Would
 to God that our country bred gentlemen of such a quality as are the
 <pb n="373" />merchants that I see Cyprus breeds!</q>  <milestone id="p00090019" />From which they passed to
 discourse of other matters, until, supper-time being come, he
 besought them to seat them at table; whereat, considering that
 the supper was but improvised, their entertainment was excellent
 and well-ordered.</p><p>The tables being cleared, Messer Torello, surmising that they
 must be weary, kept them no long time from their rest, but bestowed
 them in most comfortable beds, and soon after went to rest himself.
  <milestone id="p00090020" />Meanwhile the servant that he had sent to Pavia did his lord's errand
 to the lady, who, in the style rather of a queen than of a housewife,
 forthwith assembled not a few of Messer Torello's friends and vassals,
 and caused all meet preparation to be made for a magnificent banquet,
 and by messengers bearing torches bade not a few of the noblest of
 the citizens thereto; and had store of silken and other fabrics and
 vair brought in, and all set in order in every point as her husband
 had directed.  <milestone id="p00090021" />Day came, and the gentlemen being risen, Messer
 Torello got him to horse with them, and having sent for his hawks,
 brought them to a ford, and shewed them how the hawks flew.
 By and by, Saladin requesting of him a guide to the best inn at
 Pavia: <q direct="unspecified">I myself will be your guide,</q> returned Messer Torello,
 <q direct="unspecified">for I have occasion to go thither.</q>  <milestone id="p00090022" />Which offer they, nothing
 doubting, did gladly accept, and so with him they set forth; and
 about tierce, being come to the city, and expecting to be directed to
 the best inn, they were brought by Messer Torello to his own house,
 where they were forthwith surrounded by full fifty of the greatest
 folk of the city, gathered there to give the gentlemen a welcome;
 and 'twas who should hold a bridle or a stirrup, while they dismounted.
  <milestone id="p00090023" />Whereby Saladin and his lords more than guessing the
 truth: <q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello,</q> quoth they, <q direct="unspecified">'twas not this that we
 craved of you. Honour enough had we from you last night, and
 far in excess of our desires; wherefore thou mightst very well have
 left us to go our own road.</q>  <milestone id="p00090024" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> replied
 Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">for that which was done yestereve I have to thank
 Fortune rather than you: seeing that Fortune surprised you on the
 road at an hour when you must needs repair to my little house: for
 that which shall be done this morning I shall be beholden to you, as
 will also these gentlemen that surround you, with whom, if you
 deem it courteous so to do, you may refuse to breakfast, if you
 like.</q></p><pb n="374" /><p><milestone id="p00090025" />Fairly conquered, Saladin and his lords dismounted, and heartily
 welcomed by the gentlemen, were conducted to the chambers which
 had been most sumptuously adorned for their use; and having laid
 aside their riding dress, and taken some refreshment, repaired to the
 saloon, where all had been made ready with splendour. There,
 having washed their hands, they sat them down to table, and were
 regaled with a magnificent repast of many courses, served with all
 stately and fair ceremony, insomuch that, had the Emperor himself
 been there, 'twould not have been possible to do him more honour.
  <milestone id="p00090026" />And albeit Saladin and his lords were grandees, and used to exceeding
 great displays of pomp and state, nevertheless this shewed to them
 as not a little marvellous, and one of the greatest they had ever seen,
 having regard to the quality of their host, whom they knew to be
 but a citizen, and no lord.  <milestone id="p00090027" />Breakfast done, and the tables cleared,
 they conversed a while of high matters, and then, as 'twas very hot,
 all the gentlemen of Pavia--so it pleased Messer Torello--retired for
 their siesta, while he remained with his three guests; with whom he
 presently withdrew into a chamber, whither, that there might be
 nought that he held dear which they had not seen, he called his
 noble lady.  <milestone id="p00090028" />And so the dame, exceeding fair and stately of person,
 and arrayed in rich apparel, with her two little boys, that shewed as
 two angels, on either hand, presented herself before them, and
 graciously greeted them. Whereupon they rose, and returned her
 salutation with reverence, and caused her to sit down among them,
 and made much of her two little boys.  <milestone id="p00090029" />But after some interchange
 of gracious discourse, Messer Torello being withdrawn somewhat
 apart, she asked them courteously, whence they came and whither
 they were bound, and had of them the same answer that Messer
 Torello had received.  <milestone id="p00090030" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> quoth the lady with a joyful air,
 <q direct="unspecified">then I see that my woman's wit will be of service to you; wherefore
 I pray you as a special favour neither to reject nor to despise the
 little gift that I am about to present to you; but reflecting that, as
 women have but small minds, so they make but small gifts, accept it,
 having regard rather to the good will of the giver than the magnitude
 of the gift.</q>  <milestone id="p00090031" />She then caused bring forth for each of them
 two pair of robes, lined the one with silk, the other with vair, no
 such robes as citizens or merchants, but such as lords, use to wear,
 and three vests of taffeta, besides linen clothes, and: <q direct="unspecified">Take them,</q>
 <pb n="375" />quoth she. <q direct="unspecified">The robes I give you are even such as I have arrayed
 my lord withal: the other things, considering that you are far from
 your wives, and have come a long way, and have yet a long way to
 go, and that merchants love to be neat and trim, may, albeit they
 are of no great value, be yet acceptable to you.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090032" />Wondering, the gentlemen acknowledged without reserve that
 there was no point of courtesy wherein Messer Torello was not
 minded to acquit himself towards them. And noting the lordly
 fashion of the robes, unsuited to the quality of merchants, they misdoubted
 that Messer Torello had recognized them. However, quoth
 one of them to the lady: <q direct="unspecified">Gifts great indeed are these, Madam,
 nor such as lightly to accept, were it not that thereto we are constrained
 by your prayers, to which we may on no account say, no.</q>
  <milestone id="p00090033" />Whereupon, Messer Torello being now come back, the lady bade
 them adieu, and took her leave of them; and in like manner did she
 cause their servants to be supplied with equipment suitable to them.
 The gentlemen, being much importuned thereto by Messer Torello,
 consented to tarry the rest of the day with him; and so, having
 slept, they donned their robes, and rode a while with him about the
 city; and supper-time being come, they feasted magnificently, and
 with a numerous and honourable company.  <milestone id="p00090034" />And so in due time
 they betook them to rest; and at daybreak, being risen, they found,
 in lieu of their jaded nags, three stout and excellent palfreys, and in
 like manner fresh and goodly mounts for their servants. Which
 Saladin marking turned to his lords, and:  <milestone id="p00090035" /><q direct="unspecified">By God,</q> quoth he,
 <q direct="unspecified">never was gentleman more complete and courteous and considerate
 than this Messer Torello, and if the Christian kings are as kingly as
 he is knightly, there is none of them whose onset the Soldan of
 Babylon might well abide, to say nought of so many as we see making
 ready to fall upon him.</q> However, knowing that 'twas not permissible
 to refuse, he very courteously thanked Messer Torello: and
 so they got them to horse.  <milestone id="p00090036" />Messer Torello with a numerous company
 escorted them far beyond the gate of the city, until, loath
 though Saladin was to part from him, so greatly did he now affect
 him, yet as he must needs speed on, he besought him to turn back.
 Whereupon, albeit it irked him to take leave of them:  <milestone id="p00090037" /><q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q>
 quoth Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">since such is your pleasure, I obey;
 but this I must say to you. Who you are I know not, nor would I
 <pb n="376" />know more than you are pleased to impart; but whoever you may
 be, you will not make me believe that you are merchants this while;
 and so adieu!</q>  <milestone id="p00090038" />To whom Saladin, having already taken leave of
 all his company, thus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Peradventure, Sir, we shall
 one day give you to see somewhat of our merchandise, and thereby
 confirm your belief: and so adieu!</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090039" />Thus parted Saladin and his company from Messer Torello,
 Saladin burning with an exceeding great desire, if life should be continued
 to him, and the war, which he anticipated, should not undo
 him, to shew Messer Torello no less honour than he had received at
 his hands, and conversing not a little with his lords both of Messer
 Torello himself and of his lady, and all that he did and that in any wise
 concerned him, ever more highly commending them.  <milestone id="p00090040" />However,
 having with much diligence spied out all the West, he put to sea,
 and returned with his company to Alexandria; and having now all
 needful information, he put himself in a posture of defence. Messer
 Torello, his mind full of his late guests, returned to Pavia; but,
 though he long pondered who they might be, he came never at or
 anywhere near the truth.</p><p><milestone id="p00090041" />Then with great and general mustering of forces came the time
 for embarking on the emprise, and Messer Torello, heeding not the
 tearful entreaties of his wife, resolved to join therein. So, being fully
 equipped and about to take horse, he said to his lady, whom he most
 dearly loved:  <milestone id="p00090042" /><q direct="unspecified">Wife, for honour's sake and for the weal of my
 soul, I go, as thou seest, on this emprise: our substance and our
 honour I commend to thy care. Certain I am of my departure, but,
 for the thousand accidents that may ensue, certitude have I none of
 my return: wherefore I would have thee do me this grace, that,
 whatever be my fate, shouldst thou lack certain intelligence that I
 live, thou wilt expect me a year and a month and a day from this
 my departure, before thou marry again.</q>  <milestone id="p00090043" />Whereto the lady, weeping
 bitterly, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello, I know not how I
 shall support the distress in which, thus departing, you leave me;
 but should my life not fail beneath it, and aught befall thee,
 live and die secure that I shall live and die the wife of Messer
 Torello, and of his memory.</q>  <milestone id="p00090044" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Wife,</q> returned
 Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">well assured I am that, so far as in thee
 shall lie, this promise of thine will be kept; but thou art
 <pb n="377" />young, and fair, and of a great family, and thy virtue is rare and
 generally known:  <milestone id="p00090045" />wherefore I make no doubt that, should there be
 any suspicion of my death, thou wilt be asked of thy brothers and
 kinsmen by many a great gentleman: against whose attacks, though
 thou desire it never so, thou wilt not be able to hold out, but wilt
 perforce be fain to gratify one or other of them; for which cause it
 is that I ask thee to wait just so long and no longer.</q>  <milestone id="p00090046" /><q direct="unspecified">As I have
 said,</q> replied the lady, <q direct="unspecified">so, in so far as I may, I shall do; and if I
 must needs do otherwise, rest assured that of this your behest I shall
 render you obedience. But I pray God that He bring neither you
 nor me to such a strait yet a while.</q>  <milestone id="p00090047" />Which said, the lady wept,
 and having embraced Messer Torello, drew from her finger a ring,
 and gave it to him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Should it betide that I die before I
 see you again, mind you of me, when you look upon it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090048" />Messer Torello took the ring, and got him to horse, and having
 bidden all adieu, fared forth on his journey; and being arrived with
 his company at Genoa, he embarked on a galley, and having departed
 thence, in no long time arrived at Acre, and joined the main
 Christian host;  <milestone id="p00090049" />wherein there by and by broke out an exceeding
 great and mortal sickness; during which, whether owing to Saladin's
 strategy, or his good fortune, he made an easy capture of well-nigh
 all the remnant of the Christians that were escaped, and quartered
 them in divers prisons in many cities;  <milestone id="p00090050" />of which captives Messer
 Torello being one, was brought to Alexandria and there confined.
 Where, not being known, and fearing to make himself known, he,
 under constraint of necessity, applied him to the training of hawks,
 whereof he was a very great master; and thereby he fell under the
 notice of Saladin, who took him out of the prison, and made him his
 falconer.  <milestone id="p00090051" />The Soldan called him by no other name than <q direct="unspecified">Christian,</q>
 and neither recognized, nor was recognized by, him, who, his
 whole soul ever in Pavia, essayed many a time to escape, that he
 might return thither, but still without success:  <milestone id="p00090052" />wherefore, certain
 Genoese, that were come to Alexandria as ambassadors to the Soldan
 for the redemption of some of their townsfolk, being about to return,
 he resolved to write to his lady, how that he lived, and would come
 back to her, as soon as he might, and that she should expect his
 return; and having so done, he earnestly besought one of the
 ambassadors, whom he knew, to see that the letter reached the
 <pb n="378" />hands of the Abbot of San Pietro in Ciel d'Oro, who was his
 uncle.</p><p><milestone id="p00090053" />Now, such being the posture of Messer Torello's affairs, it befell
 one day that, while he talked with Saladin of his hawks, he smiled;
 whereby his mouth shaped itself in a fashion, of which Saladin had
 taken particular note, while he was at Pavia. And so, recalling
 Messer Torello to mind, he fixed his gaze upon him, and it seemed
 to him that 'twas indeed Messer Torello; wherefore, leaving the
 matter of which they were conversing: <q direct="unspecified">Tell me, Christian,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">of what country art thou in the West?</q>  <milestone id="p00090054" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q>
 replied Messer Torello, <q direct="unspecified">I am a Lombard, of a city called Pavia, a
 poor man, and of humble condition.</q>  <milestone id="p00090055" />Which when he heard,
 Saladin, well-nigh resolved of his doubt, said joyfully to himself:
 <q direct="unspecified">God has provided me with occasion meet to prove to this man
 what store I set by his courtesy;</q> and without another word he
 brought him into a room where he kept all his wearing apparel, and
 said: <q direct="unspecified">Look, Christian, if among these robes there be any that
 thou hast ever seen before.</q>  <milestone id="p00090056" />So Messer Torello examined the robes,
 and espied those which his lady had given to Saladin; but, deeming
 they could not be the same, he replied: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, there is no robe
 here that I recognize, albeit 'tis true that those two robes are such as
 I once wore myself, in company with three merchants that came to
 my house.</q>  <milestone id="p00090057" />Whereupon Saladin could refrain himself no longer;
 but, tenderly embracing him: <q direct="unspecified">You,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">are Messer
 Torello d'Istria, and I am one of those three merchants to whom
 your lady gave these robes; and now is the time to warrant you of
 the quality of my merchandise, as, when I parted from you, I told
 you might come to pass.</q>  <milestone id="p00090058" />Which to hear, Messer Torello was at
 once overjoyed and abashed, overjoyed to have entertained so illustrious
 a guest, and abashed, for that it seemed to him that he
 had given him but a sorry entertainment. To whom: <q direct="unspecified">Messer
 Torello,</q> quoth Saladin, <q direct="unspecified">since hither has God sent you to me,
 deem that 'tis no more I that am lord here, but you.</q>  <milestone id="p00090059" />And so
 they made great cheer together; and then Saladin caused Messer
 Torello to be royally arrayed; and presented him to all his greatest
 lords, and having extolled his merit in no stinted measure, bade
 all, as they hoped for grace from him, honour Messer Torello
 even as himself. And so from that hour did they all; but most
 <pb n="379" />especially the two lords that had been with Saladin at Messer Torello's
 house.</p><p><milestone id="p00090060" />The glory, to which Messer Torello thus suddenly found himself
 raised, somewhat diverted his mind from the affairs of Lombardy,
 and the more so, for that he entertained no doubt that his letter
 had reached his uncle's hands.  <milestone id="p00090061" />But for that in the camp, or rather
 army, of the Christians, on the day when they were taken by Saladin,
 there died and was buried one Messer Torello de Dignes, an obscure
 knight of Provence, whereas Messer Torello d'Istria was known to
 all the host for a right noble gentleman, whoso heard tell that
 Messer Torello was dead, supposed that 'twas Messer Torello d'Istria,
 and not Messer Torello de Dignes; nor did what happened after,
 to wit, the capture, avail to undeceive them;  <milestone id="p00090062" />for not a few Italians
 had carried the report home with them; among whom there were
 some who made bold to say that they had seen Messer Torello
 d'Istria's dead body, and had been present at its interment.  <milestone id="p00090063" />Which
 rumour coming to the ears of his lady and his kinsfolk, great indeed,
 nay, immeasurable was the distress that it occasioned not only to
 them, but to all that had known him.  <milestone id="p00090064" />The mode and measure of his
 lady's grief, her mourning, her lamentation, 'twere tedious to describe.
 Enough that, after some months spent in almost unmitigated
 tribulation, her sorrow shewed signs of abatement; whereupon, suit
 being made for her hand by some of the greatest men of Lombardy,
 her brothers and other kinsfolk began to importune her to marry
 again. Times not a few, and with floods of tears, she refused; but,
 overborne at last, she consented to do as they would have her, upon
 the understanding that she was to remain unmarried until the term
 for which she had bound herself to Messer Torello was fulfilled.</p><p><milestone id="p00090065" />Now the lady's affairs being in this posture at Pavia, it befell
 that some eight days or so before the time appointed for her marriage,
 Messer Torello one day espied in Alexandria one that he had
 observed go with the Genoese ambassadors aboard the galley that
 took them to Genoa; wherefore he called him, and asked him what
 sort of a voyage they had had, and when they had reached Genoa.
  <milestone id="p00090066" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> replied the other, <q direct="unspecified">the galley made but a sorry voyage of
 it, as I learned in Crete, where I remained; for that, while she was
 nearing Sicily, there arose a terrible gale from the North that drove
 her on to the shoals of Barbary, and never a soul escaped, and among
 <pb n="380" />the rest my two brothers were lost.</q>  <milestone id="p00090067" />Which report believing--and
 'twas indeed most true--and calling to mind that in a few days the
 term that he had asked of his wife would be fulfilled, and surmising
 that there could be no tidings of him at Pavia, Messer Torello made
 no question but that the lady was provided with another husband;
 whereby he sank into such a depth of woe that he lost all power to
 eat, and betook him to his bed and resigned himself to die.  <milestone id="p00090068" />Which
 when Saladin, by whom he was most dearly beloved, learned, he
 came to him, and having plied him with many and most instant
 entreaties, learned at length the cause of his distress and sickness;
 and, having chidden him not a little that he had not sooner apprised
 him thereof, he besought him to put on a cheerful courage, assuring
 him, that, if so he did, he would bring it to pass that he should be in
 Pavia at the time appointed, and told him how.  <milestone id="p00090069" />Believing Saladin's
 words the more readily that he had many times heard that 'twas
 possible, and had not seldom been done, Messer Torello recovered
 heart, and was instant with Saladin that he should make all haste.</p><p><milestone id="p00090070" />Accordingly Saladin bade one of his necromancers, of whose skill
 he had already had proof, to devise a method whereby Messer Torello
 should be transported abed in a single night to Pavia: the necromancer
 made answer that it should be done, but that 'twere best
 he put Messer Torello to sleep.  <milestone id="p00090071" />The matter being thus arranged,
 Saladin hied him back to Messer Torello, and finding him most
 earnestly desirous to be in Pavia at the time appointed, if so it might
 be, and if not, to die:  <milestone id="p00090072" /><q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">if you dearly
 love your lady, and misdoubt that she may become the bride of
 another, no wise, God wot, do I censure you, for that, of all the
 ladies that ever I saw, she, for bearing, manners, and address--to say
 nought of beauty, which is but the flower that perishes--seems to
 me the most worthy to be lauded and cherished.  <milestone id="p00090073" />Much had I been
 gratified, since Fortune has sent you hither to me, that, while you and
 I yet live, we had exercised equal lordship in the governance of this
 my realm,  <milestone id="p00090074" />and, if such was not God's will, and this must needs come
 upon you, that you are fain either to be at Pavia at the time
 appointed or to die, I had desired of all things to have been apprised
 thereof at such a time that I might have sent you home with such
 honourable circumstance and state and escort as befit your high
 desert; which not being vouchsafed me, and as nought will content
 <pb n="381" />you but to be there forthwith, I do what I can, and speed you
 thither on such wise as I have told you.</q>  <milestone id="p00090075" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> replied Messer
 Torello, <q direct="unspecified">had you said nought, you have already done enough to
 prove your goodwill towards me, and that in so high a degree as is
 quite beyond my deserts, and most assured of the truth of what you
 say shall I live and die, and so had done, had you not said it; but,
 seeing that my resolve is taken, I pray you that that, which you
 promise to do, be done speedily, for that after to-morrow I may no
 longer count on being expected.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090076" />Saladin assured him that 'twas so ordered that he should not be
 disappointed. And on the morrow, it being his purpose to speed
 him on his journey that same night, he caused to be set up in one of
 his great halls a most goodly and sumptuous bed composed of mattresses,
 all, as was their wont, of velvet and cloth of gold, and had it
 covered with a quilt, adorned at certain intervals with enormous
 pearls, and most rare precious stones, insomuch that 'twas in after
 time accounted a priceless treasure, and furnished with two pillows
 to match it.  <milestone id="p00090077" />Which done, he bade array Messer Torello, who was
 now quite recovered, in a robe after the Saracenic fashion, the
 richest and goodliest thing of the kind that was ever seen, and wrap
 about his head, according to their wont, one of their huge turbans.
  <milestone id="p00090078" />Then, at a late hour, Saladin, attended by certain of his lords,
 entered the chamber where Messer Torello was, and seating himself
 beside him, all but wept as thus he began:  <milestone id="p00090079" /><q direct="unspecified">Messer Torello, the
 time is nigh at hand when you and I must part; wherefore, since
 I may neither give you my own, nor others' company (the journey
 that you are about to make not permitting it), I am come here, as
 'tis fitting, in this chamber to take my leave of you.  <milestone id="p00090080" />Wherefore,
 before I bid you adieu, I entreat you, by that friendship, that love,
 which is between us, that you forget me not, and that, if it be
 possible, when you have settled your affairs in Lombardy, you come
 at least once, before our days are ended, to visit me, that thereby I
 may both have the delight of seeing you again, and make good that
 omission which, by reason of your haste, I must needs now make;
  <milestone id="p00090081" />and that in the meanwhile it irk thee not to visit me by letter,
 and to ask of me whatever you shall have a mind to, and be sure
 that there lives not the man whom I shall content more gladly
 than you.</q>  <milestone id="p00090082" />Messer Torello could not refrain his tears, and so,
 <pb n="382" />with words few, and broken by his sobs, he answered that 'twas
 impossible that the Soldan's generous deeds and chivalrous character
 should ever be forgotten by him, and that without fail he would
 do as he bade him, so soon as occasion should serve him.  <milestone id="p00090083" />Whereupon
 Saladin tenderly embraced and kissed him, and with many a
 tear bade him adieu, and quitted the chamber. His lords then took
 leave of Messer Torello, and followed Saladin into the hall, where
 he had had the bed made ready.</p><p><milestone id="p00090084" />'Twas now late, and the necromancer being intent to hasten
 Messer Torello's transit, a physician brought him a potion, and
 having first shewn him what he was to give him by way of viaticum,
 caused him to drink it;  <milestone id="p00090085" />and not long after he fell asleep. In which
 state he was carried by Saladin's command, and laid on the goodly
 bed, whereon he set a large and fair and most sumptuous crown,
 marking it in such sort that there could be no mistake that it was
 sent by Saladin to Messer Torello's wife.  <milestone id="p00090086" />He next placed on
 Messer Torello's finger a ring, in which was set a carbuncle of
 such brilliance that it shewed as a lighted torch, and of well-nigh
 inestimable value. After which he girded on him a sword, the
 appointments of which might not readily be appraised. And therewithal
 he adorned him in front with a pendant, wherein were
 pearls, the like of which had never been seen, and not a few other
 rare jewels. And, moreover, on either side of him he set two
 vast basins of gold full of pistoles; and strings of pearls not a few,
 and rings and girdles, and other things, which 'twere tedious to
 enumerate, he disposed around him.  <milestone id="p00090087" />Which done, he kissed Messer
 Torello again, and bade the necromancer speed him on his journey.
 Whereupon, forthwith, the bed, with Messer Torello thereon, was
 borne away from before Saladin's eyes, and he and his barons
 remained conversing thereof.</p><p><milestone id="p00090088" />The bed, as Messer Torello had requested, had already been
 deposited in the church of San Piero in Ciel d'Oro at Pavia, and
 Messer Torello, with all the aforesaid jewels and ornaments upon
 and about him, was lying thereon, and still slept, when, upon the
 stroke of matins, the sacristan came into the church, light in hand,
 and presently setting eyes on the sumptuous bed, was not only
 amazed, but mightily terrified, insomuch that he turned back, and
 took to flight. Which the abbot and monks observing with no small
 <pb n="383" />surprise, asked wherefore he fled; and he told them. Whereupon:
  <milestone id="p00090089" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh,</q> quoth the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">thou art no longer a child, nor
 yet so new to this church, that thou shouldst so lightly be appalled:
 go we now, and see who it is that has given thee this childish fright.</q>
  <milestone id="p00090090" />So, with a blaze of torches, the abbot, attended by his monks, entered
 the church, and espied this wondrous costly bed whereon the knight
 slept, and while, hesitant and fearful, daring not to approach the bed,
 they scanned the rare and splendid jewels, it befell that, the efficacy
 of the potion being exhausted, Messer Torello awoke and heaved a
 great sigh.  <milestone id="p00090091" />Whereat the monks and the abbot quaking and crying
 out: <q direct="unspecified">Lord, help us!</q> one and all took to flight.  <milestone id="p00090092" />Messer Torello,
 opening his eyes and looking about him, saw, to his no small satisfaction,
 that without a doubt he was in the very place where he had craved of
 Saladin to be; so up he sate, and taking particular note of the
 matters with which he was surrounded, accounted the magnificence
 of Saladin to exceed even the measure, great though it was, that he
 already knew.  <milestone id="p00090093" />However, he still kept quiet, save that, perceiving
 the monks in flight, and surmising the reason, he began to call the
 abbot by name, bidding him be of good courage, for that he was his
 nephew, Torello.  <milestone id="p00090094" />Whereat the abbot did but wax more terrified,
 for that he deemed Torello had been many a month dead; but, after
 a while, as he heard himself still called, sound judgment got the
 better of his fears, and making the sign of the cross, he drew nigh
 Torello;  <milestone id="p00090095" />who said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Father, what is't you fear? By
 God's grace I live, and hither am come back from overseas.</q>  <milestone id="p00090096" />Whom,
 for all he had grown a long beard and was dressed in the Saracenic
 fashion, the abbot after a while recognized, and now, quite reassured,
 took by the hand, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Son, welcome home:</q> then: <q direct="unspecified">No
 cause hast thou to marvel at our fears,</q> he went on, <q direct="unspecified">seeing that
 there is never a soul in these parts but firmly believes thee to be
 dead, insomuch that I may tell thee that Madonna Adalieta, thy wife,
 overborne by the entreaties and menaces of her kinsfolk, and against
 her will, is provided with another husband, to whom she is this
 morning to go, and all is made ready for the nuptials and the
 attendant festivities.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090097" />Whereupon Messer Torello, being risen from the sumptuous
 bed, did the abbot and the monks wondrous cheer, and besought
 them, one and all, to tell never a soul of his return, until he had
 <pb n="384" />completed something that he had on hand. After which, having
 put the costly jewels in safe keeping, he recounted to the abbot all
 the story of his adventures to that very hour.  <milestone id="p00090098" />The abbot, rejoicing
 in his good fortune, joined with him in offering thanks to God.
 Messer Torello then asked him who might be his wife's new husband,
 and the abbot told him.  <milestone id="p00090099" />Quoth then Messer Torello:
 <q direct="unspecified">Before my return be known, I purpose to see how my wife will
 comport herself at the nuptials: wherefore, though 'tis not the wont
 of men of religion to go to such gatherings, I had lief that for love of
 me you arranged for us to go thither together.</q>  <milestone id="p00090100" />The abbot answered
 that he would gladly do so, and as soon as 'twas day, he sent word
 to the bridegroom that he had thoughts of being present at his
 nuptials, accompanied by a friend; whereto the gentleman made
 answer that he was much gratified.  <milestone id="p00090101" />So, at the breakfast hour Messer
 Torello, dressed as he was, hied him with the abbot to the bridegroom's
 house, as many as saw them gazing on him with wonder,
 but none recognizing him, and the abbot giving all to understand
 that he was a Saracen sent by the Soldan as ambassador to the King
 of France.  <milestone id="p00090102" />Messer Torello was accordingly seated at a table directly
 opposite that of his lady, whom he eyed with exceeding great delight,
 the more so that he saw that in her face which shewed him that she
 was chagrined by the nuptials. She in like manner from time to time
 bent her regard on him; howbeit, what with his long beard, and his
 foreign garb, and her firm persuasion that he was dead, she had still
 no sort of recollection of him.  <milestone id="p00090103" />However, Messer Torello at length
 deemed it time to make trial of her, whether she would remember
 him; wherefore he took the ring that the lady had given him on his
 departure, and keeping it close in the palm of his hand, he called to
 him a page that waited upon her, and said to him:  <milestone id="p00090104" /><q direct="unspecified">Tell the
 bride from me that 'tis the custom in my country, that, when a
 stranger, such as I, eats with a bride, like herself, at her wedding-feast,
 she, in token that he is welcome to her board, sends him the
 cup from which she herself drinks, full of wine; and when the
 stranger has drunk his fill, he closes the cup, and the bride drinks
 what is left therein.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00090105" />The page carried the message to the lady, who, being of good
 understanding and manners, and supposing him to be some very great
 man, by way of shewing that she was gratified by his presence,
 com<pb n="385" />manded
 that a gilt cup, that was on the table before her, should be
 rinsed, and filled with wine, and borne to the gentleman.  <milestone id="p00090106" />Which
 being done, Messer Torello, having privily conveyed her ring into
 his mouth, let it fall (while he drank) into the cup on such wise that
 none wist thereof; and leaving but a little wine at the bottom, closed
 the cup and returned it to the lady;  <milestone id="p00090107" />who, having taken it, that she
 might do full honour to the custom of her guest's country, lifted
 the lid, and set the cup to her mouth; whereby espying the ring,
 she thereon mutely gazed a while, and recognizing it for that which
 she had given Messer Torello on his departure, she steadfastly
 regarded the supposed stranger, whom now she also recognized.
 Whereupon well-nigh distracted, oversetting the table in front of
 her, she exclaimed: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis my lord, 'tis verily Messer Torello;</q>
  <milestone id="p00090108" />and rushing to the table at which he sate, giving never a thought to
 her apparel, or aught that was on the table, she flung herself upon
 it; and reaching forward as far as she could, she threw her arms
 about him, and hugged him; nor, for aught that any said or did,
 could she be induced to release his neck, until Messer Torello himself
 bade her forbear a while, for that she would have time enough
 to kiss him thereafter.  <milestone id="p00090109" />The lady then stood up, and for a while all
 was disorder, albeit the feast was yet more gladsome than before by
 reason of the recovery of so honourable a knight: then, at Messer
 Torello's entreaty, all were silent, while he recounted to them the
 story of his adventures from the day of his departure to that hour,
 concluding by saying that the gentleman who, deeming him to be
 dead, had taken his lady to wife, ought not to be affronted, if he,
 being alive, reclaimed her.  <milestone id="p00090110" />The bridegroom, albeit he was somewhat
 crestfallen, made answer in frank and friendly sort, that 'twas
 for Messer Torello to do what he liked with his own.  <milestone id="p00090111" />The lady
 resigned the ring and the crown that her new spouse had given her,
 and put on the ring she had taken from the cup, and likewise the
 crown sent her by the Soldan; and so, forth they hied them, and
 with full nuptial pomp wended their way to Messer Torello's house;
 and there for a great while they made merry with his late disconsolate
 friends and kinsfolk and all the citizens, who accounted his
 restoration as little short of a miracle.</p><p><milestone id="p00090112" />Messer Torello, having bestowed part of his rare jewels upon
 him who had borne the cost of the wedding-feast, and part on the
 <pb n="386" />abbot, and many other folk; and having by more than one messenger
 sent word of his safe home-coming and prosperous estate to Saladin,
 acknowledging himself ever his friend and vassal, lived many years
 thereafter with his worthy lady, acquitting himself yet more courteously
 than of yore.  <milestone id="p00090113" />Such, then, was the end of the troubles of
 Messer Torello and his dear lady, and such the reward of their
 cheerful and ready courtesies.</p><p>Now some there are that strive to do offices of courtesy, and
 have the means, but do them with so ill a grace, that, ere they are
 done, they have in effect sold them at a price above their worth:
 wherefore, if no reward ensue to them thereof, neither they nor
 other folk have cause to marvel.</p></div2>