<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0207"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02070001" />The Soldan of Babylon sends one of his daughters overseas,
	designing to marry her to the King of Algarve.
	By divers adventures she comes in the space of four
	years into the hands of nine men in divers places.
	At last she is restored to her father, whom she quits
	again in the guise of a virgin, and, as was at first
	intended, is married to the King of Algarve.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02070002" />Had Emilia's story but lasted a little longer, the young ladies
 would perhaps have been moved to tears, so great was the sympathy
 which they felt for Madam Beritola in her various fortunes. But
 now that it was ended, the Queen bade Pamfilo follow suit; and he,
 than whom none was more obedient, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02070003" />Hardly, gracious ladies, is it given to us to know that which makes
 for our good; insomuch that, as has been observable in a multitude
 of instances, many, deeming that the acquisition of great riches would
 ensure them an easy and tranquil existence, have not only besought
 them of God in prayer, but have sought them with such ardour that
 they have spared no pains and shrunk from no danger in the quest,
 and have attained their end only to lose, at the hands of some one
 covetous of their vast inheritance, a life with which before the days
 of their prosperity they were well content. <milestone id="p02070004" />Others, whose course,
 perilous with a thousand battles, stained with the blood of their
 brothers and their friends, has raised them from base to regal estate,
 have found in place of the felicity they expected an infinity of cares
 and fears, and have proved by experience that a chalice may be
 poisoned, though it be of gold, and set on the table of a king. 
<milestone id="p02070005" />Many
 <pb n="118" />have most ardently desired beauty and strength and other advantages
 of person, and have only been taught their error by the death or
 dolorous life which these very advantages entailed upon them.
 <milestone id="p02070006" />And so, not to instance each particular human desire, I say, in sum,
 that there is none of them that men may indulge in full confidence
 as exempt from the chances and changes of fortune; wherefore, if we
 would act rightly, we ought to school ourselves to take and be
 content with that which He gives us, who alone knows and can
 afford us that of which we have need. <milestone id="p02070007" />But, divers as are the
 aberrations of desire to which men are prone, so, gracious ladies,
 there is one to which you are especially liable, in that you are unduly
 solicitous of beauty, insomuch, that, not content with the charms
 which nature has allotted you, you endeavour to enhance them with
 wondrous ingenuity of art; wherefore I am minded to make you
 acquainted with the coil of misadventures in which her beauty
 involved a fair Saracen, who in the course of, perhaps, four years was
 wedded nine several times.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02070008" />There was of yore a Soldan of Babylon,<note>I. e. according to
 medieval usage, Egypt.</note> by name of Beminedab,
 who in his day had cause enough to be well content with his luck.
 <milestone id="p02070009" />Many children male and female had he, and among them a daughter,
 Alatiel by name, who by common consent of all that saw her was
 the most beautiful woman then to be found in the world. Now the
 Soldan, having been signally aided by the King of Algarve<note>I. e.
 Garbo, the coast of Africa opposite Andalusia and Granada.</note> in
 inflicting a great defeat upon a host of Arabs that had attacked him,
 had at his instance and by way of special favour given Alatiel to the
 King to wife; wherefore, with an honourable escort of gentlemen
 and ladies most nobly and richly equipped, he placed her aboard a
 well-armed, well-furnished ship, and, commending her to God, sped
 her on her journey. <milestone id="p02070010" />The mariners, as soon as the weather was
 favourable, hoisted sail, and for some days after their departure from
 Alexandria had a prosperous voyage; but when they had passed
 Sardinia, and were beginning to think that they were nearing their
 journey's end, they were caught one day between divers cross winds,
 each blowing with extreme fury, whereby the ship laboured so sorely
 that not only the lady but the seamen from time to time gave them<pb n="119" />selves
 up for lost. <milestone id="p02070011" />But still, most manfully and skilfully they
 struggled might and main with the tempest, which, ever waxing
 rather than waning, buffeted them for two days with immense unintermittent
 surges; and being not far from the island of Majorca, as
 the third night began to close in, wrapt in clouds and mist and thick
 darkness, so that they saw neither the sky nor aught else, nor by any
 nautical skill might conjecture where they were, they felt the ship's
 timbers part. <milestone id="p02070012" />Wherefore, seeing no way to save the ship, each thought
 only how best to save himself, and, a boat being thrown out, the
 masters first, and then the men, one by one, though the first-comers
 sought with knives in their hands to bar the passage of the rest, all,
 rather than remain in the leaky ship, crowded into it, and there
 found the death which they hoped to escape. <milestone id="p02070013" />For the boat, being in
 such stress of weather and with such a burden quite unmanageable,
 went under, and all aboard her perished; whereas the ship, leaky
 though she was, and all but full of water, yet, driven by the fury of
 the tempest, was hurled with prodigious velocity upon the shore of
 the island of Majorca, and struck it with such force as to embed
 herself in the sand, perhaps a stone's throw from terra firma, where
 she remained all night beaten and washed by the sea, but no more
 to be moved by the utmost violence of the gale. None had remained
 aboard her but the lady and her women, whom the malice of
 the elements and their fears had brought to the verge of death.
      <milestone id="p02070014" />When it was broad day and the storm was somewhat abated, the
 lady, half dead, raised her head, and in faltering accents began to call
 first one and then another of her servants. She called in vain, however;
 for those whom she called were too far off to hear. <milestone id="p02070015" />Great
 indeed was her wonder and fear to find herself thus without sight of
 human face or sound of other voice than her own; but, struggling
 to her feet as best she might, she looked about her, and saw the ladies
 that were of her escort, and the other women, all prostrate on the
 deck; so, after calling them one by one, she began at length to touch
 them, and finding few that shewed sign of life, for indeed, between
 grievous sea-sickness and fear, they had little life left, she grew more
 terrified than before. <milestone id="p02070016" />However, being in sore need of counsel, all
 alone as she was, and without knowledge or means of learning where
 she was, she at last induced such as had life in them to get upon their
 feet, with whom, as none knew where the men were gone, and the
 <pb n="120" />ship was now full of water and visibly breaking up, she abandoned
 herself to piteous lamentations.</p><p><milestone id="p02070017" />It was already none before they descried any one on the shore or
 elsewhere to whom they could make appeal for help; but shortly
 after none it so chanced that a gentleman, Pericone da Visalgo by
 name, being on his return from one of his estates, passed that way
 with some mounted servants. Catching sight of the ship, he apprehended
 the circumstances at a glance, and bade one of his servants
 try to get aboard her, and let him know the result. <milestone id="p02070018" />The servant
 with some difficulty succeeded in boarding the vessel, and found the
 gentle lady with her few companions ensconced under shelter of the
 prow, and shrinking timidly from observation. <milestone id="p02070019" />At the first sight of
 him they wept, and again and again implored him to have pity on
 them; but finding that he did not understand them, nor they him,
 they sought by gestures to make him apprehend their forlorn
 condition.</p><p><milestone id="p02070020" />With these tidings the servant, after making such survey of the
 ship as he could, returned to Pericone, who forthwith caused the
 ladies, and all articles of value which were in the ship and could be
 removed, to be brought off her, and took them with him to one of
 his castles. The ladies' powers were soon in a measure restored by
 food and rest, and by the honour which was paid to Alatiel, and
 Alatiel alone by all the rest, as well as by the richness of her dress,
 Pericone perceived that she must be some great lady. <milestone id="p02070021" />Nor, though
 she was still pale, and her person bore evident marks of the sea's
 rough usage, did he fail to note that it was cast in a mould of
 extraordinary
 beauty. Wherefore his mind was soon made up that, if she
 lacked a husband, he would take her to wife, and that, if he could
 not have her to wife, then he would make her his mistress. <milestone id="p02070022" />So
 this ardent lover, who was a man of powerful frame and haughty
 mien, devoted himself for several days to the service of the
 lady with excellent effect, for the lady completely recovered her
 strength and spirits, so that her beauty far exceeded Pericone's most
 sanguine conjectures. Great therefore beyond measure was his
 sorrow that he understood not her speech, nor she his, so that neither
 could know who the other was; but being inordinately enamoured of
 her beauty, he sought by such mute blandishments as he could devise
 to declare his love, and bring her of her own accord to gratify his
 <pb n="121" />desire. All in vain, however; she repulsed his advances point blank;
 whereby his passion only grew the stronger. <milestone id="p02070023" />So some days passed;
 and the lady perceiving Pericone's constancy, and bethinking her that
 sooner or later she must yield either to force or to love, and gratify his
 passion, and judging by what she observed of the customs of the people
 that she was amongst Christians, and in a part where, were she able
 to speak their language, she would gain little by making herself
 known, determined with a lofty courage to stand firm and immovable
 in this extremity of her misfortunes. <milestone id="p02070024" />Wherefore she bade the
 three women, who were all that were left to her, on no account to let
 any know who they were, unless they were so circumstanced that
 they might safely count on assistance in effecting their escape: she
 also exhorted them most earnestly to preserve their chastity, averring
 that she was firmly resolved that none but her husband should enjoy
 her. The women heartily assented, and promised that her injunctions
 should be obeyed to the utmost of their power.</p><p><milestone id="p02070025" />Day by day Pericone's passion waxed more ardent, being fomented
 by the proximity and contrariety of its object. Wherefore seeing
 that blandishment availed nothing, he was minded to have recourse to
 wiles and stratagems, and in the last resort to force. 
<milestone id="p02070026" />The lady,
 debarred by her law from the use of wine, found it, perhaps, on that
 account all the more palatable; which Pericone observing determined
 to enlist Bacchus in the service of Venus. So, ignoring her
 coyness, he provided one evening a supper, which was ordered with
 all possible pomp and beauty, and graced by the presence of the lady.
 No lack was there of incentives to hilarity; and Pericone directed
 the servant who waited on Alatiel to ply her with divers sorts of
 blended wines; <milestone id="p02070027" />which command the man faithfully executed. She,
 suspecting nothing, and seduced by the delicious flavour of the
 liquor, drank somewhat more freely than was seemly, and forgetting
 her past woes, became frolicsome, and incited by some women who
 trod some measures in the Majorcan style, she shewed the company
 how they footed it in Alexandria. <milestone id="p02070028" />This novel demeanour was by no
 means lost on Pericone, who saw in it a good omen of his speedy
 success; so, with profuse relays of food and wine he prolonged the
 supper far into the night.</p><p><milestone id="p02070029" />When the guests were at length gone, he attended the lady alone
 to her chamber, where, the heat of the wine overpowering the cold
 <pb n="122" />counsels of modesty, she made no more account of Pericone's presence
 than if he had been one of her women, and forthwith undressed and
 went to bed. <milestone id="p02070030" />Pericone was not slow to follow her, and as soon as
 the light was out lay down by her side, and taking her in his arms,
 without the least demur on her part, began to solace himself with her
 after the manner of lovers; which experience--she knew not till then
 with what horn men butt--caused her to repent that she had not
 yielded to his blandishments; nor did she thereafter wait to be
 invited to such nights of delight, but many a time declared her readiness,
 not by words, for she had none to convey her meaning, but by
 gestures.</p><p><milestone id="p02070031" />But this great felicity which she now shared with Pericone was
 not to last: for not content with making her, instead of the consort
 of a king, the mistress of a castellan, Fortune had now in store for her
 a harsher experience, though of an amorous character. <milestone id="p02070032" />Pericone had
 a brother, twenty-five years of age, fair and fresh as a rose, his name
 Marato. On sight of Alatiel Marato had been mightily taken with
 her; he inferred from her bearing that he stood high in her good
 graces; he believed that nothing stood between him and the gratification
 of his passion but the jealous vigilance with which Pericone
 guarded her. So musing, he hit upon a ruthless expedient, which
 had effect in action as hasty as heinous.</p><p><milestone id="p02070033" />It so chanced that there then lay in the port of the city a ship,
 commanded by two Genoese, bound with a cargo of merchandise for
 Klarenza in the Morea: her sails were already hoist; and she tarried
 only for a favourable breeze. Marato approached the masters and
 arranged with them to take himself and the lady aboard on the
 following night. <milestone id="p02070034" />This done he concerted further action with some
 of his most trusty friends, who readily lent him their aid to carry his
 design into execution. So on the following evening towards nightfall,
 the conspirators stole unobserved into Pericone's house, which
 was entirely unguarded, and there hid themselves, as pre-arranged.
 <milestone id="p02070035" />Then, as the night wore on, Marato shewed them where Pericone
 and the lady slept, and they entered the room, and slew Pericone.
 The lady thus rudely roused wept; but silencing her by menaces of
 death they carried her off with the best part of Pericone's treasure,
 and hied them unobserved to the coast, where Marato parted from his
 companions, and forthwith took the lady aboard the ship. <milestone id="p02070036" />The wind
 <pb n="123" />was now fair and fresh, the mariners spread the canvas, and the vessel
 sped on her course.</p><p><milestone id="p02070037" />This new misadventure, following so hard upon the former, caused
 the lady no small chagrin; but Marato, with the aid of the good St.
 Crescent-in-hand that God has given us, found means to afford her
 such consolation that she was already grown so familiar with him as
 entirely to forget Pericone, when Fortune, not content with her
 former caprices, added a new dispensation of woe; <milestone id="p02070038" />for what with
 the beauty of her person, which, as we have often said, was extraordinary,
 and the exquisite charm of her manners, the two young
 men, who commanded the ship, fell so desperately in love with her
 that they thought of nothing but how they might best serve and
 please her, so only that Marato should not discover the reason of their
 assiduous attentions. <milestone id="p02070039" />And neither being ignorant of the other's love,
 they held secret counsel together, and resolved to make conquest of
 the lady on joint account: as if love admitted of being held in partnership
 like merchandise or money. <milestone id="p02070040" />Which design being thwarted
 by the jealousy with which Alatiel was guarded by Marato, they
 chose a day and hour, when the ship was speeding amain under canvas,
 and Marato was on the poop looking out over the sea and quite off
 his guard; and going stealthily up behind him, they suddenly laid
 hands on him, and threw him into the sea, and were already more
 than a mile on their course before any perceived that Marato was
 overboard. Which when the lady learned, and knew that he was
 irretrievably lost, she relapsed into her former plaintive mood. 
<milestone id="p02070041" />But
 the twain were forthwith by her side with soft speeches and profuse
 promises, which, however ill she understood them, were not altogether
 inapt to allay a grief which had in it more of concern for her own
 hapless self than of sorrow for her lost lover. So, in course of time,
 the lady beginning visibly to recover heart, they began privily to
 debate which of them should first take her to bed with him; <milestone id="p02070042" />and
 neither being willing to give way to the other, and no compromise
 being discoverable, high words passed between them, and the dispute
 grew so hot, that they both waxed very wroth, drew their knives, and
 rushed madly at one another, and before they could be parted by their
 men, several stabs had been given and received on either side, whereby
 the one fell dead on the spot, and the other was severely wounded in
 divers parts of the body. <milestone id="p02070043" />The lady was much disconcerted to find
 <pb n="124" />herself thus alone with none to afford her either succour or counsel,
 and was mightily afraid lest the wrath of the kinsfolk and friends of
 the twain should vent itself upon her. From this mortal peril she
 was, however, delivered by the intercessions of the wounded man and
 their speedy arrival at Klarenza.</p><p><milestone id="p02070044" />As there she tarried at the same inn with her wounded lover, the
 fame of her great beauty was speedily bruited abroad, and reached the
 ears of the Prince of the Morea, who was then staying there. The
 Prince was curious to see her, and having so done, pronounced her even
 more beautiful than rumour had reported her; nay, he fell in love
 with her in such a degree that he could think of nought else; and
 having heard in what guise she had come thither, he deemed that he
 might have her. <milestone id="p02070045" />While he was casting about how to compass his
 end, the kinsfolk of the wounded man, being apprised of the fact,
 forthwith sent her to him to the boundless delight, as well of the lady,
 who saw therein her deliverance from a great peril, as of the Prince.
 <milestone id="p02070046" />The royal bearing, which enhanced the lady's charms, did not escape
 the Prince, who, being unable to discover her true rank, set her down
 as at any rate of noble lineage; wherefore he loved her as much again
 as before, and shewed her no small honour, treating her not as his
 mistress but as his wife. <milestone id="p02070047" />So the lady, contrasting her present happy
 estate with her past woes, was comforted; and, as her gaiety revived,
 her beauty waxed in such a degree that all the Morea talked of it and
 of little else: <milestone id="p02070048" />insomuch that the Prince's friend and kinsman, the
 young, handsome and gallant Duke of Athens, was smitten with a
 desire to see her, and taking occasion to pay the Prince a visit, as he
 was now and again wont to do, came to Klarenza with a goodly
 company of honourable gentlemen. The Prince received him with
 all distinction and made him heartily welcome, but did not at first
 shew him the lady. By and by, however, their conversation began
 to turn upon her and her charms, and the Duke asked if she were
 really so marvellous a creature as folk said. <milestone id="p02070049" />The Prince replied:
 <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but even more so; and thereof thou shalt have better assurance
 than my words, to wit, the witness of thine own eyes.</q> 
<milestone id="p02070050" />So, without
 delay, for the Duke was now all impatience, they waited on the lady,
 who was prepared for their visit, and received them very courteously
 and graciously. They seated her between them, and being debarred
 from the pleasure of conversing with her, for of their speech she
 <pb n="125" />understood little or nothing, they both, and especially the Duke, who
 was scarce able to believe that she was of mortal mould, gazed upon
 her in mute admiration; whereby the Duke, cheating himself with
 the idea that he was but gratifying his curiosity, drank with his eyes,
 unawares, deep draughts of the poisoned chalice of love, and, to his
 own lamentable hurt, fell a prey to a most ardent passion. 
<milestone id="p02070051" />His first
 thought, when they had left her, and he had time for reflection, was
 that the Prince was the luckiest man in the world to have a creature so
 fair to solace him; and swayed by his passion, his mind soon inclined
 to divers other and less honourable meditations, whereof the issue was
 that, come what might, he would despoil the Prince of his felicity, and,
 if possible, make it his own. 
<milestone id="p02070052" />This resolution was no sooner taken than,
 being of a hasty temperament, he cast to the winds all considerations
 of honour and justice, and studied only how to compass his end by
 craft. So, one day, as the first step towards the accomplishment of his
 evil purpose, he arranged with the Prince's most trusted chamberlain,
 one Ciuriaci, that his horses and all other his personal effects should,
 with the utmost secrecy, be got ready against a possible sudden departure:
 and then at nightfall, attended by a single comrade (both
 carrying arms), he was privily admitted by Ciuriaci into the Prince's
 chamber. It was a hot night, and the Prince had risen without
 disturbing the lady, and was standing bare to the skin at an open
 window fronting the sea, to enjoy a light breeze that blew thence.
 <milestone id="p02070053" />So, by preconcert with his comrade, the Duke stole up to the window,
 and in a trice ran the Prince through the body, and caught him up,
 and threw him out of the window. <milestone id="p02070054" />The palace was close by the
 sea, but at a considerable altitude above it, and the window, through
 which the Prince's body was thrown, looked over some houses, which,
 being sapped by the sea, had become ruinous, and were rarely or
 never visited by a soul; whereby, as the Duke had foreseen, the fall
 of the Prince's body passed, as indeed it could not but pass, unobserved.
 <milestone id="p02070055" />Thereupon the Duke's accomplice whipped out a halter,
 which he had brought with him for the purpose, and, making as if he
 were but in play, threw it round Ciuriaci's neck, drew it so tight that
 he could not utter a sound, and then, with the Duke's aid, strangled
 him, and sent him after his master. <milestone id="p02070056" />All this was accomplished, as the
 Duke knew full well, without awakening any in the palace, not even
 the lady, whom he now approached with a light, and holding it
 <pb n="126" />over the bed gently uncovered her person, as she lay fast asleep, and
 surveyed her from head to foot to his no small satisfaction; for fair
 as she had seemed to him dressed, he found her unadorned charms
 incomparably greater. <milestone id="p02070057" />As he gazed, his passion waxed beyond
 measure, and, reckless of his recent crime, and of the blood which
 still stained his hands, he got forthwith into the bed; and she, being
 too sound asleep to distinguish between him and the Prince, suffered
 him to lie with her.</p><p><milestone id="p02070058" />But, boundless as was his delight, it brooked no long continuance;
 so, rising, he called to him some of his comrades, by whom he had
 the lady secured in such manner that she could utter no sound, and
 borne out of the palace by the same secret door by which he had
 gained entrance; he then set her on horseback and in dead silence
 put his troop in motion, taking the road to Athens. <milestone id="p02070059" />He did not,
 however, venture to take the lady to Athens, where she would have
 encountered his Duchess--for he was married--but lodged her in a
 very beautiful villa which he had hard by the city overlooking the
 sea, where, most forlorn of ladies, she lived secluded, but with no lack
 of meet and respectful service.</p><p><milestone id="p02070060" />On the following morning the Prince's courtiers awaited his
      rising until none, but perceiving no sign of it, opened the doors,
      which had not been secured, and entered his bedroom. Finding it
      vacant, they supposed that the Prince was gone off privily somewhere
      to have a few days of unbroken delight with his fair lady; and so
      they gave themselves no further trouble. <milestone id="p02070061" />But the next day it so
      chanced that an idiot, roaming about the ruins where lay the corpses
      of the Prince and Ciuriaci, drew the latter out by the halter and
      went off dragging it after him. The corpse was soon recognised by
      not a few, who, at first struck dumb with amazement, soon recovered
      sense enough to cajole the idiot into retracing his steps and shewing
      them the spot where he had found it; and having thus, to the
      immeasurable grief of all the citizens, discovered the Prince's body,
      they buried it with all honour. Needless to say that no pains were
      spared to trace the perpetrators of so heinous a crime, and that the
      absence and evidently furtive departure of the Duke of Athens
      caused him to be suspected both of the murder and of the abduction
      of the lady. <milestone id="p02070062" />So the citizens were instant with one accord that
      the Prince's brother, whom they chose as his successor, should exact
      <pb n="127" />the debt of vengeance; and he, having satisfied himself by further
      investigation that their suspicion was well founded, summoned to his
      aid his kinsfolk, friends and divers vassals, and speedily gathered a
      large, powerful and well-equipped army, with intent to make war
      upon the Duke of Athens. <milestone id="p02070063" />The Duke, being informed of his
      movements, made ready likewise to defend himself with all his
      power; nor had he any lack of allies, among whom the Emperor of
      Constantinople sent his son, Constantine, and his nephew, Manuel,
      with a great and goodly force. The two young men were honourably
      received by the Duke, and still more so by the Duchess, who
      was Constantine's sister.</p><p><milestone id="p02070064" />Day by day war grew more imminent; and at last the Duchess
      took occasion to call Constantine and Manuel into her private
      chamber, and with many tears told them the whole story at large,
      explaining the casus belli, dilating on the indignity which she
      suffered
      at the hands of the Duke, if, as was believed, he really kept a mistress
      in secret, and beseeching them in most piteous accents to do the best
      they could to devise some expedient whereby the Duke's honour
      might be cleared, and her own peace of mind assured. <milestone id="p02070065" />The young
      men knew exactly how matters stood; and so, without wearying the
      Duchess with many questions, they did their best to console her, and
      succeeded in raising her hopes. Before taking their leave they
      learned from her where the lady was, <milestone id="p02070066" />whose marvellous beauty they
      had heard lauded so often; and being eager to see her, they besought
      the Duke to afford them an opportunity. Forgetful of what a like
      complaisance had cost the Prince, he consented, and next morning
      brought them to the villa where the lady lived, and with her and a
      few of his boon companions regaled them with a lordly breakfast,
      which was served in a most lovely garden. <milestone id="p02070067" />Constantine had no
      sooner seated himself and surveyed the lady, than he was lost in
      admiration, inly affirming that he had never seen so beautiful a
      creature, and that for such a prize the Duke, or any other man,
      might well be pardoned treachery or any other crime: he scanned
      her again and again, and ever with more and more admiration; whereby
      it fared with him even as it had fared with the Duke. <milestone id="p02070068" />He went
      away hotly in love with her, and dismissing all thought of the war,
      cast about for some method by which, without betraying his passion to
      any, he might devise some means of wresting the lady from the Duke.</p><pb n="128" /><p><milestone id="p02070069" />As he thus burned and brooded, the Prince drew dangerously
      near the Duke's dominions; wherefore order was given for an
      advance, and the Duke, with Constantine and the rest, marshalled
      his forces and led them forth from Athens to bar the Prince's passage
      of the frontier at certain points. <milestone id="p02070070" />Some days thus passed, during
      which Constantine, whose mind and soul were entirely absorbed by
      his passion for the lady, bethought him, that, as the Duke was no
      longer in her neighbourhood, he might readily compass his end. He
      therefore feigned to be seriously unwell, and, having by this pretext
      obtained the Duke's leave, he ceded his command to Manuel, and
      returned to his sister at Athens. He had not been there many days
      before the Duchess recurred to the dishonour which the Duke did
      her by keeping the lady; whereupon he said that of that, if she
      approved, he would certainly relieve her by seeing that the lady was
      removed from the villa to some distant place. <milestone id="p02070071" />The Duchess,
      supposing that Constantine was prompted not by jealousy of the
      Duke but by jealousy for her honour, gave her hearty consent to his
      plan, provided he so contrived that the Duke should never know that
      she had been privy to it; on which point Constantine gave her ample
      assurance. So, being authorised by the Duchess to act as he might
      deem best, <milestone id="p02070072" />he secretly equipped a light bark and manned her with
      some of his men, to whom he confided his plan, bidding them lie to
      off the garden of the lady's villa; and so, having sent the bark
      forward, he hied him with other of his men to the villa. He gained
      ready admission of the servants, and was made heartily welcome by
      the lady, who, at his desire, attended by some of her servants, walked
      with him and some of his comrades in the garden. <milestone id="p02070073" />By and by,
      feigning that he had a message for her from the Duke, he drew her
      aside towards a gate that led down to the sea, and which one of his
      confederates had already opened. A concerted signal brought the
      bark alongside, and to seize the lady and set her aboard the bark was
      but the work of an instant. Her retinue hung back as they heard
      Constantine menace with death whoso but stirred or spoke, and
      suffered him, protesting that what he did was done not to wrong the
      Duke but solely to vindicate his sister's honour, to embark with his
      men. <milestone id="p02070074" />The lady wept, of course, but Constantine was at her side,
      the rowers gave way, and the bark, speeding like a thing of life over
      the waves, made Egina shortly after dawn. <milestone id="p02070075" />There Constantine and
      <pb n="129" />the lady landed, she still lamenting her fatal beauty, and took a
      little
      rest and pleasure. Then, re-embarking, they continued their voyage,
      and in the course of a few days reached Chios, which Constantine,
      fearing paternal censure, and that he might be deprived of his fair
      booty, deemed a safe place of sojourn. So, after some days of repose
      the lady ceased to bewail her harsh destiny, and suffering Constantine
      to console her as his predecessors had done, began once more to enjoy
      the good gifts which Fortune sent her.</p><p><milestone id="p02070076" />Now while they thus dallied, Osbech, King of the Turks, who
      was perennially at war with the Emperor, came by chance to
      Smyrna; and there learning that Constantine was wantoning in
      careless ease at Chios with a lady of whom he had made prize, he
      made a descent by night upon the island with an armed flotilla.
      Landing his men in dead silence, he made captives of not a few of
      the Chians whom he surprised in their beds; others, who took the
      alarm and rushed to arms, he slew; and having wasted the whole
      island with fire, he shipped the booty and the prisoners, and sailed
      back to Smyrna. <milestone id="p02070077" />As there he overhauled the booty, he lit upon the
      fair lady, and knew her for the same that had been taken in bed
      and fast asleep with Constantine: whereat, being a young man,
      he was delighted beyond measure, and made her his wife out of
      hand with all due form and ceremony. And so for several months
      he enjoyed her.</p><p><milestone id="p02070078" />Now there had been for some time and still was a treaty pending
      between the Emperor and Basano, King of Cappadocia, whereby
      Basano with his forces was to fall on Osbech on one side while the
      Emperor attacked him on the other. Some demands made by
      Basano, which the Emperor deemed unreasonable, had so far retarded
      the conclusion of the treaty; but no sooner had the Emperor learned
      the fate of his son than, distraught with grief, he forthwith conceded
      the King of Cappadocia's demands, and was instant with him to fall
      at once upon Osbech while he made ready to attack him on the other
      side. <milestone id="p02070079" />Getting wind of the Emperor's design, Osbech collected his
      forces, and, lest he should be caught and crushed between the convergent
      armies of two most mighty potentates, advanced against the
      King of Cappadocia. The fair lady he left at Smyrna in the care of
      a faithful dependant and friend, and after a while joined battle with
      the King of Cappadocia, in which battle he was slain, and his army
      <pb n="130" />defeated and dispersed. Wherefore Basano with his victorious host
      advanced, carrying everything before him, upon Smyrna, and receiving
      everywhere the submission due to a conqueror.</p><p><milestone id="p02070080" />Meanwhile Osbech's dependant, by name Antioco, who had
      charge of the fair lady, was so smitten with her charms that, albeit
      he was somewhat advanced in years, he broke faith with his friend
      and lord, and allowed himself to become enamoured of her. He had
      the advantage of knowing her language, which counted for much with
      one who for some years had been, as it were, compelled to live the
      life of a deaf mute, finding none whom she could understand or by
      whom she might be understood; and goaded by passion, he in the
      course of a few days established such a degree of intimacy with her
      that in no long time it passed from friendship into love, so that their
      lord, far away amid the clash of arms and the tumult of the battle,
      was forgotten, and marvellous pleasure had they of one another
      between the sheets.</p><p><milestone id="p02070081" />However, news came at last of Osbech's defeat and death, and
      the victorious and unchecked advance of Basano, whose advent they
      were by no means minded to await. Wherefore, taking with them
      the best part of the treasure that Osbech had left there, they hied
      them with all possible secrecy to Rhodes. There they had not along
      abode before Antioco fell ill of a mortal disease. <milestone id="p02070082" />He had then with
      him a Cypriote merchant, an intimate and very dear friend, to whom,
      as he felt his end approach, he resolved to leave all that he possessed,
      including his dear lady. <milestone id="p02070083" />So, when he felt death imminent, he called
      them to him and said: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis now quite evident to me that my life
	is fast ebbing away; and sorely do I regret it, for never had I so much
	pleasure of life as now. Well content indeed I am in one respect,
	in that, as die I must, I at least die in the arms of the two persons
	whom I love more than any other in the world, to wit, in thine
	arms, dearest friend, and those of this lady, whom, since I have
	known her, I have loved more than myself. <milestone id="p02070084" />But yet 'tis grievous to
	me to know that I must leave her here in a strange land with none
	to afford her either protection or counsel; and but that I leave her
	with thee, who, I doubt not, wilt have for my sake no less care of her
	than thou wouldst have had of me, 'twould grieve me still more;
	wherefore with all my heart and soul I pray thee, that, if I die, thou
	take her with all else that belongs to me into thy charge, and so
	<pb n="131" />acquit thyself of thy trust as thou mayst deem conducive to
	the peace of my soul. <milestone id="p02070085" />And of thee, dearest lady, I entreat one
	favour, that I be not forgotten of thee, after my death, so that there
	whither I go it may still be my boast to be beloved here of the
	most beautiful lady that nature ever formed. Let me but die
	with these two hopes assured, and without doubt I shall depart in
	peace.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02070086" />Both the merchant and the lady wept to hear him thus speak,
      and, when he had done, comforted him, and promised faithfully, in the
      event of his death, to do even as he besought them. He died almost
      immediately afterwards, and was honourably buried by them. <milestone id="p02070087" />A
      few days sufficed the merchant to wind up all his affairs in Rhodes;
      and being minded to return to Cyprus aboard a Catalan boat that was
      there, he asked the fair lady what she purposed to do if he went back
      to Cyprus. The lady answered, that, if it were agreeable to him, she
      would gladly accompany him, hoping that for love of Antioco he
      would treat and regard her as his sister. <milestone id="p02070088" />The merchant replied that
      it would afford him all the pleasure in the world; and, to protect her
      from insult until their arrival in Cyprus, he gave her out as his wife,
      and, suiting action to word, slept with her on the boat in an alcove
      in a little cabin in the poop. <milestone id="p02070089" />Whereby that happened which on
      neither side was intended when they left Rhodes, to wit, that the
      darkness and the comfort and the warmth of the bed, forces of no
      mean efficacy, did so prevail with them that dead Antioco was forgotten
      alike as lover and as friend, and by a common impulse they
      began to wanton together, insomuch that before they were arrived
      at Baffa, where the Cypriote resided, they were indeed man and wife.
      At Baffa the lady tarried with the merchant a good while, 
      <milestone id="p02070090" />during
      which it so befell that a gentleman, Antigono by name, a man of
      ripe age and riper wisdom but no great wealth, being one that had
      had vast and various experience of affairs in the service of the King
      of Cyprus but had found fortune adverse to him, came to Baffa on
      business; and <milestone id="p02070091" />passing one day by the house where the fair lady was
      then living by herself, for the Cypriote merchant was gone to Armenia
      with some of his wares, he chanced to catch sight of the lady at
      one of the windows, and, being struck by her extraordinary beauty,
      regarded her attentively, and began to have some vague recollection
      of having seen her before, but could by no means remember where.
      <pb n="132" />
      <milestone id="p02070092" />The fair lady, however, so long the sport of Fortune, but now nearing
      the term of her woes, no sooner saw Antigono than she remembered
      to have seen him in her father's service, and in no mean
      capacity, at Alexandria. Wherefore she forthwith sent for him,
      hoping that by his counsel she might elude her merchant and be
      reinstated in her true character and dignity of princess. 
      <milestone id="p02070093" />When he
      presented himself, she asked him with some embarrassment whether
      he were, as she took him to be, Antigono of Famagosta. 
      <milestone id="p02070094" />He answered
      in the affirmative, adding: <q direct="unspecified">And of you, madam, I have a sort of
	recollection, though I cannot say where I have seen you; wherefore,
	so it irk you not, bring, I pray you, yourself to my remembrance.</q>
      <milestone id="p02070095" />Satisfied that it was Antigono himself, the lady in a flood of tears threw
      herself upon him to his no small amazement, and embraced his neck:
      then, after a little while, she asked him whether he had never seen
      her in Alexandria. The question awakened Antigono's memory; he
      at once recognised Alatiel, the Soldan's daughter, whom he had thought
      to have been drowned at sea, and would have paid her due homage;
      but she would not suffer it, and bade him be seated with her for a
      while. <milestone id="p02070096" />Being seated, he respectfully asked her, how, and when and
      whence she had come thither, seeing that all Egypt believed for
      certain that she had been drowned at sea some years before. 
      <milestone id="p02070097" /><q direct="unspecified">And
	would that so it had been,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">rather than I should
	have led the life that I have led; and so doubtless will my father
	say, if he shall ever come to know of it.</q> And so saying, she
      burst into such a flood of tears that 'twas a wonder to see. 
      <milestone id="p02070098" />Wherefore
      <milestone id="p02070099" />Antigono said to her: <q direct="unspecified">Nay but, madam, be not distressed
	before the occasion arises. I pray you, tell me the story of your
	adventures, and what has been the tenor of your life; perchance
	'twill prove to be no such matter but, God helping us, we may set it
	all straight.</q> <q direct="unspecified">Antigono,</q> said the fair lady, <q direct="unspecified">when I saw thee,
	'twas as if I saw my father, and 'twas the tender love by which I
	am holden to him that prompted me to make myself known to thee,
	though I might have kept my secret; and few indeed there are,
	whom to have met would have afforded me such pleasure as this
	which I have in meeting and recognising thee before all others;
	wherefore I will now make known to thee as to a father that which
	in my evil fortune I have ever kept close. <milestone id="p02070100" />If, when thou hast heard
	my story, thou seest any means whereby I may be reinstated in my
	<pb n="133" />
	former honour, I pray thee use it. If not, disclose to none that thou
	hast seen me or heard aught of me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02070101" />Then, weeping between every word, she told him her whole
      story from the day of the shipwreck at Majorca to that hour.
      Antigono wept in sympathy, and then said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, as throughout
	this train of misfortunes you have happily escaped recognition, I
	undertake to restore you to your father in such sort that you shall be
	dearer to him than ever before, and be afterwards married to the King
	of Algarve. <milestone id="p02070102" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> she asked. Whereupon he explained to her
	in detail how he meant to proceed; and, lest delay should give
	occasion to another to interfere, he went back at once to Famagosta,
	and having obtained audience of the King, thus he spoke: <q direct="unspecified">Sire,
	  so please you, you have it in your power at little cost to yourself to
	  do a thing, which will at once redound most signally to your honour
	  and confer a great boon on me, who have grown poor in your
	  service.</q> 
	<milestone id="p02070103" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> asked the King. Then said Antigono: 
	<q direct="unspecified">At
	  Baffa is of late arrived a fair damsel, daughter of the Soldan, long
	  thought to be drowned, who to preserve her chastity has suffered
	  long and severe hardship. She is now reduced to poverty, and is
	  desirous of returning to her father. If you should be pleased to send
	  her back to him under my escort, your honour and my interest would
	  be served in high and equal measure; nor do I think that such a
	  service would ever be forgotten by the Soldan.</q>
      </q></p><p><milestone id="p02070104" />With true royal generosity the King forthwith signified his
      approval, and had Alatiel brought under honourable escort to Famagosta,
      where, attended by his Queen, he received her with every
      circumstance of festal pomp and courtly magnificence. Schooled by
      Antigono, she gave the King and Queen such a version of her
      adventures as satisfied their inquiries in every particular. 
      <milestone id="p02070105" />So, after a
      few days, the King sent her back to the Soldan under escort of
      Antigono, attended by a goodly company of honourable men and
      women; and of the cheer which the Soldan made her, and not her
      only but Antigono and all his company, it boots not to ask. When she
      was somewhat rested, the Soldan inquired how it was that she was
      yet alive, and where she had been so long without letting him know
      how it fared with her. <milestone id="p02070106" />Whereupon the lady, who had got Antigono's
      lesson by heart, answered thus: <q direct="unspecified">My father, 'twas perhaps the
	twentieth night after my departure from you when our ship parted her
	<pb n="134" />timbers in a terrible storm and went ashore nigh a place called
	Aguamorta, away there in the West: what was the fate of the men
	that were aboard our ship I know not, nor knew I ever; 
	<milestone id="p02070107" />I remember
	only, that, when day came, and I returned, as it were, from death to
	life, the wreck, having been sighted, was boarded by folk from all the
	country-side, intent on plunder; and I and two of my women were
	taken ashore, where the women were forthwith parted from me by
	the young men, nor did I ever learn their fate. Now hear my own.
	<milestone id="p02070108" />Struggling might and main, I was seized by two young men, who
	dragged me, weeping bitterly, by the hair of the head, towards a
	great forest; but, on sight of four men who were then passing that
	way on horseback, they forthwith loosed me and took to flight.
	<milestone id="p02070109" />Whereupon the four men, who struck me as persons of great
	authority, ran up to me; and much they questioned me, and much I
	said to them; but neither did they understand me, nor I them. So,
	after long time conferring together, they set me on one of their
	horses and brought me to a house, where dwelt a community of
	ladies, religious according to their law; and what the men may have
	said I know not, but there I was kindly received and ever honourably
	entreated by all; and with them I did afterwards most reverentially
	pay my devotions to St. Crescent-in-Hollow, who is held in great
	honour by the women of that country. <milestone id="p02070110" />When I had been some
	time with them, and had learned something of their language, they
	asked me who and whence I was: whereto I, knowing that I was in
	a convent, and fearing to be cast out as a foe to their law if I told the
	truth, answered that I was the daughter of a great gentleman of
	Cyprus, who had intended to marry me to a gentleman of Crete;
	but that on the voyage we had been driven out of our course and
	wrecked at Aguamorta. <milestone id="p02070111" />And so I continued, as occasion required,
	observing their usages with much assiduity, lest worse should befall
	me; but being one day asked by their superior, whom they call
 abbess, whether I was minded to go back to Cyprus, I answered that
	there was nought that I desired so much. <milestone id="p02070112" />However, so solicitous for
	my honour was the abbess, that there was none going to Cyprus to
	whom she would entrust me, until, two months or so ago, there
	arrived some worthy men from France, of whom one was a kinsman
	of the abbess, with their wives. They were on their way to visit the
	sepulchre where He whom they hold to be God was buried after He
	<pb n="135" />had suffered death at the hands of the Jews; and the abbess, learning
	their destination, prayed them to take charge of me, and restore me
	to my father in Cyprus. <milestone id="p02070113" />With what cheer, with what honour, these
	gentlemen and their wives entertained me, 'twere long to tell. <milestone id="p02070114" />But,
	in brief, we embarked, and in the course of a few days arrived at
	Baffa, where it was so ordered by the providence of God, who perchance
	took pity on me, that in the very hour of our disembarkation
	I, not knowing a soul and being at a loss how to answer the gentlemen,
	who would fain have discharged the trust laid upon them by
	the reverend abbess and restored me to my father, fell in, on the
	shore, with Antigono, whom I forthwith called, and in our language,
	that I might be understood neither of the gentlemen nor of their
	wives, bade him acknowledge me as his daughter. <milestone id="p02070115" />He understood
	my case at once, made much of me, and to the utmost of his
	slender power honourably requited the gentlemen. He then brought
	me to the King of Cyprus, who accorded me welcome there and
	conduct hither so honourable as words of mine can never describe. It
	aught remains to tell, you may best learn it from the lips of Antigono,
	who has often heard my story.</q>
    </p><p><milestone id="p02070116" />Then Antigono, addressing the Soldan, said: <q direct="unspecified">Sire, what she
 has told you accords with what she has often told me, and with
 what I have learned from the gentlemen and ladies who accompanied
 her. <milestone id="p02070117" />One thing, however, she has omitted, because, I suppose, it
 hardly becomes her to tell it; to wit, all that the gentlemen and
 ladies, who accompanied her, said of the virtuous and gracious and
 noble life which she led with the devout ladies, and of the tears and
 wailings of both the ladies and the gentlemen, when they parted
 with her to me. <milestone id="p02070118" />But were I to essay to repeat all that they said to
 me, the day that now is, and the night that is to follow, were all too
 short: suffice it to say so much as this, that, by what I gathered
 from their words and have been able to see for myself, you may make
 it your boast, that among all the daughters of all your peers that
 wear the crown none can be matched with yours for virtue and true
 worth.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02070119" />By all which the Soldan was so overjoyed that 'twas a wonder to
 see. Again and again he made supplication to God, that of His
 grace power might be vouchsafed him adequately to recompense all
 who had done honour to his daughter, and most especially the King
 <pb n="136" />of Cyprus, for the honourable escort under which he had sent her
 thither; for Antigono he provided a magnificent guerdon, and some
 days later gave him his cong&#232; to return to Cyprus, at the same
 time
 by a special ambassage conveying to the King his grateful acknowledgments
 of the manner in which he had treated his daughter.
 <milestone id="p02070120" />Then, being minded that his first intent, to wit, that his daughter
 should be the bride of the King of Algarve, should not be frustrate,
 he wrote to the King, telling him all, and adding that, if he were
 still minded to have her, he might send for her. <milestone id="p02070121" />The King was
 overjoyed by these tidings, and having sent for her with great pomp,
 gave her on her arrival a hearty welcome. So she, who had lain
 with eight men, in all, perhaps, ten thousand times, was bedded with
 him as a virgin, and made him believe that a virgin she was, and
 lived long and happily with him as his queen: <milestone id="p02070122" />wherefore 'twas
 said: <q direct="unspecified">Mouth, for kisses, was never the worse: like as the moon
 reneweth her course.</q></p></div2>