<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0906"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09060001" />Two young men lodge at an inn, of whom the one lies with
 the host's daughter, his wife by inadvertence lying
 with the other. He that lay with the daughter afterwards
 gets into her father's bed and tells him all,
 taking him to be his comrade. They bandy words:
 whereupon the good woman, apprehending the circumstances,
 gets her to bed with her daughter, and by
 divers apt words re-establishes perfect accord.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09060002" />Calandrino as on former occasions, so also on this, moved the
 company to laughter. However, when the ladies had done talking
 of his doings, the queen called for a story from Pamfilo, who thus
 spoke:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09060003" />Worshipful ladies, this Niccolosa, that Calandrino loved,
 has brought to my mind a story of another Niccolosa; which I am
 minded to tell you, because 'twill shew you how a good woman
 by her quick apprehension avoided a great scandal.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09060004" />In the plain of Mugnone there was not long ago a good man that
 furnished travellers with meat and drink for money, and, for that he
 was in poor circumstances, and had but a little house, gave not lodging
 to every comer, but only to a few that he knew, and if they were
 hard bested.  <milestone id="p09060005" />Now the good man had to wife a very fine woman,
 and by her had two children, to wit, a pretty and winsome girl of
 some fifteen or sixteen summers, as yet unmarried, and a little
 boy, not yet one year old, whom the mother suckled at her own
 breast.  <milestone id="p09060006" />The girl had found favour in the eyes of a goodly and
 mannerly young gentleman of our city, who was not seldom in those
 parts, and loved her to the point of passion. And she, being mightily
 flattered to be loved by such a gallant, studied how to comport herself
 <pb n="291" />so
 debonairly as to retain his regard, and while she did so, grew
 likewise enamoured of him; and divers times, by consent of both
 their love had had its fruition, but that Pinuccio--such was the
 gallant's name--shrank from the disgrace that 'twould bring upon
 the girl and himself alike.  <milestone id="p09060007" />But, as his passion daily waxed apace,
 Pinuccio, yearning to find himself abed with her, bethought him that
 he were best contrive to lodge with her father, deeming, from what
 he knew of her father's economy, that, if he did so, he might effect
 his purpose, and never a soul be the wiser: which idea no sooner
 struck him, than he set about carrying it into effect.</p><p><milestone id="p09060008" />So, late one evening Pinuccio and a trusty comrade, Adriano by
 name, to whom he had confided his love, hired two nags, and having
 set upon them two valises, filled with straw or such-like stuff, sallied
 forth of Florence, and rode by a circuitous route to the plain of
 Mugnone, which they reached after nightfall;  <milestone id="p09060009" />and having fetched a
 compass, so that it might seem as if they were coming from Romagna,
 they rode up to the good man's house, and knocked at the door.
 The good man, knowing them both very well, opened to them forthwith:
 whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Thou must even put us up to-night,</q> quoth
 Pinuccio; <q direct="unspecified">we thought to get into Florence, but, for all the speed
 we could make, we are but arrived here, as thou seest, at this hour.</q>
  <milestone id="p09060010" /><q direct="unspecified">Pinuccio,</q> replied the host, <q direct="unspecified">thou well knowest that I can but
 make a sorry shift to lodge gentlemen like you; but yet, as night
 has overtaken you here, and time serves not to betake you elsewhere,
 I will gladly give you such accommodation as I may.</q>  <milestone id="p09060011" />The two
 gallants then dismounted and entered the inn, and having first looked
 to their horses, brought out some supper that they had carried with
 them, and supped with the host.</p><p>Now the host had but one little bedroom, in which were three
 beds, set, as conveniently as he could contrive, two on one side of the
 room, and the third on the opposite side, but, for all that, there was
 scarce room enough to pass through.  <milestone id="p09060012" />The host had the least discomfortable
 of the three beds made up for the two friends; and having
 quartered them there, some little while afterwards, both being awake,
 but feigning to be asleep, he caused his daughter to get into one of
 the other two beds, while he and his wife took their places in the
 third, the good woman setting the cradle, in which was her little boy,
 beside the bed.  <milestone id="p09060013" />Such, then, being the partition made of the beds,
 <pb n="292" />Pinuccio,
 who had taken exact note thereof, waited only until he
 deemed all but himself to be asleep, and then got softly up and stole
 to the bed in which lay his beloved, and laid himself beside her; and
 she according him albeit a timorous yet a gladsome welcome, he
 stayed there, taking with her that solace of which both were most
 fain.</p><p><milestone id="p09060014" />Pinuccio being thus with the girl, it chanced that certain things,
 being overset by a cat, fell with a noise that aroused the good woman,
 who, fearing that it might be a matter of more consequence, got up
 as best she might in the dark, and betook her to the place whence the
 noise seemed to proceed.  <milestone id="p09060015" />At the same time Adriano, not by reason
 of the noise, which he heeded not, but perchance to answer the call of
 nature, also got up, and questing about for a convenient place, came
 upon the cradle beside the good woman's bed; and not being able
 otherwise to go by, took it up, and set it beside his own bed, and
 when he had accomplished his purpose, went back, and giving never
 a thought to the cradle got him to bed.  <milestone id="p09060016" />The good woman searched
 until she found that the accident was no such matter as she had
 supposed; so without troubling to strike a light to investigate it
 further, she reproved the cat, and returned to the room, and groped
 her way straight to the bed in which her husband lay asleep; but not
 finding the cradle there, quoth she to herself: Alas! blunderer that
 I am, what was I about? God's faith! I was going straight to the
 guests' bed;  <milestone id="p09060017" />and proceeding a little further, she found the cradle, and
 laid herself down by Adriano in the bed that was beside it, taking
 Adriano for her husband; and Adriano, who was still awake, received
 her with all due benignity, and tackled her more than once to her
 no small delight.</p><p><milestone id="p09060018" />Meanwhile Pinuccio fearing lest sleep should overtake him while
 he was yet with his mistress, and having satisfied his desire, got up
 and left her, to return to his bed; but when he got there, coming
 upon the cradle, he supposed that 'twas the host's bed; and so going
 a little further, he laid him down beside the host, who thereupon
 awoke.  <milestone id="p09060019" />Supposing that he had Adriano beside him: <q direct="unspecified">I warrant
 thee,</q> quoth Pinuccio to the host, <q direct="unspecified">there was never so sweet a piece
 of flesh as Niccolosa: by the body of God, such delight have I had
 of her as never had man of woman; and, mark me, since I left thee,
 I have gotten me up to the farm some six times.</q>  <milestone id="p09060020" />Which tidings <pb n="293" />the
 host being none too well pleased to learn, said first of all to
 himself: What the Devil does this fellow here? Then, his
 resentment getting the better of his prudence: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis a gross affront
 thou hast put upon me, Pinuccio,</q> quoth he; <q direct="unspecified">nor know I what
 occasion thou hast to do me such a wrong; but by the body of God
 I will pay thee out.</q>  <milestone id="p09060021" />Pinuccio, who was not the most discreet of
 gallants, albeit he was now apprised of his error, instead of doing his
 best to repair it, retorted: <q direct="unspecified">And how wilt thou pay me out?
 What canst thou do?</q>  <milestone id="p09060022" /><q direct="unspecified">Hark what high words our guests are at
 together!</q> quoth meanwhile the host's wife to Adriano, deeming
 that she spoke to her husband.  <milestone id="p09060023" /><q direct="unspecified">Let them be,</q> replied Adriano
 with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">God give them a bad year: they drank too much
 yestereve.</q>  <milestone id="p09060024" />The good woman had already half recognized her
 husband's angry tones, and now that she heard Adriano's voice, she
 at once knew where she was and with whom. Accordingly, being
 a discreet woman, she started up, and saying never a word, took her
 child's cradle, and, though there was not a ray of light in the room,
 bore it, divining rather than feeling her way, to the side of the bed
 in which her daughter slept;  <milestone id="p09060025" />and then, as if aroused by the noise
 made by her husband, she called him, and asked what he and
 Pinuccio were bandying words about. <q direct="unspecified">Hearest thou not,</q> replied
 the husband, <q direct="unspecified">what he says he has this very night done to
 Niccolosa?</q> <q direct="unspecified">Tush! he lies in the throat,</q>  <milestone id="p09060026" />returned the good
 woman: <q direct="unspecified">he has not lain with Niccolosa; for what time he might
 have done so, I laid me beside her myself, and I have been wide
 awake ever since; and thou art a fool to believe him. You men
 take so many cups before going to bed that then you dream, and
 walk in your sleep, and imagine wonders. 'Tis a great pity you do
 not break your necks. What does Pinuccio there? Why keeps he
 not in his own bed?</q></p><p><milestone id="p09060027" /> <milestone />Whereupon Adriano, in his turn, seeing how adroitly the good
 woman cloaked her own and her daughter's shame: <q direct="unspecified">Pinuccio,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I have told thee a hundred times, that thou shouldst not
 walk about at night; for this thy bad habit of getting up in thy
 dreams and relating thy dreams for truth will get thee into a scrape
 some time or another: come back, and God send thee a bad night.</q>
  <milestone id="p09060028" />Hearing Adriano thus confirm what his wife had said, the host began
 to think that Pinuccio must be really dreaming; so he took him by <pb n="294" />the
 shoulder, and fell a shaking him, and calling him by his name,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">Pinuccio, wake up, and go back to thy bed.</q>  <milestone id="p09060029" />Pinuccio,
 taking his cue from what he had heard, began as a dreamer would be
 like to do, to talk wanderingly; whereat the host laughed amain.
 Then, feigning to be aroused by the shaking, Pinuccio uttered
 Adriano's name, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Is't already day, that thou callest me?</q>
  <milestone id="p09060030" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, 'tis so,</q> quoth Adriano: <q direct="unspecified">come hither.</q> 
 <milestone id="p09060031" />Whereupon Pinuccio,
 making as if he were mighty drowsy, got him up from beside the host,
 and back to bed with Adriano. On the morrow, when they were
 risen, the host fell a laughing and making merry touching Pinuccio and
 his dreams.  <milestone id="p09060032" />And so the jest passed from mouth to mouth, while the
 gallants' horses were groomed and saddled, and their valises adjusted:
 which done, they drank with the host, mounted and rode to Florence,
 no less pleased with the manner than with the matter of the night's
 adventure.  <milestone id="p09060033" />Nor, afterwards, did Pinuccio fail to find other means of
 meeting Niccolosa, who assured her mother that he had unquestionably
 dreamed. For which cause the good woman, calling to mind
 Adriano's embrace, accounted herself the only one that had watched.</p></div2>