<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov1004"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00040001" />Messer Gentile de' Carisendi, being come from Modena,
 disinters a lady that he loves, who has been buried for
 dead. She, being reanimated, gives birth to a male
 child; and Messer Gentile restores her, with her son,
 to Niccoluccio Caccianimico, her husband.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00040002" />A thing marvellous seemed it to all that for liberality a man
 should be ready to sacrifice his own life; and herein they averred
 that Nathan had without doubt left the King of Spain and the Abbot
 of Cluny behind. However, when they had discussed the matter
 diversely and at large, the king, bending his regard on Lauretta,
 signified to her his will that she should tell; and forthwith, accordingly,
 Lauretta began:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00040003" />Goodly matters are they and magnificent that
 have been recounted to you, young ladies; nay, so much of our
 field of discourse is already filled by their grandeur, that for us that
 are yet to tell, there is, methinks, no room left, unless we seek our
 topic there where matter of discourse germane to every theme does
 most richly abound, to wit, in the affairs of love.  <milestone id="p00040004" />For which cause,
 as also for that our time of life cannot but make us especially
 inclinable thereto, I am minded that my story shall be of a feat of
 magnificence done by a lover: which, all things considered, will,
 peradventure, seem to you inferior to none that have been shewn
 you; so it be true that to possess the beloved one, men will part
 with their treasures, forget their enmities, and jeopardize their own
 lives, their honour and their reputation, in a thousand ways.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00040005" />Know, then, that at Bologna, that most famous city of Lombardy,
 there dwelt a knight, Messer Gentile Carisendi by name, worshipful
 alike for his noble lineage and his native worth: who in his youth,
 <pb n="329" />being enamoured of a young gentlewoman named Madonna Catalina,
 wife of one Niccoluccio Caccianimico, and well-nigh despairing, for
 that the lady gave him but a sorry requital of his love, betook him
 to Modena, being called thither as Podest&#224;.  <milestone id="p00040006" />Now what time he
 was there, Niccoluccio being also away from Bologna, and his lady
 gone, for that she was with child, to lie in at a house she had some
 three miles or so from the city, it befell that she was suddenly
 smitten with a sore malady of such and so virulent a quality that it
 left no sign of life in her, so that the very physicians pronounced her
 dead.  <milestone id="p00040007" />And for that the women that were nearest of kin to her
 professed to have been told by her, that she was not so far gone in
 pregnancy that the child could be perfectly formed, they, without
 more ado, laid her in a tomb in a neighbouring church, and after
 long lamentation closed it upon her.</p><p><milestone id="p00040008" />Whereof Messer Gentile being forthwith apprised by one of his
 friends, did, for all she had been most niggardly to him of her favour,
 grieve not a little, and at length fell a communing with himself on
 this wise: So, Madonna Catalina, thou art dead! While thou
 livedst, never a glance of thine might I have; wherefore, now that
 thou art dead, 'tis but right that I go take a kiss from thee.  <milestone id="p00040009" />'Twas
 night while he thus mused; and forthwith, observing strict secrecy
 in his departure, he got him to horse with a single servant, and
 halted not until he was come to the place where the lady was interred;
 and having opened the tomb he cautiously entered it. Then, having
 lain down beside her, he set his face against hers; and again and
 again, weeping profusely the while, he kissed it.  <milestone id="p00040010" />But as 'tis matter
 of common knowledge that the desires of men, and more especially
 of lovers, know no bounds, but crave ever an ampler satisfaction;
 even so Messer Gentile, albeit he had been minded to tarry there
 no longer, now said to himself: Wherefore touch I not her bosom
 a while? I have never yet touched it, nor shall I ever touch it
 again.  <milestone id="p00040011" />Obeying which impulse, he laid his hand on her bosom, and
 keeping it there some time, felt, as he thought, her heart faintly
 beating.  <milestone id="p00040012" />Whereupon, banishing all fear, and examining the body
 with closer attention, he discovered that life was not extinct, though
 he judged it but scant and flickering: and so, aided by his servant,
 he bore her, as gently as he might, out of the tomb; and set her
 before him upon his horse, and brought her privily to his house at
 <pb n="330" />Bologna,  <milestone id="p00040013" />where dwelt his wise and worthy mother, who, being fully
 apprised by him of the circumstances, took pity on the lady, and had
 a huge fire kindled, and a bath made ready, whereby she restored
 her to life. Whereof the first sign she gave was to heave a great
 sigh, and murmur: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! where am I?</q>  <milestone id="p00040014" />To which the worthy
 lady made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Be of good cheer; thou art well lodged.</q>
  <milestone id="p00040015" />By and by the lady, coming to herself, looked about her; and finding
 herself she knew not where, and seeing Messer Gentile before her,
 was filled with wonder, and besought his mother to tell her how she
 came to be there.</p><p>Messer Gentile thereupon told her all.  <milestone id="p00040016" />Sore distressed thereat,
 the lady, after a while, thanked him as best she might; after which
 she besought him by the love that he had borne her, and of his
 courtesy, that she might, while she tarried in his house, be spared
 aught that could impair her honour and her husband's; and that at
 daybreak he would suffer her to return home.  <milestone id="p00040017" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied
 Messer Gentile, <q direct="unspecified">however I did affect you in time past, since God
 in His goodness has, by means of the love I bore you, restored you
 to me alive, I mean not now, or at any time hereafter, to entreat
 you either here or elsewhere, save as a dear sister;  <milestone id="p00040018" />but yet the
 service I have to-night rendered you merits some guerdon: and
 therefore lief had I that you deny me not a favour which I shall ask
 of you.</q>  <milestone id="p00040019" />Whereto the lady graciously made answer that she would
 be prompt to grant it, so only it were in her power, and consonant
 with her honour. Said then Messer Gentile: <q direct="unspecified">Your kinsfolk,
 Madam, one and all, nay, all the folk in Bologna are fully persuaded
 that you are dead: there is therefore none to expect you at home:
 wherefore the favour I crave of you is this, that you will be pleased
 to tarry privily here with my mother, until such time--which will
 be speedily--as I return from Modena.  <milestone id="p00040020" />And 'tis for that I purpose
 to make solemn and joyous donation of you to your husband in
 presence of the most honourable folk of this city that I ask of you
 this grace.</q>  <milestone id="p00040021" />Mindful of what she owed the knight, and witting
 that what he craved was seemly, the lady, albeit she yearned not a
 little to gladden her kinsfolk with the sight of her in the flesh, consented
 to do as Messer Gentile besought her, and thereto pledged
 him her faith.  <milestone id="p00040022" />And scarce had she done so, when she felt that the
 hour of her travail was come; and so, tenderly succoured by Messer
 <pb n="331" />Gentile's mother, she not long after gave birth to a fine boy. Which
 event did mightily enhance her own and Messer Gentile's happiness.
 Then, having made all meet provision for her, and left word that
 she was to be tended as if she were his own wife, Messer Gentile,
 observing strict secrecy, returned to Modena.</p><p><milestone id="p00040023" />His time of office there ended, in anticipation of his return to
 Bologna, he appointed for the morning of his arrival in the city a
 great and goodly banquet at his house, whereto were bidden not a
 few of the gentlemen of Bologna, and among them Niccoluccio
 Caccianimico. Whom, when he was returned and dismounted, he
 found awaiting him, as also the lady, fairer and more healthful than
 ever, and her little son doing well; and so with a gladness beyond
 compare he ranged his guests at table, and regaled them with many
 a course magnificently served.  <milestone id="p00040024" />And towards the close of the feast,
 having premonished the lady of his intention, and concerted with
 her how she should behave, thus he spoke: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, I mind
 me to have once heard tell of (as I deem it) a delightsome custom
 which they have in Persia; to wit, that, when one would do his
 friend especial honour, he bids him to his house, and there shews him
 that treasure, be it wife, or mistress, or daughter, or what not, that
 he holds most dear; assuring him that yet more gladly, were it
 possible, he would shew him his heart. Which custom I am minded
 to observe here in Bologna.  <milestone id="p00040025" />You, of your courtesy, have honoured
 my feast with your presence, and I propose to do you honour in the
 Persian fashion, by shewing you that which in all the world I do,
 and must ever, hold most dear. But before I do so, tell me, I pray
 you, how you conceive of a nice question that I shall lay before you.
	  <milestone id="p00040026" />Suppose that one has in his house a good and most faithful servant,
 who falls sick of a grievous disorder; and that the master tarries not
 for the death of the servant, but has him borne out into the open
 street, and concerns himself no more with him: that then a stranger
 comes by, is moved to pity of the sick man, and takes him to his
 house, and by careful tendance and at no small cost restores him to
 his wonted health.  <milestone id="p00040027" />Now I would fain know whether the first
 master has in equity any just cause to complain of or be aggrieved
 with the second master, if he retain the servant in his employ, and
 refuse to restore him, when so required.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00040028" />The gentlemen discussed the matter after divers fashions, and
 <pb n="332" />all agreed in one sentence, which they committed to Niccoluccio
 Caccianimico, for that he was an eloquent and accomplished speaker,
 to deliver on the part of them all.  <milestone id="p00040029" />Niccoluccio began by commending
 the Persian custom: after which he said that he and the others were
 all of the same opinion, to wit, that the first master had no longer
 any right in his servant, since he had not only abandoned but cast
 him forth; and that by virtue of the second master's kind usage of
 him he must be deemed to have become his servant; wherefore, by
 keeping him, he did the first master no mischief, no violence, no
 wrong. Whereupon the rest that were at the table said, one and all,
 being worthy men, that their judgment jumped with Niccoluccio's
 answer.  <milestone id="p00040030" />The knight, well pleased with the answer, and that 'twas
 Niccoluccio that gave it, affirmed that he was of the same opinion;
 adding: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis now time that I shew you that honour which I
 promised you.</q> He then called two of his servants, and sent them
 to the lady, whom he had caused to be apparelled and adorned with
 splendour, charging them to pray her to be pleased to come and
 gladden the gentlemen with her presence.  <milestone id="p00040031" />So she, bearing in her
 arms her most lovely little son, came, attended by the two servants,
 into the saloon, and by the knight's direction, took a seat beside a
 worthy gentleman: whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> quoth the knight,
 <q direct="unspecified">this is the treasure that I hold, and mean ever to hold, more dear
 than aught else. Behold, and judge whether I have good cause.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00040032" />The gentlemen said not a little in her honour and praise, averring
 that the knight ought indeed to hold her dear: then, as they
 regarded her more attentively, there were not a few that would have
 pronounced her to be the very woman that she was, had they not
 believed that woman to be dead. But none scanned her so closely as
 Niccoluccio, who, the knight being withdrawn a little space, could
 no longer refrain his eager desire to know who she might be, but
 asked her whether she were of Bologna, or from other parts.  <milestone id="p00040033" />The
 lady, hearing her husband's voice, could scarce forbear to answer;
 but yet, not to disconcert the knight's plan, she kept silence.
 Another asked her if that was her little boy; and yet another, if she
 were Messer Gentile's wife, or in any other wise his connection. To
 none of whom she vouchsafed an answer.  <milestone id="p00040034" />Then, Messer Gentile
 coming up: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> quoth one of the guests, <q direct="unspecified">this treasure of
 yours is goodly indeed; but she seems to be dumb: is she so?</q>
 <pb n="333" /> <milestone id="p00040035" /><q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen,</q> quoth Messer Gentile, <q direct="unspecified">that she has not as yet
 spoken is no small evidence of her virtue.</q>  <milestone id="p00040036" /><q direct="unspecified">Then tell us, you, who she
 is,</q> returned the other.  <milestone id="p00040037" /><q direct="unspecified">That,</q> quoth the knight, <q direct="unspecified">will I right
 gladly, so you but promise me, that, no matter what I may say, none
 of you will stir from his place, until I have ended my story.</q>  <milestone id="p00040038" />All
 gave the required promise, and when the tables had been cleared,
 Messer Gentile, being seated beside the lady, thus spoke:
 <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, this lady is that loyal and faithful servant, touching
 whom a brief while ago I propounded to you my question, whom her
 own folk held none too dear, but cast out into the open street as a
 thing vile and no longer good for aught, but I took thence, and by
 my careful tendance wrested from the clutch of death; whom God,
 regardful of my good will, has changed from the appalling aspect of
 a corpse to the thing of beauty that you see before you.  <milestone id="p00040039" />But for
 your fuller understanding of this occurrence, I will briefly explain it
 to you.</q>  <milestone id="p00040040" />He then recounted to them in detail all that had happened
 from his first becoming enamoured of the lady to that very hour;
 whereto they hearkened with no small wonder; after which:
 <q direct="unspecified">And so,</q> he added, <q direct="unspecified">unless you, and more especially Niccoluccio,
 are now of another opinion than you were a brief while ago, the
 lady rightly belongs to me, nor can any man lawfully reclaim her
 of me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00040041" />None answered, for all were intent to hear what more he would
 say. But, while Niccoluccio, and some others that were there, wept
 for sympathy, Messer Gentile stood up, and took the little boy in his
 arms and the lady by the hand, and approached Niccoluccio, saying:
  <milestone id="p00040042" /><q direct="unspecified">Rise, my gossip: I do not, indeed, restore thee thy wife, whom thy
 kinsfolk and hers cast forth; but I am minded to give thee this lady,
 my gossip, with this her little boy, whom I know well to be thy son,
 and whom I held at the font, and named Gentile:  <milestone id="p00040043" />and I pray thee that
 she be not the less dear to thee for that she has tarried three months
 in my house; for I swear to thee by that God, who, peradventure,
 ordained that I should be enamoured of her, to the end that my love
 might be, as it has been, the occasion of her restoration to life, that
 never with her father, or her mother, or with thee, did she live more
 virtuously than with my mother in my house.</q>  <milestone id="p00040044" />Which said, he
 turned to the lady, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, I now release you from all
 promises made to me, and so deliver you to Niccoluccio.</q> Then,
 <pb n="334" />leaving the lady and the child in Niccoluccio's embrace, he returned
 to his seat.</p><p><milestone id="p00040045" />Thus to receive his wife and son was to Niccoluccio a delight
 great in the measure of its remoteness from his hope. Wherefore in
 the most honourable terms at his command he thanked the knight,
 whom all the rest, weeping for sympathy, greatly commended for
 what he had done, as did also all that heard thereof.  <milestone id="p00040046" />The lady,
 welcomed home with wondrous cheer, was long a portent to the
 Bolognese, who gazed on her as on one raised from the dead.
 Messer Gentile lived ever after as the friend of Niccoluccio, and his
 and the lady's kinsfolk.</p><p><milestone id="p00040047" />Now what shall be your verdict, gracious ladies? A king's largess,
 though it was of his sceptre and crown, an abbot's reconciliation,
 at no cost to himself, of a malefactor with the Pope, or an old man's
 submission of his throat to the knife of his enemy--will you adjudge
 that such acts as these are comparable to the deed of Messer Gentile?
  <milestone id="p00040048" />Who, though young, and burning with passion, and deeming himself
 justly entitled to that which the heedlessness of another had discarded,
 and he by good fortune had recovered, not only tempered his ardour
 with honour, but having that which with his whole soul he had long
 been bent on wresting from another, did with liberality restore it.
 Assuredly none of the feats aforesaid seem to me like unto this.</p></div2>