<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0403"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04030001" />Three young men love three sisters, and flee with them to
 Crete. The eldest of the sisters slays her lover for
 jealousy. The second saves the life of the first by
 yielding herself to the Duke of Crete. Her lover
 slays her, and makes off with the first: the thira
 sister and her lover are charged with the murder,
 are arrested and confess the crime. They escape
 death by bribing the guards, flee destitute to Rhodes,
 and there in destitution die.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04030002" />Pampinea's story ended, Filostrato mused a while, and then said
 to her: <q direct="unspecified">A little good matter there was that pleased me at the
 close of your story, but, before 'twas reached, there was far too much
 to laugh at, which I could have wished had not been there.</q> Then,
 turning to Lauretta, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, give us something better
 to follow, if so it may be.</q> <milestone id="p04030003" />Lauretta replied with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">Harsh
 beyond measure are you to the lovers, to desire that their end be
 always evil; but, as in duty bound, I will tell a story of three, who
 all alike came to a bad end, having had little joyance of their loves;</q>
 and so saying, she began.</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04030004" />Well may ye wot, young ladies, for 'tis abundantly manifest, that
	there is no vice but most grievous disaster may ensue thereon to him
	that practises it, and not seldom to others; and of all the vices that
	which hurries us into peril with loosest rein is, methinks, anger;
	which is nought but a rash and hasty impulse, prompted by a feeling
	of pain, which banishes reason, shrouds the eyes of the mind in thick
	darkness, and sets the soul ablaze with a fierce frenzy. 
	<milestone id="p04030005" />Which,
	<pb n="285" />though it not seldom befall men, and one rather than another, has
	nevertheless been observed to be fraught in women with more
	disastrous consequences, inasmuch as in them the flame is both more
	readily kindled, and burns more brightly, and with less impediment
	to its vehemence. <milestone id="p04030006" />Wherein is no cause to marvel, for, if we consider
	it, we shall see that 'tis of the nature of fire to lay hold more readily
	of things light and delicate than of matters of firmer and more solid
	substance; and sure it is that we (without offence to the men be it
	spoken) are more delicate than they, and much more mobile. 
	<milestone id="p04030007" />Wherefore,
	seeing how prone we are thereto by nature, and considering
	also our gentleness and tenderness, how soothing and consolatory they
	are to the men with whom we consort, and that thus this madness
	of wrath is fraught with grievous annoy and peril; therefore, that
	with stouter heart we may defend ourselves against it, I purpose by
	my story to shew you, how the loves of three young men, and as
	many ladies, as I said before, were by the anger of one of the ladies
	changed from a happy to a most woeful complexion.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04030008" />Marseilles, as you know, is situate on the coast of Provence, a
 city ancient and most famous, and in old time the seat of many more
 rich men and great merchants than are to be seen there to-day,
 among whom was one Narnald Cluada by name, a man of the lowest
 origin, but a merchant of unsullied probity and integrity, and boundless
 wealth in lands and goods and money, who had by his lady several
 children, three of them being daughters, older, each of them, than
 the other children, who were sons. <milestone id="p04030009" />Two of the daughters, who
 were twins, were, when my story begins, fifteen years old, and the
 third was but a year younger, so that in order to their marriage their
 kinsfolk awaited nothing but the return of Narnald from Spain,
 whither he was gone with his merchandise. One of the twins was
 called Ninette, the other Madeleine; the third daughter's name was
 Bertelle. <milestone id="p04030010" />A young man, Restagnon by name, who, though poor,
 was of gentle blood, was in the last degree enamoured of Ninette,
 and she of him; and so discreetly had they managed the affair,
 that, never another soul in the world witting aught of it, they had
 had joyance of their love, and that for a good while, when it so
 befell that two young friends of theirs, the one Foulques, the other
 Hugues by name, whom their fathers, recently dead, had left very
 wealthy, fell in love, the one with Madeleine, the other with Bertelle.
 <pb n="286" />
<milestone id="p04030011" />Whereof Restagnon being apprised by Ninette bethought him that
 in their love he might find a means to the relief of his necessities.
 He accordingly consorted freely and familiarly with them, accompanying,
 now one, now the other, and sometimes both of them, when
 they went to visit their ladies and his; <milestone id="p04030012" />and when he judged that he
 had made his footing as friendly and familiar as need was, he bade
 them one day to his house, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Comrades most dear, our
 friendship, perchance, may not have left you without assurance of
 the great love I bear you, and that for you I would do even as much
 as for myself: wherefore, loving you thus much, I purpose to impart
 to you that which is in my mind, that in regard thereof, you and I
 together may then resolve in such sort as to you shall seem the best.
 <milestone id="p04030013" />You, if I may trust your words, as also what I seem to have gathered
 from your demeanour by day and by night, burn with an exceeding
 great love for the two ladies whom you affect, as I for their sister.
 For the assuagement whereof, I have good hope that, if you will
 unite with me, I shall find means most sweet and delightsome; to
 wit, on this wise. <milestone id="p04030014" />You possess, as I do not, great wealth: now if
 you are willing to make of your wealth a common stock with me as
 third partner therein, and to choose some part of the world where
 we may live in careless ease upon our substance, without any manner
 of doubt I trust so to prevail that the three sisters with great part of
 their father's substance shall come to live with us, wherever we shall
 see fit to go; whereby, each with his own lady, we shall live as
 three brethren, the happiest men in the world. 'Tis now for you to
 determine whether you will embrace this proffered solace, or let it
 slip from you.</q> 
<milestone id="p04030015" />The two young men, whose love was beyond all
 measure fervent, spared themselves the trouble of deliberation: 'twas
 enough that they heard that they were to have their ladies: wherefore
 they answered, that, so this should ensue, they were ready to do
 as he proposed. Having thus their answer, Restagnon a few days
 later was closeted with Ninette, to whom 'twas a matter of no small
 difficulty for him to get access. Nor had he been long with her
 before he adverted to what had passed between him and the young
 men, and sought to commend the project to her for reasons not a
 few. 
<milestone id="p04030016" />Little need, however, had he to urge her: for to live their life
 openly together was the very thing she desired, far more than he:
 wherefore she frankly answered that she would have it so, that her
 <pb n="287" />sisters would do, more especially in this matter, just as she wished,
 and that he should lose no time in making all the needful arrangements.
 So Restagnon returned to the two young men, who were
 most urgent that it should be done even as he said, and told them
 that on the part of the ladies the matter was concluded. 
<milestone id="p04030017" />And so,
 having fixed upon Crete for their destination, and sold some estates
 that they had, giving out that they were minded to go a trading with
 the proceeds, they converted all else that they possessed into money,
 and bought a brigantine, which with all secrecy they handsomely
 equipped, anxiously expecting the time of their departure, while
 Ninette on her part, knowing well how her sisters were affected,
 did so by sweet converse foment their desire that, till it should be
 accomplished, they accounted their life as nought. 
<milestone id="p04030018" />The night of
 their embarcation being come, the three sisters opened a great chest
 that belonged to their father, and took out therefrom a vast quantity
 of money and jewels, with which they all three issued forth of the
 house in dead silence, as they had been charged, and found their
 three lovers awaiting them; who, having forthwith brought them
 aboard the brigantine, bade the rowers give way, and, tarrying
 nowhere, arrived the next evening at Genoa, where the new lovers
 had for the first time joyance and solace of their love.</p><p><milestone id="p04030019" />Having taken what they needed of refreshment, they resumed
 their course, touching at this port and that, and in less than eight
 days, speeding without impediment, were come to Crete. There
 they bought them domains both beautiful and broad, whereon, hard
 by Candia they built them mansions most goodly and delightsome,
 wherein they lived as barons, keeping a crowd of retainers, with
 dogs, hawks and horses, and speeding the time with their ladies in
 feasting and revelling and merrymaking, none so light-hearted as
 they. <milestone id="p04030020" />Such being the tenor of their life, it so befell that (as 'tis
 matter of daily experience that, however delightsome a thing may
 be, superabundance thereof will breed disgust) Restagnon, much as
 he had loved Ninette, being now able to have his joyance of her
 without stint or restraint, began to weary of her, and by consequence
 to abate somewhat of his love for her. <milestone id="p04030021" />And being mightily pleased
 with a fair gentlewoman of the country, whom he met at a merry-making,
 he set his whole heart upon her, and began to shew himself
 marvellously courteous and gallant towards her; which Ninette
 per<pb n="288" />ceiving
 grew so jealous that he might not go a step but she knew of
 it, and resented it to his torment and her own with high words. 
<milestone id="p04030022" />But
 as, while superfluity engenders disgust, appetite is but whetted when
 fruit is forbidden, so Ninette's wrath added fuel to the flame of
 Restagnon's new love. And whichever was the event, whether in
 course of time Restagnon had the lady's favour or had it not, Ninette,
 whoever may have brought her the tidings, firmly believed that he
 had it; whereby from the depths of distress she passed into a towering
 passion, and thus was transported into such a frenzy of rage that
 all the love she bore to Restagnon was converted into bitter hatred,
 and, blinded by her wrath, she made up her mind to avenge by
 Restagnon's death the dishonour which she deemed that he had done
 her. <milestone id="p04030023" />So she had recourse to an old Greek woman, that was very
 skilful in compounding poisons, whom by promises and gifts she
 induced to distill a deadly water, which, keeping her own counsel,
 she herself gave Restagnon to drink one evening, when he was
 somewhat heated and quite off his guard: whereby--such was the
 efficacy of the water--she despatched Restagnon before matins. On
 learning his death Foulques and Hugues and their ladies, who knew
 not that he had been poisoned, united their bitter with Ninette's
 feigned lamentations, and gave him honourable sepulture. <milestone id="p04030024" />But so it
 befell that, not many days after, the old woman, that had compounded
 the poison for Ninette, was taken for another crime; and, being put
 to the torture, confessed the compounding of the poison among other
 of her misdeeds, and fully declared what had thereby come to pass.
 Wherefore the Duke of Crete, breathing no word of his intent, came
 privily by night, and set a guard around <milestone id="p04030025" />Foulques' palace, where
 Ninette then was, and quietly, and quite unopposed, took and carried
 her off; and without putting her to the torture, learned from her in
 a trice all that he sought to know touching the death of Restagnon.
 Foulques and Hugues had learned privily of the Duke, and their
 ladies of them, for what cause Ninette was taken; and, being mightily
 distressed thereby, bestirred themselves with all zeal to save Ninette
 from the fire, to which they apprehended she would be condemned,
 as having indeed richly deserved it; but all their endeavours seemed
 to avail nothing, for the Duke was unwaveringly resolved that justice
 should be done. 
<milestone id="p04030026" />Madeleine, Foulques' fair wife, who had long been
 courted by the Duke, but had never deigned to shew him the least
 <pb n="289" />favour, thinking that by yielding herself to his will she might redeem
 her sister from the fire, despatched a trusty envoy to him with the
 intimation that she was entirely at his disposal upon the twofold
 condition, that in the first place her sister should be restored to her
 free and scatheless, and, in the second place, the affair should be kept
 secret. 
<milestone id="p04030027" />Albeit gratified by this overture, the Duke was long in doubt
 whether he should accept it; in the end, however, he made up his
 mind to do so, and signified his approval to the envoy. Then with
 the lady's consent he put Foulques and Hugues under arrest for a
 night, as if he were minded to examine them of the affair, and
 meanwhile quartered himself privily with Madeleine. 
<milestone id="p04030028" />Ninette, who,
 he had made believe, had been set in a sack, and was to be sunk
 in the sea that same night, he took with him, and presented her to
 her sister in requital of the night's joyance, which, as he parted from
 her on the morrow, he prayed her might not be the last, as it was
 the first, fruit of their love, at the same time enjoining her to send
 the guilty lady away that she might not bring reproach upon him,
 nor he be compelled to deal rigorously with her again. 
<milestone id="p04030029" />Released the
 same morning, and told that Ninette had been cast into the sea,
 Foulques and Hugues, fully believing that so it was, came home,
 thinking how they should console their ladies for the death of their
 sister; but, though Madeleine was at great pains to conceal Ninette,
 Foulques nevertheless, to his no small amazement, discovered that
 she was there; which at once excited his suspicion, for he knew that
 the Duke had been enamoured of Madeleine; and he asked how it
 was that Ninette was there. <milestone id="p04030030" />Madeleine made up a long story by
 way of explanation, to which his sagacity gave little credit, and in
 the end after long parley he constrained her to tell the truth. Whereupon,
 overcome with grief, and transported with rage, he drew his
 sword, and, deaf to her appeals for mercy, slew her. 
<milestone id="p04030031" />Then, fearing
 the vengeful justice of the Duke, he left the dead body in the room,
 and hied him to Ninette, and with a counterfeit gladsome mien said
 to her: <q direct="unspecified">Go we without delay whither thy sister has appointed
 that I escort thee, that thou fall not again into the hands of the
 Duke.</q> Ninette believed him, and being fain to go for very fear,
 she forewent further leave-taking of her sister, more particularly as
 it was now night, and set out with Foulques, who took with him
 such little money as he could lay his hands upon; and so they made
 <pb n="290" />their way to the coast, where they got aboard a bark, but none ever
 knew where their voyage ended.</p><p><milestone id="p04030032" />Madeleine's dead body being discovered next day, certain evildisposed
 folk, that bore a grudge to Hugues, forthwith apprised the
 Duke of the fact; which brought the Duke--for much he loved
 Madeleine--in hot haste to the house, where he arrested Hugues and
 his lady, who as yet knew nothing of the departure of Foulques and
 Ninette, and extorted from them a confession that they and Foulques
 were jointly answerable for Madeleine's death. 
<milestone id="p04030033" />For which cause being
 justly apprehensive of death, they with great address corrupted the
 guards that had charge of them, giving them a sum of money which
 they kept concealed in their house against occasions of need; and
 together with the guards fled with all speed, leaving all that they
 possessed behind them, and took ship by night for Rhodes, where,
 being arrived, they lived in great poverty and misery no long time.
 <milestone id="p04030034" />Such then was the issue, to which Restagnon, by his foolish love, and
 Ninette by her wrath brought themselves and others.</p></div2>