<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d10conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p00970001" />So ended Dioneo's story, whereof the ladies, diversely inclining,
 one to censure where another found matter for commendation, had
 discoursed not a little, when the king, having glanced at the sky,
 and marked that the sun was now low, insomuch that 'twas nigh the
 vesper hour, still keeping his seat, thus began:  <milestone id="p00970002" /><q direct="unspecified">Exquisite my
 ladies, as, methinks, you wot, 'tis not only in minding them of
 the past and apprehending the present that the wit of mortals
 consists; but by one means or the other to be able to foresee the
 future is by the sages accounted the height of wisdom.  <milestone id="p00970003" />Now,
 to-morrow, as you know, 'twill be fifteen days since, in quest of
 recreation and for the conservation of our health and life, we, shunning
 the dismal and dolorous and afflicting spectacles that have ceased
 not in our city since this season of pestilence began, took our departure
 from Florence.  <milestone id="p00970004" />Wherein, to my thinking, we have done
 nought that was not seemly; for, if I have duly used my powers of
 observation, albeit some gay stories, and of a kind to stimulate
 concupiscence,
 have here been told, and we have daily known no lack
 of dainty dishes and good wine, nor yet of music and song, things,
 one and all, apt to incite weak minds to that which is not seemly,
 neither on your part, nor on ours, have I marked deed or word, or
 aught of any kind, that called for reprehension;  <milestone id="p00970005" />but, by what I have
 seen and heard, seemliness and the sweet intimacy of brothers and
 sisters have ever reigned among us. Which, assuredly, for the honour
 and advantage which you and I have had thereof, is most grateful to
 <pb n="398" />me.  <milestone id="p00970006" />Wherefore, lest too long continuance in this way of life might
 beget some occasion of weariness, and that no man may be able to
 misconstrue our too long abidance here, and as we have all of us had
 our day's share of the honour which still remains in me, I should
 deem it meet, so you be of like mind, that we now go back whence
 we came:  <milestone id="p00970007" />and that the rather that our company, the bruit whereof
 has already reached divers others that are in our neighbourhood, might
 be so increased that all our pleasure would be destroyed. And so, if
 my counsel meet with your approval, I will keep the crown I have
 received of you until our departure, which, I purpose, shall be tomorrow
 morning. Should you decide otherwise, I have already
 determined whom to crown for the ensuing day.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00970008" />Much debate ensued among the ladies and young men; but in
 the end they approved the king's proposal as expedient and seemly;
 and resolved to do even as he had said. The king therefore
 summoned the seneschal; and having conferred with him of the
 order he was to observe on the morrow, he dismissed the company
 until supper-time.  <milestone id="p00970009" />So, the king being risen, the ladies and the rest
 likewise rose, and betook them, as they were wont, to their several
 diversions. Supper-time being come, they supped with exceeding
 great delight. Which done, they addressed them to song and music
 and dancing; and, while Lauretta was leading a dance, the king bade
 Fiammetta give them a song; whereupon Fiammetta right debonairly
 sang on this wise:</p><div3 who="fiammetta" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p00970010" /><l>So came but Love, and brought no jealousy,</l>
<l>So blithe, I wot, as I,</l>
<l>Dame were there none, be she whoe'er she be.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00970011" /><l>If youth's fresh, lusty pride</l>
<l>May lady of her lover well content,</l>
<l>Or valour's just renown,</l>
<l>Hardihood, prowess tried,</l>
<l>Wit, noble mien, discourse most excellent,</l>
<l>And of all grace the crown;</l>
<l>That she am I, who, fain for love to swoun,</l>
<l>There where my hope doth lie</l>
<l>These several virtues all conjoined do see.</l></lg><pb n="399" /><lg><milestone id="p00970012" /><l>But, for that I less wise</l>
<l>Than me no whit do other dames discern,</l>
<l>Trembling with sore dismay,</l>
<l>I still the worst surmise,</l>
<l>Deeming their hearts with the same flame to burn</l>
<l>That of mine maketh prey:</l>
<l>Wherefore of him that is my hope's one stay</l>
<l>Disconsolate I sigh,</l>
<l>Yea mightily, and daily do me dree.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00970013" /><l>If but my lord as true</l>
<l>As worthy to be loved I might approve,</l>
<l>I were not jealous then:</l>
<l>But, for that charmer new</l>
<l>Doth all too often gallant lure to love,</l>
<l>Forsworn I hold all men,</l>
<l>And sick at heart I am, of death full fain;</l>
<l>Nor lady doth him eye,</l>
<l>But I do quake, lest she him wrest from me.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00970014" /><l>'Fore God, then, let each she</l>
<l>List to my prayer, nor e'er in my despite</l>
<l>Such grievous wrong essay;</l>
<l>For should there any be</l>
<l>That by or speech or mien's allurements light</l>
<l>Of him to rob me may</l>
<l>Study or plot, I, witting, shall find way,</l>
<l>My beauty it aby!</l>
<l>To cause her sore lament such frenesie.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p00970015" />As soon as Fiammetta had ended her song, Dioneo, who was
 beside her, said with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, 'twould be a great courtesy
 on your part to do all ladies to wit, who he is, that he be not stolen
 from you in ignorance, seeing that you threaten such dire resentment.</q>
 Several other songs followed; and it being then nigh upon
 midnight, all, as the king was pleased to order, betook them to rest.
  <milestone id="p00970016" />With the first light of the new day they rose, and, the seneschal
 having already conveyed thence all their chattels, they, following the
 lead of their discreet king, hied them back to Florence; and in Santa
 Maria Novella, whence they had set forth, the three young men
 <pb n="400" />took leave of the seven ladies, and departed to find other diversions
 elsewhere, while the ladies in due time repaired to their homes.</p></div2>