<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0409"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04090001" />Sieur Guillaume de Roussillon slays his wife's paramour,
 Sieur Guillaume de Cabestaing, and gives her his
 heart to eat. She, coming to wit thereof, throws
 herself from a high window to the ground, and dies,
	and is buried with her lover.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04090002" />Neifile's story, which had not failed to
	move her gossips to no
	little pity, being ended, none now remained to speak but the king
	and Dioneo, whose privilege the king was minded not to infringe:
	wherefore he thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04090003" />I propose, compassionate my ladies, to
	tell you a story, which, seeing that you so commiserate ill-starred
	loves, may claim no less a share of your pity than the last, inasmuch
	as they were greater folk of whom I shall speak, and that which
	befell them was more direful.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04090004" />You are to know, then, that, as the Proven&#231;als relate, there
 were once in Provence two noble knights, each having castles and
 vassals under him, the one yclept Sieur Guillaume de Roussillon,
 and the other Sieur Guillaume de Cabestaing;<note>Boccaccio writes
 Guardastagno, but the troubadour, Cabestaing, or
	Cabestany, is the hero of the story.</note> <milestone id="p04090005" />and being both
 most doughty warriors, they were as brothers, and went ever together,
 and bearing the same device, to tournament or joust, or
 other passage of arms. <milestone id="p04090006" />And, albeit each dwelt in his own castle,
 and the castles were ten good miles apart, it nevertheless came to
 pass that, Sieur Guillaume de Roussillon having a most lovely lady,
 and amorous withal, to wife, Sieur Guillaume de Cabestaing, for all
 they were such friends and comrades, became inordinately enamoured
 of the lady, who, by this, that, and the other sign that he gave,
 dis<pb n="319" />covered
 his passion, <milestone id="p04090007" />and knowing him for a most complete knight,
 was flattered, and returned it, insomuch that she yearned and burned
 for him above all else in the world, and waited only till he should
 make his suit to her, as before long he did; and so they met from
 time to time, and great was their love. <milestone id="p04090008" />Which intercourse they
 ordered with so little discretion that 'twas discovered by the husband,
 who was very wroth, insomuch that the great love which he bore to
 Cabestaing was changed into mortal enmity; and, dissembling it
 better than the lovers their love, he made his mind up to kill Cabestaing.
 <milestone id="p04090009" />Now it came to pass that, while Roussillon was in this
 frame, a great tourney was proclaimed in France, whereof Roussillon
 forthwith sent word to Cabestaing, and bade him to his castle, so he
 were minded to come, that there they might discuss whether (or no)
 to go to the tourney, and how. Cabestaing was overjoyed, and
 made answer that he would come to sup with him next day without
 fail. <milestone id="p04090010" />Which message being delivered, Roussillon wist that the
 time was come to slay Cabestaing. So next day he armed himself,
 and, attended by a few servants, took horse, and about a mile from
 his castle lay in ambush in a wood through which Cabestaing must
 needs pass. <milestone id="p04090011" />He waited some time, and then he saw Cabestaing
 approach unarmed with two servants behind, also unarmed, for he
 was without thought of peril on Roussillon's part. So Cabestaing
 came on to the place of Roussillon's choice, and then, fell and vengeful,
 Roussillon leapt forth lance in hand, and fell upon him, exclaiming:
 <q direct="unspecified">Thou art a dead man!</q> and the words were no sooner
 spoken than the lance was through Cabestaing's breast. 
<milestone id="p04090012" />Powerless
 either to defend himself or even utter a cry, Cabestaing fell to the
 ground, and soon expired. His servants waited not to see who had
 done the deed, but turned their horses' heads and fled with all speed
 to their lord's castle. <milestone id="p04090013" />Roussillon dismounted, opened Cabestaing's
 breast with a knife, and took out the heart with his own hands,
 wrapped it up in a banderole, and gave it to one of his servants to
 carry: he then bade none make bold to breathe a word of the affair,
 mounted his horse and rode back--'twas now night--to his castle.
 <milestone id="p04090014" />The lady, who had been told that Cabestaing was to come to supper
 that evening, and was all impatience till he should come, was greatly
 surprised to see her husband arrive without him. Wherefore:
 <q direct="unspecified">How is this, my lord?</q> said she. <q direct="unspecified">Why tarries Cabestaing?</q>
 <pb n="320" />
<milestone id="p04090015" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> answered her husband, <q direct="unspecified">I have tidings from him that he
 cannot be here until to-morrow:</q> whereat the lady was somewhat
 disconcerted.</p><p><milestone id="p04090016" />Having dismounted, Roussillon called the cook, and said to him:
 <q direct="unspecified">Here is a boar's heart; take it, and make thereof the daintiest
 and most delicious dish thou canst, and when I am set at table serve
 it in a silver porringer.</q> So the cook took the heart, and expended
 all his skill and pains upon it, mincing it and mixing with it plenty
 of good seasoning, and made thereof an excellent ragout; 
<milestone id="p04090017" />and in due
 time Sieur Guillaume and his lady sat them down to table. The
 meat was served, but Sieur Guillaume, his mind engrossed with his
 crime, ate but little. The cook set the ragout before him, but he,
 feigning that he cared to eat no more that evening, had it passed on
 to the lady, and highly commended it. The lady, nothing loath,
 took some of it, and found it so good that she ended by eating the
 whole. <milestone id="p04090018" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth the knight, <q direct="unspecified">how liked
 you this dish?</q> 
<milestone id="p04090019" /><q direct="unspecified">In good faith, my lord,</q> replied the lady, <q direct="unspecified">not
 a little.</q> 
<milestone id="p04090020" /><q direct="unspecified">So help me, God,</q> returned the knight, <q direct="unspecified">I dare be
 sworn you did; 'tis no wonder that you should enjoy that dead, which
 living you enjoyed more than aught else in the world.</q> 
<milestone id="p04090021" />For a while
 the lady was silent; then: <q direct="unspecified">How say you?</q> said she; <q direct="unspecified">what is
 this you have caused me to eat?</q> 
<milestone id="p04090022" /><q direct="unspecified">That which you have eaten,</q>
 replied the knight, <q direct="unspecified">was in good sooth the heart of Sieur Guillaume
 de Cabestaing, whom you, disloyal woman that you are, did so much
 love: for assurance whereof I tell you that but a short while before
 I came back, I plucked it from his breast with my own hands.</q> 
<milestone id="p04090023" />It
 boots not to ask if the lady was sorrow-stricken to receive such tidings
 of her best beloved. But after a while she said: <q direct="unspecified">'Twas the deed
 of a disloyal and recreant knight; for if I, unconstrained by him, made
 him lord of my love, and thereby did you wrong, 'twas I, not he,
 should have borne the penalty. But God forbid that fare of such
 high excellence as the heart of a knight so true and courteous as Sieur
 Guillaume de Cabestaing be followed by aught else.</q> 
<milestone id="p04090024" />So saying she
 started to her feet, and stepping back to a window that was behind
 her, without a moment's hesitation let herself drop backwards
 therefrom. The window was at a great height from the ground, so
 that the lady was not only killed by the fall, but almost reduced to
 atoms. Stunned and conscience-stricken by the spectacle, and fear<pb n="321" />ing
 the vengeance of the country folk, and the Count of Provence,
 Sieur Guillaume had his horses saddled and rode away. 
<milestone id="p04090025" />On the
 morrow the whole countryside knew how the affair had come about;
 wherefore folk from both of the castles took the two bodies, and bore
 them with grief and lamentation exceeding great to the church in the
 lady's castle, and laid them in the same tomb, and caused verses to
 be inscribed thereon signifying who they were that were there
 interred, and the manner and occasion of their death.</p></div2>