<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0509"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05090001" /> Federigo degli Alberighi loves and is not loved in return:
 he wastes his substance by lavishness until nought is
 left but a single falcon, which, his lady being come to
 see him at his house, he gives her to eat: she, knowing
 his case, changes her mind, takes him to husband and
 makes him rich.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05090002" />So ended Filomena; and the queen, being ware that besides herself
 only Dioneo (by virtue of his privilege) was left to speak, said
 with gladsome mien: </p></div3><p><milestone id="p05090003" />'Tis now for me to take up my parable;
 which, dearest ladies, I will do with a story like in some degree to
 the foregoing, and that, not only that you may know how potent are
 your charms to sway the gentle heart, but that you may also learn
 how upon fitting occasions to make bestowal of your guerdons of
 your own accord, instead of always waiting for the guidance of
 Fortune, which most times, not wisely, but without rule or measure,
 scatters her gifts.</p><p><milestone id="p05090004" />You are then to know, that Coppo di Borghese Domenichi, a
 man that in our day was, and perchance still is, had in respect and
 great reverence in our city, being not only by reason of his noble
 lineage, but, and yet more, for manners and merit most illustrious and
 worthy of eternal renown, was in his old age not seldom wont to
 amuse himself by discoursing of things past with his neighbours and
 other folk; wherein he had not his match for accuracy and compass
 of memory and concinnity of speech.  <milestone id="p05090005" />Among other good stories, he
 would tell, how that there was of yore in Florence a gallant named
 Federigo di Messer Filippo Alberighi, who for feats of arms and
 courtesy had not his peer in Tuscany;  <milestone id="p05090006" />who, as is the common lot of
 <pb n="56" />gentlemen, became enamoured of a lady named Monna Giovanna,
 who in her day held rank among the fairest and most elegant ladies
 of Florence; to gain whose love he jousted, tilted, gave entertainments,
 scattered largess, and in short set no bounds to his expenditure.
 However the lady, no less virtuous than fair, cared not
 a jot for what he did for her sake, nor yet for him.</p><p><milestone id="p05090007" />Spending thus greatly beyond his means, and making nothing,
 Federigo could hardly fail to come to lack, and was at length reduced
 to such poverty that he had nothing left but a little estate, on the
 rents of which he lived very straitly, and a single falcon, the best in
 the world.  <milestone id="p05090008" />The estate was at Campi, and thither, deeming it no
 longer possible for him to live in the city as he desired, he repaired,
 more in love than ever before; and there, in complete seclusion,
 diverting himself with hawking, he bore his poverty as patiently as he
 might.</p><p><milestone id="p05090009" />Now, Federigo being thus reduced to extreme poverty, it so
 happened that one day Monna Giovanna's husband, who was very
 rich, fell ill, and, seeing that he was nearing his end, made his will,
 whereby he left his estate to his son, who was now growing up, and
 in the event of his death without lawful heir named Monna Giovanna,
 whom he dearly loved, heir in his stead; and having made these
 dispositions he died.</p><p><milestone id="p05090010" />Monna Giovanna, being thus left a widow, did as our ladies are
 wont, and repaired in the summer to one of her estates in the country
 which lay very near to that of Federigo.  <milestone id="p05090011" />And so it befell that
 the urchin began to make friends with Federigo, and to shew a
 fondness for hawks and dogs, and having seen Federigo's falcon fly
 not a few times, took a singular fancy to him, and greatly longed to
 have him for his own, but still did not dare to ask him of Federigo,
 knowing that Federigo prized him so much.  <milestone id="p05090012" />So the matter stood when
 by chance the boy fell sick; whereby the mother was sore distressed, for
 he was her only son, and she loved him as much as might be, insomuch
 that all day long she was beside him, and ceased not to comfort
 him, and again and again asked him if there were aught that he
 wished for, imploring him to say the word, and, if it might by any
 means be had, she would assuredly do her utmost to procure it for
 him.  <milestone id="p05090013" />Thus repeatedly exhorted, the boy said: <q direct="unspecified">Mother mine, do
 but get me Federigo's falcon, and I doubt not I shall soon be well.</q>
 <pb n="57" /> <milestone id="p05090014" />Whereupon the lady was silent a while, bethinking her what she
 should do. She knew that Federigo had long loved her, and had
 never had so much as a single kind look from her: wherefore she
 said to herself: How can I send or go to beg of him this falcon,
 which by what I hear is the best that ever flew, and moreover is his
 sole comfort? And how could I be so unfeeling as to seek to deprive
 a gentleman of the one solace that is now left him?  <milestone id="p05090015" />And so, albeit
 she very well knew that she might have the falcon for the asking, she
 was perplexed, and knew not what to say, and gave her son no
 answer. <milestone id="p05090016" />At length, however, the love she bore the boy carried the
 day, and she made up her mind, for his contentment, come what might,
 not to send, but to go herself and fetch him the falcon. So: <q direct="unspecified">Be of
 good cheer, my son,</q> she said, <q direct="unspecified">and doubt not thou wilt soon be
 well; for I promise thee that the very first thing that I shall do tomorrow
 morning will be to go and fetch thee the falcon.</q>  <milestone id="p05090017" />Whereat
 the child was so pleased that he began to mend that very day.</p><p><milestone id="p05090018" />On the morrow the lady, as if for pleasure, hied her with another
 lady to Federigo's little house, and asked to see him.  <milestone id="p05090019" />'Twas still, as
 for some days past, no weather for hawking, and Federigo was in his
 garden, busy about some small matters which needed to be set right
 there. When he heard that Monna Giovanna was at the door,
 asking to see him, he was not a little surprised and pleased, and hied
 him to her with all speed.  <milestone id="p05090020" />As soon as she saw him, she came
 forward to meet him with womanly grace, and having received his
 respectful salutation, said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Good morrow, Federigo,</q> and
 continued: <q direct="unspecified">I am come to requite thee for what thou hast lost
 by loving me more than thou shouldst: which compensation is this,
 that I and this lady that accompanies me will breakfast with thee
 without ceremony this morning.</q> <milestone id="p05090021" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> Federigo replied
 with all humility, <q direct="unspecified">I mind not ever to have lost aught by loving you,
 but rather to have been so much profited that, if I ever deserved well
 in aught, 'twas to your merit that I owed it, and to the love that I
 bore you.  <milestone id="p05090022" />And of a surety had I still as much to spend as I have
 spent in the past, I should not prize it so much as this visit you so
 frankly pay me, come as you are to one who can afford you but a
 sorry sort of hospitality.</q>  <milestone id="p05090023" />Which said, with some confusion, he
 bade her welcome to his house, and then led her into his garden,
 where, having none else to present to her by way of companion, he
 <pb n="58" />said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, as there is none other here, this good woman, wife
 of this husbandman, will bear you company, while I go to have the
 table set.</q>  <milestone id="p05090024" />Now, albeit his poverty was extreme, yet he had not
 known as yet how sore was the need to which his extravagance had
 reduced him; but this morning 'twas brought home to him, for that
 he could find nought wherewith to do honour to the lady, for love
 of whom he had done the honours of his house to men without
 number:  <milestone id="p05090025" />wherefore, distressed beyond measure, and inwardly cursing
 his evil fortune, he sped hither and thither like one beside himself,
 but never a coin found he, nor yet aught to pledge. Meanwhile it
 grew late, and sorely he longed that the lady might not leave his
 house altogether unhonoured, and yet to crave help of his own
 husbandman was more than his pride could brook. In these desperate
 straits his glance happened to fall on his brave falcon on his perch in
 his little parlour. And so, as a last resource, he took him, and finding
 him plump, deemed that he would make a dish meet for such a
 lady.  <milestone id="p05090026" />Wherefore, without thinking twice about it, he wrung the
 bird's neck, and caused his maid forthwith pluck him and set him on
 a spit, and roast him carefully; and having still some spotless table-linen,
 he had the table laid therewith, and with a cheerful countenance
 hied him back to his lady in the garden, and told her that such
 breakfast as he could give her was ready.  <milestone id="p05090027" />So the lady and her companion
 rose and came to table, and there, with Federigo, who waited on
 them most faithfully, ate the brave falcon, knowing not what they ate.</p><p><milestone id="p05090028" />When they were risen from table, and had dallied a while in gay
 converse with him, the lady deemed it time to tell the reason of her
 visit: wherefore, graciously addressing Federigo, thus began she:
 <milestone id="p05090029" /><q direct="unspecified">Federigo, by what thou rememberest of thy past life and my virtue,
 which, perchance, thou hast deemed harshness and cruelty, I doubt
 not thou must marvel at my presumption, when thou hearest the
 main purpose of my visit; but if thou hadst sons, or hadst had them, so
 that thou mightest know the full force of the love that is borne them,
 I should make no doubt that thou wouldst hold me in part excused.
  <milestone id="p05090030" />Nor, having a son, may I, for that thou hast none, claim exemption
 from the laws to which all other mothers are subject, and, being thus
 bound to own their sway, I must, though fain were I not, and
 though 'tis neither meet nor right, crave of thee that which I know
 thou dost of all things and with justice prize most highly,  <milestone id="p05090031" />seeing
 <pb n="59" />that this extremity of thy adverse fortune has left thee nought else
 wherewith to delight, divert and console thee; which gift is no other
 than thy falcon, on which my boy has so set his heart that, if I
 bring him it not, I fear lest he grow so much worse of the malady
 that he has, that thereby it may come to pass that I lose him.  <milestone id="p05090032" />And
 so, not for the love which thou dost bear me, and which may nowise
 bind thee, but for that nobleness of temper, whereof in courtesy
 more conspicuously than in aught else thou hast given proof, I implore
 thee that thou be pleased to give me the bird, that thereby
 I may say that I have kept my son alive, and thus made him for
 aye thy debtor.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05090033" />No sooner had Federigo apprehended what the lady wanted,
 than, for grief that 'twas not in his power to serve her, because he
 had given her the falcon to eat, he fell a weeping in her presence,
 before he could so much as utter a word. At first the lady supposed
 that 'twas only because he was loath to part with the brave falcon
 that he wept, and as good as made up her mind that he would refuse
 her: however, she awaited with patience Federigo's answer, which
 was on this wise: <milestone id="p05090034" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam, since it pleased God that I should set
 my affections upon you there have been matters not a few, in which
 to my sorrow I have deemed Fortune adverse to me; but they have
 all been trifles in comparison of the trick that she now plays me:
 the which I shall never forgive her, seeing that you are come here to
 my poor house, where, while I was rich, you deigned not to come,
 and ask a trifling favour of me, which she has put it out of my
 power to grant: how 'tis so, I will briefly tell you.  <milestone id="p05090035" />When I learned
 that you, of your grace, were minded to breakfast with me, having
 respect to your high dignity and desert, I deemed it due and seemly
 that in your honour I should regale you, to the best of my power,
 with fare of a more excellent quality than is commonly set before
 others;  <milestone id="p05090036" />and, calling to mind the falcon which you now ask of me,
 and his excellence, I judged him meet food for you, and so you have
 had him roasted on the trencher this morning; and well indeed I
 thought I had bestowed him; but, as now I see that you would fain
 have had him in another guise, so mortified am I that I am not able
 to serve you, that I doubt I shall never know peace of mind more.</q>
  <milestone id="p05090037" />In witness whereof he had the feathers and feet and beak of the
 bird brought in and laid before her.</p><pb n="60" /><p> The first thing the lady did, when she had heard Federigo's
 story, and seen the relics of the bird, was to chide him that he had
 killed so fine a falcon to furnish a woman with a breakfast; after
 which the magnanimity of her host, which poverty had been and
 was powerless to impair, elicited no small share of inward commendation.
 Then, frustrate of her hope of possessing the falcon, and
 doubting of her son's recovery, she took her leave with the heaviest
 of hearts, and hied her back to the boy:  <milestone id="p05090038" />who, whether for fretting,
 that he might not have the falcon, or by the unaided energy of his
 disorder, departed this life not many days after, to the exceeding
 great grief of his mother.  <milestone id="p05090039" />For a while she would do nought but
 weep and bitterly bewail herself; but being still young, and left very
 wealthy, she was often urged by her brothers to marry again, and
 though she would rather have not done so, yet being importuned,
 and remembering Federigo's high desert, and the magnificent generosity
 with which he had finally killed his falcon to do her honour,
 she said to her brothers: <milestone id="p05090040" /><q direct="unspecified">Gladly, with your consent, would I
 remain a widow, but if you will not be satisfied except I take a
 husband, rest assured that none other will I ever take save Federigo
 degli Alberighi.</q>  <milestone id="p05090041" />Whereupon her brothers derided her, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">Foolish woman, what is't thou sayst? How shouldst thou want
 Federigo, who has not a thing in the world?</q>  <milestone id="p05090042" />To whom she
 answered: <q direct="unspecified">My brothers, well wot I that 'tis as you say; but I
 had rather have a man without wealth than wealth without a man.</q>
  <milestone id="p05090043" />The brothers, perceiving that her mind was made up, and knowing
 Federigo for a good man and true, poor though he was, gave her to
 him with all her wealth. And so Federigo, being mated with such
 a wife, and one that he had so much loved, and being very wealthy
 to boot, lived happily, keeping more exact accounts, to the end of his
 days.</p></div2>