<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d08conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p08970001" />No sooner was Dioneo's story ended, than Lauretta, witting
 that therewith the end of her sovereignty was come, bestowed her
 meed of praise on Pietro Canigiano for his good counsel, and also on
 Salabaetto for the equal sagacity which he displayed in carrying it
 out, and then, taking off the laurel wreath, set it on the head of
 Emilia, saying graciously: <q direct="unspecified">I know not, Madam, how debonair
 a queen you may prove, but at least we shall have in you a fair
 one. Be it your care, then, that you exercise your authority in a
 manner answerable to your charms.</q> Which said, she resumed
 her seat.</p><p><milestone id="p08970002" />Not so much to receive the crown, as to be thus commended to
 her face and before the company for that which ladies are wont to
 covet the most, Emilia was a little shamefast; a tint like that of the
 newly-blown rose overspread her face, and a while she stood silent
 with downcast eyes: then, as the blush faded away, she raised them;
 and having given her seneschal her commands touching all matters
 pertaining to the company, thus she spake: 
<milestone id="p08970003" /><q direct="unspecified">Sweet my ladies, 'tis
 matter of common experience that, when the oxen have swunken a
 part of the day under the coercive yoke, they are relieved thereof and
 loosed, and suffered to go seek their pasture at their own sweet will
 <pb n="261" />in the woods; 
<milestone id="p08970004" />nor can we fail to observe that gardens luxuriant with
 diversity of leafage are not less, but far more fair to see, than woods
 wherein is nought but oaks. Wherefore I deem that, as for so many
 days our discourse has been confined within the bounds of certain
 laws, 'twill be not only meet but profitable for us, being in need of
 relaxation, to roam a while, and so recruit our strength to undergo
 the yoke once more. 
<milestone id="p08970005" />And therefore I am minded that to-morrow
 the sweet tenor of your discourse be not confined to any particular
 theme, but that you be at liberty to discourse on such wise as to each
 may seem best; for well assured am I that thus to speak of divers
 matters will be no less pleasurable than to limit ourselves to one topic;
 and by reason of this enlargement my successor in the sovereignty
 will find you more vigorous, and be therefore all the more forward
 to reimpose upon you the wonted restraint of our laws.</q> 
<milestone id="p08970006" />Having so
 said, she dismissed all the company until supper-time.</p><p><milestone id="p08970007" />All approved the wisdom of what the queen had said; and being
 risen betook them to their several diversions, the ladies to weave
 garlands and otherwise disport them, the young men to play and sing;
 and so they whiled away the hours until supper-time; which being
 come, they gathered about the fair fountain, and took their meal with
 gay and festal cheer. Supper ended, they addressed them to their
 wonted pastime of song and dance. 
<milestone id="p08970008" />At the close of which the queen,
 notwithstanding the songs which divers of the company had already
 gladly accorded them, called for another from Pamfilo, who without
 the least demur thus sang:</p><div3 who="panfilo" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p08970009" />
	<l>So great, O Love, the bliss</l>
	<l>Through thee I prove, so jocund my estate,</l>
	<l>That in thy flame to burn I bless my fate!</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p08970010" />
	<l>Such plenitude of joy my heart doth know</l>
	<l>Of that high joy and rare,</l>
	<l>Wherewith thou hast me blest,</l>
	<l>As, bounds disdaining, still doth overflow,</l>
	<l>And by my radiant air</l>
	<l>My blitheness manifest;</l>
	<l>For by thee thus possessed</l>
	<l>With love, where meeter 'twere to venerate,</l>
	<l>I still consume within thy flame elate.</l>
      </lg><pb n="262" /><lg><milestone id="p08970011" />
	<l>Well wot I, Love, no song may e'er reveal,</l>
	<l>Nor any sign declare</l>
	<l>What in my heart is pent:</l>
	<l>Nay, might they so, that were I best conceal,</l>
	<l>Whereof were others ware,</l>
	<l>'Twould serve but to torment</l>
	<l>Me, whose is such content,</l>
	<l>That weak were words and all inadequate</l>
	<l>A tittle of my bliss to adumbrate.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p08970012" />
	<l>Who would have dreamed that e'er in mine embrace</l>
	<l>Her I should clip and fold</l>
	<l>Whom there I still do feel,</l>
	<l>Or as 'gainst her face e'er to lay my face</l>
	<l>Attain such grace untold,</l>
	<l>And unimagined weal?</l>
	<l>Wherefore my bliss I seal</l>
	<l>Of mine own heart within the circuit strait,</l>
	<l>And still in thy sweet flame luxuriate.</l>
      </lg></div3><p><milestone id="p08970013" />So ended Pamfilo his song: whereto all the company responded
 in full chorus; nor was there any but gave to its words an inordinate
 degree of attention, endeav&#243;uring by conjecture to penetrate that
 which he intimated that 'twas meet he should keep secret. Divers
 were the interpretations hazarded, but all were wide of the mark.
 At length, however, the queen, seeing that ladies and men alike were
 fain of rest, bade all betake them to bed.</p></div2>