<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d09intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p09980002" />The luminary, before whose splendour the night takes wing, had
 already changed the eighth heaven<note>I. e. in the Ptolemaic
 system,
 the region of the fixed stars.</note> from azure to the lighter
 blue,<note>Cilestro: a word for which we have no exact equivalent, the
 dominant
 note of the Italian sky, when the sun is well up, being its intense
 luminosity.</note>
 and in the meads the flowerets were beginning to lift their heads,
 when Emilia, being risen, roused her fair gossips, and, likewise, the
 young men. And so the queen leading the way at an easy pace, and
 the rest of the company following, they hied them to a copse at no
 great distance from the palace. Where, being entered, they saw the
 goats and stags and other wild creatures, as if witting that in this
 time of pestilence they had nought to fear from the hunter, stand
 awaiting them with no more sign of fear than if they had been
      tamed: <milestone id="p09980003" />and so, making now towards this, now towards the other of
 them as if to touch them, they diverted themselves for a while by
 making them skip and run. But, as soon as the sun was in the
 ascendant, by common consent they turned back,  <milestone id="p09980004" />and whoso met
 them, garlanded as they were with oak-leaves, and carrying store of
 fragrant herbs or flowers in their hands might well have said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Either shall death not vanquish these, or they will meet it with a
 light heart.</q>  <milestone id="p09980005" />So, slowly wended they their way, now singing, now
 bandying quips and merry jests, to the palace, where they found all
 things in order meet, and their servants in blithe and merry cheer.
  <milestone id="p09980006" />A while they rested, nor went they to table until six ditties, each
 gayer than that which went before, had been sung by the young
 <pb n="264" />men and the ladies; which done, they washed their hands, and all by
 the queen's command were ranged by the seneschal at the table;
 and, the viands being served, they cheerily took their meal: wherefrom
 being risen, they trod some measures to the accompaniment
 of music; and then, by the queen's command, whoso would betook
 him to rest.  <milestone id="p09980007" />However, the accustomed hour being come, they all
 gathered at the wonted spot for their discoursing, and the queen,
 bending her regard upon Filomena, bade her make a beginning of
 the day's story-telling, which she with a smile did on this wise:</p></div2>