<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0904"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09040001" />Cecco, son of Messer Fortarrigo, loses his all at play at
 Buonconvento, besides the money of Cecco, son of
 Messer Angiulieri; whom, running after him in his
 shirt and crying out that he has robbed him, he causes
 to be taken by peasants: he then puts on his clothes,
 mounts his palfrey, and leaves him to follow in his
 shirt.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09040002" />All the company laughed beyond measure to hear what Calandrino
 said touching his wife: but, when Filostrato had done, Neifile,
 being bidden by the queen, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09040003" />Noble ladies, were it not
 more difficult for men to evince their good sense and virtue than
 their folly and their vice, many would labour in vain to set bounds
 to their flow of words: whereof you have had a most conspicuous
 example in poor blundering Calandrino, who, for the better cure
 of that with which in his simplicity he supposed himself to be
 afflicted, had no sort of need to discover in public his wife's secret
 pleasures.  <milestone id="p09040004" />Which affair has brought to my mind one that fell out
 contrariwise, inasmuch as the guile of one discomfited the good
 sense of another to the grievous loss and shame of the discomfited:
 the manner whereof I am minded to relate to you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09040005" />'Tis not many years since there were in Siena two young men,
 both of age, and both alike named Cecco, the one being son of
 Messer Angiulieri, the other of Messer Fortarrigo. Who, albeit in
 many other respects their dispositions accorded ill, agreed so well in
 one, to wit, that they both hated their fathers, that they became
 friends, and kept much together.  <milestone id="p09040006" />Now Angiulieri, being a pretty
 <pb n="279" />fellow, and well-mannered, could not brook to live at Siena on the
 allowance made him by his father, and learning that there was come
 into the March of Ancona, as legate of the Pope, a cardinal, to whom
 he was much bounden, resolved to resort to him there, thinking thereby
 to improve his circumstances. So, having acquainted his father with
 his purpose, he prevailed upon him to give him there and then all that
 he would have given him during the next six months, that he might
 have the wherewith to furnish himself with apparel and a good mount,
 so as to travel in a becoming manner.  <milestone id="p09040007" />And as he was looking out for
 some one to attend him as his servant, Fortarrigo, hearing of it,
 came presently to him and besought him with all earnestness to take
 him with him as his groom, or servant, or what he would, and he
 would be satisfied with his keep, without any salary whatsoever.
  <milestone id="p09040008" />Whereto Angiulieri made answer that he was not disposed to take
 him, not but that he well knew that he was competent for any
 service that might be required of him, but because he was given to
 play, and therewithal would at times get drunk. Fortarrigo assured
 him with many an oath that he would be on his guard to commit
 neither fault, and added thereto such instant entreaties, that Angiulieri
 was, as it were, vanquished, and consented.  <milestone id="p09040009" />So one morning they
 took the road for Buonconvento, being minded there to breakfast.
 Now when Angiulieri had breakfasted, as 'twas a very hot day, he
 had a bed made in the inn, and having undressed with Fortarrigo's
 help, he composed himself to sleep, telling Fortarrigo to call him on
 the stroke of none.  <milestone id="p09040010" />Angiulieri thus sleeping, Fortarrigo repaired to
 the tavern, where, having slaked his thirst, he sate down to a game
 with some that were there, who speedily won from him all his money,
 and thereafter in like manner all the clothes he had on his back:
 wherefore he, being anxious to retrieve his losses, went, stripped as
 he was to his shirt, to the room where lay Angiulieri; and seeing
 that he was sound asleep, he took from his purse all the money
 that he had, and so went back to the gaming-table, and staked it, and
 lost it all, as he had his own.</p><p><milestone id="p09040011" />By and by Angiulieri awoke, and got up, and dressed, and called
 for Fortarrigo; and as Fortarrigo answered not, he supposed that he
 must have had too much to drink, and be sleeping it off somewhere,
 as was his wont. He accordingly determined to leave him alone;
 and doubting not to find a better servant at Corsignano, he let saddle
 his palfrey and attach the valise; but when, being about to depart,
 <pb n="280" />he would have paid the host, never a coin could he come by.  <milestone id="p09040012" />Whereat
 there was no small stir, so that all the inn was in an uproar, Angiulieri
 averring that he had been robbed in the house, and threatening
 to have them all arrested and taken to Siena;  <milestone id="p09040013" />when, lo, who should
 make his appearance but Fortarrigo in his shirt, intent now to steal
 the clothes, as he had stolen the moneys, of Angiulieri? And marking
 that Angiulieri was accoutred for the road: <q direct="unspecified">How is this,
 Angiulieri?</q> quoth he. <q direct="unspecified">Are we to start so soon? Nay, but wait
 a little. One will be here presently that has my doublet in pawn
 for thirty-eight soldi; I doubt not he will return it me for thirty-five
 soldi, if I pay money down.</q>  <milestone id="p09040014" />And while they were yet talking,
 in came one that made it plain to Angiulieri that 'twas Fortarrigo
 that had robbed him of his money, for he told him the amount that
 Fortarrigo had lost. Whereat Angiulieri, in a towering passion,
 rated Fortarrigo right soundly, and, but that he stood more in fear of
 man than of God, would have suited action to word; and so,
 threatening to have him hanged by the neck and proclaimed an outlaw
 at the gallows-tree of Siena, he mounted his horse.</p><p><milestone id="p09040015" />Fortarrigo, making as if 'twas not to him, but to another, that
 Angiulieri thus spoke, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Come now, Angiulieri, we
 were best have done with all this idle talk, and consider the matter
 of substance: we can redeem for thirty-five soldi, if we pay forth-with,
 but if we wait till to-morrow, we shall not get off with less
 than thirty-eight, the full amount of the loan; and 'tis because I
 staked by his advice that he will make me this allowance. Now why
 should not we save these three soldi?</q>  <milestone id="p09040016" />Whereat Angiulieri waxed
 well-nigh desperate, more particularly that he marked that the
 bystanders were scanning him suspiciously, as if, so far from understanding
 that Fortarrigo had staked and lost his, Angiulieri's money,
 they gave him credit for still being in funds: so he cried out:
 <q direct="unspecified">What have I to do with thy doublet? 'Tis high time thou wast
 hanged by the neck, that, not content with robbing me and gambling
 away my money, thou must needs also keep me in parley here and
 make mock of me, when I would fain be gone.</q>  <milestone id="p09040017" />Fortarrigo, however,
 still persisted in making believe that Angiulieri did not mean
 this for him, and only said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but why wilt not thou save me
 these three soldi? Think'st thou I can be of no more use to thee?
 Prithee, an thou lov'st me, do me this turn. Wherefore in such a
 hurry? We have time enough to get to Torrenieri this evening.
 <pb n="281" /> <milestone id="p09040018" />Come now, out with thy purse. Thou knowest I might search Siena
 through, and not find a doublet that would suit me so well as this:
 and for all I let him have it for thirty-eight soldi, 'tis worth forty or
 more; so thou wilt wrong me twice over.</q> Vexed beyond measure
 that, after robbing him, Fortarrigo should now keep him clavering
 about the matter,  <milestone id="p09040019" />Angiulieri made no answer, but turned his horse's
 head, and took the road for Torrenieri.  <milestone id="p09040020" />But Fortarrigo with cunning
 malice trotted after him in his shirt, and 'twas still his doublet, his
 doublet, that he would have of him: and when they had thus ridden
 two good miles, and Angiulieri was forcing the pace to get out of
 earshot of his pestering, Fortarrigo espied some husbandmen in a field
 beside the road a little ahead of Angiulieri, and fell a shouting to
 them amain: <q direct="unspecified">Take thief! take thief!</q>  <milestone id="p09040021" />Whereupon they came
 up with their spades and their mattocks, and barred Angiulieri's way,
 supposing that he must have robbed the man that came shouting
 after him in his shirt, and stopped him and apprehended him; and
 little indeed did it avail him to tell them who he was, and how the
 matter stood.  <milestone id="p09040022" />For up came Fortarrigo with a wrathful air, and:
 <q direct="unspecified">I know not,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">why I spare to kill thee on the spot,
 traitor, thief that thou art, thus to despoil me and give me the slip!</q>
 And then, turning to the peasants: <q direct="unspecified">You see, gentlemen,</q> quoth
 he, <q direct="unspecified">in what a trim he left me in the inn, after gambling away all
 that he had with him and on him. Well indeed may I say that
 under God 'tis to you I owe it that I have thus come by my own
 again: for which cause I shall ever be beholden to you.</q>  <milestone id="p09040023" />Angiulieri
 also had his say; but his words passed unheeded. Fortarrigo with
 the help of the peasants compelled him to dismount; and having
 stripped him, donned his clothes, mounted his horse, and leaving him
 barefoot and in his shirt, rode back to Siena, giving out on all hands
 that he had won the palfrey and the clothes from Angiulieri.  <milestone id="p09040024" />So
 Angiulieri, having thought to present himself to the cardinal in the
 March a wealthy man, returned to Buonconvento poor and in his
 shirt; and being ashamed for the time to shew himself in Siena,
 pledged the nag that Fortarrigo had ridden for a suit of clothes, and
 betook him to his kinsfolk at Corsignano, where he tarried, until he
 received a fresh supply of money from his father.  <milestone id="p09040025" />Thus, then,
 Fortarrigo's guile disconcerted Angiulieri's judicious purpose, albeit
 when time and occasion served, it was not left unrequited.</p></div2>