<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0804"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08040001" />The rector of Fiesole loves a widow lady, by whom he is
 not loved, and thinking to lie with her, lies with her
 maid, with whom the lady's brothers cause him to be
 found by his Bishop.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08040002" />Elisa being come to the end of
	her story, which in the telling
	had yielded no small delight to all the company, the queen, turning
	to Emilia, signified her will, that her story should ensue at once upon
      that of Elisa. And thus with alacrity Emilia began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08040003" />Noble ladies,
	how we are teased and tormented by these priests and friars, and
	indeed by clergy of all sorts, I mind me to have been set forth in
	more than one of the stories that have been told; but as 'twere not
	possible to say so much thereof but that more would yet remain to
	say, I purpose to supplement them with the story of a rector, who, in
	defiance of all the world, was bent upon having the favour of a
	gentlewoman, whether she would or no. Which gentlewoman,
	being discreet above a little, treated him as he deserved.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08040004" />Fiesole, whose hill is here within sight, is, as each of you knows,
 a city of immense antiquity, and was aforetime great, though now
 'tis fallen into complete decay; which notwithstanding, it always was,
 and still is the see of a bishop. <milestone id="p08040005" />Now there was once a gentlewoman,
 Monna Piccarda by name, a widow, that had an estate at Fiesole,
 hard by the cathedral, on which, for that she was not in the easiest
 circumstances, she lived most part of the year, and with her her two
 brothers, very worthy and courteous young men, both of them.
 <milestone id="p08040006" />And the lady being wont frequently to resort to the cathedral, and
 being still quite young and fair and debonair withal, it so befell that
 the rector grew in the last degree enamoured of her, and waxed at
 length so bold, that he himself avowed his passion to the lady, praying
 <pb n="195" />her
 to entertain his love, and requite it in like measure. 
<milestone id="p08040007" />The rector
 was advanced in years, but otherwise the veriest springald, being bold
 and of a high spirit, of a boundless conceit of himself, and of mien
 and manners most affected and in the worst taste, and withal so tiresome
 and insufferable that he was on bad terms with everybody, and,
 if with one person more than another, with this lady, who not only
 cared not a jot for him, but had liefer have had a headache than his
 company. <milestone id="p08040008" />Wherefore the lady discreetly made answer: <q direct="unspecified">I may
 well prize your love, Sir, and love you I should and will right gladly;
 but such love as yours and mine may never admit of aught that is
 not honourable. You are my spiritual father and a priest, and now
 verging towards old age, circumstances which should ensure your
 honour and chastity; and I, on my part, am no longer a girl, such
 as these love affairs might beseem, but a widow, and well you wot
 how it behoves widows to be chaste. Wherefore I pray you to have
 me excused; for, after the sort you crave, you shall never have my
 love, nor would I in such sort be loved by you.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040009" />With this answer
 the rector was for the nonce fain to be content; but he was not the
 man to be dismayed and routed by a first repulse; and with his
 wonted temerity and effrontery he plied her again and again with
 letters and ambassages, and also by word of mouth, when he espied
 her entering the church. Wherefore the lady finding this persecution
 more grievous and harassing than she could well bear, cast about how
 she might be quit thereof in such fashion as he deserved, seeing that
 he left her no choice; howbeit she would do nought in the matter
 until she had conferred with her brothers. <milestone id="p08040010" />She therefore told them
 how the rector pursued her, and how she meant to foil him; and,
 with their full concurrence, some few days afterwards she went, as
 she was wont, to church. The rector no sooner saw her, than he
 approached and accosted her, as he was wont, in a tone of easy
 familiarity. <milestone id="p08040011" />The lady greeted him, as he came up, with a glance
 of gladsome recognition; and when he had treated her to not a little
 of his wonted eloquence, she drew him aside, and heaving a great
 sigh, said: 
<milestone id="p08040012" /><q direct="unspecified">I have oftentimes heard it said, Sir, that there is no
 castle so strong, but that, if the siege be continued day by day, it
 will sooner or later be taken; which I now plainly perceive is my
 own case. For so fairly have you hemmed me in with this, that, and
 the other pretty speech or the like blandishments, that you have
 con<pb n="196" />strained
 me to make nought of my former resolve, and, seeing that I
 find such favour with you, to surrender myself unto you.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040013" />Whereto,
 overjoyed, the rector made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, I am greatly
 honoured; and, sooth to say, I marvelled not a little how you should
 hold out so long, seeing that I have never had the like experience
 with any other woman, insomuch that I have at times said: 'Were
 women of silver, they would not be worth a denier, for there is none
 but would give under the hammer.' But no more of this: when and
 where may we come together?</q> 
<milestone id="p08040014" /><q direct="unspecified">Sweet my lord,</q> replied the lady,
 <q direct="unspecified">for the when, 'tis just as we may think best, for I have no husband
 to whom to render account of my nights, but the where passes my
 wit to conjecture.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040015" /><q direct="unspecified">How so?</q> quoth the rector. <q direct="unspecified">Why not in
 your own house?</q> 
<milestone id="p08040016" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> replied the lady, <q direct="unspecified">you know that I have
 two brothers, both young men, who day and night bring their comrades
 into the house, which is none too large: for which reason it
 might not be done there, unless we were minded to make ourselves,
 as it were, dumb and blind, uttering never a word, not so much as a
 monosyllable, and abiding in the dark: in such sort indeed it might
 be, because they do not intrude upon my chamber; but theirs is so
 near to mine that the very least whisper could not but be heard.</q>
 <milestone id="p08040017" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay but, Madam,</q> returned the rector, <q direct="unspecified">let not this stand in our
 way for a night or two, until I may bethink me where else we might
 be more at our ease.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040018" /><q direct="unspecified">Be that as you will, Sir,</q> quoth the lady,
 <q direct="unspecified">I do but entreat that the affair be kept close, so that never a word
 of it get wind.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040019" /><q direct="unspecified">Have no fear on that score, Madam,</q> replied the
 priest; <q direct="unspecified">and if so it may be, let us forgather to-night.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040020" /><q direct="unspecified">With
 pleasure,</q> returned the lady; and having appointed him how and
 when to come, she left him and went home.</p><p><milestone id="p08040021" />Now the lady had a maid, that was none too young, and had a
 countenance the ugliest and most misshapen that ever was seen; for
 indeed she was flat-nosed, wry-mouthed, and thick-lipped, with huge,
 ill-set teeth, eyes that squinted and were ever bleared, and a complexion
 betwixt green and yellow, that shewed as if she had spent the
 summer not at Fiesole but at Sinigaglia: besides which she was hipshot
 and somewhat halting on the right side. 
<milestone id="p08040022" />Her name was Ciuta,
 but, for that she was such a scurvy bitch to look upon, she was called
 by all folk Ciutazza.<note>An augmentative form, with a suggestion of
 cagnazza, bitch-like.</note> And being thus misshapen of body, she
 was
 <pb n="197" />also not without her share of guile. <milestone id="p08040023" />So the lady called her and said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Ciutazza, so thou wilt do me a service to-night, I will give thee
 a fine new shift.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040024" />At the mention of the shift Ciutazza made
 answer: <q direct="unspecified">So you give me a shift, Madam, I will throw myself
 into the very fire.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040025" /><q direct="unspecified">Good,</q> said the lady; <q direct="unspecified">then I would have
 thee lie to-night in my bed with a man, whom thou wilt caress; but
 look thou say never a word, that my brothers, who, as thou knowest,
 sleep in the next room, hear thee not; and afterwards I will give
 thee the shift.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040026" /><q direct="unspecified">Sleep with a man!</q> quoth Ciutazza: <q direct="unspecified">why, if
 need be, I will sleep with six.</q> 
<milestone id="p08040027" />So in the evening Master Rector
 came, as he had been bidden; and the two young men, as the lady
 had arranged, being in their room, and making themselves very audible,
 he stole noiselessly, and in the dark, into the lady's room, and got
 him on to the bed, which Ciutazza, well advised by the lady how to
 behave, mounted from the other side. 
<milestone id="p08040028" />Whereupon Master Rector,
 thinking to have the lady by his side, took Ciutazza in his arms, and
 fell a kissing her, saying never a word the while, and Ciutazza did
 the like; and so he enjoyed her, plucking the boon which he had so
 long desired.</p><p><milestone id="p08040029" />The rector and Ciutazza thus closeted, the lady charged her
      brothers to execute the rest of her plan. They accordingly stole
      quietly out of their room, and hied them to the piazza, where
      Fortune proved propitious beyond what they had craved of her; for,
      it being a very hot night, the bishop had been seeking them, purposing
      to go home with them, and solace himself with their society, and
      quench his thirst. <milestone id="p08040030" />With which desire he acquainted them, as soon
      as he espied them coming into the piazza; and so they escorted him
      to their house, and there in the cool of their little courtyard, which
      was bright with many a lamp, he took, to his no small comfort, a
      draught of their good wine. <milestone id="p08040031" />Which done: <q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> said the young
      men, <q direct="unspecified">since of your great courtesy you have deigned to visit our poor
	house, to which we were but now about to invite you, we should be
	gratified if you would be pleased to give a look at somewhat, a mere
	trifle though it be, which we have here to shew you.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08040032" />The bishop
      replied that he would do so with pleasure. Whereupon one of the
      young men took a lighted torch and led the way, the bishop and
      the rest following, to the chamber where Master Rector lay with
      Ciutazza.</p><pb n="198" /><p>Now the rector, being in hot haste, had ridden hard, insomuch
 that he was already gotten above three miles on his way when they
 arrived; and so, being somewhat tired, he was resting, but, hot
 though the night was, he still held Ciutazza in his arms. 
<milestone id="p08040033" />In which
 posture he was shewn to the bishop, when, preceded by the young
 man bearing the light, and followed by the others, he entered the
 chamber. <milestone id="p08040034" />And being roused, and observing the light and the folk
 that stood about him, Master Rector was mighty ashamed and
 affrighted, and popped his head under the clothes. But the bishop,
 reprimanding him severely, constrained him to thrust his head out
 again, and take a view of his bed-fellow. <milestone id="p08040035" />Thus made aware of the
 trick which the lady had played him, the rector was now, both on
 that score and by reason of his signal disgrace, the saddest man that
 ever was; and his discomfiture was complete, when, having donned
 his clothes, he was committed by the bishop's command to close
 custody and sent to prison, there to expiate his offence by a rigorous
 penance.</p><p>The bishop was then fain to know how it had come about that
 he had forgathered there with Ciutazza. <milestone id="p08040036" />Whereupon the young
 men related the whole story; which ended, the bishop commended
 both the lady and the young men not a little, for that they had taken
 condign vengeance upon him without imbruing their hands in the
 blood of a priest. <milestone id="p08040037" />The bishop caused him to bewail his transgression
 forty days; but what with his love, and the scornful requital which
 it had received, he bewailed it more than forty and nine days, not to
 mention that for a great while he could not shew himself in the
 street but the boys would point the finger at him and say:
 <q direct="unspecified">There goes he that lay with Ciutazza.</q> Which was such an
 affliction to him that he was like to go mad. On this wise the
 worthy lady rid herself of the rector's vexatious importunity, and
 Ciutazza had a jolly night and earned her shift.</p></div2>