<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov0205"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02050001" />Andreuccio da Perugia comes to Naples to buy horses,
 meets with three serious adventures in one night,
 comes safe out of them all, and returns home with
 a ruby.</p></argument><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02050002" />Landolfo's find of stones, began Fiammetta,
	on whom the
	narration now fell, has brought to my mind a story in which there are
	scarce fewer perilous scapes than in Lauretta's story, but with this
	difference, that, instead of a course of perhaps several years, a single
	night, as you shall hear, sufficed for their occurrence.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02050003" />In Perugia, by what I once gathered, there lived a young man,
 Andreuccio di Pietro by name, a horse-dealer, who, having learnt
 that horses were to be had cheap at Naples, put five hundred florins
 of gold in his purse, and in company with some other merchants
 went thither, never having been away from home before. On his
 arrival at Naples, which was on a Sunday evening, about vespers,
 he learnt from his host that the fair would be held on the following
 morning. Thither accordingly he then repaired, and looked at
 many horses which pleased him much, and cheapening them more
 and more, and failing to strike a bargain with any one, he from
 time to time, being raw and unwary, drew out his purse of florins
 in view of all that came and went, to shew that he meant business.</p><p><milestone id="p02050004" />While he was thus chaffering, and after he had shewn his purse,
 there chanced to come by a Sicilian girl, fair as fair could be, but
 ready to pleasure any man for a small consideration. He did not see
 her, but she saw him and his purse, and forthwith said to herself:
 <q direct="unspecified">Who would be in better luck than I if all those florins were
	mine?</q> and so she passed on. <milestone id="p02050005" />With the girl was an old woman,
 <pb n="93" />also a Sicilian, who, when she saw Andreuccio, dropped behind the
 girl, and ran towards him, making as if she would tenderly embrace
 him. The girl observing this said nothing, but stopped and waited
 a little way off for the old woman to rejoin her. <milestone id="p02050006" />Andreuccio turned
 as the old woman came up, recognised her, and greeted her very
 cordially; but time and place not permitting much converse, she
 left him, promising to visit him at his inn; and he resumed his
 chaffering, but bought nothing that morning.</p><p><milestone id="p02050007" />Her old woman's intimate acquaintance with Andreuccio had no
 more escaped the girl's notice than the contents of Andreuccio's
 purse; and with the view of devising, if possible, some way to make
 the money, either in whole or in part, her own, she began cautiously
 to ask the old woman, who and whence he was, what he did there,
 and how she came to know him. <milestone id="p02050008" />The old woman gave her almost
 as much and as circumstantial information touching Andreuccio and his
 affairs as he might have done himself, for she had lived a great while with
 his father, first in Sicily, and afterwards at Perugia. She likewise told
 the girl the name of his inn, and the purpose with which he had
 come to Naples. <milestone id="p02050009" />Thus fully armed with the names and all else that
 it was needful for her to know touching Andreuccio's kith and kin,
 the girl founded thereon her hopes of gratifying her cupidity, and
 forthwith devised a cunning stratagem to effect her purpose. Home
 she went, and gave the old woman work enough to occupy her all
 day, that she might not be able to visit Andreuccio; then, summoning
 to her aid a little girl whom she had well trained for such services,
 she sent her about vespers to the inn where Andreuccio lodged.
 <milestone id="p02050010" />Arrived there, the little girl asked for Andreuccio of Andreuccio
 himself, who chanced to be just outside the gate. On his answering
 that he was the man, she took him aside, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, a lady of
 this country, so please you, would fain speak with you.</q> 
      <milestone id="p02050011" />Whereto
 he listened with all his ears, and having a great conceit of his person,
 made up his mind that the lady was in love with him, as if there
 were ne'er another handsome fellow in Naples but himself; so forthwith
 he replied, that he would wait on the lady, and asked where
 and when it would be her pleasure to speak with him. 
<milestone id="p02050012" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> replied
 the little girl, <q direct="unspecified">she expects you in her own house, if you be pleased
 to come.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050013" /><q direct="unspecified">Lead on then, I follow thee,</q> said Andreuccio promptly,
 vouchsafing never a word to any in the inn. 
<milestone id="p02050014" />So the little girl guided
 <pb n="94" />him to her mistress's house, which was situated in a quarter the
 character of which may be inferred from its name, Evil Hole.
 Of this, however, he neither knew nor suspected aught, but, supposing
 that the quarter was perfectly reputable and that he was going to see
 a sweet lady, strode carelessly behind the little girl into the house of
 her mistress, whom she summoned by calling out, <q direct="unspecified">Andreuccio is
 here;</q> and Andreuccio then saw her advance to the head of the
 stairs to await his ascent. <milestone id="p02050015" />She was tall, still in the freshness of her
 youth, very fair of face, and very richly and nobly clad. As Andreuccio
 approached, she descended three steps to meet him with open
 arms, and clasped him round the neck, but for a while stood silent as
 if from excess of tenderness; then, bursting into a flood of tears, she
 kissed his brow, and in slightly broken accents said: <q direct="unspecified">O Andreuccio,
 welcome, welcome, my Andreuccio.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050016" />Quite lost in wonder
 to be the recipient of such caresses, Andreuccio could only answer:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam, well met.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050017" />Whereupon she took him by the hand, led
 him up into her saloon, and thence without another word into her
 chamber, which exhaled throughout the blended fragrance of roses,
 orange-blossoms and other perfumes. He observed a handsome curtained
 bed, dresses in plenty hanging, as is customary in that country,
 on pegs, and other appointments very fair and sumptuous; which
 sights, being strange to him, confirmed his belief that he was in the
 house of no other than a great lady. <milestone id="p02050018" />They sate down side by side
 on a chest at the foot of the bed, and thus she began to speak:
 <q direct="unspecified">Andreuccio, I cannot doubt that thou dost marvel both at the
 caresses which I bestow upon thee, and at my tears, seeing that thou
 knowest me not, and, maybe, hast never so much as heard my name;
 wait but a moment and thou shalt learn what perhaps will cause thee
 to marvel still more, to wit, that I am thy sister; and I tell thee,
 that, since of God's especial grace it is granted me to see one, albeit
 I would fain see all, of my brothers before I die, I shall not meet
 death, when the hour comes, without consolation; but thou, perchance,
 hast never heard aught of this; wherefore listen to what I
 shall say to thee. <milestone id="p02050019" />Pietro, my father and thine, as I suppose thou
 mayst have heard, dwelt a long while at Palermo, where his good
 heart and gracious bearing caused him to be (as he still is) much
 beloved by all that knew him; but by none was he loved so much as
 by a gentlewoman, afterwards my mother, then a widow, who, casting
 <pb n="95" />aside all respect for her father and brothers, ay, and her honour,
 grew so intimate with him that a child was born, which child am I,
 thy sister, whom thou seest before thee. <milestone id="p02050020" />Shortly after my birth it so
 befell that Pietro must needs leave Palermo and return to Perugia, and
 I, his little daughter, was left behind with my mother at Palermo; nor,
 so far as I have been able to learn, did he ever again bestow a thought
 upon either of us. Wherefore--to say nothing of the love which he
 should have borne me, his daughter by no servant or woman of low
 degree--I should, were he not my father, gravely censure the ingratitude
 which he shewed towards my mother, who, prompted by a most
 loyal love, committed her fortune and herself to his keeping, without so
 much as knowing who he was. <milestone id="p02050021" />But to what end? The wrongs of
 long-ago are much more easily censured than redressed; enough that so
 it was. <milestone id="p02050022" />He left me a little girl at Palermo, where, when I was grown
 to be almost as thou seest me, my mother, who was a rich lady, gave
 me in marriage to an honest gentleman of the Girgenti family, who
 for love of my mother and myself settled in Palermo, and there, being
 a staunch Guelf, entered into correspondence with our King
 Charles;<note>Charles II. of Naples, son of Charles of Anjou.</note>
 <milestone id="p02050023" />which being discovered by King Frederic<note>Frederic II. of Sicily,
 younger son of Peter III. of Arragon.</note> before the time was ripe
 for action, we had perforce to flee from Sicily just when I was expecting
 to become the greatest lady that ever was in the island. So,
 taking with us such few things as we could, few, I say, in comparison
 of the abundance which we possessed, we bade adieu to our estates
 and palaces, and found a refuge in this country, and such favour with
 King Charles that, in partial compensation for the losses which we
 had sustained on his account, he has granted us estates and houses and
 an ample pension, which he regularly pays to my husband and thy
 brother-in-law, as thou mayst yet see. In this manner I live here;
 but that I am blest with the sight of thee, I ascribe entirely to the
 mercy of God; and no thanks to thee, my sweet brother.</q> <milestone id="p02050024" />So saying
 she embraced him again, and melting anew into tears kissed his
 brow.</p><p><milestone id="p02050025" />This story, so congruous, so consistent in every detail, came trippingly
 and without the least hesitancy from her tongue. Andreuccio
 remembered that his father had indeed lived at Palermo; he knew by
 his own experience the ways of young folk, how prone they are to
 <pb n="96" />love; he saw her melt into tears, he felt her embraces and sisterly
 kisses; and he took all she said for gospel. So, when she had done,
 he answered: 
<milestone id="p02050026" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam, it should not surprise you that I marvel,
 seeing that, in sooth, my father, for whatever cause, said never a word
 of you and your mother, or, if he did so, it came not to my knowledge,
 so that I knew no more of you than if you had not been;
 wherefore, the lonelier I am here, and the less hope I had of such
 good luck, the better pleased I am to have found here my sister.
 <milestone id="p02050027" />And indeed, I know not any man, however exalted his station, who
 ought not to be well pleased to have such a sister; much more, then,
 I, who am but a petty merchant; but, I pray you, resolve me of one
 thing: how came you to know that I was here?</q> 
<milestone id="p02050028" />Then answered
 she: <q direct="unspecified">'Twas told me this morning by a poor woman who is much
 about the house, because, as she tells me, she was long in the service
 of our father both at Palermo and at Perugia; and, but that it seemed
 more fitting that thou shouldst come to see me at home than that I
 should visit thee at an inn, I had long ago sought thee out.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050029" />She
 then began to inquire particularly after all his kinsfolk by name, and
 Andreuccio, becoming ever more firmly persuaded of that which it
 was least for his good to believe, answered all her questions. 
<milestone id="p02050030" />Their
 conversation being thus prolonged and the heat great, she had Greek
 wine and sweetmeats brought in, and gave Andreuccio to drink;
 and when towards supper-time he made as if he would leave, she
 would in no wise suffer it; but, feigning to be very much vexed, she
 embraced him, saying: 
<milestone id="p02050031" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas! now 'tis plain how little thou carest
 for me: to think that thou art with thy sister, whom thou seest for
 the first time, and in her own house, where thou shouldst have
 alighted on thine arrival, and thou wouldst fain depart hence to go
 sup at an inn! Nay but, for certain, thou shalt sup with me; and
 albeit, to my great regret, my husband is not here, thou shalt see that
 I can do a lady's part in shewing thee honour.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050032" />Andreuccio, not
 knowing what else to say, replied: <q direct="unspecified">Sister, I care for you with all
 a brother's affection; but if I go not, supper will await me all the
 evening at the inn, and I shall justly be taxed with discourtesy.</q>
 <milestone id="p02050033" />Then said she: <q direct="unspecified">Blessed be God, there is even now in the house
 one by whom I can send word that they are not to expect thee at the
 inn, albeit thou wouldst far better discharge the debt of courtesy by
 sending word to thy friends, that they come here to sup; and then,
 <pb n="97" />if go thou must, you might all go in a body.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050034" />Andreuccio replied,
 that he would have none of his friends that evening, but since she
 would have him stay, he would even do her the pleasure. She then
 made a shew of sending word to the inn that they should not expect
 him at dinner. Much more talk followed; and then they sate down
 to a supper of many courses splendidly served, which she cunningly
 protracted until nightfall; nor, when they were risen from table, and
 Andreuccio was about to take his departure, would she by any means
 suffer it, saying, that Naples was no place to walk about in after
 dark, least of all for a stranger, and that, as she had sent word to the
 inn that they were not to expect him at supper, so she had done the
 like in regard of his bed. <milestone id="p02050035" />Believing what she said, and being (in his
 false confidence) overjoyed to be with her, he stayed. <milestone id="p02050036" />After supper
 there was matter enough for talk both various and prolonged; and,
 when the night was in a measure spent, she gave up her own chamber
 to Andreuccio, leaving him with a small boy to shew him aught that
 he might have need of, while she retired with her women to another
 chamber.</p><p><milestone id="p02050037" />It was a very hot night; so, no sooner was Andreuccio alone than
 he stripped himself to his doublet, and drew off his stockings and laid
 them on the bed's head; and nature demanding a discharge of the
 surplus weight which he carried within him, he asked the lad
 where this might be done, and was shewn a door in a corner of
 the room, and told to go in there. <milestone id="p02050038" />Andreuccio, nothing doubting,
 did so, but, by ill luck, set his foot on a plank which was detached
 from the joist at the further end, whereby down it went, and he
 with it. By God's grace he took no hurt by the fall, though it
 was from some height, beyond sousing himself from head to foot
 in the ordure which filled the whole place, which, <milestone id="p02050039" />that you may
 the better understand what has been said, and that which is to
 follow, I will describe to you. A narrow and blind alley, such as
 we commonly see between two houses, was spanned by planks
 supported by joists on either side, and on the planks was the stool;
 of which planks that which fell with Andreuccio was one. 
<milestone id="p02050040" />Now
 Andreuccio, finding himself down there in the alley, fell to calling on
 the lad, who, as soon as he heard him fall, had run off, and promptly
 let the lady know what had happened. She hied forthwith to her
 chamber, and after a hasty search found Andreuccio's clothes and the
 <pb n="98" />money
 in them, for he foolishly thought to secure himself against
 risk by carrying it always on his person, and thus being possessed of
 the prize for which she had played her ruse, passing herself off as the
 sister of a man of Perugia, whereas she was really of Palermo, she
 concerned herself no further with Andreuccio except to close with
 all speed the door by which he had gone out when he fell. 
<milestone id="p02050041" />As the
 lad did not answer, Andreuccio began to shout more loudly; but all
 to no purpose. Whereby his suspicions were aroused, and he began
 at last to perceive the trick that had been played upon him; so he
 climbed over a low wall that divided the alley from the street, and
 hied him to the door of the house, which he knew very well. There
 for a long while he stood shouting and battering the door till it shook
 on its hinges; but all again to no purpose. 
<milestone id="p02050042" />No doubt of his misadventure
 now lurking in his mind, he fell to bewailing himself,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! in how brief a time have I lost five hundred florins
 and a sister!</q> <milestone id="p02050043" />with much more of the like sort. Then he recommenced
 battering the door and shouting, to such a tune that not a
 few of the neighbours were roused, and finding the nuisance intolerable,
 got up; and one of the lady's servant-girls presented herself at
 the window with a very sleepy air, and said angrily: <q direct="unspecified">Who knocks
 below there?</q> 
<milestone id="p02050044" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> said Andreuccio, <q direct="unspecified">dost not know me? I
 am Andreuccio, Madam Fiordaliso's brother.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050045" /><q direct="unspecified">Good man,</q> she
 rejoined, <q direct="unspecified">if thou hast had too much to drink, go, sleep it off, and
 come back to-morrow. I know not Andreuccio, nor aught of the
 fantastic stuff thou pratest; prithee begone and be so good as to let
 us sleep in peace.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050046" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> said Andreuccio, <q direct="unspecified">dost not understand
 what I say? For sure thou dost understand; but if Sicilian kinships
 are of such a sort that folk forget them so soon, at least return me
 my clothes, which I left within, and right glad shall I be to be off.</q>
 <milestone id="p02050047" />Half laughing she rejoined: <q direct="unspecified">Good man, methinks thou dost
 dream:</q> and so saying, she withdrew and closed the window.
 <milestone id="p02050048" />Andreuccio by this time needed no further evidence of his wrongs;
 his wrath knew no bounds, and mortification well-nigh converted
 it into frenzy; he was minded to exact by force what he had
 failed to obtain by entreaties; and so, arming himself with a
 large stone, he renewed his attack upon the door with fury, dealing
 much heavier blows than at first. <milestone id="p02050049" />Wherefore, not a few of the
 neighbours, whom he had already roused from their beds, set him
 <pb n="99" />down as an ill-conditioned rogue, and his story as a mere fiction
 intended to annoy the good woman,<note>I. e. the bawd.</note> and
 resenting the din which
 he now made, came to their windows, just as, when a stranger dog
 makes his appearance, all the dogs of the quarter will run to bark at
 him, and called out in chorus: 
<milestone id="p02050050" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis a gross affront to come at this
 time of night to the house of the good woman with this silly story.
 Prithee, good man, let us sleep in peace; begone in God's name; and
 if thou hast a score to settle with her, come to-morrow, but a truce
 to thy pestering to-night.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02050051" />Emboldened, perhaps, by these words, a man who lurked within
 the house, the good woman's bully, whom Andreuccio had as yet
 neither seen nor heard, shewed himself at the window, and said in a
 gruff voice and savage, menacing tone: <q direct="unspecified">Who is below there?</q>
 <milestone id="p02050052" />Andreuccio looked up in the direction of the voice, and saw standing
 at the window, yawning and rubbing his eyes as if he had just been
 roused from his bed, or at any rate from deep sleep, a fellow with a
 black and matted beard, who, as far as Andreuccio's means of judging
 went, bade fair to prove a most redoubtable champion. It was not
 without fear, therefore, that he replied: <q direct="unspecified">I am a brother of the
 lady who is within.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050053" />The bully did not wait for him to finish his
 sentence, but, addressing him in a much sterner tone than before,
 called out: <q direct="unspecified">I know not why I come not down and give thee play
 with my cudgel, whilst thou givest me sign of life, ass, tedious driveller
 that thou must needs be, and drunken sot, thus to disturb our
 night's rest.</q> Which said, he withdrew, and closed the window.
 <milestone id="p02050054" />Some of the neighbours who best knew the bully's quality gave
 Andreuccio fair words. <q direct="unspecified">For God's sake,</q> said they, <q direct="unspecified">good man,
 take thyself off, stay not here to be murdered. 'Twere best for thee
 to go.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050055" />These counsels, which seemed to be dictated by charity,
 reinforced the fear which the voice and aspect of the bully had
 inspired in Andreuccio, who, thus despairing of recovering his money
 and in the deepest of dumps, set his face towards the quarter whence
 in the daytime he had blindly followed the little girl, and began to
 make his way back to the inn. <milestone id="p02050056" />But so noisome was the stench
 which he emitted that he resolved to turn aside and take a bath in the
 sea. So he bore leftward up a street called Ruga Catalana, and was
 <pb n="100" />on his way towards the steep of the city, when by chance he saw two
 men coming towards him, bearing a lantern, and fearing that they
 might be patrols or other men who might do him a mischief, he stole
 away and hid himself in a dismantled house to avoid them. 
<milestone id="p02050057" />The
 house, however, was presently entered by the two men, just as if they
 had been guided thither; and one of them having disburdened himself
 of some iron tools which he carried on his shoulder, they both
 began to examine them, passing meanwhile divers comments upon
 them. <milestone id="p02050058" />While they were thus occupied, <q direct="unspecified">What,</q> said one, <q direct="unspecified">means
 this? Such a stench as never before did I smell the like!</q> So
 saying, he raised the lantern a little; whereby they had a view of
 hapless Andreuccio, and asked in amazement: <q direct="unspecified">Who is there?</q>
 <milestone id="p02050059" />Whereupon Andreuccio was at first silent, but when they flashed
 the light close upon him, and asked him what he did there in such
 a filthy state, he told them all that had befallen him. Casting
 about to fix the place where it occurred, they said one to another:
 <q direct="unspecified">Of a surety 'twas in the house of Scarabone Buttafuoco.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050060" />Then
 said one, turning to Andreuccio: <q direct="unspecified">Good man, albeit thou hast
 lost thy money, thou hast cause enough to praise God that thou
 hadst the luck to fall; for hadst thou not fallen, be sure that, no
 sooner wert thou asleep, than thou hadst been knocked on the head,
 and lost not only thy money but thy life. But what boots it now
 to bewail thee? Thou mightest as soon pluck a star from the
 firmament as recover a single denier; nay, 'tis as much as thy life
 is worth if he do but hear that thou breathest a word of the affair.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02050061" />The two men then held a short consultation, at the close of
 which they said: <q direct="unspecified">Lo now; we are sorry for thee, and so we
 make thee a fair offer. If thou wilt join with us in a little matter
 which we have in hand, we doubt not but thy share of the gain
 will greatly exceed what thou hast lost.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050062" />Andreuccio, being now
 desperate, answered that he was ready to join them. 
<milestone id="p02050063" />Now Messer
 Filippo Minutolo, Archbishop of Naples, had that day been buried
 with a ruby on his finger, worth over five hundred florins of gold,
 besides other ornaments of extreme value. The two men were
 minded to despoil the Archbishop of his fine trappings, and imparted
 their design to Andreuccio, <milestone id="p02050064" />who, cupidity getting the better of
 caution, approved it; and so they all three set forth. But as they
 were on their way to the cathedral, Andreuccio gave out so rank an
 <pb n="101" />odour that one said to the other: <q direct="unspecified">Can we not contrive that he
 somehow wash himself a little, that he stink not so shrewdly?</q>
 <milestone id="p02050065" /><q direct="unspecified">Why yes,</q> said the other, <q direct="unspecified">we are now close to a well, which
 is never without the pulley and a large bucket; 'tis but a step
 thither, and we will wash him out of hand.</q> <milestone id="p02050066" />Arrived at the well,
 they found that the rope was still there, but the bucket had been
 removed; so they determined to attach him to the rope, and
 lower him into the well, there to wash himself, which done, he
 was to jerk the rope, and they would draw him up. Lowered
 accordingly he was; but just as, now washen, he jerked the rope, 
<milestone id="p02050067" />it
 so happened that a company of patrols, being thirsty because 'twas a
 hot night and some rogue had led them a pretty dance, came to the
 well to drink. The two men fled, unobserved, as soon as they caught
 sight of the newcomers, who, parched with thirst, <milestone id="p02050068" />laid aside their
 bucklers, arms and surcoats, and fell to hauling on the rope, supposing
 that it bore the bucket, full of water. <milestone id="p02050069" />When, therefore, they saw
 Andreuccio, as he neared the brink of the well, loose the rope and
 clutch the brink with his hands, they were stricken with a sudden
 terror, and without uttering a word let go the rope, and took to flight
 with all the speed they could make. Whereat Andreuccio marvelled
 mightily, and had he not kept a tight grip on the brink of the well,
 he would certainly have gone back to the bottom and hardly have
 escaped grievous hurt, or death. Still greater was his astonishment,
 when, fairly landed on terra firma, he found the patrols' arms lying
 there, which he knew had not been carried by his comrades. 
<milestone id="p02050070" />He
 felt a vague dread, he knew not why; he bewailed once more his
 evil fortune; and without venturing to touch the arms, he left the
 well and wandered he knew not whither. As he went, however, he
 fell in with his two comrades, now returning to draw him out of the
 well; who no sooner saw him than in utter amazement they
 demanded who had hauled him up. Andreuccio answered that he
 knew not, and then told them in detail how it had come about, and
 what he had found beside the well. <milestone id="p02050071" />They laughed as they apprehended
 the circumstances, and told him why they had fled, and who
 they were that had hauled him up. Then without further parley,
 for it was now midnight, they hied them to the cathedral. They had
 no difficulty in entering and finding the tomb, which was a magnificent
 structure of marble, and with their iron implements they raised
 <pb n="102" />the lid, albeit it was very heavy, to a height sufficient to allow a man
 to enter, and propped it up. <milestone id="p02050072" />This done, a dialogue ensued. <q direct="unspecified">Who
 shall go in?</q> said one. 
<milestone id="p02050073" /><q direct="unspecified">Not I,</q> said the other. 
<milestone id="p02050074" /><q direct="unspecified">Nor I,</q>
 rejoined his companion; <q direct="unspecified">let Andreuccio go in.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050075" /><q direct="unspecified">That will not I,</q> said Andreuccio. 
<milestone id="p02050076" />Whereupon both turned upon him and said:
 <q direct="unspecified">How? thou wilt not go in? By God, if thou goest not in, we
 will give thee that over the pate with one of these iron crowbars
 that thou shalt drop down dead.</q> 
<milestone id="p02050077" />Terror-stricken, into the tomb
 Andreuccio went, saying to himself as he did so: <q direct="unspecified">These men will
 have me go in, that they may play a trick upon me: when I have
 handed everything up to them, and am sweating myself to get out
 of the tomb, they will be off about their business, and I shall be left
 with nothing for my pains.</q> So he determined to make sure of his
 own part first; and bethinking him of the precious ring of which he
 had heard them speak, as soon as he had completed the descent, he
 drew the ring off the Archbishop's finger, and put it on his own: he
 then handed up one by one the crosier, mitre and gloves, and other of
 the Archbishop's trappings, stripping him to his shirt; which done, he
 told his comrades that there was nothing more. <milestone id="p02050078" />They insisted that
 the ring must be there, and bade him search everywhere. This he
 feigned to do, ejaculating from time to time that he found it not;
 and thus he kept them a little while in suspense. But they, who
 were in their way as cunning as he, kept on exhorting him to make
 a careful search, and, seizing their opportunity, withdrew the prop
 that supported the lid of the tomb, and took to their heels, leaving
 him there a close prisoner. You will readily conceive how Andreuccio
 behaved when he understood his situation. 
<milestone id="p02050079" />More than once he
 applied his head and shoulders to the lid and sought with might and
 main to heave it up; but all his efforts were fruitless; so that at
 last, overwhelmed with anguish he fell in a swoon on the corpse of
 the Archbishop, and whether of the twain were the more lifeless,
 Andreuccio or the Archbishop, 'twould have puzzled an observer to
 determine.</p><p><milestone id="p02050080" />
      When he came to himself he burst into a torrent of tears, seeing
      now nothing in store for him but either to perish there of hunger
      and fetid odours beside the corpse and among the worms, or, should
      the tomb be earlier opened, to be taken and hanged as a thief. 
<milestone id="p02050081" />These
      most lugubrious meditations were interrupted by a sound of persons
      <pb n="103" />walking and talking in the church. They were evidently a numerous
      company, and their purpose, as Andreuccio surmised, was the very
      same with which he and his comrades had come thither: whereby
      his terror was mightily increased. <milestone id="p02050082" />Presently the folk opened the
      tomb, and propped up the lid, and then fell to disputing as to who
      should go in. None was willing, and the contention was protracted;
      but at length one--'twas a priest--said: <q direct="unspecified">Of what are ye afeared?
	Think ye to be eaten by him? Nay, the dead eat not the living. I
	will go in myself.</q> 
      So saying he propped his breast upon the edge
      of the lid, threw his head back, and thrust his legs within, that he
      might go down feet foremost. <milestone id="p02050083" />On sight whereof Andreuccio started
      to his feet, and seizing hold of one of the priest's legs, made as if he
      would drag him down; which caused the priest to utter a prodigious
      yell, and bundle himself out of the tomb with no small celerity.
      The rest took to flight in a panic, as if a hundred thousand devils
      were at their heels. <milestone id="p02050084" />The tomb being thus left open, Andreuccio, the
      ring still on his finger, sprang out. The way by which he had
      entered the church served him for egress, and roaming at random, he
      arrived towards daybreak at the coast. Diverging thence he came
      by chance upon his inn, where he found that his host and his
      comrades had been anxious about him all night. <milestone id="p02050085" />When he told
      them all that had befallen him, they joined with the host in advising
      him to leave Naples at once. He accordingly did so, and returned
      to Perugia, having invested in a ring the money with which he had
      intended to buy horses.
    </p></div2>