<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0610"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06100001" />Fra Cipolla promises to shew certain country-folk a
feather of the Angel Gabriel, in lieu of which he finds coals, which he avers to be of
those with which St. Lawrence was roasted.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06100002" />All the company save Dioneo being delivered of
	their several stories, he wist that 'twas his turn to speak. Wherefore, without awaiting
	any very express command, he enjoined silence on those that were commending Guido's pithy
	quip, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06100003" />Sweet my ladies, albeit 'tis my privilege to speak of what likes me
	most, I purpose not to-day to deviate from that theme whereon you have all discoursed most
	appositely; but, following in your footsteps, I am minded to shew you with what adroitness
	and readiness of resource one of the Friars of St. Antony avoided a pickle that two young
	men had in readiness for him. <milestone id="p06100004" />Nor, if, in order to do the story
	full justice, I be somewhat prolix of speech, should it be burdensome to you, if you will
	but glance at the sun, which is yet in mid-heaven.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06100005" />Certaldo, as perchance you may have heard, is a town of
Val
 d'Elsa within our country-side, which, small though it is, had in it
aforetime people of rank and wealth. <milestone id="p06100006" />Thither, for that there he
 found good
pasture, 'twas long the wont of one of the Friars of St.
 Antony to resort
once every year, to collect the alms that fools gave
 them. Fra
Cipolla<note>Onion.</note>--so hight the friar--met with a hearty
welcome,
 no less, perchance, by reason of his name than for other cause,
the
 onions produced in that district being famous throughout Tuscany.
 <milestone id="p06100007" />He
was little of person, red-haired, jolly-visaged, and the very best
 of good
fellows; and therewithal, though learning he had none, he
 <pb n="99" />was
so excellent and ready a speaker that whoso knew him not would
 not only
have esteemed him a great rhetorician, but would have
 pronounced him Tully
himself or, perchance, Quintilian; and in all
 the country-side there was
scarce a soul to whom he was not either
 gossip or friend or lover. <milestone id="p06100008" />Being
thus wont from time to time to
 visit Certaldo, the friar came there once
upon a time in the month
 of August, and on a Sunday morning, all the good
folk of the
 neighbouring farms being come to mass in the parish church, he
took
 occasion to come forward and say: <milestone id="p06100009" /><q direct="unspecified">Ladies and gentlemen, you
 wot
'tis your custom to send year by year to the poor of Baron
 Master St.
Antony somewhat of your wheat and oats, more or less,
 according to the
ability and the devoutness of each, that blessed St.
 Antony may save your
oxen and asses and pigs and sheep from harm;
 <milestone id="p06100010" />and you are also accustomed,
and especially those whose names are
 on the books of our confraternity, to
pay your trifling annual dues.
 To collect which offerings, I am hither
sent by my superior, to wit,
 Master Abbot; wherefore, with the blessing of
God, after none,
 when you hear the bells ring, you will come out of the
church to
 the place where in the usual way I shall deliver you my sermon,
and
 you will kiss the cross; <milestone id="p06100011" />and therewithal, knowing, as I do, that you
are one and all most devoted to Baron Master St. Antony, I will by
 way of
especial grace shew you a most holy and goodly relic, which
 I brought
myself from the Holy Land overseas, which is none other
 than one of the
feathers of the Angel Gabriel, which he left behind
 him in the room of the
Virgin Mary, when he came to make her
 the annunciation in Nazareth.</q>
<milestone id="p06100012" />And having said thus much, he
 ceased, and went on with the mass. <milestone id="p06100013" />Now among
the many that
 were in the church, while Fra Cipolla made this speech, were
two
 very wily young wags, the one Giovanni del Bragoniera by name,
 the
other Biagio Pizzini; who, albeit they were on the best of
 terms with Fra
Cipolla and much in his company, had a sly laugh
 together over the relic,
and resolved to make game of him and his
 feather. <milestone id="p06100014" />So, having learned that
Fra Cipolla was to breakfast that
 morning in the town with one of his
friends, as soon as they knew
 that he was at table, down they hied them
into the street, and to the
 inn where the friar lodged, having complotted
that Biagio should
 keep the friar's servant in play, while Giovanni made
search among
 the friar's goods and chattels for this feather, whatever it
might be,
 <pb n="100" />to carry it off, that they might see how the friar
would afterwards
 explain the matter to the people. <milestone id="p06100015" />Now Fra Cipolla had for
servant
 one Guccio,<note>Diminutive of Arriguccio.</note> whom some called
by way of
 addition Balena,<note>Whale.</note> others
Imbratta,<note>Filth.</note> others again Porco,<note>Hog.</note> and who
was
 such a rascallion that
 sure it is that Lippo Topo<note>The works of
this painter seem to be
 lost.</note> himself never painted his like.
<milestone id="p06100016" />Concerning
 whom Fra Cipolla would ofttimes make merry with his
 familiars,
saying: <q direct="unspecified">My servant has nine qualities, any one of
 which in Solomon,
Aristotle, or Seneca, would have been enough to
 spoil all their virtue,
wisdom and holiness. Consider, then, what
 sort of a man he must be that
has these nine qualities, and yet never
 a spark of either virtue or wisdom
or holiness.</q> <milestone id="p06100017" />And being asked
 upon divers occasions what these nine
qualities might be, he strung
 them together in rhyme, and answered: <q direct="unspecified">I
will tell you. Lazy
 and uncleanly and a liar he is, Negligent, disobedient
and foulmouthed,
 iwis, And reckless and witless and mannerless: and
therewithal
 he has some other petty vices, which 'twere best to pass
over.
 <milestone id="p06100018" />And the most amusing thing about him is, that, wherever he goes, he
is for taking a wife and renting a house, and on the strength of a big,
black, greasy beard he deems himself so very handsome a fellow and
seductive, that he takes all the women that see him to be in love
 with
him, and, if he were left alone, he would slip his girdle and run
 after
them all. <milestone id="p06100019" />True it is that he is of great use to me, for that,
 be any
minded to speak with me never so secretly, he must still have
 his share of
the audience; and, if perchance aught is demanded of
 me, such is his fear
lest I should be at a loss what answer to make,
 that he presently replies,
ay or no, as he deems meet.</q></p><p><milestone id="p06100020" />Now, when he left this knave at the
inn, Fra Cipolla had strictly
 enjoined him on no account to suffer any one
to touch aught of his,
 and least of all his wallet, because it contained
the holy things.
 <milestone id="p06100021" />But Guccio Imbratta, who was fonder of the kitchen than
any
 nightingale of the green boughs, and most particularly if he espied
there a maid, and in the host's kitchen had caught sight of a coarse
 fat
woman, short and misshapen, with a pair of breasts that shewed
 as two
buckets of muck and a face that might have belonged to one
 of the Baronci,
all reeking with sweat and grease and smoke, left
 Fra Cipolla's room and
all his things to take care of themselves, and
 <pb n="101" />like a vulture
swooping down upon the carrion, was in the kitchen
 in a trice. <milestone id="p06100022" />Where,
though 'twas August, he sat him down by the
 fire, and fell a gossiping
with Nuta--such was the maid's name--and
 told her that he was a gentleman
by procuration,<note>One of the humorous
 ineptitudes of which Boccaccio is
fond.</note> and had more
 florins than could be reckoned, besides those
that he had to give
 away, which were rather more than less, and that he
could do and
 say such things as never were or might be seen or heard
forever, good
 Lord! and a day. <milestone id="p06100023" />And all heedless of his cowl, which had as
much
 grease upon it as would have furnished forth the caldron of
Altopascio,<note>An
 abbey near Lucca famous for its doles of
broth.</note>
 and of his rent and patched doublet, inlaid with filth about
the neck
 and under the armpits, and so stained that it shewed hues more
various than ever did silk from Tartary or the Indies, and of his
 shoes
that were all to pieces, and of his hose that were all in tatters,
 he told
her in a tone that would have become the Sieur de Ch&#226;tillon,
 that he
was minded to rehabit her and put her in trim, and raise her
 from her
abject condition, and place her where, though she would
 not have much to
call her own, at any rate she would have hope of
 better things, with much
more to the like effect; <milestone id="p06100024" />which professions,
 though made with every
appearance of good will, proved, like most
 of his schemes, insubstantial
as air, and came to nothing.</p><p><milestone id="p06100025" />Finding Guccio Porco thus occupied with
Nuta, the two young
 men gleefully accounted their work half done, and,
none gainsaying
 them, entered Fra Cipolla's room, which was open, and lit
at once
 upon the wallet, in which was the feather. <milestone id="p06100026" />The wallet opened,
they
 found, wrapt up in many folds of taffeta, a little casket, on
opening
 which they discovered one of the tail-feathers of a parrot, which
they
 deemed must be that which the friar had promised to shew the good
folk of Certaldo. <milestone id="p06100027" />And in sooth he might well have so imposed upon
 them,
for in those days the luxuries of Egypt had scarce been
 introduced into
Tuscany, though they have since been brought over
 in prodigious abundance,
to the grave hurt of all Italy. <milestone id="p06100028" />And though
 some conversance with them
there was, yet in those parts folk knew
 next to nothing of them; but,
adhering to the honest, simple ways of
 their forefathers, had not seen,
nay for the most part had not so much
 as heard tell of, a
parrot.</p><p><milestone id="p06100029" />So the young men, having found the feather, took it out
with
 <pb n="102" />great glee; and looking around for something to replace
it, they
 espied in a corner of the room some pieces of coal, wherewith
they
 filled the casket; which they then closed, and having set the room
in order exactly as they had found it, they quitted it unperceived,
 and
hied them merrily off with the feather, and posted themselves
 where they
might hear what Fra Cipolla would say when he found
 the coals in its
stead. <milestone id="p06100030" />Mass said, the simple folk that were in the
 church went home with
the tidings that the feather of the Angel
 Gabriel was to be seen after
none; and this goodman telling his
 neighbour, and that goodwife her
gossip, by the time every one had
 breakfasted, the town could scarce hold
the multitude of men and
 women that flocked thither all agog to see this
feather.</p><p><milestone id="p06100031" />Fra Cipolla, having made a hearty breakfast and had a
little nap,
 got up shortly after none, and marking the great concourse of
country-folk that were come to see the feather, sent word to Guccio
Imbratta to go up there with the bells, and bring with him the
 wallet.
<milestone id="p06100032" />Guccio, though 'twas with difficulty that he tore himself
 away from the
kitchen and Nuta, hied him up with the things
 required; and though, when
he got up, he was winded, for he was
 corpulent with drinking nought but
water, he did Fra Cipolla's
 bidding by going to the church door and
ringing the bells amain.
 <milestone id="p06100033" />When all the people were gathered about the door,
Fra Cipolla, all
 unwitting that aught of his was missing, began his
sermon, and after
 much said in glorification of himself, <milestone id="p06100034" />caused the
confiteor to be recited
 with great solemnity, and two torches to be lit by
way of preliminary
 to the shewing of the feather of the Angel Gabriel: he
then bared
 his head, carefully unfolded the taffeta, and took out the
casket,
 which, after a few prefatory words in praise and laudation of the
Angel Gabriel and his relic, he opened. <milestone id="p06100035" />When he saw that it contained
nought but coals, he did not suspect Guccio Balena of playing
 the trick,
for he knew that he was not clever enough, nor did he
 curse him, that his
carelessness had allowed another to play it, but he
 inly imprecated
himself, that he had committed his things to the
 keeping of one whom he
knew to be <q direct="unspecified">negligent and disobedient,
 reckless and witless.</q>
<milestone id="p06100036" />Nevertheless, he changed not colour, but
 with face and hands upturned to
heaven, he said in a voice that all
 might hear: <q direct="unspecified">O God, blessed be Thy
might for ever and ever.</q>
 <milestone id="p06100037" />Then, closing the casket, and turning to the
people: <q direct="unspecified">Ladies and
 <pb n="103" />gentlemen,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">you are to
know, that when I was yet a very
 young man, I was sent by my superior into
those parts where the
 sun rises, and I was expressly bidden to search
until I should find
 the Privileges of Porcellana, which, though they cost
nothing to seal,
 are of much more use to others than to us. <milestone id="p06100038" />On which
errand I set
 forth, taking my departure from Venice, and traversing the
Borgo
 de' Greci,<note>Perhaps part of the <q direct="unspecified">sesto</q> of Florence known
as the
 Borgo, as the tradition of the commentators that the friar's
itinerary is
 wholly
 Florentine is not to be lightly set aside.</note> and
thence on horseback
 the
 realm of Algarve,<note>Il
Garbo, a quarter or street in Florence,
 doubtless so called
because the wares of Algarve were there sold. Rer.
 Ital.
Script. (Muratori: Suppl. Tartini) ii. 119. Villani,
Istorie
 Fiorentine, iv. 12, xii. 18.</note> and so
by
 Baldacca<note>A famous tavern in Florence. Florio, Vocab.
Ital. e
 Ingl., ed Torriano, 1659.</note> I came to
Parione,<note>A <q direct="unspecified">borgo</q>
 in
 Florence. Villani, Istorie
Fiorentine, iv. 7.</note> whence, somewhat
 athirst, I after a
while got on to Sardinia.<note>A suburb of Florence on the Arno,
ib.
 ix. 256.</note> <milestone id="p06100039" />But wherefore go I about to
enumerate
 all the lands in which I pursued my quest? Having passed the
straits of San Giorgio, I arrived at Truffia<note>The land of
Cajolery.</note> and Buffia,<note>The land of Drollery.</note> countries
thickly populated and with great nations, whence I pursued my
 journey to
Menzogna,<note>The land of Lies.</note> where I met with many of
 our own
brethren,
 and of other religious not a few, intent one and all on
eschewing
 hardship for the love of God, making little account of others'
toil, so
 they might ensue their own advantage, and paying in nought but
unminted
 coin<note>I.e. in false promises: suggested
by Dante's Pagando di
 moneta senza conio. Parad.
xxix. 126.</note> throughout the length
 and
 breadth of the country;
 <milestone id="p06100040" />and
so I came to the land of Abruzzi, where the men and women
 go in pattens on
the mountains, and clothe the hogs with their own
 entrails;<note>A
reference to sausage-making.</note> <milestone id="p06100041" />and a little further on
 I
 found folk
that carried bread in
 staves and wine in
sacks.<note>I.e. cakes fashioned in a hollow ring,
and wines in leathern bottles.</note> And leaving them, I arrived at the
<pb n="104" />mountains of the Bachi,<note>Grubs.</note> where all the waters
run
 downwards. <milestone id="p06100042" />In
 short I penetrated so far that I came at last to India
Pastinaca,<note>In
 allusion to the shapeless fish, so called, which was
proverbially taken as a
 type of the outlandish.</note> where
 I swear to
you by the habit that I wear, that I saw pruning-hooks<note>A
jeu de mots, <q direct="unspecified">pennati,</q> pruning-hooks, signifying
also
 feathered, though <q direct="unspecified">pennuti</q> is more common
in that sense.</note>
 fly: a thing that none would believe that had not
seen it. Whereof
 be my witness that I lie not Maso del Saggio, that great
merchant,
 whom I found there cracking nuts, and selling the shells by
retail!
 <milestone id="p06100043" />However, not being able to find that whereof I was in quest,
because
 from thence one must travel by water, I turned back, and so came
at length to the Holy Land, where in summer cold bread costs four
 deniers,
and hot bread is to be had for nothing. And there I found
 the venerable
father
 Nonmiblasmetesevoipiace,<note>Takemenottotaskanitlikeyou.</note>
the most
 worshipful
 Patriarch of Jerusalem; <milestone id="p06100044" />who out of respect for the
habit that I have
 ever worn, to wit, that of Baron Master St. Antony, was
pleased to
 let me see all the holy relics that he had by him, which were
so
 many, that, were I to enumerate them all, I should not come to the
 end
of them in some miles. However, not to disappoint you, I will
 tell you a
few of them. <milestone id="p06100045" />In the first place, then, he shewed me the
 finger of the Holy
Spirit, as whole and entire as it ever was, and the
 tuft of the Seraph
that appeared to St. Francis, and one of the nails
 of the Cherubim, and
one of the ribs of the Verbum Caro hie thee
 to the
casement,<note>fatti alle finestre, a subterfuge for
factum est.</note> and some of the vestments of the
Holy Catholic
 Faith, and some of the rays of the star that appeared to the
Magi in
 the East, and a phial of the sweat of St. Michael a battling with
the
 Devil and the jaws of death of St. Lazarus, and other relics. <milestone id="p06100046" />And
 for
that I gave him a liberal supply of the
acclivities<note>piagge,
 jocularly for
pagine: doubtless some mighty tome of school divinity
is
 meant.</note> of Monte
 Morello in the vulgar and some chapters of
Caprezio, of which he
 had long been in quest, he was pleased to let me
participate in his
 holy relics, <milestone id="p06100047" />and gave me one of the teeth of the Holy
Cross, and in
 a small phial a bit of the sound of the bells of Solomon's
temple, and
 <pb n="105" />this feather of the Angel Gabriel, whereof I have
told you, and one
 of the pattens of San Gherardo da Villa Magna, which,
not long ago,
 I gave at Florence to Gherardo di Bonsi, who holds him in
prodigious
 veneration. He also gave me some of the coals with which the
most blessed martyr, St. Lawrence, was roasted. All which things
 I
devoutly brought thence, and have them all safe. <milestone id="p06100048" />True it is that
 my
superior has not hitherto permitted me to shew them, until he
 should be
certified that they are genuine. However, now that this
 is avouched by
certain miracles wrought by them, of which we have
 tidings by letter from
the Patriarch, he has given me leave to shew
 them. But, fearing to trust
them to another, I always carry them
 with me; <milestone id="p06100049" />and to tell you the truth I
carry the feather of the Angel
 Gabriel, lest it should get spoiled, in a
casket, and the coals, with
 which St. Lawrence was roasted, in another
casket; which caskets
 are so like the one to the other, that not seldom I
mistake one for
 the other, which has befallen me on this occasion; for,
whereas I
 thought to have brought with me the casket wherein is the
feather,
 I have brought instead that which contains the coals. <milestone id="p06100050" />Nor deem l
this a mischance; nay, methinks, 'tis by interposition of God, and
 that He
Himself put the casket of coals in my hand, for I mind me
 that the feast
of St. Lawrence falls but two days hence. <milestone id="p06100051" />Wherefore
 God, being minded that
by shewing you the coals, with which he
 was roasted, I should rekindle in
your souls the devotion that you
 ought to feel towards him, guided my
hand, not to the feather which
 I meant to take, but to the blessed coals
that were extinguished by
 the humours that exuded from that most holy
body. <milestone id="p06100052" />And so,
 blessed children, bare your heads and devoutly draw nigh to
see
 them. But first of all I would have you know, that whoso has the
 sign
of the cross made upon him with these coals, may live secure for
 the whole
of the ensuing year, that fire shall not touch him, that he
 feel it
not.</q></p><p><milestone id="p06100053" />Having so said, the friar, chanting a hymn in praise of
St.
 Lawrence, opened the casket, and shewed the coals. Whereon the

foolish crowd gazed a while in awe and reverent wonder, and then
 came
pressing forward in a mighty throng about Fra Cipolla with
 offerings
beyond their wont, each and all praying him to touch them
 with the coals.
<milestone id="p06100054" />Wherefore Fra Cipolla took the coals in his hand,
 and set about making on
their white blouses, and on their doublets,
 <pb n="106" />and on the veils
of the women crosses as big as might be, averring
 the while that whatever
the coals might thus lose would be made
 good to them again in the casket,
as he had often proved. <milestone id="p06100055" />On this
 wise, to his exceeding great profit, he
marked all the folk of Certaldo
 with the cross, and, thanks to his ready
wit and resource, had his
 laugh at those, who by robbing him of the
feather thought to make
 a laughing-stock of him. They, indeed, being among
his hearers,
 and marking his novel expedient, and how voluble he was, and
what
 a long story he made of it, laughed till they thought their jaws
would break; <milestone id="p06100056" />and, when the congregation was dispersed, they went
 up to
him, and never so merrily told him what they had done, and
 returned him
his feather; which next year proved no less lucrative
 to him than that day
the coals had been.</p></div2>