<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0803"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08030001" />Calandrino, Bruno and Buffalmacco go in quest of the
	heliotrope beside the Mugnone. Thinking to have
	found it, Calandrino gets him home laden with stones.
	His wife chides him: whereat he waxes wroth, beats
	her, and tells his comrades what they know better
	than he.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08030002" />Ended Pamfilo's story, which
	moved the ladies to inextinguishable
	laughter, the queen bade Elisa follow suit: whereupon,
	laughing, she thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08030003" />I know not, debonair my ladies, whether
	with my little story, which is no less true than entertaining, I shall
	give you occasion to laugh as much as Pamfilo has done with his,
	but I will do my best.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08030004" />In our city, where there has never been lack of odd humours
      and queer folk, there dwelt, no long time ago, a painter named
      Calandrino, a simple soul, of uncouth manners, that spent most of
      his time with two other painters, the one Bruno, the other
      Buffalmacco, by name, pleasant fellows enough, but not without
      their full share of sound and shrewd sense, and who kept with
      Calandrino for that they not seldom found his singular ways and
      his simplicity very diverting. <milestone id="p08030005" />There was also at the same time
      at Florence one Maso del Saggio, a fellow marvellously entertaining
      by his cleverness, dexterity and unfailing resource; who having
      heard somewhat touching Calandrino's simplicity, resolved to make
      fun of him by playing him a trick, and inducing him to believe
      some prodigy. <milestone id="p08030006" />And happening one day to come upon Calandrino in
      the church of San Giovanni, where he sate intently regarding the
      paintings and intaglios of the tabernacle above the altar, which had
      <pb n="187" />then
      but lately been set there, he deemed time and place convenient
      for the execution of his design; <milestone id="p08030007" />which he accordingly imparted to
      one of his comrades: whereupon the two men drew nigh the place
      where Calandrino sate alone, and feigning not to see him fell a
      talking of the virtues of divers stones, of which Maso spoke as aptly
      and pertinently as if he had been a great and learned lapidary.
      <milestone id="p08030008" />Calandrino heard what passed between them, and witting that 'twas
      no secret, after a while got up, and joined them, to Maso's no small
      delight. He therefore continued his discourse, and being asked by
      Calandrino, where these stones of such rare virtues were to be found,
      made answer: 
      <milestone id="p08030009" /><q direct="unspecified">Chiefly in Berlinzone, in the land of the Basques.
	The district is called Bengodi, and there they bind the vines with
	sausages, and a denier will buy a goose and a gosling into the
	bargain; and on a mountain, all of grated Parmesan cheese, dwell
	folk that do nought else but make macaroni and raviuoli,<note>A sort of
	  rissole.</note> and boil
	them in capon's broth, and then throw them down to be scrambled
	for; and hard by flows a rivulet of Vernaccia, the best that ever
	was drunk, and never a drop of water therein.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030010" /><q direct="unspecified">Ah! 'tis a sweet
	country!</q> quoth Calandrino; <q direct="unspecified">but tell me, what becomes of the
	capons that they boil?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030011" /><q direct="unspecified">They are all eaten by the Basques,</q>
      replied Maso. 
      <milestone id="p08030012" />Then: <q direct="unspecified">Wast thou ever there?</q> quoth Calandrino.
      <milestone id="p08030013" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Was I ever there, sayst thou?</q> replied Maso.
      <q direct="unspecified">Why, if I have been there once, I have been there a thousand
	times.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030014" /><q direct="unspecified">And how many miles is't from here?</q> quoth Calandrino.
      <milestone id="p08030015" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> returned Maso, <q direct="unspecified">more than thou couldst number in a night
	without slumber.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030016" /><q direct="unspecified">Farther off, then, than the Abruzzi?</q> said
      Calandrino. 
      <milestone id="p08030017" /><q direct="unspecified">Why, yes, 'tis a bit farther,</q> replied Maso.</p><p><milestone id="p08030018" />Now Calandrino, like the simple soul that he was, marking the
 composed and grave countenance with which Maso spoke, could not
 have believed him more thoroughly, if he had uttered the most patent
 truth, and thus taking his words for gospel: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis a trifle too far
 for my purse,</q> quoth he; <q direct="unspecified">were it nigher, I warrant thee, I
 would go with thee thither one while, just to see the macaroni
 come tumbling down, and take my fill thereof. But tell me, so good
 luck befall thee, are none of these stones, that have these rare virtues,
 to be found in these regions?</q> 
<milestone id="p08030019" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay,</q> replied Maso, <q direct="unspecified">two sorts of
 <pb n="188" />stone
 are found there, both of virtues extraordinary. The one sort
 are the sandstones of Settignano and Montisci, which being made
 into millstones, by virtue thereof flour is made; wherefore 'tis a
 common saying in those countries that blessings come from God and
 millstones from Montisci: but, for that these sandstones are in great
 plenty, they are held cheap by us, just as by them are emeralds,
 whereof they have mountains, bigger than Monte Morello, that shine
 at midnight, a God's name! And know this, that whoso should make
 a goodly pair of millstones, and connect them with a ring before ever
 a hole was drilled in them, and take them to the Soldan, should get
 all he would have thereby. <milestone id="p08030020" />The other sort of stone is the heliotrope,
 as we lapidaries call it, a stone of very great virtue, inasmuch as
 whoso carries it on his person is seen, so long as he keep it, by never
 another soul, where he is not.</q> 
<milestone id="p08030021" /><q direct="unspecified">These be virtues great indeed,</q>
 quoth Calandrino; <q direct="unspecified">but where is this second stone to be found?</q>
 <milestone id="p08030022" />Whereto Maso made answer that there were usually some to be
 found in the Mugnone. 
<milestone id="p08030023" /><q direct="unspecified">And what are its size and colour?</q> quoth
      Calandrino. <milestone id="p08030024" /><q direct="unspecified">The size varies,</q> replied Maso, <q direct="unspecified">for some are bigger
 and some smaller than others; but all are of the same colour, being
 nearly black.</q> 
<milestone id="p08030025" />All these matters duly marked and fixed in his memory,
 Calandrino made as if he had other things to attend to, and took his
 leave of Maso with the intention of going in quest of the stone, but
 not until he had let his especial friends, Bruno and Buffalmacco,
 know of his project. 
<milestone id="p08030026" />So, that no time might be lost, but, postponing
 everything else, they might begin the quest at once, he set about
 looking for them, and spent the whole morning in the search. 
<milestone id="p08030027" />At
 length, when 'twas already past none, he called to mind that they
 would be at work in the Faentine women's convent, and though
 'twas excessively hot, he let nothing stand in his way, but at a pace
      that was more like a run than a walk, hied him thither; and so soon
      as he had made them ware of his presence, thus he spoke: 
      <milestone id="p08030028" /><q direct="unspecified">Comrades,
	so you are but minded to hearken to me, 'tis in our power to
	become the richest men in Florence; for I am informed by one that
	may be trusted that there is a kind of stone in the Mugnone which
	renders whoso carries it invisible to every other soul in the world.
	Wherefore, methinks, we were wise to let none have the start of us,
	but go search for this stone without any delay. 
	<milestone id="p08030029" />We shall find it
	without a doubt, for I know what 'tis like, and when we have found <pb n="189" />it,
 we have but to put it in the purse, and get us to the moneychangers,
	whose counters, as you know, are always laden with groats
 and florins, and help ourselves to as many as we have a mind to.
	No one will see us, and so, hey presto! we shall be rich folk in the
	twinkling of an eye, and have no more need to go besmearing the
	walls all day long like so many snails.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030030" />Whereat Bruno and Buffalmacco
      began only to laugh, and exchanging glances, made as if they
      marvelled exceedingly, and expressed approval of Calandrino's project.
      Then Buffalmacco asked, what might be the name of the stone.
      <milestone id="p08030031" />Calandrino, like the numskull that he was, had already forgotten the
      name: so he made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Why need we concern ourselves
	with the name, since we know the stone's virtue? methinks, we
	were best to go look for it, and waste no more time.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030032" /><q direct="unspecified">Well, well,</q>
      said Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">but what are the size and shape of the stone?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030033" /><q direct="unspecified">They
	are of all sizes and shapes,</q> said Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">but they are all pretty
	nearly black; wherefore, methinks, we were best to collect all the
	black stones that we see until we hit upon it: and so, let us be off,
	and lose no more time.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030034" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but,</q> said Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">wait a bit.</q>
      And turning to Buffalmacco: <q direct="unspecified">Methinks,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that Calandrino
	says well: but I doubt this is not the time for such work,
	seeing that the sun is high, and his rays so flood the Mugnone as to
	dry all the stones; insomuch that stones will now shew as white
	that in the morning, before the sun had dried them, would shew as
	black: 
	<milestone id="p08030035" />besides which, to-day being a working-day, there will be for
	one cause or another folk not a few about the Mugnone, who, seeing
	us, might guess what we were come for, and peradventure do the like
	themselves; whereby it might well be that they found the stone, and
	we might miss the trot by trying after the amble. 
	<milestone id="p08030036" />Wherefore, so
	you agree, methinks we were best to go about it in the morning,
	when we shall be better able to distinguish the black stones from the
	white, and on a holiday, when there will be none to see us.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08030037" />Buffalmacco's advice being approved by Bruno, Calandrino
      chimed in; and so 'twas arranged that they should all three go in
      quest of the stone on the following Sunday. So Calandrino, having
      besought his companions above all things to let never a soul in the
      world hear aught of the matter, for that it had been imparted to him
      in strict confidence, <milestone id="p08030038" />and having told them what he had heard touching
      the land of Bengodi, the truth of which he affirmed with oaths, <pb n="190" />took
      leave of them; and they concerted their plan, <milestone id="p08030039" />while Calandrino
      impatiently expected the Sunday morning. Whereon, about dawn,
      he arose, and called them; and forth they issued by the Porta a San
      Gallo, and hied them to the Mugnone, and following its course,
      began their quest of the stone, Calandrino, as was natural, leading
      the way, and jumping lightly from rock to rock, and wherever he
      espied a black stone, stooping down, picking it up and putting it in
      the fold of his tunic, <milestone id="p08030040" />while his comrades followed, picking up a stone
      here and a stone there. Thus it was that Calandrino had not gone
      far, before, finding that there was no more room in his tunic, he lifted
      the skirts of his gown, which was not cut after the fashion of
      Hainault, and gathering them under his leathern girdle and making
      them fast on every side, thus furnished himself with a fresh and
      capacious lap, which, however, taking no long time to fill, he made
      another lap out of his cloak, which in like manner he soon filled
      with stones. <milestone id="p08030041" />Wherefore, Bruno and Buffalmacco seeing that
      Calandrino was well laden, and that 'twas nigh upon breakfast-time,
      and the moment for action come: <q direct="unspecified">Where is Calandrino?</q>
      quoth Bruno to Buffalmacco. <milestone id="p08030042" />Whereto Buffalmacco, who had
      Calandrino full in view, having first turned about and looked here,
      there and everywhere, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">That wot not I; but not
	so long ago he was just in front of us.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030043" /><q direct="unspecified">Not so long ago,
	forsooth,</q>
      returned Bruno; <q direct="unspecified">'tis my firm belief that at this very moment he is
 at breakfast at home, having left to us this wild-goose chase of black
	stones in the Mugnone.</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030044" /><q direct="unspecified">Marry,</q> quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">he did but
	serve us right so to trick us and leave, seeing that we were so silly as
	to believe him. Why, who could have thought that any but we
	would have been so foolish as to believe that a stone of such rare
	virtue was to be found in the Mugnone?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030045" />Calandrino, hearing their
      colloquy, forthwith imagined that he had the stone in his hand, and
      by its virtue, though present, was invisible to them; and overjoyed by
      such good fortune, would not say a word to undeceive them, but
      determined to hie him home, and accordingly faced about, and put
      himself in motion. 
      <milestone id="p08030046" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Ay!</q> quoth Buffalmacco
      to Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">what are we about that we go not back too?</q> 
      <milestone id="p08030047" /><q direct="unspecified">Go we
	then,</q> said Bruno; <q direct="unspecified">but by God I swear that Calandrino shall
	never play me another such trick; and as to this, were I nigh him,
	as I have been all the morning, I would teach him to remember it <pb n="191" />for
	a month or so, such a reminder would I give him in the heel
	with this stone.</q> And even as he spoke he threw back his arm, and
      launched the stone against Calandrino's heel. Galled by the blow,
      Calandrino gave a great hop and a slight gasp, but said nothing, and
      halted not. <milestone id="p08030048" />Then, picking out one of the stones that he had
      collected: <q direct="unspecified">Bruno,</q> quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">see what a goodly
	stone I have here, would it might but catch Calandrino in the
	back;</q> and forthwith he discharged it with main force upon the
      said back. And in short, suiting action to word, now in this way,
      now in that, they stoned him all the way up the Mugnone as far as
      the Porta a San Gallo. <milestone id="p08030049" />There they threw away the stones they had
      picked up, and tarried a while with the customs' officers, who, being
      primed by them, had let Calandrino pass unchallenged, while their
      laughter knew no bounds.</p><p><milestone id="p08030050" />So Calandrino, halting nowhere, betook him to his house, which
      was hard by the corner of the Macina. And so well did Fortune
      prosper the trick, that all the way by the stream and across the city
      there was never a soul that said a word to Calandrino, and indeed he
      encountered but few, for most folk were at breakfast. <milestone id="p08030051" />But no
      sooner was Calandrino thus gotten home with his stones, than it so
      happened that his good lady, Monna Tessa, shewed her fair face at
      the stair's head, and catching sight of him, and being somewhat
      annoyed by his long delay, chid him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">What the Devil
	brings thee here so late? Must breakfast wait thee until all other
	folk have had it?</q> <milestone id="p08030052" />Calandrino caught the words, and angered and
      mortified to find that he was not invisible, broke out with: <q direct="unspecified">Alas!
	curst woman! so 'twas thou! Thou hast undone me: but, God's
	faith, I will pay thee out.</q> Whereupon he was upstairs in a trice,
      and having discharged his great load of stones in a parlour, rushed
      with fell intent upon his wife, and laid hold of her by the hair, and
      threw her down at his feet, and beat and kicked her in every part of
      her person with all the force he had in his arms and legs, insomuch
      that he left never a hair of her head or bone of her body unscathed,
      and 'twas all in vain that she laid her palms together and crossed her
      fingers and cried for mercy.</p><p><milestone id="p08030053" />Now Buffalmacco and Bruno, after making merry a while with
      the warders of the gate, had set off again at a leisurely pace, keeping
      some distance behind Calandrino. Arrived at his door, they heard <pb n="192" />the
      noise of the sound thrashing that he was giving his wife; and
      making as if they were but that very instant come upon the scene,
      they called him. Calandrino, flushed, all of a sweat, and out of
      breath, shewed himself at the window, and bade them come up.
      <milestone id="p08030054" />They, putting on a somewhat angry air, did so; and espied Calandrino
 sitting in the parlour, amid the stones which lay all about,
 untrussed, and puffing with the air of a man spent with exertion,
 while his lady lay in one of the corners, weeping bitterly, her hair all
 dishevelled, her clothes torn to shreds, and her face livid, bruised and
 battered. <milestone id="p08030055" />So after surveying the room a while: <q direct="unspecified">What means
 this, Calandrino?</q> quoth they. <q direct="unspecified">Art thou minded to build thee a
 wall, that we see so many stones about?</q> And then, as they received
 no answer, they continued: <q direct="unspecified">And how's this? How comes
 Monna Tessa in this plight? 'Twould seem thou hast given her a
 beating! What unheard-of doings are these?</q> 
<milestone id="p08030056" />What with the
 weight of the stones that he had carried, and the fury with which he
 had beaten his wife, and the mortification that he felt at the miscarriage
 of his enterprise, Calandrino was too spent to utter a word
 by way of reply. Wherefore in a menacing tone Buffalmacco began
 again: 
<milestone id="p08030057" /><q direct="unspecified">However out of sorts thou mayst have been, Calandrino,
 thou shouldst not have played us so scurvy a trick as thou hast. To
 take us with thee to the Mugnone in quest of this stone of rare
 virtue, and then, without so much as saying either God-speed or
 Devil-speed, to be off, and leave us there like a couple of gowks!
 We take it not a little unkindly: and rest assured that thou shalt
 never so fool us again.</q> 
<milestone id="p08030058" />Whereto with an effort Calandrino replied:
 <q direct="unspecified">Comrades, be not wroth with me: 'tis not as you think.
 I, luckless wight! found the stone: listen, and you will no longer
 doubt that I say sooth. When you began saying one to the other:
 'Where is Calandrino?' I was within ten paces of you, and marking
 that you came by without seeing me, I went before, and so, keeping
 ever a little ahead of you, I came hither.</q> 
<milestone id="p08030059" />And then he told them the
 whole story of what they had said and done from beginning to end,
 and shewed them his back and heel, how they had been mauled by
 the stones; after which: 
<milestone id="p08030060" /><q direct="unspecified">And I tell you,</q> he went on, <q direct="unspecified">that,
 laden though I was with all these stones, that you see here, never a
 word was said to me by the warders of the gate as I passed in, though
 you know how vexatious and grievous these warders are wont to <pb n="193" />make
 themselves in their determination to see everything: and moreover
 I met by the way several of my gossips and friends that are ever
 wont to greet me, and ask me to drink, and never a word said any or
 them to me, no, nor half a word either; but they passed me by as
 men that saw me not. <milestone id="p08030061" />But at last, being come home, I was met
 and seen by this devil of a woman, curses upon her, forasmuch as all
 things, as you know, lose their virtue in the presence of a woman;
 whereby I from being the most lucky am become the most luckless
 man in Florence: <milestone id="p08030062" />and therefore I thrashed her as long as I could stir
 a hand, nor know I wherefore I forbear to sluice her veins for her,
 cursed be the hour that first I saw her, cursed be the hour that I
 brought her into the house!</q> And so, kindling with fresh wrath, he
 was about to start up and give her another thrashing; <milestone id="p08030063" />when Buffalmacco
 and Bruno, who had listened to his story with an air of great
 surprise, and affirmed its truth again and again, while they all but burst
 with suppressed laughter, <milestone id="p08030064" />seeing him now frantic to renew his assault
 upon his wife, got up and withstood and held him back, averring that
 the lady was in no wise to blame for what had happened, but only he,
 who, witting that things lost their virtue in the presence of women, had
 not bidden her keep aloof from him that day; which precaution God
 had not suffered him to take, either because the luck was not to be
 his, or because he was minded to cheat his comrades, to whom he
 should have shewn the stone as soon as he found it. <milestone id="p08030065" />And so, with
 many words they hardly prevailed upon him to forgive his injured
 wife, and leaving him to rue the ill-luck that had filled his house
 with stones, went their way.</p></div2>