<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0709"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p07090001" />Lydia, wife of
Nicostratus, loves Pyrrhus, who to assure himself thereof, asks three things of her, all
of which she does, and therewithal enjoys him in presence of Nicostratus, and makes
Nicostratus believe that what he saw was not real.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07090002" />So diverting did the ladies find Neifile's story that it kept
	them still laughing and talking, though the king, having bidden Pamfilo tell his story,
	had several times enjoined silence upon them. However, as soon as they had done, Pamfilo
	thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p07090003" />Methinks, worshipful ladies, there is no venture, though fraught
	with gravest peril, that whoso loves ardently will not make: of which truth, exemplified
	though it has been in stories not a few, I purpose to afford you yet more signal proof in
	one which I shall tell you; wherein you will hear of a lady who in her enterprises owed
	far more to the favour of Fortune than to the guidance of reason: <milestone id="p07090004" />wherefore I
	should not advise any of you rashly to follow in her footsteps, seeing
	that Fortune is not always in a kindly mood, nor are the eyes of all men equally
	holden.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p07090005" />In Argos, that most ancient city of Achaia, the fame of whose kings of old
time is out of all proportion to its size, there dwelt of yore Nicostratus, a nobleman, to
whom, when he was already verging on old age, Fortune gave to wife a great lady, Lydia by
name, whose courage matched her charms. <milestone id="p07090006" />Nicostratus, as suited with his rank
and wealth, kept not a few retainers and hounds and hawks, and was
mightily addicted to the chase. Among his dependants was a young man named Pyrrhus, a
gallant of no mean accomplishment, and goodly of person and beloved and trusted by
Nicostratus above all <pb n="160" />other. <milestone id="p07090007" />Of whom Lydia grew mighty enamoured,
insomuch that neither by day nor by night might her thoughts stray from him: but, whether
it was that Pyrrhus wist not her love, or would have none of it, he gave no sign of
recognition; whereby the lady's suffering waxing more than she could bear, <milestone id="p07090008" />she
made up her mind to declare her love to him; and having a chambermaid, Lusca by name, in
whom she placed great trust, she called her, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Lusca,
tokens thou hast had from me of my regard that should ensure thy obedience and loyalty;
wherefore have a care that what I shall now tell thee reach the ears of none but him to
whom I shall bid thee impart it. <milestone id="p07090009" />Thou seest, Lusca, that I am in the prime of
my youth and lustihead, and have neither lack nor stint of all such things as folk desire,
save only, to be brief, that I have one cause to repine, to wit, that my husband's years
so far outnumber my own. <milestone id="p07090010" />Wherefore with that wherein young ladies take most
pleasure I am but ill provided, and, as my desire is no less than theirs, 'tis now some
while since I determined that, if Fortune has shewn herself so little friendly to me by
giving me a husband so advanced in years, at least I will not be mine own enemy by sparing
to devise the means whereby my happiness and health may be assured; <milestone id="p07090011" />and that
herein, as in all other
matters, my joy may be complete, I have chosen, thereto to minister by his embraces, our
Pyrrhus, deeming him more worthy than any other man, and have so set my heart upon him
that I am ever ill at ease save when he is present either to my sight or to my mind,
insomuch that, unless I forgather with him without delay, I doubt not that 'twill be the
death of me. <milestone id="p07090012" />And so, if thou holdest my life dear, thou wilt shew him my love
on such wise as thou mayst deem best, and make my suit to him that he be pleased to come
to me, when thou shalt go to fetch him.</q> <milestone id="p07090013" /><q direct="unspecified">That gladly will I,</q> replied
the chambermaid; and as soon as she found convenient time and place, she drew Pyrrhus
apart, and, as best she knew how, conveyed her lady's message to him. Which Pyrrhus found
passing strange to hear, for 'twas in truth a complete surprise to him, and he doubted
the lady did but mean to try him. Wherefore he presently, and with some asperity, answered
thus: <milestone id="p07090014" /><q direct="unspecified">Lusca, believe I cannot that this message comes from my lady: have a
care, therefore, what thou sayst, and if, perchance, it does come from her, I doubt she
does not mean it; and if, perchance, she does mean it, why, then I am <pb n="161" />honoured
by my lord above what I deserve, and I would not for my life do him such a wrong: so have
a care never to speak of such matters to me again.</q> <milestone id="p07090015" />Lusca, nowise
disconcerted by his uncompliant tone, rejoined: <q direct="unspecified">I shall speak to thee, Pyrrhus, of
these and all other matters, wherewith I may be commissioned by my lady, as often as she
shall bid me, whether it pleases or irks thee; but thou art a blockhead.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07090016" />So,
somewhat chafed, Lusca bore Pyrrhus' answer back to her lady, who would fain have died,
when she heard it, and some days afterwards resumed the topic, saying: <milestone id="p07090017" /><q direct="unspecified">Thou
knowest, Lusca, that 'tis not the first stroke that fells the oak; wherefore, methinks,
thou wert best go back to this strangeman, who is minded to evince his loyalty at my
expense, and choosing a convenient time, declare to him all my passion, and do thy best
endeavour that the affair be carried through; for if it should thus lapse, 'twould be the
death of me; besides which, he would think we had but trifled with him, and, whereas 'tis
his love we would have, we should earn his hatred.</q> <milestone id="p07090018" />So, after comforting the
lady, the maid hied her in quest of Pyrrhus,
whom she found in a gladsome and propitious mood, and thus addressed: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis not many
days, Pyrrhus, since I declared to thee how ardent is the flame with which thy lady and
mine is consumed for love of thee, and now again I do thee to wit thereof, and that, if
thou shalt not relent of the harshness that thou didst manifest the other day, thou mayst
rest assured that her life will be short: wherefore I pray thee to be pleased to give her
solace of her desire, and shouldst thou persist in thy obduracy, I, that gave thee credit
for not a little sense, shall deem thee a great fool. <milestone id="p07090019" />How flattered thou
shouldst be to know thyself beloved above all else by a lady so beauteous and high-born!
<milestone id="p07090020" />And how indebted shouldst thou feel thyself to Fortune, seeing that she has in
store for thee a boon so great and so suited to the cravings of thy youth, ay, and so like
to be of service to thee upon occasion of need! <milestone id="p07090021" />Bethink thee, if there be any
of thine equals whose life is ordered more agreeably than thine will be if thou but be
wise. Which of them wilt thou find so well furnished with arms and horses, clothes and
money as thou shalt be, if thou but give my lady thy love? <milestone id="p07090022" />Receive, then, my
words with open mind; be thyself again; bethink thee that 'tis Fortune's way to confront a
man but once with smiling mien and open lap, and, if he <pb n="162" />then accept not her
bounty, he has but himself to blame, if afterward he find himself in want, in
beggary. <milestone id="p07090023" />Besides which, no such loyalty is demanded between servants and their
masters as between friends and kinsfolk; rather 'tis for servants, so far as they may, to
behave towards their masters as their masters behave towards them. <milestone id="p07090024" />Thinkest
thou, that, if thou hadst a fair wife or mother or daughter or sister that found favour in
Nicostratus' eyes, he would be so scrupulous on the point of loyalty as thou art disposed
to be in regard of his lady?  <milestone id="p07090025" />Thou art a fool, if so thou dost believe. Hold it
for certain, that, if blandishments and supplications did not suffice, he would, whatever
thou mightest think of it, have recourse to force. <milestone id="p07090026" />Observe we, then, towards
them and theirs the same rule which they observe towards us and ours. Take the boon that
Fortune offers thee; repulse her not; rather go thou to meet her, and hail her advance;
for be sure that, if thou do not so, to say nought of thy lady's death, which will
certainly ensue, thou thyself wilt repent thee thereof so often that
thou wilt be fain of death.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07090027" />Since he had last seen Lusca, Pyrrhus had
repeatedly pondered what she had said to him, and had made his mind up that, should she
come again, he would answer her in another sort, and comply in all respects with the
lady's desires, provided he might be assured that she was not merely putting him to the
proof; <milestone id="p07090028" />wherefore he now made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now, Lusca, I acknowledge the truth
of all that thou
sayst; but, on the other hand, I know that my lord is not a little wise and wary, and, as
he has committed all his affairs to my charge, I sorely misdoubt me that 'tis with his
approbation, and by his advice, and but to prove me, that Lydia does this:
<milestone id="p07090029" />wherefore let her do three things which I shall demand of her for my assurance,
and then there is nought that she shall crave of me, but I will certainly render her
prompt obedience. <milestone id="p07090030" />Which three things are these: first, let her in Nicostratus'
presence kill his fine sparrow-hawk: then she must send me a lock of Nicostratus' beard,
and lastly one of his best teeth.</q> <milestone id="p07090031" />Hard seemed these terms to Lusca, and
hard beyond measure to the lady, but Love, that great fautor of enterprise, and master of
stratagem, gave her resolution to address herself to their performance: wherefore through
the chambermaid she sent him word that what he required of her she would do, and that
without either reservation or delay; and therewithal she told him, that, as he deemed
Nicostratus so wise, she <pb n="163" />would contrive that they should enjoy one another in
Nicostratus' presence, and that Nicostratus should believe that 'twas a mere show.
<milestone id="p07090032" />Pyrrhus, therefore, anxiously expected what the lady would do. Some days thus
passed, and then Nicostratus gave a great breakfast, as was his frequent wont, to certain
gentlemen, and when the tables were removed, the lady, robed in green samite, and richly
adorned, came forth of her chamber into the hall wherein they sate, and before the eyes of
Pyrrhus and all the rest of the company hied her to the perch, on which stood the
sparrow-hawk that Nicostratus so much prized, and loosed him, and, as if she were minded
to carry him on her hand, took him by the jesses and dashed him against the wall so that
he died. <milestone id="p07090033" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! my lady, what hast thou done?</q> exclaimed
Nicostratus: but she vouchsafed no answer, save that,
turning to the gentlemen that had sate at meat with him, she said: <q direct="unspecified">My lords, ill fitted
were I to take vengeance on a king that had done me despite, if I lacked the courage to be
avenged on a sparrowhawk.  <milestone id="p07090034" />You are to know that by this bird I have long been
cheated of all the time that ought to be devoted by gentlemen to pleasuring their ladies;
for with the first streaks of dawn Nicostratus has been up and got him to horse, and hawk
on hand hied him to the champaign to see him fly, leaving me, such as you see me, alone
and ill content abed. <milestone id="p07090035" />For which cause I have oftentimes been minded to do that
which I have now done, and have only refrained therefrom, that, biding my time, I might do
it in the presence of men that should judge my cause justly, as I trust you will do.</q>
<milestone id="p07090036" />Which hearing, the gentlemen, who deemed her affections no less fixed on
Nicostratus than her words imported, broke with one accord into a laugh,
and turning to Nicostratus, who was sore displeased, fell a saying: <q direct="unspecified">Now well done of
the lady to avenge her wrongs by the death of the sparrow-hawk!</q> and so, the lady being
withdrawn to her chamber, they passed the affair off with divers pleasantries, turning the
wrath of Nicostratus to laughter.</p><p><milestone id="p07090037" />Pyrrhus, who had witnessed what had passed, said
to himself: Nobly indeed has my lady begun, and on such wise as promises well for the
felicity of my love. God grant that she so continue.  <milestone id="p07090038" />And even so Lydia did:
for not many days after she had killed the
sparrow-hawk, she, being with Nicostratus in her chamber, from caressing passed to toying
and trifling with him, and he, sportively <pb n="164" />pulling her by the hair, gave her
occasion to fulfil the second of
Pyrrhus' demands; which she did by nimbly laying hold of one of the lesser tufts of his
beard, and, laughing the while, plucking it so hard that she tore it out of his
chin. <milestone id="p07090039" />Which Nicostratus somewhat resenting: <q direct="unspecified">Now what cause hast thou,</q>
quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">to make such a wry face? 'Tis but that I have plucked some half-dozen hairs
from thy beard. Thou didst not feel it as much as did I but now thy tugging of my
hair.</q> <milestone id="p07090040" />And so they continued jesting and sporting with one another, the lady
jealously guarding the tuft that she had torn from the beard, which the very same day she
sent to her cherished lover. <milestone id="p07090041" />The third demand caused the lady more thought;
but, being amply endowed with wit, and powerfully seconded
by Love, she failed not to hit upon an apt expedient.</p><p><milestone id="p07090042" />Nicostratus had in his service two lads, who, being of gentle birth, had been placed
with him by their kinsfolk, that they might learn manners, one of whom, when Nicostratus
sate at meat, carved before him, while the other gave him to drink. Both lads Lydia called
to her, and gave them to understand that their breath smelt, and admonished them that,
when they waited on Nicostratus, they should hold their heads as far back as possible,
saying never a word of the matter to any. <milestone id="p07090043" />The lads believing her, did as she
bade them. Whereupon she took occasion to say to Nicostratus: <q direct="unspecified">Hast thou marked what
these lads do when they wait upon thee?</q> <milestone id="p07090044" /><q direct="unspecified">Troth, that have I,</q> replied
Nicostratus; <q direct="unspecified">indeed I have often had it in mind to ask them why they do so.</q>
<milestone id="p07090045" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> rejoined the lady, <q direct="unspecified">spare thyself the pains; for I can tell thee
the reason, which I have for some time kept close, lest it should vex thee; but as I now
see that others begin to be ware of it, it need no longer be withheld from
thee. <milestone id="p07090046" />'Tis for that thy breath stinks shrewdly that they thus avert their heads
from thee: 'twas not wont to be so, nor know I why it should be so; and 'tis most
offensive when thou art in converse with gentlemen; and therefore 'twould be well to find
some way of curing it.</q> <milestone id="p07090047" /><q direct="unspecified">I wonder what it could be,</q> returned
Nicostratus; <q direct="unspecified">is it perchance that I have a decayed tooth in my jaw?</q>
<milestone id="p07090048" /><q direct="unspecified">That may well be,</q> quoth Lydia: and taking him to a window, she caused
him open his mouth, and after regarding it on this side and that: <milestone id="p07090049" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!
Nicostratus,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">how couldst thou have endured it so long? Thou hast a tooth
here, <pb n="165" />which, by what I see, is not only decayed, but actually rotten
throughout; and beyond all manner of doubt, if thou let it remain long in thy head, 'twill
infect its neighbours; so 'tis my advice that thou out with it before the matter grows
worse.</q> <milestone id="p07090050" /><q direct="unspecified">My judgment jumps with thine,</q> quoth Nicostratus; <q direct="unspecified">wherefore
send without delay for a chirurgeon to draw it.</q> <milestone id="p07090051" /><q direct="unspecified">God forbid,</q> returned
the lady, <q direct="unspecified">that chirurgeon come hither for such a purpose; methinks, the case is such
that I can very well dispense with him, and draw the tooth myself. <milestone id="p07090052" />Besides
which, these chirurgeons do these things in such a cruel way, that I could never endure to
see thee or know thee under the hands of any of them: wherefore my mind is quite made up
to do it myself, that, at least, if thou shalt suffer too much, I may give it over at
once, as a chirurgeon would not do.</q> <milestone id="p07090053" />And so she caused the instruments that
are used on such occasions to be brought her, and having dismissed all other attendants
save Lusca from the chamber, and locked the door, made Nicostratus lie down on a table,
set the pincers in his mouth, and clapped them on one of his teeth, which, while Lusca
held him, so that, albeit he roared for pain, he might not move, she wrenched by main
force from his jaw, <milestone id="p07090054" />and keeping it close, took from Lusca's hand another and
horribly decayed tooth, which she shewed him, suffering and half dead as he was, saying:
<q direct="unspecified">See what thou hadst in thy jaw; mark how far gone it is.</q> <milestone id="p07090055" />Believing what
she said, and deeming that, now the tooth was out, his breath would no more be offensive,
and being somewhat eased of the pain, which had been extreme, and still remained, so that
he murmured not little, by divers comforting applications, he quitted the chamber:
<milestone id="p07090056" />whereupon the lady forthwith sent the tooth to her lover, who, having now full
assurance of her love, placed himself entirely at her service. <milestone id="p07090057" />But the lady
being
minded to make his assurance yet more sure, and deeming each hour a thousand till she
might be with him, now saw fit, for the more ready performance of the promise she had
given him, to feign sickness; and Nicostratus, coming to see her one day after breakfast,
attended only by Pyrrhus, she besought him for her better solacement, to help her down to
the garden. <milestone id="p07090058" />Wherefore Nicostratus on one side, and Pyrrhus on the other, took
her and bore her down to the garden, and set her on a lawn at the foot of a beautiful
pear-tree: and after they had sate there a while, the lady, who had already <pb n="166" />given Pyrrhus to understand what he must do, said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Pyrrhus, I should
greatly like to have some of those pears; get thee up the tree, and shake some of them
down.</q> <milestone id="p07090059" />Pyrrhus climbed the tree in a trice, and began to shake down the
pears, and while he did so: <q direct="unspecified">Fie! Sir,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what is this you do? And you,
Madam, have you no shame, that you suffer him to do so in my presence?  Think you that I
am blind? 'Twas but now that you were gravely indisposed.  Your cure has been speedy
indeed to permit of your so behaving: and as for such a purpose you have so many goodly
chambers, why betake you not yourselves to one of them, if you must needs so disport
yourselves?  'Twould be much more decent than to do so in my presence.</q>
<milestone id="p07090060" />Whereupon the lady, turning to her husband: <q direct="unspecified">Now what can Pyrrhus mean?</q>
said she. <q direct="unspecified">Is he mad?</q> <milestone id="p07090061" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, Madam,</q> quoth Pyrrhus; <q direct="unspecified">mad am not I.
Think you I see you not?</q> <milestone id="p07090062" />Whereat Nicostratus marvelled not a little; and:
<q direct="unspecified">Pyrrhus,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I verily believe thou dreamest.</q> <milestone id="p07090063" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, my
lord,</q> replied Pyrrhus, <q direct="unspecified">not a whit do I dream; neither do you; rather you wag it
with such vigour, that, if this pear-tree did the like, there would be never a pear left
on it.</q> <milestone id="p07090064" />Then the lady: <q direct="unspecified">What can this mean?</q> quoth she: <q direct="unspecified">can it be
that it really seems to him to be as he says? Upon my hope of salvation, were I but in my
former health, I would get me up there to judge for myself what these wonders are which he
professes to see.</q> <milestone id="p07090065" />Whereupon, as Pyrrhus in the pear-tree continued talking
in the same strange strain: <q direct="unspecified">Come down,</q> quoth Nicostratus;
and when he was down: <q direct="unspecified">Now what,</q> said Nicostratus, <q direct="unspecified">is it thou sayst thou seest up
there?</q> <milestone id="p07090066" /><q direct="unspecified">I suppose,</q> replied Pyrrhus, <q direct="unspecified">that you take me to be deluded
or dreaming: but as I must needs tell you the truth, I saw you lying upon your wife, and
then, when I came down, I saw you get up and sit you down here where you now are.</q>
<milestone id="p07090067" /><q direct="unspecified">Therein,</q> said Nicostratus, <q direct="unspecified">thou wast certainly deluded, for, since
thou clombest the pear-tree, we have not budged a jot, save as thou seest.</q>
<milestone id="p07090068" />Then said Pyrrhus: <q direct="unspecified">Why make more words about the matter? See you I certainly
did; and, seeing you, I saw you lying upon your own.</q> <milestone id="p07090069" />Nicostratus' wonder
now waxed momently, insomuch that he said: <q direct="unspecified">I am minded to see if this
pear-tree be enchanted, so that whoso is in it sees marvels;</q> and so he got him up into
it. Whereupon the lady and Pyrrhus fell <pb n="167" />to disporting them, and Nicostratus,
seeing what they were about, exclaimed: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! lewd woman, what is this thou doest? And
thou, Pyrrhus, in whom I so much trusted!</q> And so saying, he began to climb
down. <milestone id="p07090070" />Meanwhile the lady and Pyrrhus had made answer: <q direct="unspecified">We are sitting
here:</q> and seeing him descending, they placed themselves as they had been when he had
left them, whom Nicostratus, being come down, no sooner saw, than he fell a
rating them. <milestone id="p07090071" />Then quoth Pyrrhus: <q direct="unspecified">Verily, Nicostratus, I now acknowledge,
that, as you said a while ago, what I saw when I was in the pear-tree was but a false
show, albeit I had never understood that so it was but that I now see and know that thou
hast also seen a false show. <milestone id="p07090072" />And that I speak truth, you may sufficiently
assure yourself, if you but reflect whether 'tis likely that your wife, who for virtue and
discretion has not her peer among women, would, if she were minded so to dishonour you,
see fit to do so before your very eyes. Of myself I say nought, albeit I had liefer be
hewn in pieces than that I should so much as think of such a thing, much less do it in
your presence. <milestone id="p07090073" />Wherefore 'tis evident
that 'tis some illusion of sight that is propagated from the pear-tree;
for nought in the world would have made me believe that I saw not you lying there in
carnal intercourse with your wife, had I not heard you say that you saw me doing that
which most assuredly, so far from doing, I never so much as thought of.</q> <milestone id="p07090074" />The
lady then started up with a most resentful mien, and burst out with: <q direct="unspecified">Foul fall thee, if
thou knowest so little of me as to suppose that, if I were minded to do thee such foul
dishonour as thou sayst thou didst see me do, I would come hither to do it before thine
eyes! <milestone id="p07090075" />Rest assured that for such a purpose, were it ever mine, I should deem
one of our chambers more meet, and it should go hard but I would so order the matter that
thou shouldst never know aught of it.</q> <milestone id="p07090076" />Nicostratus, having heard both, and
deeming that what they both

averred must be true, to wit, that they would never have ventured upon such an act in his
presence, passed from chiding to talk of the

singularity of the thing, and how marvellous it was that the vision should reshape itself
for every one that clomb the tree. <milestone id="p07090077" />The lady, however, made a show of being
distressed that Nicostratus should so have thought of her, and: <q direct="unspecified">Verily,</q> quoth she,
<q direct="unspecified">no woman, neither I nor another, shall again suffer loss of honour by this <pb n="168" />pear-tree: <milestone id="p07090078" />run, Pyrrhus, and bring hither an axe, and at one and the
same time vindicate thy honour and mine by felling it, albeit 'twere better far
Nicostratus' skull should feel the weight of the axe, seeing that in utter heedlessness he
so readily suffered the eyes of his mind to be blinded; for, albeit this vision was seen
by the bodily eye, yet ought the understanding by no means to have entertained and
affirmed it as real.</q></p><p><milestone id="p07090079" />So Pyrrhus presently hied him to fetch the axe, and
returning therewith felled the pear; whereupon the lady, turning towards Nicostratus:
<q direct="unspecified">Now that this foe of my honour is fallen,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">my wrath is gone from
me.</q> Nicostratus then craving her pardon, she graciously granted it him, bidding him
never again to suffer himself to be betrayed into thinking such a thing of her, who loved
him more dearly than herself. <milestone id="p07090080" />So the poor duped husband went back with her and
her lover to the palace, where not seldom in time to come Pyrrhus and Lydia took their
pastime together more at ease. God grant us the like.</p></div2>