<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov0508"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05080001" /> Nastagio degli Onesti, loving a damsel of the Traversari
 family, by lavish expenditure gains not her love. At
 the instance of his kinsfolk he hies him to Chiassi,
 where he sees a knight hunt a damsel and slay her and
 cause her to be devoured by two dogs. He bids his
 kinsfolk and the lady that he loves to breakfast.
 During the meal the said damsel is torn in pieces
 before the eyes of the lady, who, fearing a like fate,
 takes Nastagio to husband.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05080002" /> Lauretta was no sooner silent than thus at the queen's behest
 began Filomena:</p></div3><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05080003" />Sweet ladies, as in us pity has ever its meed of
 praise, even so Divine justice suffers not our cruelty to escape severe
 chastisement: the which that I may shew you, and thereby dispose
 you utterly to banish that passion from your souls, I am minded to
 tell you a story no less touching than delightsome.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p05080004" />In Ravenna, that most ancient city of Romagna, there dwelt of yore
 noblemen and gentlemen not a few, among whom was a young man,
 Nastagio degli Onesti by name, who by the death of his father and one
 of his uncles inherited immense wealth.  <milestone id="p05080005" />Being without a wife, Nastagio,
 as 'tis the way with young men, became enamoured of a daughter
 of Messer Paolo Traversaro, a damsel of much higher birth than his,
 whose love he hoped to win by gifts and the like modes of courting,
 which,  <milestone id="p05080006" />albeit they were excellent and fair and commendable, not
 only availed him not, but seemed rather to have the contrary effect,
 so harsh and ruthless and unrelenting did the beloved damsel shew
 herself towards him; for whether it was her uncommon beauty or
 <pb n="50" />her noble lineage that puffed her up, so haughty and disdainful was
 she grown that pleasure she had none either in him or in aught that
 pleased him.  <milestone id="p05080007" />The burden of which disdain Nastagio found so hard
 to bear, that many a time, when he had made his moan, he longed to
 make away with himself. However he refrained therefrom, and
 many a time resolved to give her up altogether, or, if so he might, to
 hold her in despite, as she did him:  <milestone id="p05080008" />but 'twas all in vain, for it
 seemed as if, the more his hope dwindled, the greater grew his love.
  <milestone id="p05080009" />And, as thus he continued, loving and spending inordinately, certain
 of his kinsfolk and friends, being apprehensive lest he should waste
 both himself and his substance, did many a time counsel and beseech
 him to depart Ravenna, and go tarry for a time elsewhere, that so he
 might at once cool his flame and reduce his charges.  <milestone id="p05080010" />For a long
 while Nastagio answered their admonitions with banter; but as they
 continued to ply him with them, he grew weary of saying no so
 often, and promised obedience. Whereupon he equipped himself as
 if for a journey to France or Spain, or other distant parts, got on
 horseback and sallied forth of Ravenna, accompanied by not a few of
 his friends, and being come to a place called Chiassi, about three
 miles from Ravenna,  <milestone id="p05080011" />he halted, and having sent for tents and pavilions,
 told his companions that there he meant to stay, and they might go
 back to Ravenna.  <milestone id="p05080012" />So Nastagio pitched his camp, and there commenced
 to live after as fine and lordly a fashion as did ever any man,
 bidding divers of his friends from time to time to breakfast or sup
 with him, as he had been wont to do.  <milestone id="p05080013" />Now it so befell that about
 the beginning of May, the season being very fine, he fell a brooding
 on the cruelty of his mistress, and, that his meditations might be the
 less disturbed, he bade all his servants leave him, and sauntered slowly,
 wrapt in thought, as far as the pinewood.  <milestone id="p05080014" />Which he had threaded
 for a good half-mile, when, the fifth hour of the day being well-nigh
 past, yet he recking neither of food nor of aught else, 'twas as if he
 heard a woman wailing exceedingly and uttering most piercing
 shrieks: whereat, the train of his sweet melancholy being broken,
 he raised his head to see what was toward, and wondered to find himself
 in the pinewood;  <milestone id="p05080015" />and saw, moreover, before him running through
 a grove, close set with underwood and brambles, towards the place
 where he was, a damsel most comely, stark naked, her hair dishevelled,
 and her flesh all torn by the briers and brambles, who wept and cried
 <pb n="51" />piteously for mercy;  <milestone id="p05080016" />and at her flanks he saw two mastiffs, exceeding
 great and fierce, that ran hard upon her track, and not seldom
 came up with her and bit her cruelly; and in the rear he saw, riding
 a black horse, a knight sadly accoutred, and very wrathful of mien,
 carrying a rapier in his hand, and with despiteful, blood-curdling
 words threatening her with death.  <milestone id="p05080017" />Whereat he was at once amazed
 and appalled, and then filled with compassion for the hapless lady,
 whereof was bred a desire to deliver her, if so he might, from such
 anguish and peril of death.  <milestone id="p05080018" />Wherefore, as he was unarmed, he ran
 and took in lieu of a cudgel a branch of a tree, with which he prepared
 to encounter the dogs and the knight.  <milestone id="p05080019" />Which the knight observing,
 called to him before he was come to close quarters, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Hold
 off, Nastagio, leave the dogs and me alone to deal with this vile
 woman as she has deserved.</q>  <milestone id="p05080020" />And, even as he spoke, the dogs
 gripped the damsel so hard on either flank that they arrested her flight,
 and the knight, being come up, dismounted. Whom Nastagio
 approached, saying: <q direct="unspecified">I know not who thou art, that knowest me
 so well, but thus much I tell thee: 'tis a gross outrage for an armed
 knight to go about to kill a naked woman, and set his dogs upon her
 as if she were a wild beast: rest assured that I shall do all I can to
 protect her.</q>  <milestone id="p05080021" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Nastagio,</q> replied the knight, <q direct="unspecified">of
 the same city as thou was I, and thou wast yet a little lad when I,
 Messer Guido degli Anastagi by name, being far more enamoured of
 this damsel than thou art now of her of the Traversari, was by her
 haughtiness and cruelty brought to so woeful a pass that one day
 in a fit of despair I slew myself with this rapier which thou seest
 in my hand; for which cause I am condemned to the eternal
 pains.  <milestone id="p05080022" />Nor was it long after my death that she, who exulted
 therein over measure, also died, and for that she repented her
 not of her cruelty and the joy she had of my sufferings, for
 which she took not blame to herself, but merit, was likewise
 condemned to the pains of hell.  <milestone id="p05080023" />Nor had she sooner made her
 descent, than for her pain and mine 'twas ordained, that she should
 flee before me, and that I, who so loved her, should pursue her, not as
 my beloved lady, but as my mortal enemy,  <milestone id="p05080024" />and so, as often as I come
 up with her, I slay her with this same rapier with which I slew
 myself, and having ripped her up by the back, I take out that hard
 and cold heart, to which neither love nor pity had ever access, and
 <pb n="52" />therewith her other inward parts, as thou shalt forthwith see, and
 cast them to these dogs to eat.  <milestone id="p05080025" />And in no long time, as the just
 and mighty God decrees, she rises even as if she had not died, and
 recommences her dolorous flight, I and the dogs pursuing her.  <milestone id="p05080026" />And
 it so falls out that every Friday about this hour I here come up with
 her, and slaughter her as thou shalt see; but ween not that we rest
 on other days; for there are other places in which I overtake her,
 places in which she used, or devised how she might use, me cruelly;
 on which wise, changed as thou seest from her lover into her foe, I
 am to pursue her for years as many as the months during which she
 shewed herself harsh to me.  <milestone id="p05080027" />Wherefore leave me to execute the
 decree of the Divine justice, and presume not to oppose that which
 thou mayst not avail to withstand.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05080028" />Affrighted by the knight's words, insomuch that there was scarce
 a hair on his head but stood on end, Nastagio shrank back, still gazing
 on the hapless damsel, and waited all a tremble to see what the knight
 would do.  <milestone id="p05080029" />Nor had he long to wait; for the knight, as soon as he
 had done speaking, sprang, rapier in hand, like a mad dog upon the
 damsel, who, kneeling, while the two mastiffs gripped her tightly,
 cried him mercy; but the knight, thrusting with all his force, struck
 her between the breasts, and ran her clean through the body.  <milestone id="p05080030" />Thus
 stricken, the damsel fell forthwith prone on the ground sobbing and
 shrieking: whereupon the knight drew forth a knife, and having
 therewith opened her in the back, took out the heart and all the
 circumjacent parts, and threw them to the two mastiffs, who, being
 famished, forthwith devoured them. <milestone id="p05080031" />And in no long time the
 damsel, as if nought thereof had happened, started to her feet, and
 took to flight towards the sea, pursued, and ever and anon bitten, by
 the dogs, while the knight, having gotten him to horse again, followed
 them as before, rapier in hand; and so fast sped they that they were
 quickly lost to Nastagio's sight.</p><p><milestone id="p05080032" />Long time he stood musing on what he had seen, divided between
 pity and terror, and then it occurred to him that, as this passed
 every Friday, it might avail him not a little. So, having marked the
 place, he rejoined his servants, and in due time thereafter sent for
 some of his kinsfolk and friends, and said to them: <milestone id="p05080033" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis now a
 long while that you urge me to give up loving this lady that is no
 friend to me, and therewith make an end of my extravagant way of
 <pb n="53" />living; and I am now ready so to do, provided you procure me one
 favour, to wit, that next Friday Messer Paolo Traversaro, and his
 wife and daughter, and all the ladies, their kinswomen, and as many
 other ladies as you may be pleased to bid, come hither to breakfast
 with me:  <milestone id="p05080034" />when you will see for yourselves the reason why I so
 desire.</q>  <milestone id="p05080035" />A small matter this seemed to them; and so, on their
 return to Ravenna, they lost no time in conveying Nastagio's message
 to his intended guests: and, albeit she was hardly persuaded, yet in
 the end the damsel that Nastagio loved came with the rest.</p><p><milestone id="p05080036" />Nastagio caused a lordly breakfast to be prepared, and had the
 tables set under the pines about the place where he had witnessed
 the slaughter of the cruel lady; and in ranging the ladies and
 gentlemen at table he so ordered it, that the damsel whom he loved
 was placed opposite the spot where it should be enacted.  <milestone id="p05080037" />The last
 course was just served, when the despairing cries of the hunted
 damsel became audible to all, to their no small amazement; and
 each asking, and none knowing, what it might import, up they all
 started intent to see what was toward; and perceived the suffering
 damsel, and the knight and the dogs, who in a trice were in their
 midst.  <milestone id="p05080038" />They hollaed amain to dogs and knight, and not a few
 advanced to succour the damsel: but the words of the knight, which
 were such as he had used to Nastagio, caused them to fall back,
 terror-stricken and lost in amazement.  <milestone id="p05080039" />And when the knight proceeded
 to do as he had done before, all the ladies that were there,
 many of whom were of kin to the suffering damsel and to the knight,
 and called to mind his love and death, wept as bitterly as if 'twere
 their own case.</p><p><milestone id="p05080040" />When 'twas all over, and the lady and the knight had disappeared,
 the strange scene set those that witnessed it pondering many and
 divers matters: but among them all none was so appalled as the
 cruel damsel that Nastagio loved, who, having clearly seen and heard
 all that had passed, and being ware that it touched her more nearly
 than any other by reason of the harshness that she had ever shewn to
 Nastagio, seemed already to be fleeing from her angered lover, and
 to have the mastiffs on her flanks.  <milestone id="p05080041" />And so great was her terror that,
 lest a like fate should befall her, she converted her aversion into
 affection, and as soon as occasion served, which was that very night,
 sent a trusty chambermaid privily to Nastagio with a request that he
 <pb n="54" />would be pleased to come to her, for that she was ready in all respects
 to pleasure him to the full.  <milestone id="p05080042" />Nastagio made answer that he was
 greatly flattered, but that he was minded with her consent to have
 his pleasure of her in an honourable way, to wit, by marrying her.
  <milestone id="p05080043" />The damsel, who knew that none but herself was to blame that she
 was not already Nastagio's wife, made answer that she consented.
 Wherefore by her own mouth she acquainted her father and mother
 that she agreed to marry Nastagio; and, they heartily approving her
 choice,  <milestone id="p05080044" />Nastagio wedded her on the ensuing Sunday, and lived
 happily with her many a year. Nor was it in her instance alone that
 this terror was productive of good: on the contrary, it so wrought
 among the ladies of Ravenna that they all became, and have ever
 since been, much more compliant with men's desires than they had
 been wont to be.</p></div2>