<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov1007"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00070001" />King Pedro, being apprised of the fervent love borne him
 by Lisa, who thereof is sick, comforts her, and forthwith
 gives her in marriage to a young gentleman, and
 having kissed her on the brow, ever after professes
 himself her knight.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00070002" />When Fiammetta was come to the end of her story, and
 not a little praise had been accorded to the virile magnificence
 of King Charles, albeit one there was of the ladies, who, being a
 Ghibelline, joined not therein, Pampinea, having received the king's
 command, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00070003" />None is there of discernment, worshipful
 my ladies, that would say otherwise than you have said touching
 good King Charles, unless for some other cause she bear him a
 grudge; however, for that there comes to my mind the, perchance
 no less honourable, entreatment of one of our Florentine girls by one
 of his adversaries, I am minded to recount the same to you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00070004" />What time the French were driven forth of Sicily there dwelt
 at Palermo one of our Florentines, that was an apothecary, Bernardo
 Puccini by name, a man of great wealth, that by his lady had an
 only and exceeding fair daughter, then of marriageable age.  <milestone id="p00070005" />Now
 King Pedro of Arragon, being instated in the sovereignty of the
 island, did at Palermo make with his barons marvellous celebration
 thereof; during which, as he tilted after the Catalan fashion, it
 befell that Bernardo's daughter, Lisa by name, being with other
 ladies at a window, did thence espy him in the course, whereat being
 prodigiously delighted, she regarded him again and again, and grew
 fervently enamoured of him;  <milestone id="p00070006" />nor yet, when the festivities were
 ended, and she was at home with her father, was there aught she
 <pb n="347" />could think of but this her exalted and aspiring love. In regard
 whereof that which most irked her was her sense of her low rank,
 which scarce permitted her any hope of a happy issue; but, for all
 that, give over her love for the King she would not; nor yet, for
 fear of worse to come, dared she discover it.  <milestone id="p00070007" />The King, meanwhile,
 recking, witting nothing of the matter, her suffering waxed immeasurable,
 intolerable;  <milestone id="p00070008" />and her love ever growing with ever fresh
 accessions of melancholy, the fair maiden, overborne at last, fell sick,
 and visibly day by day wasted like snow in sunlight.  <milestone id="p00070009" />Distraught
 with grief thereat, her father and mother afforded her such succour
 as they might with words of good cheer, and counsel of physicians,
 and physic; but all to no purpose; for that she in despair of her
 love was resolved no more to live.</p><p><milestone id="p00070010" />Now her father assuring her that there was no whim of hers but
 should be gratified, the fancy took her that, if she might find apt
 means, she would, before she died, make her love and her resolve
 known to the King: wherefore one day she besought her father to
 cause Minuccio d'Arezzo to come to her;  <milestone id="p00070011" />which Minuccio was a
 singer and musician of those days, reputed most skilful, and well seen
 of King Pedro. Bernardo, deeming that Lisa desired but to hear
 him play and sing a while, conveyed her message to him; and he,
 being an agreeable fellow, came to her forthwith, and after giving her
 some words of loving cheer, sweetly discoursed some airs upon his
 viol, and then sang her some songs; whereby, while he thought to
 comfort her, he did but add fire and flame to her love.  <milestone id="p00070012" />Presently
 the girl said that she would fain say a few words to him in private,
 and when all else were withdrawn from the chamber: <q direct="unspecified">Minuccio,</q>
 quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">thee have I chosen, deeming thee most trusty, to be the
 keeper of my secret, relying upon thee in the first place never to
 betray it to a soul, and next to lend me in regard thereof such aid as
 thou mayst be able; and so I pray thee to do.  <milestone id="p00070013" />Thou must know,
 then, Minuccio mine, that on the day when our lord King Pedro
 held the great festival in celebration of his triumph, I, seeing him
 tilt, was so smitten with love of him that thereof was kindled within
 my soul the fire which has brought me, as thou seest, to this pass;
 and knowing how ill it beseems me to love a king, and being unable,
 I say not to banish it from my heart, but so much as to bring it
 within bounds, and finding it exceeding grievous to bear, I have
 <pb n="348" />made choice of death as the lesser pain; and die I shall.  <milestone id="p00070014" />But should
 he wot not of my love before I die, sore disconsolate should I depart;
 and knowing not by whom more aptly than by thee I might give
 him to know this my frame, I am minded to entrust the communication
 thereof to thee; which office I entreat thee not to refuse, and
 having discharged it, to let me know, that dying thus consoled, I may
 depart this pain.</q> Which said, she silently wept.</p><p><milestone id="p00070015" />Marvelling at the loftiness of the girl's spirit and her desperate
 determination, Minuccio commiserated her not a little; and presently
 it occurred to him that there was a way in which he might honourably
 serve her: wherefore:  <milestone id="p00070016" /><q direct="unspecified">Lisa,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">my faith I plight
 thee, wherein thou mayst place sure confidence that I shall never
 play thee false, and lauding thy high emprise, to wit, the setting thine
 affections upon so great a king, I proffer thee mine aid, whereby,
 so thou wilt be of good cheer, I hope, and believe, that, before thou
 shalt see the third day from now go by, I shall have brought thee
 tidings which will be to thee for an exceeding great joy; and, not
 to lose time, I will set to work at once.</q>  <milestone id="p00070017" />And so Lisa, assuring
 him that she would be of good cheer, and plying him afresh with
 instant obsecrations, bade him Godspeed;  <milestone id="p00070018" />and Minuccio, having
 taken leave of her, hied him to one Mico da Siena, a very expert
 rhymester of those days, who at his instant request made the ensuing
 song:</p><div3 type="song"><lg><milestone id="p00070019" /><l>Hence hie thee, Love; and hasting to my King,</l>
<l>Give him to know what torment dire I bear,</l>
<l>How that to death I fare,</l>
<l>Still close, for fear, my passion harbouring.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00070020" /><l>Lo, Love, to thee with clasp&#232;d hands I turn,</l>
<l>And pray thee seek him where he tarrieth,</l>
<l>And tell him how I oft for him do yearn,</l>
<l>So sweetly he my heart enamoureth;</l>
<l>And of the fire, wherewith I throughly burn,</l>
<l>I think to die, but may the hour uneath</l>
<l>Say, when my grievous pain shall with my breath</l>
<l>Surcease; till when, neither may fear nor shame</l>
<l>The least abate the flame.</l>
<l>Ah! to his ears my woeful story bring.</l></lg><pb n="349" /><lg><milestone id="p00070021" /><l>Since of him I was first enamour&#232;d,</l>
<l>Never hast thou, O Love, my fearful heart</l>
<l>With any such fond hope encourag&#232;d,</l>
<l>As e'er its message to him to impart,</l>
<l>To him, my lord, that me so sore bested</l>
<l>Holds: dying thus, 'twere grievous to depart:</l>
<l>Perchance, were he to know my cruel smart,</l>
<l>'Twould not displease him; might I but make bold</l>
<l>My soul to him to unfold,</l>
<l>And shew him all my woeful languishing.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p00070022" /><l>Love, since 'twas not thy will me to accord</l>
<l>Such boldness as that e'er unto my King</l>
<l>I may discover my sad heart's full hoard,</l>
<l>Or any word or sign thereof him bring:</l>
<l>This all my prayer to thee, O sweet my Lord:</l>
<l>Hie thee to him, and so him whispering</l>
<l>Mind of the day I saw him tourneying</l>
<l>With all his paladins environ&#232;d,</l>
<l>And grew enamour&#232;d</l>
<l>Ev'n to my very heart's disrupturing.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p00070023" />Which words Minuccio forthwith set to music after a soft and
 plaintive fashion befitting their sense; and on the third day thereafter
 hied him to court, while King Pedro was yet at breakfast.
 And being bidden by the King to sing something to the accompaniment
 of his viol,  <milestone id="p00070024" />he gave them this song with such sweet concord of
 words and music that all the folk that were in the King's hall seemed,
 as it were, entranced, so intent and absorbed stood they to listen,
 and the King rather more than the rest.  <milestone id="p00070025" />And when Minuccio had
 done singing, the King asked whence the song came, that, as far as
 he knew, he had never heard it before.  <milestone id="p00070026" /><q direct="unspecified">Sire,</q> replied Minuccio,
 <q direct="unspecified">'tis not yet three days since 'twas made, words and music alike.</q>
 And being asked by the King in regard of whom 'twas made:
 <q direct="unspecified">I dare not,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">discover such a secret save to you
 alone.</q>
  <milestone id="p00070027" />Bent on hearing the story, the King, when the tables were cleared,
 took Minuccio into his privy chamber; and there Minuccio told
 him everything exactly as he had heard it from Lisa's lips. Whereby
 the King was much gratified, and lauded the maiden not a little, and
 <pb n="350" />said that a girl of such high spirit merited considerate treatment, and
 bade Minuccio be his envoy to her, and comfort her, and tell her
 that without fail that very day at vespers he would come to visit her.
  <milestone id="p00070028" />Overjoyed to bear the girl such gladsome tidings, Minuccio tarried
 not, but hied him back to the girl with his viol, and being closeted
 with her, told her all that had passed, and then sang the song to the
 accompaniment of his viol.  <milestone id="p00070029" />Whereby the girl was so cheered and
 delighted that forthwith there appeared most marked and manifest
 signs of the amendment of her health, while with passionate longing
 (albeit none in the house knew or divined it) she awaited the vesper
 hour, when she was to see her lord.</p><p><milestone id="p00070030" />Knowing the girl very well, and how fair she was, and pondering
 divers times on what Minuccio had told him, the King, being a prince
 of a liberal and kindly disposition, grew ever more compassionate.
 So, about vespers, he mounted his horse, and rode forth, as if for
 mere pleasure, and being come to the apothecary's house, demanded
 access to a very goodly garden that the apothecary had, and having
 dismounted, after a while enquired of Bernardo touching his
 daughter, and whether he had yet bestowed her in marriage.  <milestone id="p00070031" /><q direct="unspecified">Sire,</q>
 replied Bernardo, <q direct="unspecified">she is not yet married; and indeed she has been
 and still is very ill: howbeit since none she is wonderfully amended.</q>
  <milestone id="p00070032" />The significance of which amendment being forthwith apprehended
 by the King: <q direct="unspecified">In good faith,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'twere a pity so fair
 a creature were reft from the world so early; we would go in and
 visit her.</q>  <milestone id="p00070033" />And presently, attended only by two of his lords and
 Bernardo, he betook him to her chamber, where being entered,
 he drew nigh the bed, whereon the girl half reclined, half sate in
 eager expectation of his coming; and taking her by the hand:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madonna,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what means this? A maiden like you
 should be the comfort of others, and you suffer yourself to languish.
 We would entreat you that for love of us you be of good cheer, so
 as speedily to recover your health.</q>  <milestone id="p00070034" />To feel the touch of his hand
 whom she loved above all else, the girl, albeit somewhat shamefast,
 was so enraptured that 'twas as if she was in Paradise; and as soon
 as she was able: <q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> she said, <q direct="unspecified">'twas the endeavour, weak
 as I am, to sustain a most grievous burden that brought this sickness
 upon me; but 'twill not be long ere you will see me quit thereof,
 thanks to your courtesy.</q>  <milestone id="p00070035" />The hidden meaning of which words
 <pb n="351" />was apprehended only by the King, who momently made more
 account of the girl, and again and again inly cursed Fortune, that had
 decreed that she should be the daughter of such a man. And yet a
 while he tarried with her, and comforted her, and so took his leave.
  <milestone id="p00070036" />Which gracious behaviour of the King was not a little commended,
 and accounted a signal honour to the apothecary and his daughter.</p><p>The girl, glad at heart as was ever lady of her lover, mended
 with reviving hope, and in a few days recovered her health, and
 therewith more than all her wonted beauty.  <milestone id="p00070037" />Whereupon the King,
 having taken counsel with the Queen how to reward so great a love,
 got him one day to horse with a great company of his barons, and
 hied him to the apothecary's house; and being come into the garden,
 he sent for the apothecary and his daughter; and there, being joined
 by the Queen with not a few ladies, who received the girl into their
 company, they made such cheer as 'twas a wonder to see.  <milestone id="p00070038" />And
 after a while the King and Queen having called Lisa to them, quoth
 the King: <q direct="unspecified">Honourable damsel, by the great love that you have
 borne us we are moved greatly to honour you; and we trust that,
 for love of us, the honour that we design for you will be acceptable
 to you. Now 'tis thus we would honour you: to wit, that, seeing
 that you are of marriageable age, we would have you take for
 husband him that we shall give you; albeit 'tis none the less our
 purpose ever to call ourself your knight, demanding no other tribute
 of all your love but one sole kiss.</q>  <milestone id="p00070039" />Scarlet from brow to neck,
 the girl, making the King's pleasure her own, thus with a low
 voice replied: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, very sure am I that, should it come to
 be known that I was grown enamoured of you, most folk would hold
 me for a fool, deeming, perchance, that I was out of my mind, and
 witless alike of my own rank and yours;  <milestone id="p00070040" />but God, who alone reads
 the hearts of us mortals, knows that even then, when first I did
 affect you, I wist that you were the King, and I but the daughter of
 Bernardo the apothecary, and that to suffer my passion to soar so
 high did ill become me;  <milestone id="p00070041" />but, as you know far better than I, none
 loves of set and discreet purpose, but only according to the dictates
 of impulse and fancy; which law my forces, albeit not seldom
 opposed, being powerless to withstand, I loved and still love and
 shall ever love you.  <milestone id="p00070042" />But as no sooner knew I myself subjugated to
 your love, than I vowed to have ever no will but yours; therefore not
 <pb n="352" />only am I compliant to take right gladly him whom you shall be
 pleased to give me for husband, thereby conferring upon me great
 honour and dignity; but if you should bid me tarry in the fire,
 delighted were I to obey, so thereby I might pleasure you.  <milestone id="p00070043" />How
 far it beseems me to have you, my King, for my knight, you best
 know; and therefore I say nought thereof; nor will the kiss which
 you crave as your sole tribute of my love be granted you save by
 leave of my Lady the Queen.  <milestone id="p00070044" />Natheless, may you have of this
 great graciousness that you and my Lady the Queen have shewn
 me, and which I may not requite, abundant recompense in the blessing
 and favour of God;</q> and so she was silent.</p><p><milestone id="p00070045" />The Queen was mightily delighted with the girl's answer, and
 deemed her as discreet as the King had said. The King then sent
 for the girl's father and mother, and being assured that his intention
 had their approval, summoned to his presence a young man, Perdicone
 by name, that was of gentle birth, but in poor circumstances, and
 put certain rings into his hand, and (he nowise gainsaying) wedded
 him to Lisa.  <milestone id="p00070046" />Which done, besides jewels many and precious that
 he and the Queen gave the girl, he forthwith bestowed upon Perdicone
 two domains, right goodly and of ample revenues, to wit,
 Ceffal&#249; and Calatabellotta, saying: <q direct="unspecified">We give them to thee for thy
 wife's dowry; what we have in store for thee thou wilt learn hereafter.</q>
 Which said, he turned to the girl, and:  <milestone id="p00070047" /><q direct="unspecified">Now,</q> quoth
 he, <q direct="unspecified">we are minded to cull that fruit which is due to us of thy
 love;</q> and so, taking her head between both his hands, he kissed her
 brow.  <milestone id="p00070048" />Wherefore, great was the joy of Perdicone, and the father
 and mother of Lisa, and Lisa herself, and mighty the cheer they
 made, and gaily did they celebrate the nuptials. And, as many
 affirm, right well did the King keep his promise to the girl; for that
 ever, while he lived, he called himself her knight, nor went to any
 passage of arms bearing other device than that which he had
 from her.</p><p><milestone id="p00070049" />Now 'tis by doing after this sort that sovereigns win the hearts
 of their subjects, give others occasion of well-doing, and gain for
 themselves an imperishable renown. At which mark few or none in
 our times have bent the bow of their understanding, the more part
 of the princes having become but cruel tyrants.</p></div2>