<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0106"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p01060001" />A worthy man by an apt saying puts to shame the wicked
 hypocrisy of the religious.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01060002" />When all had commended the virtue of the Marchioness and the
 spirited reproof which she administered to the King of France,
 Emilia, who sate next to Fiammetta, obeyed the queen's behest, and
 with a good courage thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01060003" />My story is also of a reproof, but of one administered by a
 worthy man, who lived the secular life, to a greedy religious, by
      a jibe as merry as admirable.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p01060004" />Know then, dear ladies, that there
 was in our city, not long ago, a friar minor, an inquisitor in
 matters of heresy, who, albeit he strove might and main to pass
 himself off as a holy man and tenderly solicitous for the integrity
 of the Christian Faith, as they all do, yet he had as keen a
 scent for a full purse as for a deficiency of faith. <milestone id="p01060005" />Now it so
 chanced that his zeal was rewarded by the discovery of a good man
 far better furnished with money than with sense, who in an unguarded
 moment, not from defect of faith, but rather, perhaps, from
 excess of hilarity, being heated with wine, had happened to say to
 his boon companions, that he had a wine good enough for Christ
 Himself to drink. <milestone id="p01060006" />Which being reported to the inquisitor, he,
 knowing the man to be possessed of large estates and a well-lined
 purse, set to work in hot haste, <q direct="unspecified">cum gladiis et fustibus,</q> to bring
 all the rigour of the law to bear upon him, designing thereby not to
 lighten the load of his victim's misbelief, but to increase the weight of
 his own purse by the florins, which he might, as he did, receive from
 him. <milestone id="p01060007" />So he cited him to his presence, and asked him whether what
 was alleged against him were true. The good man answered in the
 affirmative, and told him how it had happened. 
<milestone id="p01060008" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said our
 <pb n="49" />most holy and devout inquisitor of St. John Goldenbeard,<note>The
 fiorino
 d'oro bore the effigy of St. John.</note> <q direct="unspecified">then hast
 thou made Christ a wine-bibber, and a lover of rare vintages, as if
 He were a sot, a toper and a tavern-haunter even as one of you. And
 thinkest thou now by a few words of apology to pass this off as a
 light matter? It is no such thing as thou supposest. Thou hast
 deserved the fire; and we should but do our duty, did we inflict it
 upon thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p01060009" />With these and the like words in plenty he upbraided
 him, bending on him meanwhile a countenance as stern as if
 Epicurus had stood before him denying the immortality of the soul.
 In short he so terrified him that the good man was fain to employ
 certain intermediaries to anoint his palms with a liberal allowance of
 St. John Goldenmouth's grease, an excellent remedy for the disease of
 avarice which spreads like a pestilence among the clergy, and notably
 among the friars minors, who dare not touch a coin, that he might
 deal gently with him. <milestone id="p01060010" />And great being the virtue of this ointment,
 albeit no mention is made thereof by Galen in any part of his
 Medicines, it had so gracious an effect that the threatened fire gave
 place to a cross, which he was to wear as if he were bound for the
 emprise over seas; and to make the ensign more handsome the
 inquisitor ordered that it should be yellow upon a black ground.
 <milestone id="p01060011" />Besides which, after pocketing the coin, he kept him dangling about
 him for some days, bidding him by way of penance hear mass every
 morning at Santa Croce, and afterwards wait upon him at the
 breakfast-hour, after which he was free to do as he pleased for the
 rest of the day. 
<milestone id="p01060012" />All which he most carefully observed; and so it
 fell out that one of these mornings there were chanted at the mass
 at which he assisted the following words of the Gospel: You shall
 receive an hundredfold and shall possess eternal life. With these
 words deeply graven in his memory, he presented himself, as he was
 bidden, before the inquisitor, where he sate taking his breakfast, and
 being asked whether he had heard mass that morning, 
<milestone id="p01060013" />he promptly answered: <q direct="unspecified">Yes, sir.</q> 
<milestone id="p01060014" />And being further asked: <q direct="unspecified">Heardest
 thou aught therein, as to which thou art in doubt, or hast thou any
 question to propound?</q> 
<milestone id="p01060015" />the good man responded: <q direct="unspecified">Nay indeed,
 doubt have I none of aught that I heard; but rather assured faith in
 the verity of all. One thing, however, I heard, which caused me to
 <pb n="50" />commiserate you and the rest of you friars very heartily, in regard
 of the evil plight in which you must find yourselves in the other
 world.</q> 
<milestone id="p01060016" /><q direct="unspecified">And what,</q> said the inquisitor, <q direct="unspecified">was the passage that so
 moved thee to commiserate us?</q> 
<milestone id="p01060017" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> rejoined the good man,
 <q direct="unspecified">it was that passage in the Gospel which says: You shall receive
 an hundredfold.</q> 
<milestone id="p01060018" /><q direct="unspecified">You heard aright,</q> said the inquisitor; <q direct="unspecified">but
 why did the passage so affect you?</q> 
<milestone id="p01060019" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> replied the good man,
 <q direct="unspecified">I will tell you. Since I have been in attendance here, I have seen
 a crowd of poor folk receive a daily dole, now of one, now of two,
 huge tureens of swill, being the refuse from your table, and that of
 the brothers of this convent; whereof if you are to receive an hundredfold
 in the other world, you will have so much that it will go hard
 but you are all drowned therein.</q> 
<milestone id="p01060020" />This raised a general laugh
 among those who sat at the inquisitor's table, whereat the inquisitor,
 feeling that their gluttony and hypocrisy had received a home-thrust,
 was very wroth, and, but that what he had already done had not
 escaped censure, would have instituted fresh proceedings against him
 in revenge for the pleasantry with which he had rebuked the baseness
 of himself and his brother friars; so in impotent wrath he bade
 him go about his business and shew himself there no more.</p></div2>