<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov0901"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09010001" />Madonna Francesca, having two lovers, the one Rinuccio,
 the other Alessandro, by name, and loving neither of
 them, induces the one to simulate a corpse in a tomb,
 and the other to enter the tomb to fetch him out:
 whereby, neither satisfying her demands, she artfully
 rids herself of both.</p></argument><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09010002" />Madam, since so it pleases you, well pleased am I that in this
 vast, this boundless field of discourse, which you, our Lady Bountiful,
 have furnished us withal, 'tis mine to run the first course; wherein
 if I do well, I doubt not that those, who shall follow me, will do
 not only well but better.  <milestone id="p09010003" />Such, sweet my ladies, has been the tenor
 of our discourse, that times not a few the might of Love, how great
 and singular it is, has been set forth; but yet I doubt the topic is not
 exhausted, nor would it be so, though we should continue to speak
 of nought else for the space of a full year.  <milestone id="p09010004" />And as Love not only
 leads lovers to debate with themselves whether they were not best to
 die, but also draws them into the houses of the dead in quest of the
 dead, I am minded in this regard to tell you a story, wherein you
 will not only discern the power of Love, but will also learn how the
 ready wit of a worthy lady enabled her to disembarrass herself of two
 lovers, whose love was displeasing to her.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09010005" />Know, then, that there dwelt aforetime in the city of Pistoia a
 most beauteous widow lady, of whom it so befell that two of our
 citizens, the one Rinuccio Palermini, the other Alessandro Chiarmontesi,
 by name, tarrying at Pistoia, for that they were banished
 from Florence, became, neither witting how it stood with the other,
 in the last degree enamoured.  <milestone id="p09010006" />Wherefore each used all his arts
 <pb n="266" />to win the love of Madonna Francesca de' Lazzari--such was the
 lady's name--and she, being thus continually plied with ambassages
 and entreaties on the part of both, and having indiscreetly lent ear
 to them from time to time, found it no easy matter discreetly to
 extricate herself, when she was minded to be rid of their pestering,
  <milestone id="p09010007" />until it occurred to her to adopt the following expedient, to wit,
 to require of each a service, such as, though not impracticable,
 she deemed none would actually perform, to the end that, they
 making default, she might have a decent and colourable pretext
 for refusing any longer to receive their ambassages. Which expedient
 was on this wise.  <milestone id="p09010008" />One day there died in Pistoia, and was
 buried in a tomb outside the church of the Friars Minors, a man,
 who, though his forbears had been gentlefolk, was reputed the very
 worst man, not in Pistoia only, but in all the world,  <milestone id="p09010009" />and therewithal
 he was of form and feature so preternaturally hideous that
 whoso knew him not could scarce see him for the first time without
 a shudder. Now, the lady pondering her design on the day of this
 man's death, it occurred to her that he might in a measure subserve
 its accomplishment:  <milestone id="p09010010" />wherefore she said to her maid: <q direct="unspecified">Thou
 knowest to what worry and annoyance I am daily put by the
 ambassages of these two Florentines, Rinuccio and Alessandro.
 Now I am not disposed to gratify either of them with my love, and
 therefore, to shake them off, I am minded, as they make such great
 protestations, to put them to the proof by requiring of each something
 which I am sure he will not perform, and thus to rid myself
 of their pestering:  <milestone id="p09010011" />so list what I mean to do. Thou knowest that
 this morning there was interred in the ground of the Friars Minors
 this Scannadio (such was the name of the bad man of whom we
 spoke but now) whose aspect, while he yet lived, appalled even the
 bravest among us.  <milestone id="p09010012" />Thou wilt therefore go privily to Alessandro,
 and say to him: 'Madonna Francesca sends thee word by me that
 the time is now come when thou mayst win that which thou hast
 so much desired, to wit, her love and joyance thereof, if thou be so
 minded, on the following terms.  <milestone id="p09010013" />For a reason, which thou shalt
 learn hereafter, one of her kinsmen is to bring home to her to-night
 the corpse of Scannadio, who was buried this morning; and she,
 standing in mortal dread of this dead man, would fain not see him;
  <milestone id="p09010014" />wherefore she prays thee to do her a great service, and be so good as
 <pb n="267" />to get thee this evening at the hour of first sleep to the tomb wherein
 Scannadio is buried, and go in, and having wrapped thyself in his
 grave-clothes, lie there, as thou wert Scannadio himself, until one
 come for thee, when thou must say never a word, but let him carry
 thee forth, and bear thee to Madonna Francesca's house, where she
 will give thee welcome, and let thee stay with her, until thou art
 minded to depart, and, for the rest, thou wilt leave it to her.'  <milestone id="p09010015" />And
 if he says that he will gladly do so, well and good; if not, then thou
 wilt tell him from me, never more to shew himself where I am,
 and, as he values his life, to have a care to send me no more ambassages.
  <milestone id="p09010016" />Which done, thou wilt go to Rinuccio Palermini, and
 wilt say to him: 'Madonna Francesca lets thee know that she is
 ready in all respects to comply with thy wishes, so thou wilt do her
 a great service, which is on this wise: to-night, about midnight,
 thou must go to the tomb wherein was this morning interred
 Scannadio, and saying never a word, whatever thou mayst hear
 or otherwise be ware of, bear him gently forth to Madonna
 Francesca's house,  <milestone id="p09010017" />where thou shalt learn wherefore she requires
 this of thee, and shalt have thy solace of her; and if thou art not
 minded to obey her in this, see that thou never more send her
 ambassage.'</q></p><p><milestone id="p09010018" />The maid did her mistress's errand, omitting nothing, to both
 the men, and received from each the same answer, to wit, that to
 pleasure the lady, he would adventure a journey to hell, to say
 nothing of entering a tomb. With which answer the maid returned
 to the lady, who waited to see if they would be such fools as to make
 it good.  <milestone id="p09010019" />Night came, and at the hour of first sleep Alessandro
 Chiarmontesi, stripped to his doublet, quitted his house, and bent his
 steps towards Scannadio's tomb, with intent there to take the dead
 man's place. As he walked, there came upon him a great fear,  <milestone id="p09010020" />and
 he fell a saying to himself: Ah! what a fool am I! Whither go
 I? How know I that her kinsmen, having detected my love, and
 surmising that which is not, have not put her upon requiring this of
 me, in order that they may slay me in the tomb? In which event I
 alone should be the loser, for nought would ever be heard of it, so
 that they would escape scot-free. Or how know I but that 'tis
 some machination of one of my ill-wishers, whom perchance she
 loves, and is therefore minded to abet?  <milestone id="p09010021" />And again quoth he to
 <pb n="268" />himself: But allowing that 'tis neither the one nor the other, and
 that her kinsmen are really to carry me to her house, I scarce believe
 that 'tis either that they would fain embrace Scannadio's corpse themselves,
 or let her do so: rather it must be that they have a mind to
 perpetrate some outrage upon it, for that, perchance, he once did
 them an evil turn.  <milestone id="p09010022" />She bids me say never a word, no matter what
 I may hear or be otherwise ware of. Suppose they were to pluck
 out my eyes, or my teeth, or cut off my hands, or treat me to some
 other horse-play of the like sort, how then? how could I keep
 quiet?  <milestone id="p09010023" />And if I open my mouth, they will either recognize me,
 and perchance do me a mischief, or, if they spare me, I shall have
 been at pains for nought, for they will not leave me with the lady,
 and she will say that I disobeyed her command, and I shall never
 have aught of her favours.</p><p><milestone id="p09010024" />As thus he communed with himself, he was on the point of
 turning back; but his overmastering love plied him with opposing
 arguments of such force that he kept on his way, and reached
 the tomb; which having opened, he entered, and after stripping
 Scannadio, and wrapping himself in the grave-clothes, closed it, and
 laid himself down in Scannadio's place. He then fell a thinking of the
 dead man, and his manner of life, and the things which he had heard
 tell of as happening by night, and in other less appalling places than
 the houses of the dead;  <milestone id="p09010025" />whereby all the hairs of his head stood on end,
 and he momently expected Scannadio to rise and cut his throat.
  <milestone id="p09010026" />However, the ardour of his love so fortified him that he overcame
 these and all other timorous apprehensions, and lay as if he were
 dead, awaiting what should betide him.</p><p><milestone id="p09010027" />Towards midnight Rinuccio, bent likewise upon fulfilling his
 lady's behest, sallied forth of his house, revolving as he went divers
 forebodings of possible contingencies, as that, having Scannadio's
 corpse upon his shoulders, he might fall into the hands of the Signory,
 and be condemned to the fire as a wizard, or that, should the affair
 get wind, it might embroil him with his kinsfolk, or the like, which
 gave him pause.  <milestone id="p09010028" />But then with a revulsion of feeling: Shall I,
 quoth he to himself, deny this lady, whom I so much have loved and
 love, the very first thing that she asks of me? And that too when
 I am thereby to win her favour? No, though 'twere as much as my
 life is worth, far be it from me to fail of keeping my word. So on
 <pb n="269" />he fared, and arrived at the tomb, which he had no difficulty in
 opening, and being entered, laid hold of  <milestone id="p09010029" />Alessandro, who, though
 in mortal fear, had given no sign of life, by the feet, and dragged
 him forth, and having hoisted him on to his shoulders, bent his steps
 towards the lady's house. And as he went, being none too careful
 of Alessandro, he swung him from time to time against one or other
 of the angles of certain benches that were by the wayside; and
 indeed the night was so dark and murky that he could not see where
 he was going.  <milestone id="p09010030" />And when he was all but on the threshold of the
 lady's house (she standing within at a window with her maid, to mark
 if Rinuccio would bring Alessandro, and being already provided with
 an excuse for sending them both away), it so befell that the patrol of
 the Signory, who were posted in the street in dead silence, being on
 the look-out for a certain bandit, hearing the tramp of Rinuccio's
 feet, suddenly shewed a light, the better to know what was toward,
 and whither to go, and advancing targes and lances,  <milestone id="p09010031" />cried out:
 <q direct="unspecified">Who goes there?</q> Whereupon Rinuccio, having little leisure
 for deliberation, let Alessandro fall, and took to flight as fast as his
 legs might carry him. Alessandro, albeit encumbered by the graveclothes,
 which were very long, also jumped up and made off.  <milestone id="p09010032" />By
 the light shewn by the patrol the lady had very plainly perceived
 Rinuccio, with Alessandro on his back, as also that Alessandro had
 the grave-clothes upon him; and much did she marvel at the daring
 of both, but, for all that, she laughed heartily to see Rinuccio drop
 Alessandro, and Alessandro run away.  <milestone id="p09010033" />Overjoyed at the turn the
 affair had taken, and praising God that He had rid her of their harass,
 she withdrew from the window, and betook her to her chamber,
 averring to her maid that for certain they must both be mightily in
 love with her, seeing that 'twas plain they had both done her
 bidding.</p><p><milestone id="p09010034" />Crestfallen and cursing his evil fortune, Rinuccio nevertheless
 went not home, but, as soon as the street was clear of the patrol,
 came back to the spot where he had dropped Alessandro, and stooped
 down and began feeling about, if haply he might find him, and so do
 his devoir to the lady; but, as he found him not, he supposed the
 patrol must have borne him thence, and so at last home he went; as
 did also Alessandro, knowing not what else to do, and deploring his
 mishap.  <milestone id="p09010035" />On the morrow, Scannadio's tomb being found open and
 <pb n="270" />empty, for Alessandro had thrown the corpse into the vault below,
 all Pistoia debated of the matter with no small diversity of opinion,
 the fools believing that Scannadio had been carried off by devils.
  <milestone id="p09010036" />Neither of the lovers, however, forbore to make suit to the lady for
 her favour and love, telling her what he had done, and what had happened,
 and praying her to have him excused that he had not perfectly
 carried out her instructions. But she, feigning to believe neither of
 them, disposed of each with the same curt answer, to wit, that, as he
 had not done her bidding, she would never do aught for him.</p></div2>