<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d04intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p04980002" />Dearest ladies, as well from what I heard in converse with the
 wise, as from matters that not seldom fell within my own observation
 and reading, I formed the opinion that the vehement and
 scorching blast of envy was apt to vent itself only upon lofty towers
      or the highest tree-tops: but therein I find that I misjudged; <milestone id="p04980003" />for,
 whereas I ever sought and studied how best to elude the buffetings
 of that furious hurricane, and to that end kept a course not merely
 on the plain, but, by preference, in the depth of the valley; as
 should be abundantly clear to whoso looks at these little stories,
 written as they are not only in the vulgar Florentine, and in prose,
 and without dedicatory flourish, but also in as homely and simple a
 style as may be; <milestone id="p04980004" />nevertheless all this has not stood me in such stead
 but that I have been shrewdly shaken, nay, all but uprooted by the
 blast, and altogether lacerated by the bite of this same envy.
 Whereby I may very well understand that 'tis true, what the sages
 aver, that only misery is exempt from envy in the present life.
 <milestone id="p04980005" />Know then, discreet my ladies, that some there are, who, reading
 these little stories, have alleged that I am too fond of you, and that
 'tis not a seemly thing that I should take so much pleasure in
 ministering to your gratification and solace; and some have found
 more fault with me for praising you as I do. <milestone id="p04980006" />Others, affecting to
 deliver a more considered judgment, have said that it ill befits my
 time of life to ensue such matters, to wit, the discoursing of women,
 or endeavouring to pleasure them. And not a few, feigning a mighty
 tender regard to my fame, aver that I should do more wisely to keep
 <pb n="259" />ever with the Muses on Parnassus, than to forgather with you in such
 vain dalliance. <milestone id="p04980007" />Those again there are, who, evincing less wisdom
 than despite, have told me that I should shew sounder sense if I
 bethought me how to get my daily bread, than, going after these idle
 toys, to nourish myself upon the wind; while certain others, in
 disparagement of my work, strive might and main to make it appear
 that the matters which I relate fell out otherwise than as I set them
 forth. <milestone id="p04980008" />Such then, noble ladies, are the blasts, such the sharp and
 cruel fangs, by which, while I champion your cause, I am assailed,
 harassed and well-nigh pierced through and through. <milestone id="p04980009" />Which
 censures I hear and mark, God knows, with equal mind: and,
 though to you belongs all my defence, yet I mean not to be niggard
 of my own powers, but rather, without dealing out to them the
 castigation they deserve, to give them such slight answer as may
 secure my ears some respite of their clamour; and that without
 delay; <milestone id="p04980010" />seeing that, if already, though I have not completed the
 third part of my work, they are not a few and very presumptuous, I
 deem it possible, that before I have reached the end, should they
 receive no check, they may have grown so numerous, that 'twould
 scarce tax their powers to sink me; and that your forces, great though
 they be, would not suffice to withstand them. <milestone id="p04980011" />However I am
 minded to answer none of them, until I have related in my behoof,
 not indeed an entire story, for I would not seem to foist my stories in
 among those of so honourable a company as that with which I have
 made you acquainted, but a part of one, that its very incompleteness
 may shew that it is not one of them: wherefore, addressing my
 assailants, I say: <milestone id="p04980012" />That in our city there was in old time a citizen
 named Filippo Balducci, a man of quite low origin, but of good
 substance and well versed and expert in matters belonging to his
 condition, who had a wife that he most dearly loved, as did she him,
 so that their life passed in peace and concord, nor there was aught
 they studied so much as how to please each other perfectly. <milestone id="p04980013" />Now it
 came to pass, as it does to every one, that the good lady departed this
 life, leaving Filippo nought of hers but an only son, that she had had
 by him, and who was then about two years old. <milestone id="p04980014" />His wife's death left
 Filippo as disconsolate as ever was any man for the loss of a loved
 one: and sorely missing the companionship that was most dear to
 him, he resolved to have done with the world, and devote himself
 <pb n="260" />and his little son to the service of God. <milestone id="p04980015" />Wherefore, having dedicated
 all his goods to charitable uses, he forthwith betook him to the summit
 of Monte Asinaio, where he installed himself with his son in a little
 cell, and living on alms, passed his days in fasting and prayer, being
 careful above all things to say nothing to the boy of any temporal
 matters, nor to let him see aught of the kind, lest they should
 distract his mind from his religious exercises, but discoursing with
 him continually of the glory of the life eternal and of God and the
 saints, and teaching him nought else but holy orisons: in which way
 of life he kept him not a few years, never suffering him to quit the
 cell or see aught but himself. <milestone id="p04980016" />From time to time the worthy man
 would go Florence, where divers of the faithful would afford him
 relief according to his needs, and so he would return to his cell.
 <milestone id="p04980017" />And thus it fell out that one day Filippo, now an aged man, being
 asked by the boy, who was about eighteen years old, whither he went,
 told him. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Father,</q> said the boy, <q direct="unspecified">you are now old,
 and scarce able to support fatigue; why take you me not with you
 for once to Florence, and give me to know devout friends of God
 and you, so that I, who am young and fitter for such exertion than
 you, may thereafter go to Florence for our supplies at your pleasure,
 and you remain here?</q></p><p><milestone id="p04980018" />The worthy man, bethinking him that his son was now grown
 up, and so habituated to the service of God as hardly to be seduced
 by the things of the world, said to himself: <q direct="unspecified">He says tell.</q> And
 so, as he must needs go to Florence, he took the boy with him.
 <milestone id="p04980019" />Where, seeing the palaces, the houses, the churches, and all matters
 else with which the city abounds, and of which he had no more
 recollection than if he had never seen them, the boy found all passing
 strange, and questioned his father of not a few of them, what they
 were and how they were named; <milestone id="p04980020" />his curiosity being no sooner
 satisfied in one particular than he plied his father with a further
 question. And so it befell that, while son and father were thus
 occupied in asking and answering questions, they encountered a bevy
 of damsels, fair and richly arrayed, being on their return from a
 wedding; whom the young man no sooner saw, than he asked his
 father what they might be. 
<milestone id="p04980021" /><q direct="unspecified">My son,</q> answered the father, <q direct="unspecified">fix
 thy gaze on the ground, regard them not at all, for naughty things
 are they.</q> 
<milestone id="p04980022" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> said the son, <q direct="unspecified">and what is their name?</q> 
<milestone id="p04980023" />The
 <pb n="261" />father, fearing to awaken some mischievous craving of concupiscence
 in the young man, would not denote them truly, to wit, as women,
 but said: <q direct="unspecified">They are called goslings.</q> 
<milestone id="p04980024" />Whereupon, wonderful
 to tell! the lad who had never before set eyes on any woman,
 thought no more of the palaces, the oxen, the horses, the asses,
 the money, or aught else that he had seen, but exclaimed:
 <q direct="unspecified">Prithee, father, let me have one of those goslings.</q> 
<milestone id="p04980025" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas,
 my son,</q> replied the father, <q direct="unspecified">speak not of them; they are
 naughty things.</q> 
<milestone id="p04980026" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> questioned the son; <q direct="unspecified">but are naughty
 things made like that?</q> 
<milestone id="p04980027" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay,</q> returned the father. 
<milestone id="p04980028" />Whereupon
 the son: <q direct="unspecified">I know not,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">what you say, nor why they
 should be naughty things: for my part I have as yet seen nought
 that seemed to me so fair and delectable. They are fairer than the
 painted angels that you have so often shewn me. Oh! if you love
 me, do but let us take one of these goslings up there, and I will see
 that she have whereon to bill.</q> 
<milestone id="p04980029" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> said the father, <q direct="unspecified">that will
 not I. Thou knowest not whereon they bill;</q> and straightway,
 being ware that nature was more potent than his art, he repented
 him that he had brought the boy to Florence.</p><p><milestone id="p04980030" />But enough of this story: 'tis time for me to cut it short, and
 return to those, for whose instruction 'tis told. They say then,
 some of these my censors, that I am too fond of you, young ladies,
 and am at too great pains to pleasure you. Now that I am fond of
 you, and am at pains to pleasure you, <milestone id="p04980031" />I do most frankly and fully
 confess; and I ask them whether, considering only all that it means
 to have had, and to have continually, before one's eyes your debonair
 demeanour, your bewitching beauty and exquisite grace, and therewithal
 your modest womanliness, not to speak of having known the
 amorous kisses, the caressing embraces, the voluptuous comminglings,
 whereof our intercourse with you, ladies most sweet, not seldom is
 productive, they do verily marvel that I am fond of you, seeing that
 one who was nurtured, reared, and brought up on a savage and solitary
 mountain, within the narrow circuit of a cell, without other companion
 than his father, had no sooner seen you than 'twas you alone
 that he desired, that he demanded, that he sought with ardour?
 <milestone id="p04980032" />Will they tear, will they lacerate me with their censures, if I,
 whose body Heaven fashioned all apt for love, whose soul from
 very boyhood was dedicate to you, am not insensible to the power
 <pb n="262" />of the light of your eyes, to the sweetness of your honeyed words,
 to the flame that is kindled by your gentle sighs, but am fond of you
 and sedulous to pleasure you; you, again I bid them remember,
 in whom a hermit, a rude, witless lad, liker to an animal than to a
 human being, found more to delight him than in aught else that he
 saw? Of a truth whoso taxes me thus must be one that, feeling,
 knowing nought of the pleasure and power of natural affection, loves
 you not, nor craves your love; and such an one I hold in light esteem.
 <milestone id="p04980033" />And as for those that go about to find ground of exception in my
 age, they do but shew that they ill understand that the leek, albeit
 its head is white, has a green tail. But jesting apart, thus I answer
 them, that never to the end of my life shall I deem it shameful to
 me to pleasure those to whom Guido Cavalcanti and Dante Alighieri
 in their old age, and Messer Cino da Pistoia in extreme old age,
 accounted it an honour and found it a delight to minister gratification.
 <milestone id="p04980034" />And but that 'twere a deviation from the use and wont of
 discourse, I would call history to my aid, and shew it to abound
 with stories of noble men of old time, who in their ripest age studied
 above all things else to pleasure the ladies; whereof if they be
 ignorant, go they and get them to school. <milestone id="p04980035" />To keep with the Muses
 on Parnassus is counsel I approve; but tarry with them always we
 cannot, nor they with us, nor is a man blameworthy, if, when he
 happen to part from them, he find his delight in those that resemble
 them. The Muses are ladies, and albeit ladies are not the peers of
 the Muses, yet they have their outward semblance; for which cause,
 if for no other, 'tis reasonable that I should be fond of them.
 Besides which, ladies have been to me the occasion of composing
 some thousand verses, but of never a verse that I made were the
 Muses the occasion. <milestone id="p04980036" />Howbeit 'twas with their aid, 'twas under their
 influence that I composed those thousand verses, and perchance they
 have sometimes visited me to encourage me in my present task, humble
 indeed though it be, doing honour and paying, as it were, tribute,
 to the likeness which the ladies have to them; wherefore, while I
 weave these stories, I stray not so far from Mount Parnassus and the
 Muses as not a few perchance suppose. <milestone id="p04980037" />But what shall we say to
 those, in whom my hunger excites such commiseration that they
 bid me get me bread? Verily I know not, save this: Suppose that
 in my need I were to beg bread of them, what would be their
 <pb n="263" />answer? I doubt not they would say: <q direct="unspecified">Go seek it among the
 fables.</q> 
<milestone id="p04980038" />And in sooth the poets have found more bread among their
 fables than many rich men among their treasures. And many that
 have gone after fables have crowned their days with splendour, while,
 on the other hand, not a few, in the endeavour to get them more
 bread than they needed, have perished miserably. But why waste
 more words on them? Let them send me packing, when I ask
 bread of them; not that, thank God, I have yet need of it, and
 should I ever come to be in need of it, I know, like the Apostle,
 how to abound and to be in want, and so am minded to be beholden
 to none but myself. <milestone id="p04980039" />As for those who say that these matters fell out
 otherwise than as I relate them, I should account it no small favour,
 if they would produce the originals, and should what I write not
 accord with them, I would acknowledge the justice of their censure,
 and study to amend my ways; but, until better evidence is forthcoming
 than their words, I shall adhere to my own opinion without
 seeking to deprive them of theirs, and give them tit for tat. <milestone id="p04980040" />And
 being minded that for this while this answer suffice, I say that with
 God and you, in whom I trust, most gentle ladies, to aid and protect
 me, and patience for my stay, I shall go forward with my work,
 turning my back on this tempest, however it may rage; for I see
 not that I can fare worse than the fine dust, which the blast of the
 whirlwind either leaves where it lies, or bears aloft, not seldom over
 the heads of men, over the crowns of kings, of emperors, and sometimes
 suffers to settle on the roofs of lofty palaces, and the summits
 of the tallest towers, whence if it fall, it cannot sink lower than the
 level from which it was raised. <milestone id="p04980041" />And if I ever devoted myself and
 all my powers to minister in any wise to your gratification, I am
 now minded more than ever so to do, because I know that there is
 nought that any can justly say in regard thereof, but that I, and
 others who love you, follow the promptings of nature, whose laws
 whoso would withstand, has need of powers pre-eminent, and, even
 so, will oft-times labour not merely in vain but to his own most
 grievous disadvantage. <milestone id="p04980042" />Such powers I own that I neither have, nor,
 to such end, desire to have; and had I them, I would rather leave
 them to another than use them myself. Wherefore let my detractors
 hold their peace, and if they cannot get heat, why, let them shiver
 their life away; and, while they remain addicted to their delights,
 <pb n="264" />or rather corrupt tastes, let them leave me to follow my own bent
 during the brief life that is accorded us. <milestone id="p04980043" />But this has been a long
 digression, fair ladies, and 'tis time to retrace our steps to the point
 where we deviated, and continue in the course on which we started.</p><p><milestone id="p04980044" />The sun had chased every star from the sky, and lifted the dank
 murk of night from the earth, when, Filostrato being risen, and
 having roused all his company, they hied them to the fair garden,
 and there fell to disporting themselves: the time for breakfast being
 come, they took it where they had supped on the preceding evening,
 <milestone id="p04980045" />and after they had slept they rose, when the sun was in his zenith,
 and seated themselves in their wonted manner by the beautiful
 fountain; where Fiammetta, being bidden by Filostrato to lead off
 the story-telling, awaited no second command, but debonairly thus
 began.</p></div2>