<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d01conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p01970001" />As the young ladies and the three young men finished their story-telling
      the sun was westering and the heat of the day in great
      measure abated. <milestone id="p01970002" />Which their queen observing, debonairly thus she
      spoke: <q direct="unspecified">Now, dear gossips, my day of sovereignty draws to a close,
	and nought remains for me to do but to give you a new queen, by
	<pb n="64" />whom on the morrow our common life may be ordered as she may
	deem best in a course of seemly pleasure; and though there seems to
	be still some interval between day and night, yet, as whoso does not
	in some degree anticipate the course of time, cannot well provide for
	the future; and in order that what the new queen shall decide to be
	meet for the morrow may be made ready beforehand, I decree that
	from this time forth the days begin at this hour. <milestone id="p01970003" />And so in reverent
	submission to Him, in whom is the life of all beings, for our comfort
	and solace we commit the governance of our realm for the morrow
	into the hands of Queen Filomena, most discreet of damsels.</q> 
      <milestone id="p01970004" />So saying she arose, took the laurel wreath from her brow, and with a
      gesture of reverence set it on the brow of Filomena, whom she then,
      and after her all the other ladies and the young men, saluted as
      queen, doing her due and graceful homage.</p><p><milestone id="p01970005" />Queen Filomena modestly blushed a little to find herself thus
      invested with the sovereignty; but, being put on her mettle by
      Pampinea's recent admonitions, she was minded not to seem awkward,
      and soon recovered her composure. She then began by confirming
      all the appointments made by Pampinea, and making all needful
      arrangements for the following morning and evening, which they
      were to pass where they then were. Whereupon she thus spoke:
      <milestone id="p01970006" /><q direct="unspecified">Dearest gossips, though, thanks rather to Pampinea's courtesy than
	to merit of mine, I am made queen of you all; yet I am not on
	that account minded to have respect merely to my own judgment in
	the governance of our life, but to unite your wisdom with mine; and
	that you may understand what I think of doing, and by consequence
	may be able to amplify or curtail it at your pleasure, I will in few
	words make known to you my purpose. <milestone id="p01970007" />The course observed by
	Pampinea to-day, if I have judged aright, seems to be alike commendable
	and delectable; wherefore, until by lapse of time, or for some
	other cause, it grow tedious, I purpose not to alter it. 
	<milestone id="p01970008" />So when we
	have arranged for what we have already taken in hand, we will go
	hence and enjoy a short walk; at sundown we will sup in the cool;
	and we will then sing a few songs and otherwise divert ourselves,
	until it is time to go to sleep. <milestone id="p01970009" />To-morrow we will rise in the cool
	of the morning, and after enjoying another walk, each at his or her
	sweet will, we will return, as to-day, and in due time break our fast,
	dance, sleep, and having risen, will here resume our story-telling,
	<pb n="65" />wherein, methinks, pleasure and profit unite in superabundant
	measure. <milestone id="p01970010" />True it is that Pampinea, by reason of her late election to
	the sovereignty, neglected one matter, which I mean to introduce,
	to wit, the circumscription of the topic of our story-telling, and its
	preassignment, that each may be able to premeditate some apt story
	bearing upon the theme; and seeing that from the beginning of the
	world Fortune has made men the sport of divers accidents, and so it
	will continue until the end, the theme, so please you, shall in each
	case be the same; 
	<milestone id="p01970011" /><seg type="topic">to wit, the fortune of such as after divers adventures
	  have at last attained a goal of unexpected felicity.</seg></q></p><p><milestone id="p01970012" />The ladies and the young men alike commended the rule thus
      laid down, and agreed to follow it. Dioneo, however, when the rest
      had done speaking, said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, as all the rest have said, so say
	I, briefly, that the rule prescribed by you is commendable and delectable;
	but of your especial grace I crave a favour, which, I trust,
	may be granted and continued to me, so long as our company shall
	endure; which favour is this: that I be not bound by the assigned
	theme if I am not so minded, but that I have leave to choose such
	topic as best shall please me. <milestone id="p01970013" />And lest any suppose that I crave this
	grace as one that has not stories ready to hand, I am henceforth
	content that mine be always the last.</q> 
      <milestone id="p01970014" />The queen, knowing him to
      be a merry and facetious fellow, and feeling sure that he only craved
      this favour in order that, if the company were jaded, he might have
      an opportunity to recreate them by some amusing story, gladly, with
      the consent of the rest, granted his petition. 
      <milestone id="p01970015" />She then rose, and
      attended by the rest sauntered towards a stream, which, issuing clear
      as crystal from a neighbouring hill, precipitated itself into a valley
      shaded by trees close set amid living rock and fresh green herbage.
      Bare of foot and arm they entered the stream, and roving hither and
      thither amused themselves in divers ways till <milestone id="p01970016" />in due time they returned
      to the palace, and gaily supped. Supper ended, the queen sent for
      instruments of music, and bade Lauretta lead a dance, while Emilia
      was to sing a song accompanied by Dioneo on the lute.</p><p><milestone id="p01970017" />Accordingly Lauretta led a dance, while Emilia with passion
      sang the following song:</p><div3 who="emilia" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p01970018" />
	<l>So fain I am of my own loveliness,</l>
	<l>I hope, nor think not e'er</l>
	<l>The weight to feel of other amorousness.</l>
      </lg><pb n="66" /><lg><milestone id="p01970019" />
	<l>When in the mirror I my face behold,</l>
	<l>That see I there which doth my mind content,</l>
	<l>Nor any present hap or memory old</l>
	<l>May me deprive of such sweet ravishment.</l>
	<l>Where else, then, should I find such blandishment</l>
	<l>Of sight and sense that e'er</l>
	<l>My heart should know another amorousness?</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p01970020" />
	<l>Nor need I fear lest the fair thing retreat,</l>
	<l>When fain I am my solace to renew;</l>
	<l>Rather, I know, 'twill me advance to meet,</l>
	<l>To pleasure me, and shew so sweet a view</l>
	<l>That speech or thought of none its semblance true</l>
	<l>Paint or conceive may e'er,</l>
	<l>Unless he burn with ev'n such amorousness.</l>
      </lg><lg><milestone id="p01970021" />
	<l>Thereon as more intent I gaze, the fire</l>
	<l>Waxeth within me hourly more and more,</l>
	<l>Myself I yield thereto, myself entire,</l>
	<l>And foretaste have of what it hath in store,</l>
	<l>And hope of greater joyance than before,</l>
	<l>Nay, such as ne'er</l>
	<l>None knew; for ne'er was felt such amorousness.</l>
      </lg></div3><p><milestone id="p01970022" />This ballade, to which all heartily responded, albeit its words
      furnished much matter of thought to some, was followed by some
      other dances, and part of the brief night being thus spent, the queen
      proclaimed the first day ended, and bade light the torches, that all
      might go to rest until the following morning; and so, seeking their
      several chambers, to rest they went.</p></div2>