<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0208"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02080001" />The Count of Antwerp, labouring under a false accusation,
	goes into exile. He leaves his two children in
	different places in England, and takes service in
	Ireland. Returning to England an unknown man, he
	finds his sons prosperous. He serves as a groom in
	the army of the King of France; his innocence is
	established, and he is restored to his former honours.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02080002" />The ladies heaved many sighs over the various
	fortunes of the
	fair lady: but what prompted those sighs who shall say? With
	some, perchance, 'twas as much envy as pity of one to whose lot
	fell so many nights of delight. But, however this may be, when
	Pamfilo's story was ended, and the laughter which greeted his last
	words had subsided, the queen turned to Elisa, and bade her follow
	suit with one of her stories. So Elisa with a cheerful courage thus
	began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02080003" />Vast indeed is the field that lies before us, wherein to roam
	at large; 'twould readily afford each of us not one course but ten,
	so richly has Fortune diversified it with episodes both strange and
	sombre; wherefore selecting one such from this infinite store, I
	say:</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02080004" />That, after the transference of the Roman Empire from the
 Franks to the Germans, the greatest enmity prevailed between the
 two nations, with warfare perpetual and relentless: wherefore,
 deeming that the offensive would be their best defence, the King of
 France and his son mustered all the forces they could raise from
 their own dominions and those of their kinsmen and allies, and
 arrayed a grand army for the subjugation of their enemies. Before
 <pb n="138" />they took the field, as they could not leave the realm without a
 governor, they chose for that office Gautier, Count of Antwerp, a
 true knight and sage counsellor, and their very loyal ally and vassal,
 choosing him the rather, because, albeit he was a thorough master of
 the art of war, yet they deemed him less apt to support its hardships
 than for the conduct of affairs of a delicate nature. Him, therefore,
 they set in their place as their vicar-general and regent of the whole
 realm of France, and having so done, they took the field.</p><p><milestone id="p02080005" />Count Gautier ordered his administration wisely and in a regular
 course, discussing all matters with the queen and her daughter-in-law;
 whom, albeit they were left under his charge and jurisdiction,
 he nevertheless treated as his ladies paramount. <milestone id="p02080006" />The Count was
 about forty years of age, and the very mould of manly beauty; in
 bearing as courteous and chivalrous as ever a gentleman might be,
 and withal so debonair and dainty, so feat and trim of person that
 he had not his peer among the gallants of that day. <milestone id="p02080007" />His wife was
 dead, leaving him two children and no more, to wit, a boy and a
 girl, still quite young. Now the King and his son being thus away
 at the war, and the Count frequenting the court of the two said
 ladies, and consulting with them upon affairs of state, it so befell
 that the Prince's lady regarded him with no small favour, being very
 sensible alike of the advantages of his person and the nobility of his
 bearing; whereby she conceived for him a passion which was all the
 more ardent because it was secret. <milestone id="p02080008" />And, as he was without a wife,
 and she was still in the freshness of her youth, she saw not why she
 should not readily be gratified; but supposing that nothing stood in
 the way but her own shamefastness, she resolved to be rid of that,
 and disclose her mind to him without any reserve. <milestone id="p02080009" />So one day,
 when she was alone, she seized her opportunity, and sent for him, as
 if she were desirous to converse with him on indifferent topics. <milestone id="p02080010" />The
 Count, his mind entirely aloof from the lady's purpose, presented
 himself forthwith, and at her invitation sate down by her side on a
 settee. They were quite alone in the room; but the Count had
 twice asked her the reason why she had so honoured him, before,
 overcome by passion, she broke silence, and crimson from brow to
 neck with shame, half sobbing, trembling in every limb, and faltering
 at every word, she thus spoke: 
<milestone id="p02080011" /><q direct="unspecified">Dearest friend and sweet my lord,
 sagacity such as yours cannot but be apt to perceive how great is the
 <pb n="139" />frailty of men and women, and how, for divers reasons, it varies in
 different persons in such a degree that no just judge would mete
 out the same measure to each indifferently, though the fault were
 apparently the same. 
<milestone id="p02080012" />Who would not acknowledge that a poor man
 or woman, fain to earn daily bread by the sweat of the brow, is far
 more reprehensible in yielding to the solicitations of love, than a
 rich lady, whose life is lapped in ease and unrestricted luxury? 
<milestone id="p02080013" />Not
 a soul, I am persuaded, but would so acknowledge! Wherefore I
 deem that the possession of these boons of fortune should go far
 indeed to acquit the possessor, if she, perchance, indulge an errant
 love; and, for the rest, that, if she have chosen a wise and worthy
 lover, she should be entirely exonerated. 
<milestone id="p02080014" />And as I think I may
 fairly claim the benefit of both these pleas, and of others beside, to
 wit, my youth and my husband's absence, which naturally incline me
 to love, 'tis meet that I now urge them in your presence in defence
 of my passion; and if they have the weight with you which they
 should have with the wise, I pray you to afford me your help and
 counsel in the matter wherein I shall demand it. <milestone id="p02080015" />I avow that in the
 absence of my husband I have been unable to withstand the promptings
 of the flesh and the power of love, forces of such potency that
 even the strongest men--not to speak of delicate women--have not
 seldom been, nay daily are, overcome by them; and so, living thus,
 as you see me, in ease and luxury, I have allowed the allurements of
 love to draw me on until at last I find myself a prey to passion.
 <milestone id="p02080016" />Wherein were I discovered, I were, I confess, dishonoured; but
 discovery being avoided, I count the dishonour all but nought.
 Moreover, love has been so gracious to me that not only has he
 spared to blind me in the choice of my lover, but he has even lent me
 his most effective aid, pointing me to one well worthy of the love of
 a lady such as I, even to yourself; <milestone id="p02080017" />whom, if I misread not my
 mind, I deem the most handsome and courteous and debonair, and
 therewithal the sagest cavalier that the realm of France may shew.
 And as you are without a wife, so may I say that I find myself
 without a husband. <milestone id="p02080018" />Wherefore in return for this great love I bear
 you, deny me not, I pray you, yours; but have pity on my youth,
 which wastes away for you like ice before the fire.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02080019" />These words were followed by such a flood of tears, that, albeit
 she had intended yet further to press her suit, speech failed her; her
 <pb n="140" />eyes drooped, and, almost swooning with emotion, she let her head
 fall upon the Count's breast. <milestone id="p02080020" />The Count, who was the most loyal
 of knights, began with all severity to chide her mad passion and to
 thrust her from him--for she was now making as if she would throw
 her arms around his neck--and to asseverate with oaths that he
 would rather be hewn in pieces than either commit, or abet another
 in committing such an offence against the honour of his lord; 
<milestone id="p02080021" />when
 the lady, catching his drift, and forgetting all her love in a sudden
 frenzy of rage, cried out: <q direct="unspecified">So! unknightly knight, is it thus you
 flout my love? Now Heaven forbid, but, as you would be the death
 of me, I either do you to death or drive you from the world!</q> 
<milestone id="p02080022" />So
 saying, she dishevelled and tore her hair and rent her garments to
 shreds about her bosom. Which done, she began shrieking at the top
 of her voice: <q direct="unspecified">Help! help! The Count of Antwerp threatens to
 violate me!</q> 
<milestone id="p02080023" />Whereupon the Count, who knew that a clear conscience
 was no protection against the envy of courtiers, and doubted that
 his innocence would prove scarce a match for the cunning of the
 lady, started to his feet, and hied him with all speed out of the room,
 out of the palace, and back to his own house. Counsel of none he
 sought; but forthwith set his children on horseback, and taking
 horse himself, departed post haste for Calais. 
<milestone id="p02080024" />The lady's cries
 brought not a few to her aid, who, observing her plight, not only
 gave entire credence to her story, but improved upon it, alleging that
 the debonair and accomplished Count had long employed all the arts
 of seduction to compass his end. So they rushed in hot haste to the
 Count's house, with intent to arrest him, and not finding him, sacked
 it and razed it to the ground. 
<milestone id="p02080025" />The news, as glosed and garbled,
 being carried to the King and Prince in the field, they were mightily
 incensed, and offered a great reward for the Count, dead or alive, and
 condemned him and his posterity to perpetual banishment.</p><p><milestone id="p02080026" />Meanwhile the Count, sorely troubled that by his flight his
 innocence shewed as guilt, pursued his journey, and concealing his
 identity, and being recognised by none, arrived with his two children
 at Calais. Thence he forthwith crossed to England, and, meanly
 clad, fared on for London, taking care as he went to school his
 children in all that belonged to their new way of life, and especially
 in two main articles: to wit, that they should bear with resignation
 the poverty to which, by no fault of theirs, but solely by one of
 <pb n="141" />Fortune's caprices, they and he were reduced, and that they should
 be most sedulously on their guard to betray to none, as they valued
 their lives, whence they were, or who their father was. 
<milestone id="p02080027" />The son,
 Louis by name, was perhaps nine, and the daughter, Violante, perhaps
 seven years of age. For years so tender they proved apt pupils, and
 afterwards shewed by their conduct that they had well learned their
 father's lesson. <milestone id="p02080028" />He deemed it expedient to change their names, and
 accordingly called the boy Perrot and the girl Jeannette. So, meanly
 clad, the Count and his two children arrived at London, and there
 made shift to get a living by going about soliciting alms in the guise
 of French mendicants.</p><p><milestone id="p02080029" />Now, as for this purpose they waited one morning outside a
      church, it so befell that a great lady, the wife of one of the marshals
      of the King of England, observed them, as she left the church, asking
      alms, and demanded of the Count whence he was, and whether
      the children were his. <milestone id="p02080030" />He answered that he was from Picardy, that
      the children were his, and that he had been fain to leave Picardy by
      reason of the misconduct of their reprobate elder brother. 
      <milestone id="p02080031" />The lady
      looked at the girl, who being fair, and of gentle and winning mien
      and manners, found much favour in her eyes. So the kind-hearted
      lady said to the Count: <q direct="unspecified">My good man, if thou art willing to
	leave thy little daughter with me, I like her looks so well that I will
	gladly take her; and if she grow up a good woman, I will see that
	she is suitably married when the right time comes.</q> 
      <milestone id="p02080032" />The Count
      was much gratified by the proposal, which he forthwith accepted,
      and parted with the girl, charging the lady with tears to take every
      care of her.</p><p>Having thus placed the girl with one in whom he felt sure that he
 might trust, he determined to tarry no longer in London; wherefore,
 taking Perrot with him and begging as he went, he made his way
 to Wales, not without great suffering, being unused to go afoot.
 <milestone id="p02080033" />Now in Wales another of the King's marshals had his court, maintaining
 great state and a large number of retainers; to which court
 the Count and his son frequently repaired, there to get food; 
<milestone id="p02080034" />and
 there Perrot, finding the marshal's son and other gentlemen's sons
 vying with one another in boyish exercises, as running and leaping,
 little by little joined their company, and shewed himself a match or
 more for them all in all their contests. <milestone id="p02080035" />The marshal's attention
 <pb n="142" />being thus drawn to him, he was well pleased with the boy's mien
 and bearing, and asked who he was. He was told that he was the
 son of a poor man who sometimes came there to solicit alms.
 Whereupon he asked the Count to let him have the boy, and the
 Count, to whom God could have granted no greater boon, readily
 consented, albeit he was very loath to part with Perrot.</p><p><milestone id="p02080036" />Having thus provided for his son and daughter, the Count
 resolved to quit the island; and did so, making his way as best he
 could to Stamford, in Ireland, where he obtained a menial's place in
 the service of a knight, retainer to one of the earls of that country,
 and so abode there a long while, doing all the irksome and wearisome
 drudgery of a lackey or groom.</p><p><milestone id="p02080037" />Meanwhile under the care of the gentle lady at London Violante
 or Jeannette increased, as in years and stature so also in beauty, and
 in such favour with the lady and her husband and every other
 member of the household and all who knew her that 'twas a
 wonder to see; nor was there any that, observing her bearing and
 manners, would not have said that estate or dignity there was none so
 high or honourable but she was worthy of it. <milestone id="p02080038" />So the lady, who, since
 she had received her from her father, had been unable to learn aught
 else about him than what he had himself told, was minded to marry
 her honourably according to what she deemed to be her rank. 
<milestone id="p02080039" />But
 God, who justly apportions reward according to merit, having
 regard to her noble birth, her innocence, and the load of suffering
 which the sin of another had laid upon her, ordered otherwise; and
 in His good providence, lest the young gentlewoman should be mated
 with a churl, permitted, we must believe, events to take the course
 they did.</p><p><milestone id="p02080040" />The gentle lady with whom Jeannette lived had an only son,
 whom she and her husband loved most dearly, as well because he was
 a son as for his rare and noble qualities, for in truth there were few
 that could compare with him in courtesy and courage and personal
 beauty. <milestone id="p02080041" />Now the young man marked the extraordinary beauty and
 grace of Jeannette, who was about six years his junior, and fell so
 desperately in love with her that he had no eyes for any other maiden;
 but, deeming her to be of low degree, he not only hesitated to ask her
 of his parents in marriage, but, fearing to incur reproof for indulging
 a passion for an inferior, he did his utmost to conceal his love.
 <pb n="143" />Whereby it gave him far more disquietude than if he had avowed
 it; <milestone id="p02080042" />insomuch that--so extreme waxed his suffering--he fell ill, and
 that seriously. Divers physicians were called in, but, for all their
 scrutiny of his symptoms, they could not determine the nature of
 his malady, and one and all gave him up for lost. <milestone id="p02080043" />Nothing could
 exceed the sorrow and dejection of his father and mother, who again
 and again piteously implored him to discover to them the cause of his
 malady, and received no other answer than sighs or complaints that
 he seemed to be wasting away. <milestone id="p02080044" />Now it so happened that one day,
 Jeannette, who from regard for his mother was sedulous in waiting
 upon him, for some reason or another came into the room where he
 lay, while a very young but very skilful physician sate by him and
 held his pulse. <milestone id="p02080045" />The young man gave her not a word or other sign
 of recognition; but his passion waxed, his heart smote him, and the
 acceleration of his pulse at once betrayed his inward commotion to
 the physician, who, albeit surprised, remained quietly attentive to see
 how long it would last, <milestone id="p02080046" />and observing that it ceased when Jeannette
 left the room, conjectured that he was on the way to explain the
 young man's malady. So, after a while, still holding the young
 man's pulse, he sent for Jeannette, as if he had something to ask
 of her. She returned forthwith; the young man's pulse mounted
 as soon as she entered the room, and fell again as soon as she left
 it. <milestone id="p02080047" />Wherefore the physician no longer hesitated, but rose, and
 taking the young man's father and mother aside, said to them:
 <q direct="unspecified">The restoration of your son's health rests not with medical skill,
 but solely with Jeannette, whom, as by unmistakable signs I have
 discovered, he ardently loves, though, so far I can see, she is not
 aware of it. So you know what you have to do, if you value his
 life.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080048" />The prospect thus afforded of their son's deliverance from
 death reassured the gentleman and his lady, albeit they were troubled,
 misdoubting it must be by his marriage with Jeannette. <milestone id="p02080049" />So, when
 the physician was gone, they went to the sick lad, and the lady
 thus spoke: <q direct="unspecified">My son, never would I have believed that thou
 wouldst have concealed from me any desire of thine, least of all
 if such it were that privation should cause thee to languish; for
 well assured thou shouldst have been and shouldst be, that I hold
 thee dear as my very self, and that whatever may be for thy
 contentment, even though it were scarce seemly, I would do it
 <pb n="144" />for thee; 
<milestone id="p02080050" />but, for all thou hast so done, God has shewn Himself
 more merciful to theeward than thyself, and, lest thou die of this
 malady, has given me to know its cause, which is nothing else than
 the excessive love which thou bearest to a young woman, be she
 who she may. <milestone id="p02080051" />Which love in good sooth thou needest not have
 been ashamed to declare; for it is but natural at thy age; and
 hadst thou not loved, I should have deemed thee of very little
 worth. <milestone id="p02080052" />So, my son, be not shy of me, but frankly discover to me
 thy whole heart; and away with this gloom and melancholy
 whereof thy sickness is engendered, and be comforted, and assure
 thyself that there is nought that thou mayst require of me which
 I will not do to give thee ease, so far as my powers may reach,
 seeing that thou art dearer to me than my own life. <milestone id="p02080053" />Away with
 thy shamefastness and fears, and tell me if there is aught wherein
 I may be helpful to thee in the matter of thy love; and if I bestir
 not myself and bring it to pass, account me the most harsh mother
 that ever bore son.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02080054" />The young man was at first somewhat shamefast to hear his
 mother thus speak, but, reflecting that none could do more for his
 happiness than she, he took courage, and thus spoke: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,
 my sole reason for concealing my love from you was that I have
 observed that old people for the most part forget that they once were
 young; <milestone id="p02080055" />but, as I see that no such unreasonableness is to be apprehended
 in you, I not only acknowledge the truth of what you say
 that you have discerned, but I will also disclose to you the object of
 my passion, on the understanding that your promise shall to the best
 of your power be performed, as it must be, if I am to be restored to
 you in sound health.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080056" />Whereupon the lady, making too sure of that
 which was destined to fall out otherwise than she expected, gave him
 every encouragement to discover all his heart, and promised to lose
 no time and spare no pains in endeavouring to compass his gratification.
 <milestone id="p02080057" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> said then the young man, <q direct="unspecified">the rare beauty and
 exquisite manners of our Jeannette, my powerlessness to make her
 understand--I do not say commiserate--my love, and my reluctance
 to disclose it to any, have brought me to the condition in which you
 see me; and if your promise be not in one way or another performed,
 be sure that my life will be brief.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080058" />The lady, deeming that the
 occasion called rather for comfort than for admonition, replied with a
 <pb n="145" />smile: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! my son, was this then of all things the secret of thy
 suffering? Be of good cheer, and leave me to arrange the affair,
 when you are recovered.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080059" />So, animated by a cheerful hope, the
 young man speedily gave sign of a most marked improvement, which
 the lady observed with great satisfaction, and then began to cast about
 how she might keep her promise. So one day she sent for Jeannette,
 and in a tone of gentle raillery asked her if she had a lover.
 <milestone id="p02080060" />Jeannette turned very red as she answered: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, 'twould scarce,
 nay, 'twould ill become a damsel such as I, poor, outcast from home,
 and in the service of another, to occupy herself with thoughts of
 love.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080061" />Whereto the lady answered: <q direct="unspecified">So you have none, we will
 give you one, who will brighten all your life and give you more joy
 of your beauty; for it is not right that so fair a damsel as you remain
 without a lover.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080062" /><q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> rejoined Jeannette, <q direct="unspecified">you found me
 living in poverty with my father, you adopted me, you have brought
 me up as your daughter; wherefore I should, if possible, comply with
 your every wish; but in this matter I will render you no compliance,
 nor do I doubt that I do well. So you will give me a husband, I
 will love him, but no other will I love; for, as patrimony I now have
 none save my honour, that I am minded to guard and preserve while
 my life shall last.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080063" />Serious though the obstacle was which these
 words opposed to the plan by which the lady had intended to keep
 her promise to her son, her sound judgment could not but secretly
 acknowledge that the spirit which they evinced was much to be
 commended in the damsel. Wherefore she said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay but,
 Jeannette; suppose that our Lord the King, who is a young knight
 as thou art a most fair damsel, craved some indulgence of thy
 love, wouldst thou deny him?</q> 
<milestone id="p02080064" /><q direct="unspecified">The King,</q> returned Jeannette
 without the least hesitation, <q direct="unspecified">might constrain me, but with my
 consent he should never have aught of me that was not honourable.</q>
 <milestone id="p02080065" />Whereto the lady made no answer, for she now understood the girl's
 temper; but, being minded to put her to the proof, she told her son
 that, as soon as he was recovered, she would arrange that he should
 be closeted with her in the same room, and be thus able to use all his
 arts to bring her to his will, saying that it ill became her to play the
 part of procuress and urge her son's suit upon her own maid. 
<milestone id="p02080066" />But
 as the young man, by no means approving this idea, suddenly grew
 worse, the lady at length opened her mind to Jeannette, 
<milestone id="p02080067" />whom she
 <pb n="146" />found in the same frame as before, and indeed even more resolute.
 Wherefore she told her husband all that she had done; and as both
 preferred that their son should marry beneath him, and live, than that
 he should remain single and die, they resolved, albeit much disconcerted,
 to give Jeannette to him to wife; and so after long debate
 they did. <milestone id="p02080068" />Whereat Jeannette was overjoyed, and with devout heart
 gave thanks to God that He had not forgotten her; nevertheless she
 still gave no other account of herself than that she was the daughter
 of a Picard. So the young man recovered, and blithe at heart as
 ne'er another, was married, and began to speed the time gaily with
 his bride.</p><p><milestone id="p02080069" />Meanwhile Perrot, left in Wales with the marshal of the King
 of England, had likewise with increase of years increase of favour
 with his master, and grew up most shapely and well-favoured, and of
 such prowess that in all the island at tourney or joust or any other
 passage of arms he had not his peer; being everywhere known and
 renowned as Perrot the Picard. <milestone id="p02080070" />And as God had not forgotten
 Jeannette, so likewise He made manifest by what follows that He had
 not forgotten Perrot. Well-nigh half the population of those parts
 being swept off by a sudden visitation of deadly pestilence, most of the
 survivors fled therefrom in a panic, so that the country was, to all
 appearance, entirely deserted. <milestone id="p02080071" />Among those that died of the pest
 were the marshal, his lady, and his son, besides brothers and nephews
 and kinsfolk in great number; whereby of his entire household there
 were left only one of his daughters, now marriageable, and a few
 servants, among them Perrot. <milestone id="p02080072" />Now Perrot being a man of such
 notable prowess, the damsel, soon after the pestilence had spent
 itself, took him, with the approval and by the advice of the few folk
 that survived, to be her husband, and made him lord of all that fell
 to her by inheritance. <milestone id="p02080073" />Nor was it long before the King of England,
 learning that the marshal was dead, made Perrot the Picard, to whose
 merit he was no stranger, marshal in the dead man's room. Such,
 in brief, was the history of the two innocent children, with whom
 the Count of Antwerp had parted, never expecting to see them
 again.</p><p><milestone id="p02080074" />'Twas now the eighteenth year since the Count of Antwerp had
 taken flight from Paris, when, being still in Ireland, where he had
 led a very sorry and suffering sort of life, and feeling that age was
 <pb n="147" />now come upon him, he felt a longing to learn, if possible, what was
 become of his children. <milestone id="p02080075" />The fashion of his outward man was now
 completely changed; for long hardship had (as he well knew) given
 to his age a vigour which his youth, lapped in ease, had lacked. So
 he hesitated not to take his leave of the knight with whom he had
 so long resided, and poor and in sorry trim he crossed to England,
 and made his way to the place where he had left Perrot--to find him
 a great lord and marshal of the King, and in good health, and withal
 a hardy man and very handsome. All which was very grateful to
 the old man; but yet he would not make himself known to his son,
 until he had learned the fate of Jeannette. <milestone id="p02080076" />So forth he fared again,
 nor did he halt until he was come to London, where, cautiously
 questing about for news of the lady with whom he had left his
 daughter, and how it fared with her, he learned that Jeannette was
 married to the lady's son. Whereat, in the great gladness of his
 heart, he counted all his past adversity but a light matter, since
 he had found his children alive and prosperous. <milestone id="p02080077" />But sore he
 yearned to see Jeannette. Wherefore he took to loitering, as poor
 folk are wont, in the neighbourhood of the house. And so one
 day Jacques Lamiens--such was the name of Jeannette's husband--saw
 him and had pity on him, observing that he was poor and aged,
 and bade one of his servants take him indoors, and for God's sake
 give him something to eat; and nothing loath the servant did so.
 <milestone id="p02080078" />Now Jeannette had borne Jacques several children, the finest and the
 most winsome children in the world, the eldest no more than eight
 years old; who gathered about the Count as he ate, and, as if by
 instinct divining that he was their grandfather, began to make friends
 with him. <milestone id="p02080079" />He, knowing them for his grandchildren, could not
 conceal his love, and repaid them with caresses; insomuch that they
 would not hearken to their governor when he called them, but
 remained with the Count. Which being reported to Jeannette, she
 came out of her room, crossed to where the Count was sitting with
 the children, and bade them do as their master told them, or she
 would certainly have them whipped. <milestone id="p02080080" />The children began to cry,
 and to say that they would rather stay with the worthy man, whom
 they liked much better than their master; whereat both the lady and
 the Count laughed in sympathy. <milestone id="p02080081" />The Count had risen, with no
 other intention--for he was not minded to disclose his paternity--<pb n="148" />than
 to pay his daughter the respect due from his poverty to her
 rank, and the sight of her had thrilled his soul with a wondrous
 delight. By her he was and remained unrecognised; utterly
 changed as he was from his former self; aged, grey-haired, bearded,
 lean and tanned--in short to all appearance another man than the
 Count.</p><p><milestone id="p02080082" />However, seeing that the children were unwilling to leave him,
 but wept when she made as if she would constrain them, she bade
 the master let them be for a time. <milestone id="p02080083" />So the children remained with
 the worthy man, until by chance Jacques' father came home, and
 learned from the master what had happened. Whereupon, having a
 grudge against Jeannette, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Let them be; and God give
 them the ill luck which He owes them: whence they sprang, thither
 they must needs return; they descend from a vagabond on the
 mother's side, and so 'tis no wonder that they consort readily with
 vagabonds.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080084" />The Count caught these words and was sorely pained,
 but, shrugging his shoulders, bore the affront silently as he had borne
 many another. Jacques, who had noted his children's fondness for
 the worthy man, to wit, the Count, was displeased; but nevertheless,
 such was the love he bore them, that, rather than see them weep, he
 gave order that, if the worthy man cared to stay there in his service,
 he should be received. <milestone id="p02080085" />The Count answered that he would gladly
 do so, but that he was fit for nothing except to look after horses, to
 which he had been used all his life. So a horse was assigned him,
 and when he had groomed him, he occupied himself in playing with
 the children.</p><p><milestone id="p02080086" />While Fortune thus shaped the destinies of the Count of Antwerp
 and his children, it so befell that after a long series of truces
 made with the Germans the King of France died, and his crown
 passed to his son, whose wife had been the occasion of the Count's
 banishment. <milestone id="p02080087" />The new king, as soon as the last truce with the
 Germans was run out, renewed hostilities with extraordinary vigour,
 being aided by his brother of England with a large army under the
 command of his marshal, Perrot, and his other marshal's son,
 Jacques Lamiens. With them went the worthy man, that is to say,
 the Count, who, unrecognised by any, served for a long while in the
 army in the capacity of groom, and acquitted himself both in counsel
 and in arms with a wisdom and valour unwonted in one of his
 <pb n="149" />supposed rank. 
<milestone id="p02080088" />The war was still raging when the Queen of France
 fell seriously ill, and, as she felt her end approach, made a humble and
 contrite confession of all her sins to the Archbishop of Rouen, who
 was universally reputed a good and most holy man. Among her other
 sins she confessed the great wrong that she had done to the Count
 of Antwerp; <milestone id="p02080089" />nor was she satisfied to confide it to the Archbishop,
 but recounted the whole affair, as it had passed, to not a few other
 worthy men, whom she besought to use their influence with the
 King to procure the restitution of the Count, if he were still alive,
 and if not, of his children, to honour and estate. And so, dying
 shortly afterwards, she was honourably buried. 
<milestone id="p02080090" />The Queen's confession
 wrung from the King a sigh or two of compunction for a
 brave man cruelly wronged; after which he caused proclamation
 to be made throughout the army and in many other parts, that
 whoso should bring him tidings of the Count of Antwerp, or his
 children, should receive from him such a guerdon for each of them
 as should justly be matter of marvel; seeing that he held him
 acquitted, by confession of the Queen, of the crime for which he
 had been banished, and was therefore now minded to grant him not
 only restitution but increase of honour and estate.</p><p><milestone id="p02080091" />Now the Count, being still with the army in his character of
 groom, heard the proclamation, which he did not doubt was made
 in good faith. Wherefore he hied him forthwith to Jacques, and
 begged a private interview with him and Perrot, that he might discover
 to them that whereof the King was in quest. <milestone id="p02080092" />So the meeting
 was had; and Perrot was on the point of declaring himself, when
 the Count anticipated him: <q direct="unspecified">Perrot,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">Jacques here has
 thy sister to wife, but never a dowry had he with her. Wherefore
 that thy sister be not dowerless, 'tis my will that he, and no other,
 have this great reward which the King offers for thee, son, as he
 shall certify, of the Count of Antwerp, and for his wife and thy
 sister, Violante, and for me, Count of Antwerp, thy father.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080093" />So
 hearing, Perrot scanned the Count closely, and forthwith recognising
 him, burst into tears, and throwing himself at his feet embraced
 him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">My father, welcome, welcome indeed art thou.</q>
 <milestone id="p02080094" />Whereupon, between what he had heard from the Count and what
 he had witnessed on the part of Perrot, Jacques was so overcome
 with wonder and delight, that at first he was at a loss to know how
 <pb n="150" />to act. However, giving entire credence to what he had heard, and
 recalling insulting language which he had used towards the quondam
 groom, the Count, he was sore stricken with shame, and wept, and
 fell at the Count's feet, and humbly craved his pardon for all past
 offences; which the Count, raising him to his feet, most graciously
 granted him. <milestone id="p02080095" />So with many a tear and many a hearty laugh the
 three men compared their several fortunes; which done, Perrot and
 Jacques would have arrayed the Count in manner befitting his rank,
 but he would by no means suffer it, being minded that Jacques, so
 soon as he was well assured that the guerdon was forthcoming,
 should present him to the King in his garb of groom, that thereby
 the King might be the more shamed. <milestone id="p02080096" />So Jacques, with the Count
 and Perrot, went presently to the King and offered to present to him
 the Count and his children, provided the guerdon were forthcoming
 according to the proclamation. Jacques wondered not a little as
 forthwith at a word from the King a guerdon was produced ample
 for all three, and he was bidden take it away with him, so only that
 he should in very truth produce, as he had promised, the Count and
 his children in the royal presence. <milestone id="p02080097" />Then, withdrawing a little and
 causing his quondam groom, now Count, to come forward with
 Perrot, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Sire, father and son are before you; the daughter,
 my wife, is not here, but, God willing, you shall soon see her.</q> 
<milestone id="p02080098" />So
 hearing, the King surveyed the Count, whom, notwithstanding his
 greatly changed appearance, he at length recognised, and well-nigh
 moved to tears, he raised him from his knees to his feet, and kissed
 and embraced him. He also gave a kindly welcome to Perrot, and
 bade forthwith furnish the Count with apparel, servants and horses,
 suited to his rank; all which was no sooner said than done. 
<milestone id="p02080099" />Moreover
 the King shewed Jacques no little honour, and particularly
 questioned him of all his past adventures.</p><p><milestone id="p02080100" />As Jacques was about to take the noble guerdons assigned him for
 the discovery of the Count and his children, the Count said to
 him: <q direct="unspecified">Take these tokens of the magnificence of our Lord the
 King, and forget not to tell thy father that 'tis from no vagabond
 that thy children, his and my grandchildren, descend on the mother's
 side.</q> So Jacques took the guerdons, and sent for his wife and
 mother to join him at Paris. Thither also came Perrot's wife: and
 there with all magnificence they were entertained by the Count, to
 <pb n="151" />whom the King had not only restored all his former estates and
 honours, but added thereto others, whereby he was now become a
 greater man than he had ever been before. Then with the
 Count's leave they all returned to their several houses. The
 Count himself spent the rest of his days at Paris in greater glory
 than ever.</p></div2>