<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d01intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p01980002" />As often, most gracious ladies, as I bethink me, how compassionate
 you are by nature one and all, I do not disguise from
 myself that the present work must seem to you to have but a
 heavy and distressful prelude, in that it bears upon its very front
 what must needs revive the sorrowful memory of the late mortal
 pestilence, the course whereof was grievous not merely to eyewitnesses
 but to all who in any other wise had cognisance of it.
      <milestone id="p01980003" />But I would have you know, that you need not therefore be fearful
 to read further, as if your reading were ever to be accompanied
 by sighs and tears. <milestone id="p01980004" />This horrid beginning will be to you even
 such as to wayfarers is a steep and rugged mountain, beyond which
 stretches a plain most fair and delectable, which the toil of the ascent
 and descent does but serve to render more agreeable to them; <milestone id="p01980005" />for, as
 the last degree of joy brings with it sorrow, so misery has ever its
 sequel of happiness. <milestone id="p01980006" />To this brief exordium of woe--brief, I say,
 inasmuch as it can be put within the compass of a few letters--succeed
 forthwith the sweets and delights which I have promised you, and
 which, perhaps, had I not done so, were not to have been expected
 from it. <milestone id="p01980007" />In truth, had it been honestly possible to guide you whither
 I would bring you by a road less rough than this will be, I would
 gladly have so done. But, because without this review of the past, it
 would not be in my power to shew how the matters, of which you
 <pb n="5" />will hereafter read, came to pass, I am almost bound of necessity to
 enter upon it, if I would write of them at all.</p><p><milestone id="p01980008" />I say, then, that the years of the beatific incarnation of the Son
 of God had reached the tale of one thousand three hundred and
 forty-eight, when in the illustrious city of Florence, the fairest of all
 the cities of Italy, there made its appearance that deadly pestilence,
 which, whether disesminated by the influence of the celestial bodies,
 or sent upon us mortals by God in His just wrath by way of
 retribution for our iniquities, had had its origin some years before in
 the East, whence, after destroying an innumerable multitude of living
 beings, it had propagated itself without respite from place to place,
 and so, calamitously, had spread into the West.</p><p><milestone id="p01980009" />In Florence, despite all that human wisdom and forethought could
 devise to avert it, as the cleansing of the city from many impurities
 by officials appointed for the purpose, the refusal of entrance to all
 sick folk, and the adoption of many precautions for the preservation
 of health; despite also humble supplications addressed to God, and
 often repeated both in public procession and otherwise, by the devout;
 towards the beginning of the spring of the said year the doleful
 effects of the pestilence began to be horribly apparent by symptoms
 that shewed as if miraculous.</p><p><milestone id="p01980010" />Not such were they as in the East, where an issue of blood from
 the nose was a manifest sign of inevitable death; but in men and
 women alike it first betrayed itself by the emergence of certain
 tumours in the groin or the armpits, some of which grew as large as
 a common apple, others as an egg, some more, some less, which the
 common folk called gavoccioli. <milestone id="p01980011" />From the two said parts of the
 body this deadly gavocciolo soon began to propagate and spread itself
 in all directions indifferently; after which the form of the malady
 began to change, black spots or livid making their appearance in
 many cases on the arm or the thigh or elsewhere, now few and large,
 now minute and numerous. <milestone id="p01980012" />And as the gavocciolo had been and
 still was an infallible token of approaching death, such also were
 these spots on whomsoever they shewed themselves. <milestone id="p01980013" />Which maladies
 seemed to set entirely at naught both the art of the physician and
 the virtues of physic; indeed, whether it was that the disorder was
 of a nature to defy such treatment, or that the physicians were at
 fault--besides the qualified there was now a multitude both of men
 <pb n="6" />and of women who practised without having received the slightest
 tincture of medical science--and, being in ignorance of its source,
 failed to apply the proper remedies; in either case, not merely were
 those that recovered few, but almost all within three days from the
 appearance of the said symptoms, sooner or later, died, and in most
 cases without any fever or other attendant malady.</p><p><milestone id="p01980014" />Moreover, the virulence of the pest was the greater by reason that
 intercourse was apt to convey it from the sick to the whole, just as
 fire devours things dry or greasy when they are brought close to it.
 <milestone id="p01980015" />Nay, the evil went yet further, for not merely by speech or association
 with the sick was the malady communicated to the healthy with
 consequent peril of common death; but any that touched the clothes
 of the sick or aught else that had been touched or used by them,
 seemed thereby to contract the disease.</p><p><milestone id="p01980016" />So marvellous sounds that which I have now to relate, that, had
 not many, and I among them, observed it with their own eyes, I had
 hardly dared to credit it, much less to set it down in writing, though
 I had had it from the lips of a credible witness.</p><p><milestone id="p01980017" />I say, then, that such was the energy of the contagion of the said
 pestilence, that it was not merely propagated from man to man,
 but, what is much more startling, it was frequently observed, that
 things which had belonged to one sick or dead of the disease, if
 touched by some other living creature, not of the human species,
 were the occasion, not merely of sickening, but of an almost instantaneous
 death. <milestone id="p01980018" />Whereof my own eyes (as I said a little before) had
 cognisance, one day among others, by the following experience. The
 rags of a poor man who had died of the disease being strewn about
 the open street, two hogs came thither, and after, as is their wont,
 no little trifling with their snouts, took the rags between their
 teeth and tossed them to and fro about their chaps; whereupon,
 almost immediately, they gave a few turns, and fell down dead,
 as if by poison, upon the rags which in an evil hour they had
 disturbed.</p><p><milestone id="p01980019" />In which circumstances, not to speak of many others of a similar
 or even graver complexion, divers apprehensions and imaginations
 were engendered in the minds of such as were left alive, inclining
 almost all of them to the same harsh resolution, to wit, to shun and
 abhor all contact with the sick and all that belonged to them,
 <pb n="7" />thinking thereby to make each his own health secure. <milestone id="p01980020" />Among whom
 there were those who thought that to live temperately and avoid all
 excess would count for much as a preservative against seizures of this
 kind. Wherefore they banded together, and, dissociating themselves
 from all others, formed communities in houses where there were no
 sick, and lived a separate and secluded life, which they regulated with
 the utmost care, avoiding every kind of luxury, but eating and
 drinking very moderately of the most delicate viands and the finest
 wines, holding converse with none but one another, lest tidings of
 sickness or death should reach them, and diverting their minds with
 music and such other delights as they could devise. <milestone id="p01980021" />Others, the bias
 of whose minds was in the opposite direction, maintained, that to
 drink freely, frequent places of public resort, and take their pleasure
 with song and revel, sparing to satisfy no appetite, and to laugh and
 mock at no event, was the sovereign remedy for so great an evil: and
 that which they affirmed they also put in practice, so far as they were
 able, resorting day and night, now to this tavern, now to that, drinking
 with an entire disregard of rule or measure, and by preference making
 the houses of others, as it were, their inns, if they but saw in them
 aught that was particularly to their taste or liking; <milestone id="p01980022" />which they were
 readily able to do, because the owners, seeing death imminent, had
 become as reckless of their property as of their lives; so that most of
 the houses were open to all comers, and no distinction was observed
 between the stranger who presented himself and the rightful lord.
 Thus, adhering ever to their inhuman determination to shun the sick,
 as far as possible, they ordered their life. <milestone id="p01980023" />In this extremity of our
 city's suffering and tribulation the venerable authority of laws,
 human and divine, was abased and all but totally dissolved, for lack
 of those who should have administered and enforced them, most of
 whom, like the rest of the citizens, were either dead or sick, or so
 hard bested for servants that they were unable to execute any
 office; whereby every man was free to do what was right in his
 own eyes.</p><p><milestone id="p01980024" />Not a few there were who belonged to neither of the two said
 parties, but kept a middle course between them, neither laying the
 same restraint upon their diet as the former, nor allowing themselves
 the same license in drinking and other dissipations as the latter, but
 living with a degree of freedom sufficient to satisfy their appetites,
 <pb n="8" />and not as recluses. They therefore walked abroad, carrying in
 their hands flowers or fragrant herbs or divers sorts of spices, which
 they frequently raised to their noses, deeming it an excellent thing
 thus to comfort the brain with such perfumes, because the air seemed
 to be everywhere laden and reeking with the stench emitted by the
 dead and the dying, and the odours of drugs.</p><p><milestone id="p01980025" />Some again, the most sound, perhaps, in judgment, as they were
 also the most harsh in temper, of all, affirmed that there was no
 medicine for the disease superior or equal in efficacy to flight; following
 which prescription a multitude of men and women, negligent
 of all but themselves, deserted their city, their houses, their estates,
 their kinsfolk, their goods, and went into voluntary exile, or migrated
 to the country parts, as if God in visiting men with this pestilence in
 requital of their iniquities would not pursue them with His wrath
 wherever they might be, but intended the destruction of such alone
 as remained within the circuit of the walls of the city; or deeming,
 perchance, that it was now time for all to flee from it, and that its
 last hour was come.</p><p><milestone id="p01980026" />Of the adherents of these divers opinions not all died, neither did
 all escape; but rather there were, of each sort and in every place, many
 that sickened, and by those who retained their health were treated after
 the example which they themselves, while whole, had set, being everywhere
 left to languish in almost total neglect. <milestone id="p01980027" />Tedious were it to
 recount, how citizen avoided citizen, how among neighbours was
 scarce found any that shewed fellow-feeling for another, how kinsfolk
 held aloof, and never met, or but rarely; enough that this sore affliction
 entered so deep into the minds of men and women, that in the
 horror thereof brother was forsaken by brother, nephew by uncle,
 brother by sister, and oftentimes husband by wife; nay, what is more,
 and scarcely to be believed, fathers and mothers were found to abandon
 their own children, untended, unvisited, to their fate, as if they had
 been strangers. <milestone id="p01980028" />Wherefore the sick of both sexes, whose number
 could not be estimated, were left without resource but in the charity
 of friends (and few such there were), or the interest of servants, who
 were hardly to be had at high rates and on unseemly terms, and
 being, moreover, one and all, men and women of gross understanding,
 and for the most part unused to such offices, concerned themselves
 no further than to supply the immediate and expressed wants of the
 <pb n="9" />sick, and to watch them die; in which service they themselves not
 seldom perished with their gains. <milestone id="p01980029" />In consequence of which dearth
 of servants and dereliction of the sick by neighbours, kinsfolk and
 friends, it came to pass--a thing, perhaps, never before heard of--that
 no woman, however dainty, fair or well-born she might be,
 shrank, when stricken with the disease, from the ministrations of a
 man, no matter whether he were young or no, or scrupled to expose
 to him every part of her body, with no more shame than if he had
 been a woman, submitting of necessity to that which her malady
 required; wherefrom, perchance, there resulted in after time some
 loss of modesty in such as recovered. <milestone id="p01980030" />Besides which many succumbed,
 who with proper attendance, would, perhaps, have escaped
 death; so that, what with the virulence of the plague and the lack
 of due tendance of the sick, the multitude of the deaths, that daily
 and nightly took place in the city, was such that those who heard
 the tale--not to say witnessed the fact--were struck dumb with
      amazement. <milestone id="p01980031" />Whereby, practices contrary to the former habits of
 the citizens could hardly fail to grow up among the survivors.</p><p><milestone id="p01980032" />It had been, as to-day it still is, the custom for the women that
 were neighbours and of kin to the deceased to gather in his house
 with the women that were most closely connected with him, to
 wail with them in common, while on the other hand his male kinsfolk
 and neighbours, with not a few of the other citizens, and a due
 proportion of the clergy according to his quality, assembled without,
 in front of the house, to receive the corpse; and so the dead man
 was borne on the shoulders of his peers, with funeral pomp of taper
 and dirge, to the church selected by him before his death. <milestone id="p01980033" />Which
 rites, as the pestilence waxed in fury, were either in whole or in
 great part disused, and gave way to others of a novel order. <milestone id="p01980034" />For
 not only did no crowd of women surround the bed of the dying, but
 many passed from this life unregarded, and few indeed were they to
 whom were accorded the lamentations and bitter tears of sorrowing
 relations; nay, for the most part, their place was taken by the laugh,
 the jest, the festal gathering; observances which the women, domestic
 piety in large measure set aside, had adopted with very great
 advantage to their health. <milestone id="p01980035" />Few also there were whose bodies were
 attended to the church by more than ten or twelve of their neighbours,
 and those not the honourable and respected citizens; but a sort
 <pb n="10" />of corpse-carriers drawn from the baser ranks, who called themselves
 becchini<note>Probably from the name of the pronged or hooked implement
 with
 which they dragged the corpses out of the houses.</note> and performed such
 offices for hire, would shoulder the
 bier, and with hurried steps carry it, not to the church of the dead
 man's choice, but to that which was nearest at hand, with four or
 six priests in front and a candle or two, or, perhaps, none; nor did
 the priests distress themselves with too long and solemn an office,
 but with the aid of the becchini hastily consigned the corpse to the
 first tomb which they found untenanted. <milestone id="p01980036" />The condition of the
 lower, and, perhaps, in great measure of the middle ranks, of the
 people shewed even worse and more deplorable; for, deluded by
 hope or constrained by poverty, they stayed in their quarters, in their
 houses, where they sickened by thousands a day, and, being without
 service or help of any kind, were, so to speak, irredeemably devoted
 to the death which overtook them. <milestone id="p01980037" />Many died daily or nightly in
 the public streets; of many others, who died at home, the departure
 was hardly observed by their neighbours, until the stench of their
 putrefying bodies carried the tidings; and what with their corpses
 and the corpses of others who died on every hand the whole place
 was a sepulchre.</p><p><milestone id="p01980038" />It was the common practice of most of the neighbours, moved no
 less by fear of contamination by the putrefying bodies than by charity
 towards the deceased, <milestone id="p01980039" />to drag the corpses out of the houses with their
 own hands, aided, perhaps, by a porter, if a porter was to be had, and
 to lay them in front of the doors, where any one who made the
 round might have seen, especially in the morning, more of them than
 he could count; afterwards they would have biers brought up, or, in
 default, planks, whereon they laid them. Nor was it once or twice
 only that one and the same bier carried two or three corpses at once;
 but quite a considerable number of such cases occurred, one bier
 sufficing for husband and wife, two or three brothers, father and son,
 and so forth. <milestone id="p01980040" />And times without number it happened, that, as two
 priests, bearing the cross, were on their way to perform the last office
 for some one, three or four biers were brought up by the porters in
 rear of them, so that, whereas the priests supposed that they had
 but one corpse to bury, they discovered that there were six or
 eight, or sometimes more. <milestone id="p01980041" />Nor, for all their number, were their
 <pb n="11" />obsequies honoured by either tears or lights or crowds of mourners;
 rather, it was come to this, that a dead man was then of no more
 account than a dead goat would be to-day. From all which it is
 abundantly manifest, that that lesson of patient resignation, which
 the sages were never able to learn from the slight and infrequent
 mishaps which occur in the natural course of events, was now brought
 home even to the minds of the simple by the magnitude of their
 disasters, so that they became indifferent to them.</p><p><milestone id="p01980042" />As consecrated ground there was not in extent sufficient to
 provide tombs for the vast multitude of corpses which day and night,
 and almost every hour, were brought in eager haste to the churches
 for interment, least of all, if ancient custom were to be observed and
 a separate resting-place assigned to each, they dug, for each graveyard,
 as soon as it was full, a huge trench, in which they laid the
 corpses as they arrived by hundreds at a time, piling them up as
 merchandise is stowed in the hold of a ship, tier upon tier, each
 covered with a little earth, until the trench would hold no more.
 <milestone id="p01980043" />But I spare to rehearse with minute particularity each of the woes
 that came upon our city, and say in brief, that, harsh as was the
 tenor of her fortunes, the surrounding country knew no mitigation;
 for there--not to speak of the castles, each, as it were, a little city in
 itself--in sequestered village, or on the open champaign, by the wayside,
 on the farm, in the homestead, the poor hapless husbandmen
 and their families, forlorn of physicians' care or servants' tendance,
 perished day and night alike, not as men, but rather as beasts.
 <milestone id="p01980044" />Wherefore, they too, like the citizens, abandoned all rule of life, all
 habit of industry, all counsel of prudence; nay, one and all, as if
 expecting each day to be their last, not merely ceased to aid Nature
 to yield her fruit in due season of their beasts and their lands and
 their past labours, but left no means unused, which ingenuity could
 devise, to waste their accumulated store; <milestone id="p01980045" />denying shelter to their
 oxen, asses, sheep, goats, pigs, fowls, nay, even to their dogs, man's
 most faithful companions, and driving them out into the fields to
 roam at large amid the unsheaved, nay, unreaped corn. <milestone id="p01980046" />Many of
 which, as if endowed with reason, took their fill during the day, and
 returned home at night without any guidance of herdsman. <milestone id="p01980047" />But
 enough of the country! What need we add, but (reverting to the
 city) that such and so grievous was the harshness of heaven, and
 <pb n="12" />perhaps in some degree of man, that, what with the fury of the
 pestilence, the panic of those whom it spared, and their consequent
 neglect or desertion of not a few of the stricken in their need, it is
 believed without any manner of doubt, that between March and the
 ensuing July upwards of a hundred thousand human beings lost their
 lives within the walls of the city of Florence, which before the
 deadly visitation would not have been supposed to contain so many
 people! <milestone id="p01980048" />How many grand palaces, how many stately homes, how
 many splendid residences, once full of retainers, of lords, of ladies,
 were now left desolate of all, even to the meanest servant! How
 many families of historic fame, of vast ancestral domains, and wealth
 proverbial, found now no scion to continue the succession! How
 many brave men, how many fair ladies, how many gallant youths,
 whom any physician, were he Galen, Hippocrates, or &#198;sculapius
 himself, would have pronounced in the soundest of health, broke fast
 with their kinsfolk, comrades and friends in the morning, and when
 evening came, supped with their forefathers in the other world!</p><p><milestone id="p01980049" />Irksome it is to myself to rehearse in detail so sorrowful a history.
 Wherefore, being minded to pass over so much thereof as I fairly
 can, I say, that our city, being thus well-nigh depopulated, it so
 happened, as I afterwards learned from one worthy of credit, that
 on a Tuesday morning after Divine Service the venerable church of
 Santa Maria Novella was almost deserted save for the presence of
 seven young ladies habited sadly in keeping with the season. All
 were connected either by blood or at least as friends or neighbours;
 and fair and of good understanding were they all, as also of noble
 birth, gentle manners, and a modest sprightliness. In age none
 exceeded twenty-eight, or fell short of eighteen years. <milestone id="p01980050" />Their names
 I would set down in due form, had I not good reason to withhold
 them, being solicitous lest the matters which here ensue, as told
 and heard by them, should in after time be occasion of reproach to
 any of them, in view of the ample indulgence which was then, for the
 reasons heretofore set forth, accorded to the lighter hours of persons of
 much riper years than they, but which the manners of to-day have
 somewhat restricted; nor would I furnish material to detractors,
 ever ready to bestow their bite where praise is due, to cast by invidious
 speech the least slur upon the honour of these noble ladies. <milestone id="p01980051" />Wherefore,
 that what each says may be apprehended without confusion, I
 <pb n="13" />intend to give them names more or less appropriate to the character
 of each. The first, then, being the eldest of the seven, we will call
 Pampinea, the second Fiammetta, the third Filomena, the fourth
 Emilia, the fifth we will distinguish as Lauretta, the sixth as Neifile,
 and the last, not without reason, shall be named Elisa.</p><p><milestone id="p01980052" />'Twas not of set purpose but by mere chance that these ladies met
 in the same part of the church; but at length grouping themselves
 into a sort of circle, after heaving a few sighs, they gave up saying
 paternosters, and began to converse (among other topics) on the
 times.</p><p><milestone id="p01980053" />So they continued for a while, and then Pampinea, the rest listening
 in silent attention, thus began: <q direct="unspecified">Dear ladies mine, often have I
 heard it said, and you doubtless as well as I, that wrong is done to
 none by whoso but honestly uses his reason. And to fortify, preserve,
 and defend his life to the utmost of his power is the dictate of natural
 reason in every one that is born. Which right is accorded in such
 measure that in defence thereof men have been held blameless in
 taking life. <milestone id="p01980054" />And if this be allowed by the laws, albeit on their
 stringency depends the well-being of every mortal, how much more
 exempt from censure should we, and all other honest folk, be in
 taking such means as we may for the preservation of our life? <milestone id="p01980055" />As
 often as I bethink me how we have been occupied this morning, and
 not this morning only, and what has been the tenor of our conversation,
 I perceive--and you will readily do the like--that each of
 us is apprehensive on her own account; nor thereat do I marvel, but
 at this I do marvel greatly, that, though none of us lacks a woman's
 wit, yet none of us has recourse to any means to avert that which
 we all justly fear. <milestone id="p01980056" />Here we tarry, as if, methinks, for no other
 purpose than to bear witness to the number of the corpses that are
 brought hither for interment, or to hearken if the brothers there
 within, whose number is now almost reduced to nought, chant their
 offices at the canonical hours, or, by our weeds of woe, to obtrude on
 the attention of every one that enters, the nature and degree of our
 sufferings. <milestone id="p01980057" />And if we quit the church, we see dead or sick folk carried
 about,
 or we see those, who for their crimes were of late condemned to
 exile by the outraged majesty of the public laws, but who now, in
 contempt of those laws, well knowing that their ministers are a prey
 <pb n="14" />to death or disease, have returned, and traverse the city in packs,
 making it hideous with their riotous antics; or else we see the refuse
 of the people, fostered on our blood, becchini, as they call themselves,
 who for our torment go prancing about here and there and everywhere,
 making mock of our miseries in scurrilous songs. <milestone id="p01980058" />Nor hear
 we aught but: Such and such are dead; or, Such and such are
 dying; and should hear dolorous wailing on every hand, were there
 but any to wail. <milestone id="p01980059" />Or go we home, what see we there? I know not
 if you are in like case with me; but there, where once were servants
 in plenty, I find none left but my maid, and shudder with terror, and
 feel the very hairs of my head to stand on end; and turn or tarry
 where I may, I encounter the ghosts of the departed, not with their
 wonted mien, but with something horrible in their aspect that appals
 me. <milestone id="p01980060" />For which reasons church and street and home are alike distressful
 to me, and the more so that none, methinks, having means and place
 of retirement as we have, abides here save only we; <milestone id="p01980061" />or if any such
 there be, they are of those, as my senses too often have borne witness,
 who make no distinction between things honourable and their
 opposites, so they but answer the cravings of appetite, and, alone or
 in company, do daily and nightly what things soever give promise of
 most gratification. <milestone id="p01980062" />Nor are these secular persons alone; but such as
 live recluse in monasteries break their rule, and give themselves up
 to carnal pleasures, persuading themselves that they are permissible
 to them, and only forbidden to others, and, thereby thinking to
 escape, are become unchaste and dissolute. <milestone id="p01980063" />If such be our circumstances--and
 such most manifestly they are--what do we here?
 what wait we for? what dream we of? why are we less prompt to
 provide for our own safety than the rest of the citizens? Is life less
 dear to us than to all other women? or think we that the bond
 which unites soul and body is stronger in us than in others, so that
 there is no blow that may light upon it, of which we need be
 apprehensive? <milestone id="p01980064" />If so, we err, we are deceived. What insensate folly
 were it in us so to believe! We have but to call to mind the
 number and condition of those, young as we, and of both sexes, who
 have succumbed to this cruel pestilence, to find therein conclusive
 evidence to the contrary. <milestone id="p01980065" />And lest from lethargy or indolence we
 fall into the vain imagination that by some lucky accident we may
 in some way or another, when we would, escape--I know not if
 <pb n="15" />your opinion accord with mine--I should deem it most wise in us,
 our case being what it is, if, as many others have done before us, and
 are still doing, we were to quit this place, and, shunning like death
 the evil example of others, betake ourselves to the country, and there
 live as honourable women on one of the estates, of which none of us
 has any lack, with all cheer of festal gathering and other delights, so
 long as in no particular we overstep the bounds of reason. <milestone id="p01980066" />There we
 shall hear the chant of birds, have sight of verdant hills and plains, of
 cornfields undulating like the sea, of trees of a thousand sorts; there
 also we shall have a larger view of the heavens, which, however harsh
 to usward, yet deny not their eternal beauty; things fairer far for
 epe to rest on than the desolate walls of our city. <milestone id="p01980067" />Moreover, we
 shall there breathe a fresher air, find ampler store of things meet for
 such as live in these times, have fewer causes of annoy. <milestone id="p01980068" />For, though
 the husbandmen die there, even as here the citizens, they are
 dispersed in scattered homesteads, and 'tis thus less painful to witness.
 <milestone id="p01980069" />Nor, so far as I can see, is there a soul here whom we shall desert;
 rather we may truly say, that we are ourselves deserted; for, our
 kinsfolk being either dead or fled in fear of death, no more regardful
 of us than if we were strangers, we are left alone in our great
 affliction. <milestone id="p01980070" />No censure, then, can fall on us if we do as I propose;
 and otherwise grievous suffering, perhaps death, may ensue. <milestone id="p01980071" />Wherefore,
 if you agree, 'tis my advice, that, attended by our maids with al???
 things needful, we sojourn, now on this, now on the other estate,
 and in such way of life continue, until we see--if death should not
 first overtake us--the end which Heaven reserves for these events.
 <milestone id="p01980072" />And I remind you that it will be at least as seemly in us to leave
 with honour, as in others, of whom there are not a few, to stay with
 dishonour.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01980073" />The other ladies praised Pampinea's plan, and indeed were so
 prompt to follow it, that they had already begun to discuss the
 manner in some detail, as if they were forthwith to rise from their
 seats and take the road, <milestone id="p01980074" />when Filomena, whose judgment was
 excellent, interposed, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Ladies, though Pampinea has spoken
 to most excellent effect, yet it were not well to be so precipitate as
 you seem disposed to be. Bethink you that we are all women; nor
 is there any here so young, but she is of years to understand how
 women are minded towards one another, when they are alone
 <pb n="16" />together, and how ill they are able to rule themselves without the
 guidance of some man. <milestone id="p01980075" />We are sensitive, perverse, suspicious,
 pusillanimous and timid; wherefore I much misdoubt, that, if we
 find no other guidance than our own, this company is like to break
 up sooner, and with less credit to us, than it should. Against which
 it were well to provide at the outset.</q> <milestone id="p01980076" />Said then Elisa: 
      <q direct="unspecified">Without
 doubt man is woman's head, and, without man's governance, it is
 seldom that aught that we do is brought to a commendable conclusion.
 But how are we to come by the men? <milestone id="p01980077" />Every one of us
 here knows that her kinsmen are for the most part dead, and that the
 survivors are dispersed, one here, one there, we know not where, bent
 each on escaping the same fate as ourselves; nor were it seemly to
 seek the aid of strangers; for, as we are in quest of health, we must
 find some means so to order matters that, wherever we seek diversion
 or repose, trouble and scandal do not follow us.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01980078" />While the ladies were thus conversing, there came into the church
 three young men, young, I say, but not so young that the age of the
 youngest was less than twenty-five years; in whom neither the
 sinister course of events, nor the loss of friends or kinsfolk, nor fear
 for their own safety, had availed to quench, or even temper, the
 ardour of their love. <milestone id="p01980079" />The first was called Pamfilo, the second
 Filostrato, and the third Dioneo. Very debonair and chivalrous
 were they all; and in this troublous time they were seeking if haply,
 to their exceeding great solace, they might have sight of their fair
 friends, all three of whom chanced to be among the said seven ladies,
 besides some that were of kin to the young men. <milestone id="p01980080" />At one and the
 same moment they recognised the ladies and were recognised by
 them: wherefore, with a gracious smile, Pampinea thus began:
 <q direct="unspecified">Lo, fortune is propitious to our enterprise, having vouchsafed us the
 good offices of these young men, who are as gallant as they are
 discreet, and will gladly give us their guidance and escort, so we but
 take them into our service.</q> <milestone id="p01980081" />Whereupon Neifile, crimson from brow
 to neck with the blush of modesty, being one of those that had a
 lover among the young men, said: <milestone id="p01980082" /><q direct="unspecified">For God's sake, Pampinea,
 have a care what you say. Well assured am I that nought but good
 can be said of any of them, and I deem them fit for office far more
 onerous than this which you propose for them, and their good and
 honourable company worthy of ladies fairer by far and more tenderly
 <pb n="17" />to be cherished than such as we. <milestone id="p01980083" />But 'tis no secret that they love
 some of us here; wherefore I misdoubt that, if we take them with
 us, we may thereby give occasion for scandal and censure merited
 neither by us nor by them.</q> <milestone id="p01980084" /><q direct="unspecified">That,</q> said Filomena, <q direct="unspecified">is of no
 consequence;
 so I but live honestly, my conscience gives me no
 disquietude; if others asperse me, God and the truth will take arms
 in my defence. <milestone id="p01980085" />Now, should they be disposed to attend us, of a truth
 we might say with Pampinea, that fortune favours our enterprise.</q>
 <milestone id="p01980086" />The silence which followed betokened consent on the part of the other
 ladies, who then with one accord resolved to call the young men, and
 acquaint them with their purpose, and pray them to be of their company.
 <milestone id="p01980087" />So without further parley Pampinea, who had a kinsman
 among the young men, rose and approached them where they stood
 intently regarding them; and greeting them gaily, she opened to them
 their plan, and besought them on the part of herself and her friends
 to join their company on terms of honourable and fraternal comradeship.
 <milestone id="p01980088" />At first the young men thought she did but trifle with them;
 but when they saw that she was in earnest, they answered with
 alacrity that they were ready, and promptly, even before they left
 the church, set matters in train for their departure. <milestone id="p01980089" />So all things
 meet being first sent forward in due order to their intended place
 of sojourn, the ladies with some of their maids, and the three young
 men, each attended by a man-servant, sallied forth of the city on
 the morrow, being Wednesday, about daybreak, and took the road;
 nor had they journeyed more than two short miles when they
 arrived at their destination. <milestone id="p01980090" />The estate<note>Identified by tradition with
 the Villa Palmieri (now Crawford) on the
 slope of Fiesole.</note> lay upon a little hill some
 distance from the nearest highway, and, embowered in shrubberies
 of divers hues, and other greenery, afforded the eye a pleasant
 prospect. <milestone id="p01980091" />On the summit of the hill was a palace with galleries,
 halls and chambers, disposed around a fair and spacious court, each
 very fair in itself, and the goodlier to see for the gladsome pictures
 with which it was adorned; the whole set amidst meads and gardens
 laid out with marvellous art, wells of the coolest water, and vaults of
 the finest wines, things more suited to dainty drinkers than to sober
 and honourable women. On their arrival the company, to their no
 small delight, found their beds already made, the rooms well swept
 <pb n="18" />and garnished with flowers of every sort that the season could afford,
 and the floors carpeted with rushes. <milestone id="p01980092" />When they were seated,
 Dioneo, a gallant who had not his match for courtesy and wit, spoke
 thus: <q direct="unspecified">My ladies, 'tis not our forethought so much as your own
 mother-wit that has guided us hither. <milestone id="p01980093" />How you mean to dispose
 of your cares I know not; mine I left behind me within the citygate
 when I issued thence with you a brief while ago. Wherefore,
 I pray you, either address yourselves to make merry, to laugh and
 sing with me (so far, I mean, as may consist with your dignity), or
 give me leave to hie me back to the stricken city, there to abide
 with my cares.</q> <milestone id="p01980094" />To whom blithely Pampinea replied, as if she too
 had cast off all her cares: <q direct="unspecified">Well sayest thou, Dioneo, excellent
 well; gaily we mean to live; 'twas a refuge from sorrow that here
 we sought, nor had we other cause to come hither. <milestone id="p01980095" />But, as no
 anarchy can long endure, I who initiated the deliberations of which
 this fair company is the fruit, do now, to the end that our joy may
 be lasting, deem it expedient, that there be one among us in chief
 authority, honoured and obeyed by us as our superior, whose
 exclusive care it shall be to devise how we may pass our time
 blithely. <milestone id="p01980096" />And that each in turn may prove the weight of the care,
 as well as enjoy the pleasure, of sovereignty, and, no distinction being
 made of sex, envy be felt by none by reason of exclusion from the
 office; I propose, that the weight and honour be borne by each one
 for a day; and let the first to bear sway be chosen by us all,
 those that follow to be appointed towards the vesper hour by him
 or her who shall have had the signory for that day; and let each
 holder of the signory be, for the time, sole arbiter of the place and
 manner in which we are to pass our time.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01980097" />Pampinea's speech was received with the utmost applause, and
 with one accord she was chosen queen for the first day. Whereupon
 Filomena hied her lightly to a bay-tree, having often heard of the
 great honour in which its leaves, and such as were deservedly
 crowned therewith, were worthy to be holden; and having gathered
 a few sprays, she made thereof a goodly wreath of honour, and set
 it on Pampinea's head; which wreath was thenceforth, while
 their company endured, the visible sign of the wearer's sway and
 sovereignty.</p><p><milestone id="p01980098" />No sooner was Queen Pampinea crowned than she bade all be
 <pb n="19" />silent. She then caused summon to her presence their four maids,
 and the servants of the three young men, and, all keeping silence,
 said to them: <q direct="unspecified">That I may shew you all at once, how,
 well still giving place to better, our company may flourish and
 endure, as long as it shall pleasure us, with order meet and assured
 delight and without reproach, I first of all constitute Dioneo's man,
 Parmeno, my seneschal, and entrust him with the care and control
 of all our household, and all that belongs to the service of the hall.
 <milestone id="p01980099" />Pamfilo's man, Sirisco, I appoint treasurer and chancellor of our
 exchequer; and be he ever answerable to Parmeno. While Parmeno
 and Sirisco are too busy about their duties to serve their masters,
 let Filostrato's man, Tindaro, have charge of the chambers of all
 three. <milestone id="p01980100" />My maid, Misia, and Filomena's maid, Licisca, will keep in
 the kitchen, and with all due diligence prepare such dishes as
 Parmeno shall bid them. <milestone id="p01980101" />Lauretta's maid, Chimera, and Fiammetta's
 maid, Stratilia we make answerable for the ladies' chambers, and
 wherever we may take up our quarters, let them see that all is
 spotless. And now we enjoin you, one and all alike, as you value
 our favour, that none of you, go where you may, return whence
 you may, hear or see what you may, bring us any tidings but such as
 be cheerful.</q> <milestone id="p01980102" />These orders thus succinctly given were received with
 universal approval. Whereupon Pampinea rose, and said gaily:
 <q direct="unspecified">Here are gardens, meads, and other places delightsome enough,
 where you may wander at will, and take your pleasure; but on the
 stroke of tierce,<note>The canonical hour following prime, roughly speaking
 about 9 a.m.</note> let all be here to breakfast in the shade.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01980103" />Thus dismissed by their new queen the gay company sauntered
 gently through a garden, the young men saying sweet things to the
 fair ladies, who wove fair garlands of divers sorts of leaves and sang
 love-songs.</p><p><milestone id="p01980104" />Having thus spent the time allowed them by the queen, they
 returned to the house, where they found that Parmeno had entered
 on his office with zeal; for in a hall on the ground-floor they saw
 tables covered with the whitest of cloths, and beakers that shone
 like silver, and sprays of broom scattered everywhere. So, at the bidding
 of the queen, they washed their hands, and all took their places
 as marshalled by Parmeno. <milestone id="p01980105" />Dishes, daintily prepared, were served,
 <pb n="20" />and the finest wines were at hand; the three serving-men did their
 office noiselessly; in a word all was fair and ordered in a seemly
 manner; <milestone id="p01980106" />whereby the spirits of the company rose, and they
 seasoned their viands with pleasant jests and sprightly sallies.
 Breakfast done, the tables were removed, and the queen bade fetch
 instruments of music; for all, ladies and young men alike, knew
 how to tread a measure, and some of them played and sang with
 great skill: so, at her command, Dioneo having taken a lute, and
 Fiammetta a viol, they struck up a dance in sweet concert; <milestone id="p01980107" />and,
 the servants being dismissed to their repast, the queen, attended by
 the other ladies and the two young men, led off a stately carol; which
 ended they fell to singing ditties dainty and gay. <milestone id="p01980108" />Thus they diverted
 themselves until the queen, deeming it time to retire to rest, dismissed
 them all for the night. So the three young men and the
 ladies withdrew to their several quarters, which were in different
 parts of the palace. There they found the beds well made, and
 abundance of flowers, as in the hall; and so they undressed, and
 went to bed.</p><p><milestone id="p01980109" />Shortly after none<note>The canonical hour following sext, i. e. 3
 p.m.</note> the queen rose, and roused the rest of the
 ladies, as also the young men, averring that it was injurious to the
 health to sleep long in the daytime. They therefore hied them to
 a meadow, where the grass grew green and luxuriant, being nowhere
 scorched by the sun, and a light breeze gently fanned them. So at
 the queen's command they all ranged themselves in a circle on the
 grass, and hearkened while she thus spoke:</p><p><milestone id="p01980110" /><q direct="unspecified">You mark that the sun is high, the heat intense, and the silence
 unbroken save by the cicalas among the olive-trees. It were therefore
 the height of folly to quit this spot at present. Here the air
 is cool and the prospect fair, and here, observe, are dice and chess.
 Take, then, your pleasure as you may be severally minded; <milestone id="p01980111" />but, if
 you take my advice, you will find pastime for the hot hours before
 us, not in play, in which the loser must needs be vexed, and
 neither the winner nor the onlooker much the better pleased, but
 in telling of stories, in which the invention of one may afford
 solace to all the company of his hearers. <milestone id="p01980112" />You will not each have
 told a story before the sun will be low, and the heat abated, so that
 <pb n="21" />we shall be able to go and severally take our pleasure where it may
 seem best to each. Wherefore, if my proposal meet with your
 approval--for in this I am disposed to consult your pleasure--let us
 adopt it; if not, divert yourselves as best you may, until the vesper
 hour.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01980113" />The queen's proposal being approved by all, ladies and men alike,
 she added: <milestone id="p01980114" /><q direct="unspecified">So please you, then, I ordain, that, for this first day,
 we be free to discourse of such matters as most commend themselves
 to each in turn.</q> <milestone id="p01980115" />She then addressed Pamfilo, who sat on her
 right hand, bidding him with a gracious air to lead off with one of
 his stories. And prompt at the word of command, Pamfilo, while
 all listened intently, thus began:</p></div2>