<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0102"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p01020001" />Abraham, a Jew, at the instance of Jehannot de
 Chevigny, goes to the court of Rome, and having
 marked the evil life of the clergy, returns to Paris,
 and becomes a Christian.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01020002" />Pamfilo's story elicited the mirth of some of the ladies and the
	hearty commendation of all, who listened to it with close attention
	until the end. Whereupon the queen bade Neifile, who sat next
	her, to tell a story, that the commencement thus made of their
	diversions might have its sequel. Neifile, whose graces of mind
	matched the beauty of her person, consented with a gladsome goodwill,
	and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01020003" />Pamfilo has shewn by his story that the goodness of God spares
 to regard our errors when they result from unavoidable ignorance;
 and in mine I mean to shew you how the same goodness, bearing
 patiently with the shortcomings of those who should be its faithful
 witness in deed and word, draws from them contrariwise evidence
 of His infallible truth; to the end that what we believe we may
 with more assured conviction follow.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p01020004" />In Paris, gracious ladies, as I have heard tell, there was once
 a great merchant, a large dealer in drapery, a good man, most loyal
 and righteous, his name Jehannot de Chevigny, between whom and
 a Jew, Abraham by name, also a merchant, and a man of great
 wealth, as also most loyal and righteous, there subsisted a very close
 friendship. <milestone id="p01020005" />Now Jehannot, observing Abraham's loyalty and rectitude,
 began to be sorely vexed in spirit that the soul of one so
 worthy and wise and good should perish for want of faith. 
<milestone id="p01020006" />Wherefore
 he began in a friendly manner to plead with him, that he should
 <pb n="35" />leave the errors of the Jewish faith and turn to the Christian verity,
 which, being sound and holy, he might see daily prospering and
 gaining ground, whereas, on the contrary, his own religion was
 dwindling and was almost come to nothing. <milestone id="p01020007" />The Jew replied that
 he believed that there was no faith sound and holy except the Jewish
 faith, in which he was born, and in which he meant to live and die;
 nor would anything ever turn him therefrom. <milestone id="p01020008" />Nothing daunted,
 however, Jehannot some days afterwards began again to ply Abraham
 with similar arguments, explaining to him in such crude fashion as
 merchants use the reasons why our faith is better than the Jewish.
 <milestone id="p01020009" />And though the Jew was a great master in the Jewish law, yet,
 whether it was by reason of his friendship for Jehannot, or that the
 Holy Spirit dictated the words that the simple merchant used, at any
 rate the Jew began to be much interested in Jehannot's arguments,
 though still too staunch in his faith to suffer himself to be converted.
 <milestone id="p01020010" />But Jehannot was no less assiduous in plying him with argument
 than he was obstinate in adhering to his law, insomuch that at length
 the Jew, overcome by such incessant appeals, said: <q direct="unspecified">Well, well,
 Jehannot, thou wouldst have me become a Christian, and I am
 disposed to do so, provided I first go to Rome and there see him
 whom thou callest God's vicar on earth, and observe what manner
 of life he leads and his brother cardinals with him; <milestone id="p01020011" />and if such it
 be that thereby, in conjunction with thy words, I may understand
 that thy faith is better than mine, as thou hast sought to shew me,
 I will do as I have said: otherwise, I will remain as I am a Jew.</q>
 <milestone id="p01020012" />When Jehannot heard this, he was greatly distressed, saying to himself:
 <q direct="unspecified">I thought to have converted him; but now I see that the
 pains which I took for so excellent a purpose are all in vain; for, if he
 goes to the court of Rome and sees the iniquitous and foul life which
 the clergy lead there, so far from turning Christian, had he been
 converted already, he would without doubt relapse into Judaism.</q>
 <milestone id="p01020013" />Then turning to Abraham he said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but, my friend, why
 wouldst thou be at all this labour and great expense of travelling
 from here to Rome? to say nothing of the risks both by sea and by
 land which a rich man like thee must needs run. <milestone id="p01020014" />Thinkest thou
 not to find here one that can give thee baptism? And as for any
 doubts that thou mayst have touching the faith to which I point thee,
 where wilt thou find greater masters and sages therein than here, to
 <pb n="36" />resolve thee of any question thou mayst put to them? <milestone id="p01020015" />Wherefore
 in my opinion this journey of thine is superfluous. Think that the
 prelates there are such as thou mayst have seen here, nay, as much
 better as they are nearer to the Chief Pastor. And so, by my advice
 thou wilt spare thy pains until some time of indulgence, when I,
 perhaps, may be able to bear thee company.</q> <milestone id="p01020016" />The Jew replied:
 <q direct="unspecified">Jehannot, I doubt not that so it is as thou sayst; but once and
 for all I tell thee that I am minded to go there, and will never otherwise
 do that which thou wouldst have me and hast so earnestly
 besought me to do.</q> <milestone id="p01020017" /><q direct="unspecified">Go then,</q> said Jehannot, seeing that his
 mind was made up, <q direct="unspecified">and good luck go with thee;</q> and so he gave
 up the contest because nothing would be lost, though he felt sure
 that he would never become a Christian after seeing the court of
 Rome. <milestone id="p01020018" />The Jew took horse, and posted with all possible speed
 to Rome; where on his arrival he was honourably received by his
 fellow Jews. <milestone id="p01020019" />He said nothing to any one of the purpose for which
 he had come; but began circumspectly to acquaint himself with the
 ways of the Pope and the cardinals and the other prelates and all the
 courtiers; and from what he saw for himself, being a man of great
 intelligence, or learned from others, he discovered that without
 distinction of rank they were all sunk in the most disgraceful lewdness,
 sinning not only in the way of nature but after the manner
 of the men of Sodom, without any restraint of remorse or shame, in
 such sort that, when any great favour was to be procured, the influence
 of the courtesans and boys was of no small moment. <milestone id="p01020020" />Moreover he
 found them one and all gluttonous, wine-bibbers, drunkards, and next
 after lewdness, most addicted to the shameless service of the belly,
 like brute beasts. <milestone id="p01020021" />And, as he probed the matter still further, he
 perceived that they were all so greedy and avaricious that human, nay
 Christian blood, and things sacred of what kind soever, spiritualities
 no less than temporalities, they bought and sold for money; which
 traffic was greater and employed more brokers than the drapery trade
 and all the other trades of Paris put together; open simony and
 gluttonous excess being glosed under such specious terms as
 <q direct="unspecified">arrangement</q>
 and <q direct="unspecified">moderate use of creature comforts,</q> as if God could not
 penetrate the thoughts of even the most corrupt hearts, to say nothing
 of the signification of words, and would suffer Himself to be misled
 after the manner of men by the names of things. <milestone id="p01020022" />Which matters,
 <pb n="37" />with many others which are not to be mentioned, our modest and
 sober-minded Jew found by no means to his liking, so that, his
 curiosity being fully satisfied, he was minded to return to Paris; which
 accordingly he did. <milestone id="p01020023" />There, on his arrival, he was met by Jehannot;
 and the two made great cheer together. Jehannot expected Abraham's
 conversion least of all things, and allowed him some days of rest before
 he asked what he thought of the Holy Father and the cardinals and
 the other courtiers. <milestone id="p01020024" />To which the Jew forthwith replied: <q direct="unspecified">I think
 God owes them all an evil recompense: I tell thee, so far as I was
 able to carry my investigations, holiness, devotion, good works or
 exemplary living in any kind was nowhere to be found in any clerk;
 but only lewdness, avarice, gluttony, and the like, and worse, if worse
 may be, appeared to be held in such honour of all, that (to my thinking)
 the place is a centre of diabolical rather than of divine activities.
 <milestone id="p01020025" />To the best of my judgment, your Pastor, and by consequence all
 that are about him devote all their zeal and ingenuity and subtlety
 to devise how best and most speedily they may bring the Christian
 religion to nought and banish it from the world. <milestone id="p01020026" />And because I see
 that what they so zealously endeavour does not come to pass, but
 that on the contrary your religion continually grows, and shines
 more and more clear, therein I seem to discern a very evident token
 that it, rather than any other, as being more true and holy than any
 other, has the Holy Spirit for its foundation and support. <milestone id="p01020027" />For which
 cause, whereas I met your exhortations in a harsh and obdurate
 temper, and would not become a Christian, now I frankly tell you
 that I would on no account omit to become such. Go we then to
 the church, and there according to the traditional rite of your holy
 faith let me receive baptism.</q> <milestone id="p01020028" />Jehannot, who had anticipated a
 diametrically opposite conclusion, as soon as he heard him so speak,
 was the best pleased man that ever was in the world. So taking
 Abraham with him to Notre Dame he prayed the clergy there to
 baptise him. <milestone id="p01020029" />When they heard that it was his own wish, they forthwith
 did so, and Jehannot raised him from the sacred font, and named
 him Jean; and afterwards he caused teachers of great eminence
 thoroughly to instruct him in our faith, which he readily learned,
 and afterwards practised in a good, a virtuous, nay, a holy life.</p></div2>