<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div1 type="Day" ruler="emilia" id="day09"><pb n="263" /><head>Ninth Day</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09990001" />Endeth here the eighth day of the Decameron, beginneth
 the ninth, in which, under the rule of Emilia, discourse
 is had, at the discretion of each, of such matters as
 most commend themselves to each in turn.</p></argument><div2 type="introduction" who="author" id="d09intro"><head>Introduction</head><p><milestone id="p09980002" />The luminary, before whose splendour the night takes wing, had
 already changed the eighth heaven<note>I. e. in the Ptolemaic
 system,
 the region of the fixed stars.</note> from azure to the lighter
 blue,<note>Cilestro: a word for which we have no exact equivalent, the
 dominant
 note of the Italian sky, when the sun is well up, being its intense
 luminosity.</note>
 and in the meads the flowerets were beginning to lift their heads,
 when Emilia, being risen, roused her fair gossips, and, likewise, the
 young men. And so the queen leading the way at an easy pace, and
 the rest of the company following, they hied them to a copse at no
 great distance from the palace. Where, being entered, they saw the
 goats and stags and other wild creatures, as if witting that in this
 time of pestilence they had nought to fear from the hunter, stand
 awaiting them with no more sign of fear than if they had been
      tamed: <milestone id="p09980003" />and so, making now towards this, now towards the other of
 them as if to touch them, they diverted themselves for a while by
 making them skip and run. But, as soon as the sun was in the
 ascendant, by common consent they turned back,  <milestone id="p09980004" />and whoso met
 them, garlanded as they were with oak-leaves, and carrying store of
 fragrant herbs or flowers in their hands might well have said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Either shall death not vanquish these, or they will meet it with a
 light heart.</q>  <milestone id="p09980005" />So, slowly wended they their way, now singing, now
 bandying quips and merry jests, to the palace, where they found all
 things in order meet, and their servants in blithe and merry cheer.
  <milestone id="p09980006" />A while they rested, nor went they to table until six ditties, each
 gayer than that which went before, had been sung by the young
 <pb n="264" />men and the ladies; which done, they washed their hands, and all by
 the queen's command were ranged by the seneschal at the table;
 and, the viands being served, they cheerily took their meal: wherefrom
 being risen, they trod some measures to the accompaniment
 of music; and then, by the queen's command, whoso would betook
 him to rest.  <milestone id="p09980007" />However, the accustomed hour being come, they all
 gathered at the wonted spot for their discoursing, and the queen,
 bending her regard upon Filomena, bade her make a beginning of
 the day's story-telling, which she with a smile did on this wise:</p></div2><pb n="265" /><div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov0901"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09010001" />Madonna Francesca, having two lovers, the one Rinuccio,
 the other Alessandro, by name, and loving neither of
 them, induces the one to simulate a corpse in a tomb,
 and the other to enter the tomb to fetch him out:
 whereby, neither satisfying her demands, she artfully
 rids herself of both.</p></argument><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09010002" />Madam, since so it pleases you, well pleased am I that in this
 vast, this boundless field of discourse, which you, our Lady Bountiful,
 have furnished us withal, 'tis mine to run the first course; wherein
 if I do well, I doubt not that those, who shall follow me, will do
 not only well but better.  <milestone id="p09010003" />Such, sweet my ladies, has been the tenor
 of our discourse, that times not a few the might of Love, how great
 and singular it is, has been set forth; but yet I doubt the topic is not
 exhausted, nor would it be so, though we should continue to speak
 of nought else for the space of a full year.  <milestone id="p09010004" />And as Love not only
 leads lovers to debate with themselves whether they were not best to
 die, but also draws them into the houses of the dead in quest of the
 dead, I am minded in this regard to tell you a story, wherein you
 will not only discern the power of Love, but will also learn how the
 ready wit of a worthy lady enabled her to disembarrass herself of two
 lovers, whose love was displeasing to her.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09010005" />Know, then, that there dwelt aforetime in the city of Pistoia a
 most beauteous widow lady, of whom it so befell that two of our
 citizens, the one Rinuccio Palermini, the other Alessandro Chiarmontesi,
 by name, tarrying at Pistoia, for that they were banished
 from Florence, became, neither witting how it stood with the other,
 in the last degree enamoured.  <milestone id="p09010006" />Wherefore each used all his arts
 <pb n="266" />to win the love of Madonna Francesca de' Lazzari--such was the
 lady's name--and she, being thus continually plied with ambassages
 and entreaties on the part of both, and having indiscreetly lent ear
 to them from time to time, found it no easy matter discreetly to
 extricate herself, when she was minded to be rid of their pestering,
  <milestone id="p09010007" />until it occurred to her to adopt the following expedient, to wit,
 to require of each a service, such as, though not impracticable,
 she deemed none would actually perform, to the end that, they
 making default, she might have a decent and colourable pretext
 for refusing any longer to receive their ambassages. Which expedient
 was on this wise.  <milestone id="p09010008" />One day there died in Pistoia, and was
 buried in a tomb outside the church of the Friars Minors, a man,
 who, though his forbears had been gentlefolk, was reputed the very
 worst man, not in Pistoia only, but in all the world,  <milestone id="p09010009" />and therewithal
 he was of form and feature so preternaturally hideous that
 whoso knew him not could scarce see him for the first time without
 a shudder. Now, the lady pondering her design on the day of this
 man's death, it occurred to her that he might in a measure subserve
 its accomplishment:  <milestone id="p09010010" />wherefore she said to her maid: <q direct="unspecified">Thou
 knowest to what worry and annoyance I am daily put by the
 ambassages of these two Florentines, Rinuccio and Alessandro.
 Now I am not disposed to gratify either of them with my love, and
 therefore, to shake them off, I am minded, as they make such great
 protestations, to put them to the proof by requiring of each something
 which I am sure he will not perform, and thus to rid myself
 of their pestering:  <milestone id="p09010011" />so list what I mean to do. Thou knowest that
 this morning there was interred in the ground of the Friars Minors
 this Scannadio (such was the name of the bad man of whom we
 spoke but now) whose aspect, while he yet lived, appalled even the
 bravest among us.  <milestone id="p09010012" />Thou wilt therefore go privily to Alessandro,
 and say to him: 'Madonna Francesca sends thee word by me that
 the time is now come when thou mayst win that which thou hast
 so much desired, to wit, her love and joyance thereof, if thou be so
 minded, on the following terms.  <milestone id="p09010013" />For a reason, which thou shalt
 learn hereafter, one of her kinsmen is to bring home to her to-night
 the corpse of Scannadio, who was buried this morning; and she,
 standing in mortal dread of this dead man, would fain not see him;
  <milestone id="p09010014" />wherefore she prays thee to do her a great service, and be so good as
 <pb n="267" />to get thee this evening at the hour of first sleep to the tomb wherein
 Scannadio is buried, and go in, and having wrapped thyself in his
 grave-clothes, lie there, as thou wert Scannadio himself, until one
 come for thee, when thou must say never a word, but let him carry
 thee forth, and bear thee to Madonna Francesca's house, where she
 will give thee welcome, and let thee stay with her, until thou art
 minded to depart, and, for the rest, thou wilt leave it to her.'  <milestone id="p09010015" />And
 if he says that he will gladly do so, well and good; if not, then thou
 wilt tell him from me, never more to shew himself where I am,
 and, as he values his life, to have a care to send me no more ambassages.
  <milestone id="p09010016" />Which done, thou wilt go to Rinuccio Palermini, and
 wilt say to him: 'Madonna Francesca lets thee know that she is
 ready in all respects to comply with thy wishes, so thou wilt do her
 a great service, which is on this wise: to-night, about midnight,
 thou must go to the tomb wherein was this morning interred
 Scannadio, and saying never a word, whatever thou mayst hear
 or otherwise be ware of, bear him gently forth to Madonna
 Francesca's house,  <milestone id="p09010017" />where thou shalt learn wherefore she requires
 this of thee, and shalt have thy solace of her; and if thou art not
 minded to obey her in this, see that thou never more send her
 ambassage.'</q></p><p><milestone id="p09010018" />The maid did her mistress's errand, omitting nothing, to both
 the men, and received from each the same answer, to wit, that to
 pleasure the lady, he would adventure a journey to hell, to say
 nothing of entering a tomb. With which answer the maid returned
 to the lady, who waited to see if they would be such fools as to make
 it good.  <milestone id="p09010019" />Night came, and at the hour of first sleep Alessandro
 Chiarmontesi, stripped to his doublet, quitted his house, and bent his
 steps towards Scannadio's tomb, with intent there to take the dead
 man's place. As he walked, there came upon him a great fear,  <milestone id="p09010020" />and
 he fell a saying to himself: Ah! what a fool am I! Whither go
 I? How know I that her kinsmen, having detected my love, and
 surmising that which is not, have not put her upon requiring this of
 me, in order that they may slay me in the tomb? In which event I
 alone should be the loser, for nought would ever be heard of it, so
 that they would escape scot-free. Or how know I but that 'tis
 some machination of one of my ill-wishers, whom perchance she
 loves, and is therefore minded to abet?  <milestone id="p09010021" />And again quoth he to
 <pb n="268" />himself: But allowing that 'tis neither the one nor the other, and
 that her kinsmen are really to carry me to her house, I scarce believe
 that 'tis either that they would fain embrace Scannadio's corpse themselves,
 or let her do so: rather it must be that they have a mind to
 perpetrate some outrage upon it, for that, perchance, he once did
 them an evil turn.  <milestone id="p09010022" />She bids me say never a word, no matter what
 I may hear or be otherwise ware of. Suppose they were to pluck
 out my eyes, or my teeth, or cut off my hands, or treat me to some
 other horse-play of the like sort, how then? how could I keep
 quiet?  <milestone id="p09010023" />And if I open my mouth, they will either recognize me,
 and perchance do me a mischief, or, if they spare me, I shall have
 been at pains for nought, for they will not leave me with the lady,
 and she will say that I disobeyed her command, and I shall never
 have aught of her favours.</p><p><milestone id="p09010024" />As thus he communed with himself, he was on the point of
 turning back; but his overmastering love plied him with opposing
 arguments of such force that he kept on his way, and reached
 the tomb; which having opened, he entered, and after stripping
 Scannadio, and wrapping himself in the grave-clothes, closed it, and
 laid himself down in Scannadio's place. He then fell a thinking of the
 dead man, and his manner of life, and the things which he had heard
 tell of as happening by night, and in other less appalling places than
 the houses of the dead;  <milestone id="p09010025" />whereby all the hairs of his head stood on end,
 and he momently expected Scannadio to rise and cut his throat.
  <milestone id="p09010026" />However, the ardour of his love so fortified him that he overcame
 these and all other timorous apprehensions, and lay as if he were
 dead, awaiting what should betide him.</p><p><milestone id="p09010027" />Towards midnight Rinuccio, bent likewise upon fulfilling his
 lady's behest, sallied forth of his house, revolving as he went divers
 forebodings of possible contingencies, as that, having Scannadio's
 corpse upon his shoulders, he might fall into the hands of the Signory,
 and be condemned to the fire as a wizard, or that, should the affair
 get wind, it might embroil him with his kinsfolk, or the like, which
 gave him pause.  <milestone id="p09010028" />But then with a revulsion of feeling: Shall I,
 quoth he to himself, deny this lady, whom I so much have loved and
 love, the very first thing that she asks of me? And that too when
 I am thereby to win her favour? No, though 'twere as much as my
 life is worth, far be it from me to fail of keeping my word. So on
 <pb n="269" />he fared, and arrived at the tomb, which he had no difficulty in
 opening, and being entered, laid hold of  <milestone id="p09010029" />Alessandro, who, though
 in mortal fear, had given no sign of life, by the feet, and dragged
 him forth, and having hoisted him on to his shoulders, bent his steps
 towards the lady's house. And as he went, being none too careful
 of Alessandro, he swung him from time to time against one or other
 of the angles of certain benches that were by the wayside; and
 indeed the night was so dark and murky that he could not see where
 he was going.  <milestone id="p09010030" />And when he was all but on the threshold of the
 lady's house (she standing within at a window with her maid, to mark
 if Rinuccio would bring Alessandro, and being already provided with
 an excuse for sending them both away), it so befell that the patrol of
 the Signory, who were posted in the street in dead silence, being on
 the look-out for a certain bandit, hearing the tramp of Rinuccio's
 feet, suddenly shewed a light, the better to know what was toward,
 and whither to go, and advancing targes and lances,  <milestone id="p09010031" />cried out:
 <q direct="unspecified">Who goes there?</q> Whereupon Rinuccio, having little leisure
 for deliberation, let Alessandro fall, and took to flight as fast as his
 legs might carry him. Alessandro, albeit encumbered by the graveclothes,
 which were very long, also jumped up and made off.  <milestone id="p09010032" />By
 the light shewn by the patrol the lady had very plainly perceived
 Rinuccio, with Alessandro on his back, as also that Alessandro had
 the grave-clothes upon him; and much did she marvel at the daring
 of both, but, for all that, she laughed heartily to see Rinuccio drop
 Alessandro, and Alessandro run away.  <milestone id="p09010033" />Overjoyed at the turn the
 affair had taken, and praising God that He had rid her of their harass,
 she withdrew from the window, and betook her to her chamber,
 averring to her maid that for certain they must both be mightily in
 love with her, seeing that 'twas plain they had both done her
 bidding.</p><p><milestone id="p09010034" />Crestfallen and cursing his evil fortune, Rinuccio nevertheless
 went not home, but, as soon as the street was clear of the patrol,
 came back to the spot where he had dropped Alessandro, and stooped
 down and began feeling about, if haply he might find him, and so do
 his devoir to the lady; but, as he found him not, he supposed the
 patrol must have borne him thence, and so at last home he went; as
 did also Alessandro, knowing not what else to do, and deploring his
 mishap.  <milestone id="p09010035" />On the morrow, Scannadio's tomb being found open and
 <pb n="270" />empty, for Alessandro had thrown the corpse into the vault below,
 all Pistoia debated of the matter with no small diversity of opinion,
 the fools believing that Scannadio had been carried off by devils.
  <milestone id="p09010036" />Neither of the lovers, however, forbore to make suit to the lady for
 her favour and love, telling her what he had done, and what had happened,
 and praying her to have him excused that he had not perfectly
 carried out her instructions. But she, feigning to believe neither of
 them, disposed of each with the same curt answer, to wit, that, as he
 had not done her bidding, she would never do aught for him.</p></div2><pb n="271" /><div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0902"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09020001" />An abbess rises in haste and in the dark, with intent to
 surprise an accused nun abed with her lover: thinking
 to put on her veil, she puts on instead the breeches
 of a priest that she has with her: the nun, espying
 her headgear, and doing her to wit thereof, is acquitted,
 and thenceforth finds it easier to forgather with her
 lover.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09020002" />So ended Filomena; and when all had commended the address
 shewn by the lady in ridding herself of the two lovers that she
 affected not, and contrariwise had censured the hardihood of the two
 lovers as not love but madness, the queen turned to Elisa, and with
 a charming air: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Elisa, follow,</q> quoth she: whereupon Elisa
 began on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09020003" />Dearest ladies, 'twas cleverly done of Madonna
 Francesca, to disembarrass herself in the way we have heard: but I
 have to tell of a young nun, who by a happy retort, and the favour
 of Fortune, delivered herself from imminent peril.  <milestone id="p09020004" />And as you
 know that there are not a few most foolish folk, who, notwithstanding
 their folly, take upon themselves the governance and correction of
 others; so you may learn from my story that Fortune at times justly
 puts them to shame; which befell the abbess, who was the superior
 of the nun of whom I am about to speak.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09020005" />You are to know, then, that in a convent in Lombardy of very
 great repute for strict and holy living there was, among other ladies
 that there wore the veil, a young woman of noble family, and extraordinary
 beauty. Now Isabetta--for such was her name--having
 speech one day of one of her kinsmen at the grate, became enamoured
 <pb n="272" />of a fine young gallant that was with him; who, seeing her to be
 very fair, and reading her passion in her eyes, was kindled with a like
 flame for her: which mutual and unsolaced love they bore a great
 while not without great suffering to both.  <milestone id="p09020006" />But at length, both being
 intent thereon, the gallant discovered a way by which he might with
 all secrecy visit his nun; and she approving, he paid her not one visit
 only, but many, to their no small mutual solace.  <milestone id="p09020007" />But, while thus they
 continued their intercourse, it so befell that one night one of the
 sisters observed him take his leave of Isabetta and depart, albeit neither
 he nor she was ware that they had thus been discovered. The sister
 imparted what she had seen to several others. At first they were
 minded to denounce her to the abbess, one Madonna Usimbalda,
 who was reputed by the nuns, and indeed by all that knew her, to
 be a good and holy woman; but on second thoughts they deemed it
 expedient, that there might be no room for denial, to cause the abbess
 to take her and the gallant in the act. So they held their peace, and
 arranged between them to keep her in watch and close espial, that
 they might catch her unawares.  <milestone id="p09020008" />Of which practice Isabetta recking,
 witting nought, it so befell that one night, when she had her lover
 to see her, the sisters that were on the watch were soon ware of it,
 and at what they deemed the nick of time parted into two companies,
 of which one mounted guard at the threshold of Isabetta's cell, while
 the other hasted to the abbess's chamber, and knocking at the door,
 roused her, and as soon as they heard her voice, said: <q direct="unspecified">Up, Madam,
 without delay: we have discovered that Isabetta has a young man
 with her in her cell.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09020009" />Now that night the abbess had with her a priest whom she used
 not seldom to have conveyed to her in a chest; and the report of the
 sisters making her apprehensive lest for excess of zeal and hurry they
 should force the door open, she rose in a trice; and huddling on
 her clothes as best she might in the dark, instead of the veil that
 they wear, which they call the psalter, she caught up the priest's
 breeches, and having clapped them on her head,  <milestone id="p09020010" />hied her forth,
 and locked the door behind her, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Where is this woman
 accursed of God?</q>  <milestone id="p09020011" />And so, guided by the sisters, all so agog to catch
 Isabetta a sinning that they perceived not what manner of headgear
 the abbess wore, she made her way to the cell, and with their
 aid broke open the door; and entering they found the two lovers
 <pb n="273" />abed in one another's arms; who, as it were, thunderstruck to be
 thus surprised, lay there, witting not what to do.  <milestone id="p09020012" />The sisters took
 the young nun forthwith, and by command of the abbess brought her
 to the chapter-house. The gallant, left behind in the cell, put on
 his clothes and waited to see how the affair would end, being minded
 to make as many nuns as he might come at pay dearly for any despite
 that might be done his mistress, and to bring her off with him.  <milestone id="p09020013" />The
 abbess, seated in the chapter-house with all her nuns about her, and
 all eyes bent upon the culprit, began giving her the severest reprimand
 that ever woman got, for that by her disgraceful and abominable conduct,
 should it get wind, she had sullied the fair fame of the convent;
 whereto she added menaces most dire.  <milestone id="p09020014" />Shamefast and timorous, the
 culprit essayed no defence, and her silence begat pity of her in
 the rest; but, while the abbess waxed more and more voluble, it
 chanced that the girl raised her head and espied the abbess's headgear,
 and the points that hung down on this side and that.  <milestone id="p09020015" />The significance
 whereof being by no means lost upon her, she quite plucked
 up heart, and: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">so help you God, tie up
 your coif, and then you may say what you will to me.</q>  <milestone id="p09020016" />Whereto
 the abbess, not understanding her, replied: <q direct="unspecified">What coif, lewd
 woman? So thou hast the effrontery to jest! Think'st thou that
 what thou hast done is a matter meet for jests?</q>  <milestone id="p09020017" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth the girl again, <q direct="unspecified">I pray you, tie up your coif, and
 then you may say to me whatever you please.</q> Which occasioned
 not a few of the nuns to look up at the abbess's head, and the abbess
 herself to raise her hands thereto, and so she and they at one and the
 same time apprehended Isabetta's meaning.  <milestone id="p09020018" />Wherefore the abbess,
 finding herself detected by all in the same sin, and that no disguise
 was possible, changed her tone, and held quite another sort of language
 than before, the upshot of which was that 'twas impossible to withstand
 the assaults of the flesh, and that, accordingly, observing due
 secrecy as theretofore, all might give themselves a good time, as they
 had opportunity. So, having dismissed Isabetta to rejoin her lover in
 her cell, she herself returned to lie with her priest.  <milestone id="p09020019" />And many a
 time thereafter, in spite of the envious, Isabetta had her gallant to
 see her, the others, that lacked lovers, doing in secret the best they
 might to push their fortunes.</p></div2><pb n="274" /><div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0903"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09030001" />Master Simone, at the instance of Bruno and Buffalmacco
 and Nello, makes Calandrino believe that he is with
 child. Calandrino, accordingly, gives them capons and
 money for medicines, and is cured without being
 delivered.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09030002" />When Elisa had ended her story, and all had given thanks to
 God that He had vouchsafed the young nun a happy escape from
 the fangs of her envious companions, the queen bade Filostrato follow
 suit; and without expecting a second command, thus Filostrato
 began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09030003" />Fairest my ladies, the uncouth judge from the Marches, or
 whom I told you yesterday, took from the tip of my tongue a story
 of Calandrino, which I was on the point of narrating: and as nought
 can be said of him without mightily enhancing our jollity, albeit not
 a little has already been said touching him and his comrades, I will
 now give you the story which I had meant yesterday to give you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09030004" />Who they were, this Calandrino and the others that I am to tell of
 in this story, has already been sufficiently explained; wherefore,
 without more ado, I say that one of Calandrino's aunts having died,
 leaving him two hundred pounds in petty cash, Calandrino gave out
 that he was minded to purchase an estate, and, as if he had had ten
 thousand florins of gold to invest, engaged every broker in Florence
 to treat for him, the negotiation always falling through, as soon as
 the price was named.  <milestone id="p09030005" />Bruno and Buffalmacco, knowing what was
 afoot, told him again and again that he had better give himself a
 jolly time with them than go about buying earth as if he must needs
 make pellets;<note>I.e. bolts of clay for the cross-bow.</note> but
 so far were they from effecting their purpose,
 <pb n="275" />that they could not even prevail upon him to give them a single
 meal.  <milestone id="p09030006" />Whereat as one day they grumbled, being joined by a comrade
 of theirs, one Nello, also a painter, they all three took counsel how
 they might wet their whistle at Calandrino's expense; and, their
 plan being soon concerted, the next morning Calandrino was scarce
 gone out, when Nello met him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Good day, Calandrino:</q>
  <milestone id="p09030007" />whereto Calandrino replied: <q direct="unspecified">God give thee a good day and a
 good year.</q> Nello then drew back a little, and looked him steadily
 in the face, until: <q direct="unspecified">What seest thou to stare at?</q> quoth Calandrino.
  <milestone id="p09030008" /><q direct="unspecified">Hadst thou no pain in the night?</q> returned Nello; <q direct="unspecified">thou
 seemest not thyself to me.</q> Which Calandrino no sooner heard,
 than he began to be disquieted, and:  <milestone id="p09030009" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas! How sayst thou?</q>
 quoth he. <q direct="unspecified">What tak'st thou to be the matter with me?</q>  <milestone id="p09030010" /><q direct="unspecified">Why,
 as to that I have nothing to say,</q> returned Nello; <q direct="unspecified">but thou
 seemest to be quite changed: perchance 'tis not what I suppose;</q>
 and with that he left him.</p><p><milestone id="p09030011" />Calandrino, anxious, though he could not in the least have said
 why, went on; and soon Buffalmacco, who was not far off, and had
 observed him part from Nello, made up to him, and greeted him,
 asking him if he was not in pain. <q direct="unspecified">I cannot say,</q> replied Calandrino;
 <q direct="unspecified">'twas but now that Nello told me that I looked quite changed:
 can it be that there is aught the matter with me?</q> <q direct="unspecified">Aught?</q>
  <milestone id="p09030012" />quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">ay, indeed, there might be a trifle the matter
 with thee. Thou look'st to be half dead, man.</q>  <milestone id="p09030013" />Calandrino now
 began to think he must have a fever. And then up came Bruno;
 and the first thing he said was: <q direct="unspecified">Why, Calandrino, how ill thou
 look'st! thy appearance is that of a corpse. How dost thou feel?</q>
  <milestone id="p09030014" />To be thus accosted by all three left no doubt in Calandrino's mind
 that he was ill, and so: <q direct="unspecified">What shall I do?</q> quoth he, in a great
 fright.  <milestone id="p09030015" /><q direct="unspecified">My advice,</q> replied Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">is that thou go home and
 get thee to bed and cover thee well up, and send thy water to
 Master Simone, who, as thou knowest, is such a friend of ours. He
 will tell thee at once what thou must do; and we will come to see
 thee, and will do aught that may be needful.</q>  <milestone id="p09030016" />And Nello then
 joining them, they all three went home with Calandrino, who, now
 quite spent, went straight to his room, and said to his wife: <q direct="unspecified">Come
 now, wrap me well up; I feel very ill.</q>  <milestone id="p09030017" />And so he laid himself on
 the bed, and sent a maid with his water to Master Simone, who had
 then his shop in the Mercato Vecchio, at the sign of the pumpkin.
 <pb n="276" />Whereupon quoth Bruno to his comrades: <q direct="unspecified">You will stay here
 with him, and I will go hear what the doctor has to say, and if need
 be, will bring him hither.</q>  <milestone id="p09030018" /><q direct="unspecified">Prithee, do so, my friend,</q> quoth
 Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">and bring me word how it is with me, for I feel as
 how I cannot say in my inside.</q>  <milestone id="p09030019" />So Bruno hied him to Master
 Simone, and before the maid arrived with the water, told him what
 was afoot. The Master, thus primed, inspected the water, and then
 said to the maid: <q direct="unspecified">Go tell Calandrino to keep himself very warm,
 and I will come at once, and let him know what is the matter with
 him, and what he must do.</q>  <milestone id="p09030020" />With which message the maid was
 scarce returned, when the Master and Bruno arrived, and the Master,
 having seated himself beside Calandrino, felt his pulse, and by and by,
 in the presence of his wife, said: <q direct="unspecified">Harkye, Calandrino, I speak to
 thee as a friend, and I tell thee that what is amiss with thee is just
 that thou art with child.</q>  <milestone id="p09030021" />Whereupon Calandrino cried out querulously:
 <q direct="unspecified">Woe's me! 'Tis thy doing, Tessa, for that thou must
 needs be uppermost: I told thee plainly what would come of it.</q>
  <milestone id="p09030022" />Whereat the lady, being not a little modest, coloured from brow to
 neck, and with downcast eyes, withdrew from the room, saying
 never a word by way of answer.  <milestone id="p09030023" />Calandrino ran on in the same
 plaintive strain: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! woe's me! What shall I do? How shall
 I be delivered of this child? What passage can it find? Ah! I see
 only too plainly that the lasciviousness of this wife of mine has been
 the death of me: God make her as wretched as I would fain be
 happy!  <milestone id="p09030024" />Were I as well as I am not, I would get me up and thrash
 her, till I left not a whole bone in her body, albeit it does but serve
 me right for letting her get the upper place; but if I do win through
 this, she shall never have it again; verily she might pine to death for
 it, but she should not have it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09030025" />Which to hear, Bruno and Buffalmacco and Nello were like to
 burst with suppressed laughter, and Master Scimmione<note>I.e.
 great
 ape: with a play on Simone.</note> laughed so
 frantically, that all his teeth were ready to start from his jaws.  <milestone id="p09030026" />However,
 at length, in answer to Calandrino's appeals and entreaties for
 counsel and succour: <q direct="unspecified">Calandrino,</q> quoth the Master, <q direct="unspecified">thou
 mayst dismiss thy fears, for, God be praised, we were apprised of thy
 state in such good time that with but little trouble, in the course of a
 few days, I shall set thee right; but 'twill cost a little.</q>  <milestone id="p09030027" /><q direct="unspecified">Woe's
 <pb n="277" />me,</q> returned Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">be it so, Master, for the love of God:
 I have here two hundred pounds, with which I had thoughts of buying
 an estate: take them all, all, if you must have all, so only I may escape
 being delivered, for I know not how I should manage it, seeing that
 women, albeit 'tis much easier for them, do make such a noise in
 the hour of their labour, that I misdoubt me, if I suffered so, I should
 die before I was delivered.</q>  <milestone id="p09030028" /><q direct="unspecified">Disquiet not thyself,</q> said the
 doctor:
 <q direct="unspecified">I will have a potion distilled for thee; of rare virtue it is, and not
 a little palatable, and in the course of three days 'twill purge thee of
 all, and leave thee in better fettle than a fish; but thou wilt do well
 to be careful thereafter, and commit no such indiscretions again.
  <milestone id="p09030029" />Now to make this potion we must have three pair of good fat
 capons, and, for divers other ingredients, thou wilt give one of thy
 friends here five pounds in small change to purchase them, and thou
 wilt have everything sent to my shop, and so, please God, I will
 send thee this distilled potion to-morrow morning, and thou wilt
 take a good beakerful each time.</q>  <milestone id="p09030030" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Be it as you
 bid, Master mine,</q> quoth Calandrino, and handing Bruno five
 pounds, and money enough to purchase three pair of capons, he
 begged him, if it were not too much trouble, to do him the service
 to buy these things for him.  <milestone id="p09030031" />So away went the doctor, and made a
 little decoction by way of draught, and sent it him. Bruno bought
 the capons and all else that was needed to furnish forth the feast,
 with which he and his comrades and the doctor regaled them.
  <milestone id="p09030032" />Calandrino drank of the decoction for three mornings, after which
 he had a visit from his friends and the doctor, who felt his pulse, and
 then: <q direct="unspecified">Beyond a doubt, Calandrino,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">thou art cured,
 and so thou hast no more occasion to keep indoors, but needst have
 no fear to do whatever thou hast a mind to.</q>  <milestone id="p09030033" />Much relieved,
 Calandrino got up, and resumed his accustomed way of life, and,
 wherever he found any one to talk to, was loud in praise of
 Master Simone for the excellent manner in which he had cured
 him, causing him in three days without the least suffering to
 be quit of his pregnancy. And Bruno and Buffalmacco and
 Nello were not a little pleased with themselves that they had so
 cleverly got the better of Calandrino's niggardliness, albeit Monna
 Tessa, who was not deceived, murmured not a little against her
 husband.</p></div2><pb n="278" /><div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0904"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09040001" />Cecco, son of Messer Fortarrigo, loses his all at play at
 Buonconvento, besides the money of Cecco, son of
 Messer Angiulieri; whom, running after him in his
 shirt and crying out that he has robbed him, he causes
 to be taken by peasants: he then puts on his clothes,
 mounts his palfrey, and leaves him to follow in his
 shirt.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09040002" />All the company laughed beyond measure to hear what Calandrino
 said touching his wife: but, when Filostrato had done, Neifile,
 being bidden by the queen, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09040003" />Noble ladies, were it not
 more difficult for men to evince their good sense and virtue than
 their folly and their vice, many would labour in vain to set bounds
 to their flow of words: whereof you have had a most conspicuous
 example in poor blundering Calandrino, who, for the better cure
 of that with which in his simplicity he supposed himself to be
 afflicted, had no sort of need to discover in public his wife's secret
 pleasures.  <milestone id="p09040004" />Which affair has brought to my mind one that fell out
 contrariwise, inasmuch as the guile of one discomfited the good
 sense of another to the grievous loss and shame of the discomfited:
 the manner whereof I am minded to relate to you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09040005" />'Tis not many years since there were in Siena two young men,
 both of age, and both alike named Cecco, the one being son of
 Messer Angiulieri, the other of Messer Fortarrigo. Who, albeit in
 many other respects their dispositions accorded ill, agreed so well in
 one, to wit, that they both hated their fathers, that they became
 friends, and kept much together.  <milestone id="p09040006" />Now Angiulieri, being a pretty
 <pb n="279" />fellow, and well-mannered, could not brook to live at Siena on the
 allowance made him by his father, and learning that there was come
 into the March of Ancona, as legate of the Pope, a cardinal, to whom
 he was much bounden, resolved to resort to him there, thinking thereby
 to improve his circumstances. So, having acquainted his father with
 his purpose, he prevailed upon him to give him there and then all that
 he would have given him during the next six months, that he might
 have the wherewith to furnish himself with apparel and a good mount,
 so as to travel in a becoming manner.  <milestone id="p09040007" />And as he was looking out for
 some one to attend him as his servant, Fortarrigo, hearing of it,
 came presently to him and besought him with all earnestness to take
 him with him as his groom, or servant, or what he would, and he
 would be satisfied with his keep, without any salary whatsoever.
  <milestone id="p09040008" />Whereto Angiulieri made answer that he was not disposed to take
 him, not but that he well knew that he was competent for any
 service that might be required of him, but because he was given to
 play, and therewithal would at times get drunk. Fortarrigo assured
 him with many an oath that he would be on his guard to commit
 neither fault, and added thereto such instant entreaties, that Angiulieri
 was, as it were, vanquished, and consented.  <milestone id="p09040009" />So one morning they
 took the road for Buonconvento, being minded there to breakfast.
 Now when Angiulieri had breakfasted, as 'twas a very hot day, he
 had a bed made in the inn, and having undressed with Fortarrigo's
 help, he composed himself to sleep, telling Fortarrigo to call him on
 the stroke of none.  <milestone id="p09040010" />Angiulieri thus sleeping, Fortarrigo repaired to
 the tavern, where, having slaked his thirst, he sate down to a game
 with some that were there, who speedily won from him all his money,
 and thereafter in like manner all the clothes he had on his back:
 wherefore he, being anxious to retrieve his losses, went, stripped as
 he was to his shirt, to the room where lay Angiulieri; and seeing
 that he was sound asleep, he took from his purse all the money
 that he had, and so went back to the gaming-table, and staked it, and
 lost it all, as he had his own.</p><p><milestone id="p09040011" />By and by Angiulieri awoke, and got up, and dressed, and called
 for Fortarrigo; and as Fortarrigo answered not, he supposed that he
 must have had too much to drink, and be sleeping it off somewhere,
 as was his wont. He accordingly determined to leave him alone;
 and doubting not to find a better servant at Corsignano, he let saddle
 his palfrey and attach the valise; but when, being about to depart,
 <pb n="280" />he would have paid the host, never a coin could he come by.  <milestone id="p09040012" />Whereat
 there was no small stir, so that all the inn was in an uproar, Angiulieri
 averring that he had been robbed in the house, and threatening
 to have them all arrested and taken to Siena;  <milestone id="p09040013" />when, lo, who should
 make his appearance but Fortarrigo in his shirt, intent now to steal
 the clothes, as he had stolen the moneys, of Angiulieri? And marking
 that Angiulieri was accoutred for the road: <q direct="unspecified">How is this,
 Angiulieri?</q> quoth he. <q direct="unspecified">Are we to start so soon? Nay, but wait
 a little. One will be here presently that has my doublet in pawn
 for thirty-eight soldi; I doubt not he will return it me for thirty-five
 soldi, if I pay money down.</q>  <milestone id="p09040014" />And while they were yet talking,
 in came one that made it plain to Angiulieri that 'twas Fortarrigo
 that had robbed him of his money, for he told him the amount that
 Fortarrigo had lost. Whereat Angiulieri, in a towering passion,
 rated Fortarrigo right soundly, and, but that he stood more in fear of
 man than of God, would have suited action to word; and so,
 threatening to have him hanged by the neck and proclaimed an outlaw
 at the gallows-tree of Siena, he mounted his horse.</p><p><milestone id="p09040015" />Fortarrigo, making as if 'twas not to him, but to another, that
 Angiulieri thus spoke, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Come now, Angiulieri, we
 were best have done with all this idle talk, and consider the matter
 of substance: we can redeem for thirty-five soldi, if we pay forth-with,
 but if we wait till to-morrow, we shall not get off with less
 than thirty-eight, the full amount of the loan; and 'tis because I
 staked by his advice that he will make me this allowance. Now why
 should not we save these three soldi?</q>  <milestone id="p09040016" />Whereat Angiulieri waxed
 well-nigh desperate, more particularly that he marked that the
 bystanders were scanning him suspiciously, as if, so far from understanding
 that Fortarrigo had staked and lost his, Angiulieri's money,
 they gave him credit for still being in funds: so he cried out:
 <q direct="unspecified">What have I to do with thy doublet? 'Tis high time thou wast
 hanged by the neck, that, not content with robbing me and gambling
 away my money, thou must needs also keep me in parley here and
 make mock of me, when I would fain be gone.</q>  <milestone id="p09040017" />Fortarrigo, however,
 still persisted in making believe that Angiulieri did not mean
 this for him, and only said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but why wilt not thou save me
 these three soldi? Think'st thou I can be of no more use to thee?
 Prithee, an thou lov'st me, do me this turn. Wherefore in such a
 hurry? We have time enough to get to Torrenieri this evening.
 <pb n="281" /> <milestone id="p09040018" />Come now, out with thy purse. Thou knowest I might search Siena
 through, and not find a doublet that would suit me so well as this:
 and for all I let him have it for thirty-eight soldi, 'tis worth forty or
 more; so thou wilt wrong me twice over.</q> Vexed beyond measure
 that, after robbing him, Fortarrigo should now keep him clavering
 about the matter,  <milestone id="p09040019" />Angiulieri made no answer, but turned his horse's
 head, and took the road for Torrenieri.  <milestone id="p09040020" />But Fortarrigo with cunning
 malice trotted after him in his shirt, and 'twas still his doublet, his
 doublet, that he would have of him: and when they had thus ridden
 two good miles, and Angiulieri was forcing the pace to get out of
 earshot of his pestering, Fortarrigo espied some husbandmen in a field
 beside the road a little ahead of Angiulieri, and fell a shouting to
 them amain: <q direct="unspecified">Take thief! take thief!</q>  <milestone id="p09040021" />Whereupon they came
 up with their spades and their mattocks, and barred Angiulieri's way,
 supposing that he must have robbed the man that came shouting
 after him in his shirt, and stopped him and apprehended him; and
 little indeed did it avail him to tell them who he was, and how the
 matter stood.  <milestone id="p09040022" />For up came Fortarrigo with a wrathful air, and:
 <q direct="unspecified">I know not,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">why I spare to kill thee on the spot,
 traitor, thief that thou art, thus to despoil me and give me the slip!</q>
 And then, turning to the peasants: <q direct="unspecified">You see, gentlemen,</q> quoth
 he, <q direct="unspecified">in what a trim he left me in the inn, after gambling away all
 that he had with him and on him. Well indeed may I say that
 under God 'tis to you I owe it that I have thus come by my own
 again: for which cause I shall ever be beholden to you.</q>  <milestone id="p09040023" />Angiulieri
 also had his say; but his words passed unheeded. Fortarrigo with
 the help of the peasants compelled him to dismount; and having
 stripped him, donned his clothes, mounted his horse, and leaving him
 barefoot and in his shirt, rode back to Siena, giving out on all hands
 that he had won the palfrey and the clothes from Angiulieri.  <milestone id="p09040024" />So
 Angiulieri, having thought to present himself to the cardinal in the
 March a wealthy man, returned to Buonconvento poor and in his
 shirt; and being ashamed for the time to shew himself in Siena,
 pledged the nag that Fortarrigo had ridden for a suit of clothes, and
 betook him to his kinsfolk at Corsignano, where he tarried, until he
 received a fresh supply of money from his father.  <milestone id="p09040025" />Thus, then,
 Fortarrigo's guile disconcerted Angiulieri's judicious purpose, albeit
 when time and occasion served, it was not left unrequited.</p></div2><pb n="282" /><div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov0905"><head>Novel V</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09050001" />Calandrino being enamoured of a damsel, Bruno gives
 him a scroll, averring that, if he but touch her therewith,
 she will go with him: he is found with her by his
 wife, who subjects him to a most severe and vexatious
 examination.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09050002" />So, at no great length, ended Neifile her story, which the
 company
 allowed to pass with none too much laughter or remark:
 whereupon the queen, turning to Fiammetta, bade her follow suit.
 Fiammetta, with mien most gladsome, made answer that she willingly
 obeyed, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09050003" />As I doubt not, ye know, ladies most
 debonair, be the topic of discourse never so well worn, it will still
 continue to please, if the speaker knows how to make due choice of
 time and occasion meet.  <milestone id="p09050004" />Wherefore, considering the reason for
 which we are here (how that 'tis to make merry and speed the time
 gaily, and that merely) I deem that there is nought that may afford
 us mirth and solace but here may find time and occasion meet, and,
 after serving a thousand turns of discourse, should still prove not
 unpleasing
 for another thousand.  <milestone id="p09050005" />Wherefore, notwithstanding that of
 Calandrino and his doings not a little has from time to time been
 said among us, yet, considering that, as a while ago Filostrato
 observed, there is nought that concerns him that is not entertaining,
 I will make bold to add to the preceding stories another, which I
 might well, had I been minded to deviate from the truth, have disguised,
 and so recounted it to you, under other names; but as whoso
 in telling a story diverges from the truth does thereby in no small
 measure diminish the delight of his hearers, I purpose for the reason
 aforesaid to give you the narrative in proper form.</p></div3><pb n="283" /><p><milestone id="p09050006" />Niccol&#242; Cornacchini, one of our citizens, and a man of wealth,
 had among other estates a fine one at Camerata, on which he had
 a grand house built, and engaged Bruno and Buffalmacco to paint it
 throughout; in which task, for that 'twas by no means light, they associated
 with them Nello and Calandrino, and so set to work.  <milestone id="p09050007" />There
 were a few rooms in the house provided with beds and other furniture,
 and an old female servant lived there as caretaker, but otherwise
 the house was unoccupied, for which cause Niccol&#242;'s son, Filippo,
 being
 a young man and a bachelor, was wont sometimes to bring thither a
 woman for his pleasure, and after keeping her there for a few days to
 escort her thence again.  <milestone id="p09050008" />Now on one of these occasions it befell
 that he brought thither one Niccolosa, whom a vile fellow, named
 Mangione, kept in a house at Camaldoli as a common prostitute.
  <milestone id="p09050009" />And a fine piece of flesh she was, and wore fine clothes, and, for
 one of her sort, knew how to comport herself becomingly and talk
 agreeably.</p><p>Now one day at high noon forth tripped the damsel from her
 chamber in a white gown, her locks braided about her head, to
 wash her hands and face at a well that was in the courtyard of the
 house, and, while she was so engaged, it befell that Calandrino came
 there for water, and greeted her familiarly.  <milestone id="p09050010" />Having returned his
 salutation, she, rather because Calandrino struck her as something
 out of the common, than for any other interest she felt in him,
 regarded him attentively. Calandrino did the like by her, and being
 smitten by her beauty, found reasons enough why he should not go
 back to his comrades with the water; but, as he knew not who she
 was, he made not bold to address her.  <milestone id="p09050011" />She, upon whom his gaze
 was not lost, being minded to amuse herself at his expense, let her
 glance from time to time rest upon him, while she heaved a slight
 sigh or two. Whereby Calandrino was forthwith captivated, and
 tarried in the courtyard, until Filippo called her back into the chamber.
  <milestone id="p09050012" />Returned to his work, Calandrino sighed like a furnace: which
 Bruno, who was ever regardful of his doings for the diversion they
 afforded him, failed not to mark, and by and by: <q direct="unspecified">What the
 Devil is amiss with thee, comrade Calandrino?</q> quoth he. <q direct="unspecified">Thou
 dost nought but puff and blow.</q>  <milestone id="p09050013" /><q direct="unspecified">Comrade,</q> replied Calandrino,
 <q direct="unspecified">I should be in luck, had I but one to help me.</q> <milestone id="p09050014" /><q direct="unspecified">How so?</q>
 quoth Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050015" /><q direct="unspecified">Why,</q> returned Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not to go farther,
 <pb n="284" />but there is a damsel below, fairer than a lamia, and so mightily in
 love with me that 'twould astonish thee. I observed it but now,
 when I went to fetch the water.</q>  <milestone id="p09050016" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but, Calandrino, make
 sure she be not Filippo's wife,</q> quoth Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050017" /><q direct="unspecified">I doubt 'tis even
 so,</q> replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">for he called her and she joined him in the
 chamber; but what signifies it? I would circumvent Christ Himself
 in such case, not to say Filippo. Of a truth, comrade, I tell thee
 she pleases me I could not say how.</q>  <milestone id="p09050018" /><q direct="unspecified">Comrade,</q> returned Bruno,
 <q direct="unspecified">I will find out for thee who she is, and if she be Filippo's wife, two
 words from me will make it all straight for thee, for she is much my
 friend. But how shall we prevent Buffalmacco knowing it? I can
 never have a word with her, but he is with me.</q>  <milestone id="p09050019" /><q direct="unspecified">As to Buffalmacco,</q>
 replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">I care not if he do know it; but let
 us make sure that it come not to Nello's ears, for he is of kin to
 Monna Tessa, and would spoil it all.</q>  <milestone id="p09050020" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Thou art in
 the right,</q> returned Bruno.</p><p><milestone id="p09050021" />Now Bruno knew what the damsel was, for he had seen her
 arrive, and moreover Filippo had told him. So, Calandrino having
 given over working for a while, and betaken him to her, Bruno
 acquainted Nello and Buffalmacco with the whole story; and thereupon
 they privily concerted how to entreat him in regard of this love
 affair.  <milestone id="p09050022" />Wherefore, upon his return, quoth Bruno softly: <q direct="unspecified">Didst
 see her?</q>  <milestone id="p09050023" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, woe's me!</q> replied Calandrino: <q direct="unspecified">she has
 stricken me to the death.</q>  <milestone id="p09050024" />Quoth Bruno: <q direct="unspecified">I will go see if she
 be the lady I take her to be, and if I find that 'tis so, leave the
 rest to me.</q>  <milestone id="p09050025" />Whereupon down went Bruno, and found Filippo and
 the damsel, and fully apprised them what sort of fellow Calandrino
 was, and what he had told them, and concerted with them what
 each should do and say, that they might have a merry time together
	over Calandrino's love affair. <milestone id="p09050026" />He then rejoined Calandrino, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">'Tis the very same; and therefore the affair needs very delicate
 handling, for, if Filippo were but ware thereof, not all Arno's waters
 would suffice to cleanse us. However, what should I say to her
 from thee, if by chance I should get speech of her?</q>  <milestone id="p09050027" /><q direct="unspecified">I' faith,</q>
 replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">why, first, first of all, thou wilt tell her that I
 wish her a thousand bushels of the good seed of generation, and then
 that I am her servant, and if she is fain of--aught--thou tak'st
 me?</q>  <milestone id="p09050028" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay,</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">leave it to me.</q></p><pb n="285" /><p><milestone id="p09050029" />Supper-time came; and, the day's work done, they went down
 into the courtyard, Filippo and Niccolosa being there, and there
 they tarried a while to advance Calandrino's suit. Calandrino's gaze
 was soon riveted on Niccolosa, and such and so strange and startling
 were the gestures that he made that they would have given sight to
 the blind.  <milestone id="p09050030" />She on her part used all her arts to inflame his passion,
 primed as she had been by Bruno, and diverted beyond measure as
 she was by Calandrino's antics, while Filippo, Buffalmacco and the
 rest feigned to be occupied in converse, and to see nought of what
 passed.  <milestone id="p09050031" />However, after a while, to Calandrino's extreme disgust, they
 took their leave; and as they bent their steps towards Florence:
 <q direct="unspecified">I warrant thee,</q> quoth Bruno to Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">she wastes away
 for thee like ice in the sunlight; by the body o' God, if thou
 wert to bring thy rebeck, and sing her one or two of thy love-songs,
 she'd throw herself out of window to be with thee.</q>  <milestone id="p09050032" />Quoth Calandrino:
 <q direct="unspecified">Think'st thou, comrade, think'st thou, 'twere well I
 brought it?</q>  <milestone id="p09050033" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, indeed,</q> returned Bruno. 
 <milestone id="p09050034" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Ah! comrade,</q> quoth Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">so thou wouldst not believe
 me when I told thee to-day? Of a truth I perceive there's ne'er
 another knows so well what he would be at as I.  <milestone id="p09050035" />Who but I
 would have known how so soon to win the love of a lady like that?
 Lucky indeed might they deem themselves, if they did it, those
 young gallants that go about, day and night, up and down, a strumming
 on the one-stringed viol, and would not know how to gather
 a handful of nuts once in a millennium. Mayst thou be by to see
 when I bring her the rebeck! thou wilt see fine sport.  <milestone id="p09050036" />List well
 what I say: I am not so old as I look; and she knows it right well:
 ay, and anyhow I will soon let her know it, when I come to grapple
 her. By the very body of Christ I will have such sport with her,
 that she will follow me as any love-sick maid follows her swain.</q>
  <milestone id="p09050037" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> quoth Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">I doubt not thou wilt make her thy prey:
 and I seem to see thee bite her dainty vermeil mouth and her cheeks,
 that shew as twin roses, with thy teeth, that are as so many lute-pegs,
 and afterwards devour her bodily.</q>  <milestone id="p09050038" />So encouraged, Calandrino
 fancied himself already in action, and went about singing and capering
 in such high glee that 'twas as if he would burst his skin.  <milestone id="p09050039" />And so
 next day he brought the rebeck, and to the no small amusement
 of all the company sang several songs to her. And, in short, by
 <pb n="286" />frequently seeing her, he waxed so mad with passion that he gave
 over working; and a thousand times a day he would run now to the
 window, now to the door, and anon to the courtyard on the chance
 of catching sight of her; nor did she, astutely following Bruno's
 instructions, fail to afford him abundance of opportunity.  <milestone id="p09050040" />Bruno
 played the go-between, bearing him her answers to all his messages,
 and sometimes bringing him messages from her. When she was not
 at home, which was most frequently the case, he would send him
 letters from her, in which she gave great encouragement to his hopes,
 at the same time giving him to understand that she was at the house
 of her kinsfolk, where as yet he might not visit her.</p><p><milestone id="p09050041" />On this wise Bruno and Buffalmacco so managed the affair as to
 divert themselves inordinately, causing him to send her, as at her
 request, now an ivory comb, now a purse, now a little knife, and
 other such dainty trifles; in return for which they brought him, now
 and again, a counterfeit ring of no value, with which Calandrino was
 marvellously pleased. And Calandrino, to stimulate their zeal in his
 interest, would entertain them hospitably at table, and otherwise
 flatter them.  <milestone id="p09050042" />Now, when they had thus kept him in play for two
 good months, and the affair was just where it had been, Calandrino,
 seeing that the work was coming to an end, and bethinking him that,
 if it did so before he had brought his love affair to a successful issue,
 he must give up all hopes of ever so doing, began to be very instant
 and importunate with Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050043" />So, in the presence of the damsel, and
 by preconcert with her and Filippo, quoth Bruno to Calandrino:
 <q direct="unspecified">Harkye, comrade, this lady has vowed to me a thousand times that
 she will do as thou wouldst have her, and as, for all that, she does
 nought to pleasure thee, I am of opinion that she leads thee by the
 nose: wherefore, as she keeps not her promises, we will make her
 do so, willy-nilly, if thou art so minded.</q>  <milestone id="p09050044" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but, for the love
 of God, so be it,</q> replied Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">and that speedily.</q>
	<milestone id="p09050045" /><q direct="unspecified">Darest
 thou touch her, then, with a scroll that I shall give thee?</q> quoth
 Bruno.  <milestone id="p09050046" /><q direct="unspecified">I dare,</q> replied Calandrino. 
 <milestone id="p09050047" /><q direct="unspecified">Fetch me, then,</q> quoth
 Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">a bit of the skin of an unborn lamb, a live bat, three grains of
 incense, and a blessed candle; and leave the rest to me.</q>  <milestone id="p09050048" />To catch
 the bat taxed all Calandrino's art and craft for the whole of the evening;
 but having at length taken him, he brought him with the other
 matters to Bruno: who, having withdrawn into a room by himself,
 <pb n="287" />wrote on the skin some cabalistic jargon, and handed it to him,
 saying:  <milestone id="p09050049" /><q direct="unspecified">Know, Calandrino, that, if thou touch her with this
 scroll, she will follow thee forthwith, and do whatever thou shalt
 wish. Wherefore, should Filippo go abroad to-day, get thee somehow
 up to her, and touch her; and then go into the barn that is
 hereby--'tis the best place we have, for never a soul goes there--and
 thou wilt see that she will come there too. When she is there, thou
 wottest well what to do.</q>  <milestone id="p09050050" />Calandrino, overjoyed as ne'er another,
 took the scroll, saying only: <q direct="unspecified">Comrade, leave that to me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09050051" />Now Nello, whom Calandrino mistrusted, entered with no less
 zest than the others into the affair, and was their confederate for
 Calandrino's discomfiture; accordingly by Bruno's direction he hied
 to Florence, and finding Monna Tessa:  <milestone id="p09050052" /><q direct="unspecified">Thou hast scarce forgotten,
 Tessa,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">what a beating Calandrino gave thee,
 without the least cause, that day when he came home with the stones
 from Mugnone; for which I would have thee be avenged, and, so
 thou wilt not, call me no more kinsman or friend. He is fallen in
 love with a lady up there, who is abandoned enough to go closeting
 herself not seldom with him, and 'tis but a short while since they
 made assignation to forgather forthwith: so I would have thee go
 there, and surprise him in the act, and give him a sound trouncing.</q>
  <milestone id="p09050053" />Which when the lady heard, she deemed it no laughing matter; but
 started up and broke out with: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, the arrant knave! is't thus
 he treats me? By the Holy Rood, never fear but I will pay him
 out!</q>  <milestone id="p09050054" />And wrapping herself in her cloak, and taking a young woman
 with her for companion, she sped more at a run than at a walk, escorted
 by Nello, up to Camerata. Bruno, espying her from afar, said to
 Filippo: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, here comes our friend.</q>  <milestone id="p09050055" />Whereupon Filippo went
 to the place where Calandrino and the others were at work, and
 said: <q direct="unspecified">My masters, I must needs go at once to Florence; slacken
 not on that account.</q> And so off he went, and hid himself where,
 unobserved, he might see what Calandrino would do.  <milestone id="p09050056" />Calandrino
 waited only until he saw that Filippo was at some distance, and then
 he went down into the courtyard, where he found Niccolosa alone,
 and fell a talking with her. She, knowing well what she had to do,
 drew close to him, and shewed him a little more familiarity than she
 was wont: whereupon Calandrino touched her with the scroll,  <milestone id="p09050057" />and
 having so done, saying never a word, bent his steps towards the
 <pb n="288" />barn, whither Niccolosa followed him, and being entered, shut the
 door, and forthwith embraced him, threw him down on the straw
 that lay there, and got astride of him, and holding him fast by the
 arms about the shoulders, suffered him not to approach his face to
 hers, but gazing upon him, as if he were the delight of her heart:
  <milestone id="p09050058" /><q direct="unspecified">O Calandrino, sweet my Calandrino,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">heart of my
 body, my very soul, my bliss, my consolation, ah! how long have I
 yearned to hold thee in my arms and have thee all my own! Thy
 endearing ways have utterly disarmed me; thou hast made prize of
 my heart with thy rebeck. Do I indeed hold thee in mine embrace?</q>
  <milestone id="p09050059" />Calandrino, scarce able to move, murmured: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! sweet
 my soul, suffer me to kiss thee.</q>  <milestone id="p09050060" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but thou art
 too hasty,</q> replied Niccolosa. <q direct="unspecified">Let me first feast mine eyes on
 thee; let me but sate them with this sweet face of thine.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09050061" />Meanwhile Bruno and Buffalmacco had joined Filippo, so that
 what passed was seen and heard by all three. And while Calandrino
 was thus intent to kiss Niccolosa, lo, up came Nello with Monna
 Tessa. <q direct="unspecified">By God, I swear they are both there,</q> ejaculated Nello,  <milestone id="p09050062" />as
 they entered the doorway; but the lady, now fairly furious, laid hold
 of him and thrust him aside, and rushing in, espied Niccolosa astride
 of Calandrino. Niccolosa no sooner caught sight of the lady, than
 up she jumped, and in a trice was beside Filippo.  <milestone id="p09050063" />Monna Tessa fell
 upon Calandrino, who was still on the floor, planted her nails in his
 face, and scratched it all over: she then seized him by the hair, and
 haling him to and fro about the barn: <q direct="unspecified">Foul, pestilent cur,</q> quoth
 she, <q direct="unspecified">is this the way thou treatest me? Thou old fool! A murrain
 on the love I have borne thee! Hast thou not enough to do at
 home, that thou must needs go falling in love with strange women?
  <milestone id="p09050064" />And a fine lover thou wouldst make! Dost not know thyself,
 knave? Dost not know thyself, wretch? Thou, from whose whole
 body 'twere not possible to wring enough sap for a sauce! God's
 faith, 'twas not Tessa that got thee with child: God's curse on her,
 whoever she was: verily she must be a poor creature to be enamoured
 of a jewel of thy rare quality.</q>  <milestone id="p09050065" />At sight of his wife, Calandrino,
 suspended, as it were, between life and death, ventured no defence; but,
 his face torn to shreds, his hair and clothes all disordered, fumbled about
 for his capuche, which having found, up he got, and humbly besought
 his wife not to publish the matter, unless she were minded that he
 <pb n="289" />should be cut to pieces, for that she that was with him was the wife
 of the master of the house. <q direct="unspecified">Then God give her a bad year,</q>
 replied the lady.  <milestone id="p09050066" />Whereupon Bruno and Buffalmacco, who by this
 time had laughed their fill with Filippo and Niccolosa, came up as if
 attracted by the noise; and after not a little ado pacified the lady,
 and counselled Calandrino to go back to Florence, and stay there,
 lest Filippo should get wind of the affair, and do him a mischief.
  <milestone id="p09050067" />So Calandrino, crestfallen and woebegone, got him back to Florence
 with his face torn to shreds; where, daring not to shew himself at
 Camerata again, he endured day and night the grievous torment of
 his wife's vituperation. Such was the issue, to which, after ministering
 not a little mirth to his comrades, as also to Niccolosa and Filippo,
 this ardent lover brought his amour.</p></div2><pb n="290" /><div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0906"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09060001" />Two young men lodge at an inn, of whom the one lies with
 the host's daughter, his wife by inadvertence lying
 with the other. He that lay with the daughter afterwards
 gets into her father's bed and tells him all,
 taking him to be his comrade. They bandy words:
 whereupon the good woman, apprehending the circumstances,
 gets her to bed with her daughter, and by
 divers apt words re-establishes perfect accord.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09060002" />Calandrino as on former occasions, so also on this, moved the
 company to laughter. However, when the ladies had done talking
 of his doings, the queen called for a story from Pamfilo, who thus
 spoke:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09060003" />Worshipful ladies, this Niccolosa, that Calandrino loved,
 has brought to my mind a story of another Niccolosa; which I am
 minded to tell you, because 'twill shew you how a good woman
 by her quick apprehension avoided a great scandal.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09060004" />In the plain of Mugnone there was not long ago a good man that
 furnished travellers with meat and drink for money, and, for that he
 was in poor circumstances, and had but a little house, gave not lodging
 to every comer, but only to a few that he knew, and if they were
 hard bested.  <milestone id="p09060005" />Now the good man had to wife a very fine woman,
 and by her had two children, to wit, a pretty and winsome girl of
 some fifteen or sixteen summers, as yet unmarried, and a little
 boy, not yet one year old, whom the mother suckled at her own
 breast.  <milestone id="p09060006" />The girl had found favour in the eyes of a goodly and
 mannerly young gentleman of our city, who was not seldom in those
 parts, and loved her to the point of passion. And she, being mightily
 flattered to be loved by such a gallant, studied how to comport herself
 <pb n="291" />so
 debonairly as to retain his regard, and while she did so, grew
 likewise enamoured of him; and divers times, by consent of both
 their love had had its fruition, but that Pinuccio--such was the
 gallant's name--shrank from the disgrace that 'twould bring upon
 the girl and himself alike.  <milestone id="p09060007" />But, as his passion daily waxed apace,
 Pinuccio, yearning to find himself abed with her, bethought him that
 he were best contrive to lodge with her father, deeming, from what
 he knew of her father's economy, that, if he did so, he might effect
 his purpose, and never a soul be the wiser: which idea no sooner
 struck him, than he set about carrying it into effect.</p><p><milestone id="p09060008" />So, late one evening Pinuccio and a trusty comrade, Adriano by
 name, to whom he had confided his love, hired two nags, and having
 set upon them two valises, filled with straw or such-like stuff, sallied
 forth of Florence, and rode by a circuitous route to the plain of
 Mugnone, which they reached after nightfall;  <milestone id="p09060009" />and having fetched a
 compass, so that it might seem as if they were coming from Romagna,
 they rode up to the good man's house, and knocked at the door.
 The good man, knowing them both very well, opened to them forthwith:
 whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Thou must even put us up to-night,</q> quoth
 Pinuccio; <q direct="unspecified">we thought to get into Florence, but, for all the speed
 we could make, we are but arrived here, as thou seest, at this hour.</q>
  <milestone id="p09060010" /><q direct="unspecified">Pinuccio,</q> replied the host, <q direct="unspecified">thou well knowest that I can but
 make a sorry shift to lodge gentlemen like you; but yet, as night
 has overtaken you here, and time serves not to betake you elsewhere,
 I will gladly give you such accommodation as I may.</q>  <milestone id="p09060011" />The two
 gallants then dismounted and entered the inn, and having first looked
 to their horses, brought out some supper that they had carried with
 them, and supped with the host.</p><p>Now the host had but one little bedroom, in which were three
 beds, set, as conveniently as he could contrive, two on one side of the
 room, and the third on the opposite side, but, for all that, there was
 scarce room enough to pass through.  <milestone id="p09060012" />The host had the least discomfortable
 of the three beds made up for the two friends; and having
 quartered them there, some little while afterwards, both being awake,
 but feigning to be asleep, he caused his daughter to get into one of
 the other two beds, while he and his wife took their places in the
 third, the good woman setting the cradle, in which was her little boy,
 beside the bed.  <milestone id="p09060013" />Such, then, being the partition made of the beds,
 <pb n="292" />Pinuccio,
 who had taken exact note thereof, waited only until he
 deemed all but himself to be asleep, and then got softly up and stole
 to the bed in which lay his beloved, and laid himself beside her; and
 she according him albeit a timorous yet a gladsome welcome, he
 stayed there, taking with her that solace of which both were most
 fain.</p><p><milestone id="p09060014" />Pinuccio being thus with the girl, it chanced that certain things,
 being overset by a cat, fell with a noise that aroused the good woman,
 who, fearing that it might be a matter of more consequence, got up
 as best she might in the dark, and betook her to the place whence the
 noise seemed to proceed.  <milestone id="p09060015" />At the same time Adriano, not by reason
 of the noise, which he heeded not, but perchance to answer the call of
 nature, also got up, and questing about for a convenient place, came
 upon the cradle beside the good woman's bed; and not being able
 otherwise to go by, took it up, and set it beside his own bed, and
 when he had accomplished his purpose, went back, and giving never
 a thought to the cradle got him to bed.  <milestone id="p09060016" />The good woman searched
 until she found that the accident was no such matter as she had
 supposed; so without troubling to strike a light to investigate it
 further, she reproved the cat, and returned to the room, and groped
 her way straight to the bed in which her husband lay asleep; but not
 finding the cradle there, quoth she to herself: Alas! blunderer that
 I am, what was I about? God's faith! I was going straight to the
 guests' bed;  <milestone id="p09060017" />and proceeding a little further, she found the cradle, and
 laid herself down by Adriano in the bed that was beside it, taking
 Adriano for her husband; and Adriano, who was still awake, received
 her with all due benignity, and tackled her more than once to her
 no small delight.</p><p><milestone id="p09060018" />Meanwhile Pinuccio fearing lest sleep should overtake him while
 he was yet with his mistress, and having satisfied his desire, got up
 and left her, to return to his bed; but when he got there, coming
 upon the cradle, he supposed that 'twas the host's bed; and so going
 a little further, he laid him down beside the host, who thereupon
 awoke.  <milestone id="p09060019" />Supposing that he had Adriano beside him: <q direct="unspecified">I warrant
 thee,</q> quoth Pinuccio to the host, <q direct="unspecified">there was never so sweet a piece
 of flesh as Niccolosa: by the body of God, such delight have I had
 of her as never had man of woman; and, mark me, since I left thee,
 I have gotten me up to the farm some six times.</q>  <milestone id="p09060020" />Which tidings <pb n="293" />the
 host being none too well pleased to learn, said first of all to
 himself: What the Devil does this fellow here? Then, his
 resentment getting the better of his prudence: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis a gross affront
 thou hast put upon me, Pinuccio,</q> quoth he; <q direct="unspecified">nor know I what
 occasion thou hast to do me such a wrong; but by the body of God
 I will pay thee out.</q>  <milestone id="p09060021" />Pinuccio, who was not the most discreet of
 gallants, albeit he was now apprised of his error, instead of doing his
 best to repair it, retorted: <q direct="unspecified">And how wilt thou pay me out?
 What canst thou do?</q>  <milestone id="p09060022" /><q direct="unspecified">Hark what high words our guests are at
 together!</q> quoth meanwhile the host's wife to Adriano, deeming
 that she spoke to her husband.  <milestone id="p09060023" /><q direct="unspecified">Let them be,</q> replied Adriano
 with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">God give them a bad year: they drank too much
 yestereve.</q>  <milestone id="p09060024" />The good woman had already half recognized her
 husband's angry tones, and now that she heard Adriano's voice, she
 at once knew where she was and with whom. Accordingly, being
 a discreet woman, she started up, and saying never a word, took her
 child's cradle, and, though there was not a ray of light in the room,
 bore it, divining rather than feeling her way, to the side of the bed
 in which her daughter slept;  <milestone id="p09060025" />and then, as if aroused by the noise
 made by her husband, she called him, and asked what he and
 Pinuccio were bandying words about. <q direct="unspecified">Hearest thou not,</q> replied
 the husband, <q direct="unspecified">what he says he has this very night done to
 Niccolosa?</q> <q direct="unspecified">Tush! he lies in the throat,</q>  <milestone id="p09060026" />returned the good
 woman: <q direct="unspecified">he has not lain with Niccolosa; for what time he might
 have done so, I laid me beside her myself, and I have been wide
 awake ever since; and thou art a fool to believe him. You men
 take so many cups before going to bed that then you dream, and
 walk in your sleep, and imagine wonders. 'Tis a great pity you do
 not break your necks. What does Pinuccio there? Why keeps he
 not in his own bed?</q></p><p><milestone id="p09060027" /> <milestone />Whereupon Adriano, in his turn, seeing how adroitly the good
 woman cloaked her own and her daughter's shame: <q direct="unspecified">Pinuccio,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I have told thee a hundred times, that thou shouldst not
 walk about at night; for this thy bad habit of getting up in thy
 dreams and relating thy dreams for truth will get thee into a scrape
 some time or another: come back, and God send thee a bad night.</q>
  <milestone id="p09060028" />Hearing Adriano thus confirm what his wife had said, the host began
 to think that Pinuccio must be really dreaming; so he took him by <pb n="294" />the
 shoulder, and fell a shaking him, and calling him by his name,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">Pinuccio, wake up, and go back to thy bed.</q>  <milestone id="p09060029" />Pinuccio,
 taking his cue from what he had heard, began as a dreamer would be
 like to do, to talk wanderingly; whereat the host laughed amain.
 Then, feigning to be aroused by the shaking, Pinuccio uttered
 Adriano's name, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Is't already day, that thou callest me?</q>
  <milestone id="p09060030" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, 'tis so,</q> quoth Adriano: <q direct="unspecified">come hither.</q> 
 <milestone id="p09060031" />Whereupon Pinuccio,
 making as if he were mighty drowsy, got him up from beside the host,
 and back to bed with Adriano. On the morrow, when they were
 risen, the host fell a laughing and making merry touching Pinuccio and
 his dreams.  <milestone id="p09060032" />And so the jest passed from mouth to mouth, while the
 gallants' horses were groomed and saddled, and their valises adjusted:
 which done, they drank with the host, mounted and rode to Florence,
 no less pleased with the manner than with the matter of the night's
 adventure.  <milestone id="p09060033" />Nor, afterwards, did Pinuccio fail to find other means of
 meeting Niccolosa, who assured her mother that he had unquestionably
 dreamed. For which cause the good woman, calling to mind
 Adriano's embrace, accounted herself the only one that had watched.</p></div2><pb n="295" /><div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0907"><head>Novel VII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09070001" />Talano di Molese dreams that a wolf tears and rends all
 the neck and face of his wife: he gives her warning
 thereof, which she heeds not, and the dream comes
 true.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09070002" />When Pamfilo had brought his story to a close, and all had
 commended
 the good woman's quick perception, the queen bade Pampinea
 tell hers; and thus Pampinea began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09070003" />A while ago, debonair my
 ladies, we held discourse of the truths that dreams shew forth, which
 not a few of us deride; for which cause, albeit the topic has been
 handled before, I shall not spare to tell you that which not long ago
 befell a neighbour of mine, for that she disbelieved a dream that her
 husband had.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09070004" />I wot not if you knew Talano di Molese, a man right worthy to
 be had in honour; who, having married a young wife--Margarita
 by name--fair as e'er another, but without her match for whimsical,
 fractious, and perverse humours, insomuch that there was nought she
 would do at the instance of another, either for his or her own good,
 found her behaviour most grievous to bear, but was fain to endure
 what he might not cure.  <milestone id="p09070005" />Now it so befell that Talano and
 Margarita being together at an estate that Talano had in the contado,
 he, sleeping, saw in a dream a very beautiful wood that was on the
 estate at no great distance from the house, and his lady there walking.
  <milestone id="p09070006" />And as she went, there leapt forth upon her a huge and fierce wolf that
 griped her by the throat, and bore her down to the ground, and (she
 shrieking the while for succour) would have carried her off by main
 force; but she got quit of his jaws, albeit her neck and face shewed as
 quite disfigured.  <milestone id="p09070007" />On the morrow, as soon as he was risen, Talano said
 <pb n="296" />to
 his wife: <q direct="unspecified">Albeit for thy perversity I have not yet known a single
 good day with thee, yet I should be sorry, wife, that harm should
 befall thee; and therefore, if thou take my advice, thou wilt not stir
 out of doors to-day.</q> <q direct="unspecified">Wherefore?</q> quoth the lady; and thereupon
 he recounted to her all his dream.</p><p><milestone id="p09070008" />The lady shook her head, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Who means ill, dreams ill.
 Thou makest as if thou wast mighty tender of me, but thou bodest of
 me in thy dream that which thou wouldst fain see betide me. I
 warrant thee that to-day and all days I will have a care to avoid
 this or any other calamity that might gladden thy heart.</q>  <milestone id="p09070009" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Well wist I,</q> replied Talano, <q direct="unspecified">that thou wouldst so say,
 for such is ever the requital of those that comb scurfy heads; but
 whatever thou mayst be pleased to believe, I for my part speak to
 thee for thy good, and again I advise thee to keep indoors to-day, or
 at least not to walk in the wood.</q>  <milestone id="p09070010" /><q direct="unspecified">Good,</q> returned the lady, <q direct="unspecified">I
 will look to it,</q> and then she began communing with herself on this
 wise: Didst mark how artfully he thinks to have scared me from
 going into the wood to-day? Doubtless 'tis that he has an assignation
 there with some light o' love, with whom he had rather I did not
 find him. Ah! he would sup well with the blind, and what a fool
 were I to believe him! But I warrant he will be disappointed, and
 needs must I, though I stay there all day long, see what commerce it
 is that he will adventure in to-day.</p><p><milestone id="p09070011" />Having so said, she quitted the house on one side, while her
 husband did so on the other; and forthwith, shunning observation as
 best she might, she hied her to the wood, and hid her where 'twas
 most dense, and there waited on the alert, and glancing, now this
 way and now that, to see if any were coming.  <milestone id="p09070012" />And while thus she
 stood, nor ever a thought of a wolf crossed her mind, lo, forth of
 a close covert hard by came a wolf of monstrous size and appalling
 aspect, and scarce had she time to say, God help me! before he sprang
 upon her and griped her by the throat so tightly that she might not
 utter a cry, but, passive as any lambkin, was borne off by him,  <milestone id="p09070013" />and
 had certainly been strangled, had he not encountered some shepherds,
 who with shouts compelled him to let her go. The shepherds
 recognized the poor hapless woman, and bore her home, where the
 physicians by dint of long and careful treatment cured her; howbeit
 the whole of her throat and part of her face remained so disfigured
 <pb n="297" />that,
 fair as she had been before, she was ever thereafter most foul
 and hideous to look upon.  <milestone id="p09070014" />Wherefore, being ashamed to shew her
 face, she did many a time bitterly deplore her perversity, in that, when
 it would have cost her nothing, she would nevertheless pay no heed
 to the true dream of her husband.</p></div2><pb n="298" /><div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0908"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09080001" />Biondello gulls Ciacco in the matter of a breakfast: for
 which prank Ciacco is cunningly avenged on Biondello,
 causing him to be shamefully beaten.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09080002" />All the company by common consent pronounced it no dream
 but a vision that Talano had had in his sleep, so exactly, no circumstance
 lacking, had it fallen out according as he had seen it. However,
 as soon as all had done speaking, the queen bade Lauretta
 follow suit; which Lauretta did on this wise:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09080003" />As, most discreet
 my ladies, those that have preceded me to-day have almost all taken
 their cue from somewhat that has been said before, so, prompted by
 the stern vengeance taken by the scholar in Pampinea's narrative of
 yesterday, I am minded to tell you of a vengeance that was indeed
 less savage, but for all that grievous enough to him on whom it was
 wreaked.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09080004" />Wherefore I say that there was once at Florence one that all
 folk called Ciacco, a man second to none that ever lived for inordinate
 gluttony, who, lacking the means to support the expenditure
 which his gluttony demanded, and being, for the rest, well-mannered
 and well furnished with excellent and merry jests, did, without turning
 exactly court jester, cultivate a somewhat biting wit, and loved
 to frequent the houses of the rich, and such as kept good tables;
 whither, bidden or unbidden, he not seldom resorted for breakfast or
 supper.  <milestone id="p09080005" />There was also in those days at Florence one that was called
 Biondello, a man very short of stature, and not a little debonair, more
 trim than any fly, with his blond locks surmounted by a coif, and
 never a hair out of place; and he and Ciacco were two of a trade.</p><p><milestone id="p09080006" />Now one morning in Lent Biondello, being in the fish-market
 purchasing two mighty fat lampreys for Messer Vieri de' Cerchi, was
 <pb n="299" />observed
 thus engaged by Ciacco, who came up to him, and:
 <q direct="unspecified">What means this?</q> quoth he.  <milestone id="p09080007" /><q direct="unspecified">Why,</q> replied Biondello, <q direct="unspecified">'tis
 that yestereve Messer Corso Donati had three lampreys much finer
 than these and a sturgeon sent to his house, but as they did not
 suffice for a breakfast that he is to give certain gentlemen, he has
 commissioned me to buy him these two beside. Wilt thou not be
	there?</q> <milestone id="p09080008" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, marry, that will I,</q> returned Ciacco.  
<milestone id="p09080009" />And in what
 he deemed due time he hied him to Messer Corso Donati's house, where
 he found him with some of his neighbours not yet gone to breakfast.
 And being asked by Messer Corso with what intent he was come,
 he answered: <q direct="unspecified">I am come, Sir, to breakfast with you and your
 company.</q>  <milestone id="p09080010" /><q direct="unspecified">And welcome art thou,</q> returned Messer Corso, <q direct="unspecified">go
 we then to breakfast, for 'tis now the time.</q>  <milestone id="p09080011" />So to table they went,
 where nought was set before them but pease and the inward part of
 the tunny salted, and afterwards the common fish of the Arno fried.
 Wherefore Ciacco, not a little wroth at the trick that he perceived
 Biondello had played him, resolved to pay him out. And not many
 days after Biondello, who had meanwhile had many a laugh with his
 friends over Ciacco's discomfiture,  <milestone id="p09080012" />met him, and after greeting him,
 asked him with a laugh what Messer Corso's lampreys had been like.
 <q direct="unspecified">That question,</q> replied Ciacco, <q direct="unspecified">thou wilt be able to answer much
 better than I before eight days are gone by.</q>  <milestone id="p09080013" />And parting from
 Biondello upon the word, he went forthwith and hired a cozening
 rogue, and having thrust a glass bottle into his hand, brought him
 within sight of the Loggia de' Cavicciuli; and there, pointing to a
 knight, one Messer Filippo Argenti, a tall man and stout, and of
 a high courage, and haughty, choleric and cross-grained as ne'er
 another, he said to him:  <milestone id="p09080014" /><q direct="unspecified">Thou wilt go, flask in hand, to Messer
 Filippo, and wilt say to him: 'I am sent to you, Sir, by Biondello,
 who entreats you to be pleased to colour this flask for him with some
 of your good red wine, for that he is minded to have a good time with
 his catamites.' And of all things have a care that he lay not hands
 upon thee, for he would make thee rue the day, and would spoil my
 sport.</q>  <milestone id="p09080015" /><q direct="unspecified">Have I aught else to say?</q> enquired the rogue.
  <milestone id="p09080016" /><q direct="unspecified">Nothing
 more,</q> returned Ciacco: <q direct="unspecified">and now get thee gone, and when thou
 hast delivered the message, bring me back the flask, and I will pay
 thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09080017" />So away went the rogue, and did the errand to Messer Filippo, <pb n="300" />who
 forthwith, being a hasty man, jumped to the conclusion that
 Biondello, whom he knew, was making mock of him, and while an
 angry flush overspread his face: <q direct="unspecified">'Colour the flask, forsooth!'</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">and 'Catamites!' God send thee and him a bad year!</q>
 and therewith up he started, and reached forward to lay hold of the
 rogue,  <milestone id="p09080018" />who, being on the alert, gave him the slip and was off, and
 reported Messer Filippo's answer to Ciacco, who had observed what
 had passed.  <milestone id="p09080019" />Having paid the rogue, Ciacco rested not until he had
 found Biondello, to whom: <q direct="unspecified">Wast thou but now,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">at
 the Loggia de' Cavicciuli?</q>  <milestone id="p09080020" /><q direct="unspecified">Indeed no,</q> replied Biondello:
 <q direct="unspecified">wherefore
 such a question?</q>  <milestone id="p09080021" /><q direct="unspecified">Because,</q> returned Ciacco, <q direct="unspecified">I may tell
 thee that thou art sought for by Messer Filippo, for what cause I know
 not.</q>  <milestone id="p09080022" /><q direct="unspecified">Good,</q> quoth Biondello, <q direct="unspecified">I will go thither and speak with
 him.</q>  <milestone id="p09080023" />So away went Biondello, and Ciacco followed him to see
 what course the affair would take.</p><p>Now having failed to catch the rogue, Messer Filippo was still
 very wroth, and inly fumed and fretted, being unable to make out
 aught from what the rogue had said save that Biondello was set on
 by some one or another to flout him. And while thus he vexed his
 spirit, up came Biondello; whom he no sooner espied than he made
 for him, and dealt him a mighty blow in the face, and tore his hair
 and coif, and cast his capuche on the ground,  <milestone id="p09080024" />and to his <q direct="unspecified">Alas, Sir,
 what means this?</q>  <milestone id="p09080025" />still beating him amain: <q direct="unspecified">Traitor,</q> cried he; <q direct="unspecified">I
 will give thee to know what it means to send me such a message.
 'Colour the flask,' forsooth, and 'Catamites!' Dost take me for a
 stripling, to be befooled by thee?</q>  <milestone id="p09080026" />And therewith he pummelled
 Biondello's face all over with a pair of fists that were liker to iron
 than aught else, until it was but a mass of bruises; he also tore and
 dishevelled all his hair, tumbled him in the mud, rent all his clothes
 upon his back, and that without allowing him breathing-space to ask
 why he thus used him, or so much as utter a word. <q direct="unspecified">Colour me
 the flask!</q> and <q direct="unspecified">Catamites!</q> rang in his ears;  <milestone id="p09080027" />but what the
 words signified he knew not.  <milestone id="p09080028" />In the end very badly beaten, and in
 very sorry and ragged trim, many folk having gathered around them,
 they, albeit not without the utmost difficulty, rescued him from
 Messer Filippo's hands, and told him why Messer Filippo had thus
 used him, censuring him for sending him such a message, and adding
 that thenceforth he would know Messer Filippo better, and that he <pb n="301" />was
 not a man to be trifled with.  <milestone id="p09080029" />Biondello told them in tearful
 exculpation that he had never sent for wine to Messer Filippo:
 then, when they had put him in a little better trim, crestfallen and
 woebegone, he went home imputing his misadventure to Ciacco.
  <milestone id="p09080030" />And when, many days afterwards, the marks of his ill-usage being
 gone from his face, he began to go abroad again, it chanced that
 Ciacco met him, and with a laugh: <q direct="unspecified">Biondello,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">how
 didst thou relish Messer Filippo's wine?</q>  <milestone id="p09080031" /><q direct="unspecified">Why, as to that,</q>
 replied Biondello, <q direct="unspecified">would thou hadst relished the lampreys of Messer
 Corso as much!</q>  <milestone id="p09080032" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> returned Ciacco, <q direct="unspecified">such meat as thou then
 gavest me, thou mayst henceforth give me, as often as thou art so
 minded; and I will give thee even such drink as I have given thee.</q>
  <milestone id="p09080033" />So Biondello, witting that against Ciacco his might was not equal to
 his spite, prayed God for his peace, and was careful never to flout
 him again.</p></div2><pb n="302" /><div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0909"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09090001" />Two young men ask counsel of Solomon; the one, how he
 is to make himself beloved, the other, how he is to reduce
 an unruly wife to order. The King bids the one to
 love, and the other to go to the Bridge of Geese.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09090002" />None now remained to tell save the queen, unless she were
      minded to infringe Dioneo's privilege. Wherefore, when the ladies
      had laughed their fill over the misfortunes of Biondello, thus gaily
      the queen began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09090003" />Observe we, lovesome ladies, the order of things
      with a sound mind, and we shall readily perceive that we women are
      one and all subjected by Nature and custom and law unto man, by
      him to be ruled and governed at his discretion; wherefore she, that
      would fain enjoy quietude and solace and comfort with the man to
      whom she belongs, ought not only to be chaste but lowly, patient
      and obedient: the which is the discreet wife's chief and most precious
      possession.  <milestone id="p09090004" />And if the laws, which in all matters have regard unto
      the common weal, and use and wont or custom (call it what you
      will), a power very great and to be had in awe, should not suffice to
      school us thereto; yet abundantly clear is the witness of Nature,
      which has fashioned our frames delicate and sensitive, and our spirits
      timorous and fearful, and has decreed that our bodily strength shall
      be slight, our voices tunable, and our movements graceful; which
      qualities do all avouch that we have need of others' governance.
       <milestone id="p09090005" />And whoso has need of succour and governance ought in all reason
      to be obedient and submissive and reverent towards his governor.
      And whom have we to govern and succour us save men? 'Tis then
      our bounden duty to give men all honour and submit ourselves unto
      them: from which rule if any deviate, I deem her most deserving
      not only of grave censure but of severe chastisement.  <milestone id="p09090006" />Which
      <pb n="303" />reflections,
      albeit they are not new to me, I am now led to make by
      what but a little while ago Pampinea told us touching the perverse
      wife of Talano, on whom God bestowed that chastisement which
      the husband had omitted; and accordingly it jumps with my judgment
      that all such women as deviate from the graciousness, kindliness
      and compliancy, which Nature and custom and law prescribe, merit,
      as I said, stern and severe chastisement.  <milestone id="p09090007" />Wherefore, as a salutary
      medicine for the healing of those of us who may be afflicted with
      this disease, I am minded to relate to you that which was once
      delivered by Solomon by way of counsel in such a case. Which let
      none that stands not in need of such physic deem to be meant for
      her, albeit a proverb is current among men; to wit:</p><p><q type="proverb" direct="unspecified">	Good steed, bad steed, alike need the rowel's prick,
	Good wife, bad wife, alike demand the stick.</q>
    </p><p><milestone id="p09090008" />Which whoso should construe as a merry conceit would find you all
      ready enough to acknowledge its truth. But even in its moral
      significance I say that it ought to command assent.  <milestone id="p09090009" />For women are
      all by nature apt to be swayed and to fall; and therefore, for the
      correction of the wrong-doing of such as transgress the bounds
      assigned to them, there is need of the stick punitive; and also for the
      maintenance of virtue in others, that they transgress not these
      appointed bounds, there is need of the stick auxiliary and deterrent.
      However, to cut short this preachment, and to come to that which I
      purpose to tell you, I say:</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09090010" />That the bruit of the incomparable renown of the prodigious
 wisdom of Solomon, as also of the exceeding great liberality with
 which he accorded proof thereof to all that craved such assurance,
 being gone forth over well-nigh all the earth, many from divers parts
 were wont to resort to him for counsel in matters of most pressing
 and arduous importance; among whom was a young man, Melisso
 by name, a very wealthy nobleman, who was, as had been his fathers
 before him, of Lazistan, and there dwelt.  <milestone id="p09090011" />And as Melisso fared
 toward Jerusalem, on his departure from Antioch he fell in with
 another young man, Giosefo by name, who was going the same way,
 and with whom, after the manner of travellers, he entered into converse.
  <milestone id="p09090012" />Melisso, having learned from Giosefo, who and whence he
 was, asked him whither he went, and on what errand: whereupon <pb n="304" />Giosefo
 made an answer that he was going to seek counsel of Solomon,
 how he should deal with his wife, who had not her match among
 women for unruliness and perversity, insomuch that neither entreaties
 nor blandishments nor aught else availed him to bring her to a better
 frame. And thereupon he in like manner asked Melisso whence he
 was, and whither he was bound, and on what errand:  <milestone id="p09090013" />whereto:
 <q direct="unspecified">Of Lazistan, I,</q> replied Melisso, <q direct="unspecified">and like thyself in evil plight;
 for albeit I am wealthy and spend my substance freely in hospitably
 entertaining and honourably entreating my fellow-citizens, yet for
 all that, passing strange though it be to think upon, I find never a
 soul to love me; and therefore I am bound to the self-same place as
 thou, to be advised how it may come to pass that I be beloved.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09090014" />So the two men fared on together, and being arrived at Jerusalem,
 were, by the good offices of one of Solomon's barons, ushered
 into his presence, and Melisso having briefly laid his case before the
 King, was answered in one word: <q direct="unspecified">Love.</q>  <milestone id="p09090015" />Which said, Melisso
 was forthwith dismissed, and Giosefo discovered the reason of his
 coming. To whom Solomon made no answer but: <q direct="unspecified">Get thee
 to the Bridge of Geese.</q> Whereupon Giosefo was likewise promptly
 ushered out of the King's presence, and finding Melisso awaiting
 him, told him what manner of answer he had gotten.  <milestone id="p09090016" />Which
 utterances of the King the two men pondered, but finding therein
 nought that was helpful or relevant to their need, they doubted
 the King had but mocked them, and set forth upon their homeward
 journey.</p><p>Now when they had been some days on the road, they came to
 a river, which was spanned by a fine bridge, and a great caravan of
 sumpter mules and horses being about to cross, they must needs
 tarry, until the caravan had passed by.  <milestone id="p09090017" />The more part of which
 had done so, when it chanced that a mule turned sulky, as we know
 they will not seldom do, and stood stock still; wherefore a muleteer
 took a stick and fell a beating the mule therewith, albeit at first with
 no great vigour, to urge the mule forward.  <milestone id="p09090018" />The mule, however,
 swerving, now to this, now to the other side of the bridge, and sometimes
 facing about, utterly refused to go forward. Whereat the
 muleteer, wroth beyond measure, fell a belabouring him with the stick
 now on the head, now on the flanks, and anon on the croup, never
 so lustily, but all to no purpose.  <milestone id="p09090019" />Which caused Melisso and Giosefo
 <pb n="305" />ofttimes
 to say to him: <q direct="unspecified">How now, caitiff? What is this thou
 doest? Wouldst kill the beast? Why not try if thou canst not
 manage him kindly and gently? He would start sooner so than for
 this cudgelling of thine.</q>  <milestone id="p09090020" />To whom: <q direct="unspecified">You know your horses,</q>
 replied the muleteer, <q direct="unspecified">and I know my mule: leave me to deal with
 him.</q> Which said, he resumed his cudgelling of the mule, and laid
 about him on this side and on that to such purpose that he started
 him; and so the honours of the day rested with the muleteer.  <milestone id="p09090021" />Now,
 as the two young men were leaving the bridge behind them, Giosefo
 asked a good man that sate at its head what the bridge was called,
 and was answered: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, 'tis called the Bridge of Geese.</q>  <milestone id="p09090022" />Which
 Giosefo no sooner heard than he called to mind Solomon's words,
 and turning to Melisso: <q direct="unspecified">Now, comrade, I warrant thee I may
 yet find Solomon's counsel sound and good, for that I knew not how
 to beat my wife is abundantly clear to me; and this muleteer has
 shewn me what I have to do.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09090023" />Now some days afterwards they arrived at Antioch, where
 Giosefo prevailed upon Melisso to tarry with him and rest a day or
 two; and meeting with but a sorry welcome on the part of his wife,
 he told her to take her orders as to supper from Melisso, who, seeing
 that such was Giosefo's will, briefly gave her his instructions; which
 the lady, as had been her wont, not only did not obey, but contravened
 in almost every particular.  <milestone id="p09090024" />Which Giosefo marking: <q direct="unspecified">Wast
 thou not told,</q> quoth he angrily, <q direct="unspecified">after what fashion thou wast to
 order the supper?</q>  <milestone id="p09090025" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">So!</q> replied the lady haughtily:
 <q direct="unspecified">what means this? If thou hast a mind to sup, why take not thy
 supper? No matter what I was told, 'tis thus I saw fit to order it.
 If it like thee, so be it: if not, 'tis thine affair.</q>  <milestone id="p09090026" />Melisso heard the
 lady with surprise and inward disapprobation: Giosefo retorted:
 <q direct="unspecified">Ay, wife, thou art still as thou wast used to be; but I will make
 thee mend thy manners.</q> Then, turning to Melisso: <q direct="unspecified">Friend,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">thou wilt soon prove the worth of Solomon's counsel:
 but, prithee, let it not irk thee to look on, and deem that what I shall
 do is but done in sport; and if thou shouldst be disposed to stand in
 my way, bear in mind how we were answered by the muleteer,
 when we pitied his mule.</q>  <milestone id="p09090027" /><q direct="unspecified">I am in thy house,</q> replied Melisso,
 <q direct="unspecified">and thy pleasure is to me law.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09090028" />Thereupon Giosefo took a stout cudgel cut from an oak sapling, <pb n="306" />and
 hied him into the room whither the lady had withdrawn from
 the table in high dudgeon, seized her by the hair, threw her on to
 the floor at his feet, and fell a beating her amain with the cudgel.
  <milestone id="p09090029" />The lady at first uttered a shriek or two, from which she passed to
 threats; but seeing that, for all that, Giosefo slackened not, by the
 time she was thoroughly well thrashed, she began to cry him mercy,
 imploring him not to kill her, and adding that henceforth his will
 should be to her for law.  <milestone id="p09090030" />But still Giosefo gave not over, but with
 ever fresh fury dealt her mighty swingeing blows, now about the
 ribs, now on the haunches, now over the shoulders; nor had he
 done with the fair lady, until, in short, he had left never a bone or
 other part of her person whole, and he was fairly spent.  <milestone id="p09090031" />Then,
 returning to Melisso: <q direct="unspecified">To-morrow,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">we shall see
 whether 'Get thee to the Bridge of Geese' will prove to have been
 sound advice or no.</q> And so, having rested a while, and then washed
 his hands, he supped with Melisso.  <milestone id="p09090032" />With great pain the poor lady
 got upon her feet and laid herself on her bed, and having there taken
 such rest as she might, rose betimes on the morrow, and craved to
 know of Giosefo what he was minded to have to breakfast.  <milestone id="p09090033" />Giosefo,
 laughing with Melisso over the message, gave her his directions, and
 when in due time they came to breakfast, they found everything
 excellently ordered according as it had been commanded: for which
 cause the counsel, which they had at first failed to understand, now
 received their highest commendation.</p><p><milestone id="p09090034" />Some few days later Melisso, having taken leave of Giosefo,
 went home, and told a wise man the counsel he had gotten from
 Solomon. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">And no truer or sounder advice could
 he have given thee,</q> quoth the sage: <q direct="unspecified">thou knowest that thou
 lovest never a soul, and that the honours thou payest and the services
 thou renderest to others are not prompted by love of them, but by
 love of display. Love, then, as Solomon bade thee, and thou shalt
 be loved.</q>  <milestone id="p09090035" />On such wise was the unruly chastised; and the young
 man, learning to love, was beloved.</p></div2><pb n="307" /><div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0910"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09100001" />Dom Gianni at the instance of his gossip Pietro uses an
 enchantment to transform Pietro's wife into a mare;
 but, when he comes to attach the tail, Gossip Pietro,
 by saying that he will have none of the tail, makes
 the enchantment of no effect.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09100002" />The queen's story evoked some murmurs from the ladies and
 some laughter from the young men; however, when they were
 silent, Dioneo thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09100003" />Dainty my ladies, a black crow among a
 flock of white doves enhances their beauty more than would a white
 swan; and so, when many sages are met together, their ripe wisdom
 not only shews the brighter and goodlier for the presence of one
 that is not so wise, but may even derive pleasure and diversion therefrom.
  <milestone id="p09100004" />Wherefore as you, my ladies, are one and all most discreet
 and judicious, I, who know myself to be somewhat scant of sense,
 should, for that by my demerit I make your merit shew the more
 glorious, be more dear to you, than if by my greater merit I eclipsed
 yours, and by consequence should have more ample license to reveal
 myself to you as I am; and therefore have more patient sufferance
 on your part than would be due to me, were I more discreet, in the
 relation of the tale which I am about to tell you.  <milestone id="p09100005" />'Twill be, then,
 a story none too long, wherefrom you may gather with what exactitude
 it behoves folk to observe the injunctions of those that for any
 purpose use an enchantment, and how slight an error committed
 therein make bring to nought all the work of the enchanter.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09100006" />A year or so ago there was at Barletta a priest named Dom
 Gianni di Barolo, who, to eke out the scanty pittance his church
 afforded him, set a pack-saddle upon his mare, and took to going <pb n="308" />the
 round of the fairs of Apulia, buying and selling merchandise.
  <milestone id="p09100007" />And so it befell that he clapped up a close acquaintance with one
 Pietro da Tresanti, who plied the same trade as he, albeit instead of
 a mare he had but an ass; whom in token of friendship and goodfellowship
 Dom Gianni after the Apulian fashion called ever Gossip
 Pietro, and had him to his house and there lodged and honourably
 entreated him as often as he came to Barletta.  <milestone id="p09100008" />Gossip Pietro on his
 part, albeit he was very poor and had but a little cot at Tresanti
 that scarce sufficed for himself, his fair, young wife, and their ass,
 nevertheless, whenever Dom Gianni arrived at Tresanti, made him
 welcome, and did him the honours of his house as best he might, in
 requital of the hospitality which he received at Barletta.  <milestone id="p09100009" />However,
 as Gossip Pietro had but one little bed, in which he slept with his
 fair wife, 'twas not in his power to lodge Dom Gianni as comfortably
 as he would have liked; but the priest's mare being quartered beside
 the ass in a little stable, the priest himself must needs lie beside her
 on the straw.  <milestone id="p09100010" />Many a time when the priest came, the wife, knowing
 how honourably he entreated her husband at Barletta, would
 fain have gone to sleep with a neighbour, one Zita Carapresa di
 Giudice Leo, that the priest might share the bed with her husband,
 and many a time had she told the priest so: howbeit he would never
 agree to it,  <milestone id="p09100011" />and on one occasion: <q direct="unspecified">Gossip Gemmata,</q> quoth he,
 <q direct="unspecified">trouble not thyself about me; I am well lodged; for, when I am
 so minded, I turn the mare into a fine lass and dally with her, and
 then, when I would, I turn her back into a mare; wherefore I could
 ill brook to part from her.</q>  <milestone id="p09100012" />The young woman, wondering but
 believing, told her husband what the priest had said, adding: <q direct="unspecified">If
 he is even such a friend as thou sayst, why dost thou not get him
 to teach thee the enchantment, so that thou mayst turn me into a
 mare, and have both ass and mare for thine occasions? We should
 then make twice as much gain as we do, and thou couldst turn me
 back into a woman when we came home at night.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09100013" />Gossip Pietro, whose wit was somewhat blunt, believed that 'twas
 as she said, approved her counsel, and began adjuring Dom Gianni,
 as persuasively as he might, to teach him the incantation. Dom
 Gianni did his best to wean him of his folly; but as all was in vain:
 <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">as you are both bent on it, we will be up,
 as is our wont, before the sun to-morrow morning, and I will shew <pb n="309" />you
 how 'tis done. The truth is that 'tis in the attachment of the
 tail that the great difficulty lies, as thou wilt see.</q>  <milestone id="p09100014" />Scarce a wink of
 sleep had either Gossip Pietro or Gossip Gemmata that night, so great
 was their anxiety; and towards daybreak up they got, and called
 Dom Gianni; who, being risen, came in his shirt into Gossip Pietro's
 little bedroom, and: <q direct="unspecified">I know not,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that there is
 another soul in the world for whom I would do this, save you, my
 gossips; however, as you will have it so, I will do it, but it behoves
 you to do exactly as I bid you, if you would have the enchantment
 work.</q>  <milestone id="p09100015" />They promised obedience, and Dom Gianni thereupon took
 a light, which he handed to Gossip Pietro, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Let nought
 that I shall do or say escape thee; and have a care, so thou wouldst
 not ruin all, to say never a word, whatever thou mayst see or hear;
 and pray God that the tail may be securely attached.</q>  <milestone id="p09100016" />So Gossip
 Pietro took the light, and again promised obedience;  <milestone id="p09100017" />Dom Gianni
 caused Gossip Gemmata to strip herself stark naked, and stand on all
 fours like a mare, at the same time strictly charging her that, whatever
 might happen, she must utter no word. Then, touching her
 head and face: <q direct="unspecified">Be this a fine head of a mare,</q> quoth he; in like
 manner touching her hair, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Be this a fine mane of a
 mare;</q> touching her arms: <q direct="unspecified">Be these fine legs and fine hooves of
 a mare;</q>  <milestone id="p09100018" />then, as he touched her breast and felt its firm roundness,
 and there awoke and arose one that was not called: <q direct="unspecified">And be this
 a fine breast of a mare,</q> quoth he; and in like manner he dealt with
 her back, belly, croup, thighs, and legs. Last of all, the work being
 complete save for the tail, he lifted his shirt and took in his hand the
 tool with which he was used to plant men, and forthwith thrust it
 into the furrow made for it, saying: <q direct="unspecified">And be this a fine tail of a
 mare.</q>  <milestone id="p09100019" />Whereat Gossip Pietro, who had followed everything very
 heedfully to that point, disapproving that last particular, exclaimed:
 <q direct="unspecified">No! Dom Gianni, I'll have no tail, I'll have no tail.</q>  <milestone id="p09100020" />The
 essential juice, by which all plants are propagated, was already discharged,
 when Dom Gianni withdrew the tool, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Alas!
 Gossip Pietro, what hast thou done? Did I not tell thee to say never
 a word, no matter what thou mightst see? The mare was all but
 made; but by speaking thou hast spoiled all; and 'tis not possible to
 repeat the enchantment.</q>  <milestone id="p09100021" /><q direct="unspecified">Well and good,</q> replied Gossip Pietro,
 <q direct="unspecified">I would have none of that tail. Why saidst thou not to me: <pb n="310" />'Make
 it thou'? And besides, thou wast attaching it too low.</q>
  <milestone id="p09100022" /><q direct="unspecified">'Twas because,</q> returned Dom Gianni, <q direct="unspecified">thou wouldst not have
 known, on the first essay, how to attach it so well as I.</q>  <milestone id="p09100023" />Whereupon
 the young woman stood up, and in all good faith said to her
 husband: <q direct="unspecified">Fool that thou art, wherefore hast thou brought to
 nought what had been for the good of us both? When didst thou
 ever see mare without a tail? So help me God, poor as thou art,
 thou deservest to be poorer still.</q>  <milestone id="p09100024" />So, after Gossip Pietro's ill-timed
 speech, there being no way left of turning the young woman into a
 mare, downcast and melancholy she resumed her clothes; and Gossip
 Pietro plied his old trade with his ass, and went with Dom Gianni
 to the fair of Bitonto, and never asked him so to serve him again.</p></div2><div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d09conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p09970001" />What laughter this story drew from the ladies, who understood it
 better than Dioneo had wished, may be left to the imagination of
 the fair one that now laughs thereat.  <milestone id="p09970002" />However, as the stories were
 ended, and the sun now shone with a tempered radiance, the queen,
 witting that the end of her sovereignty was come, stood up and took
 off the crown, and set it on the head of Pamfilo, whom alone it now
 remained thus to honour; and said with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, 'tis
 a great burden that falls upon thee, seeing that thou, coming last, art
 bound to make good my shortcomings and those of my predecessors;
 which God give thee grace to accomplish, even as He has given me
 grace to make thee king.</q>  <milestone id="p09970003" />With gladsome acknowledgment of the
 honour: <q direct="unspecified">I doubt not,</q> replied Pamfilo, <q direct="unspecified">that, thanks to your
 noble qualities and those of my other subjects, I shall win even such
 praise as those that have borne sway before me.</q> Then, following
 the example of his predecessors, he made all meet arrangements in
 concert with the seneschal: after which, he turned to the expectant
 ladies, and thus spoke:  <milestone id="p09970004" /><q direct="unspecified">Enamoured my ladies, Emilia, our queen
 of to-day, deeming it proper to allow you an interval of rest to recruit
 your powers, gave you license to discourse of such matters as should
 most commend themselves to each in turn; and as thereby you are
 now rested, I judge that 'tis meet to revert to our accustomed rule.
 Wherefore I ordain that for to-morrow you do each of you take
 thought how you may discourse of the ensuing theme: to wit, of
 such as in matters of love, or otherwise, have done something with
 liberality or magnificence.  <milestone id="p09970005" />By the telling, and (still more) by the
 doing of such things, your spirits will assuredly be duly attuned and
 <pb n="311" />animated
 to emprise high and noble; whereby our life, which cannot
 but be brief, seeing that 'tis enshrined in a mortal body, fame
 shall perpetuate in glory; which whoso serves not the belly, as do the
 beasts, must not only covet, but with all zeal seek after and labour to
 attain.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09970006" />The gay company having, one and all, approved the theme, rose
 at a word from their new king, and betook them to their wonted
 pastimes, and so, according as they severally had most lief, diverted
 them,  <milestone id="p09970007" />until they blithely reunited for supper, which being served
 with all due care and despatched, they rose up to dance, as they were
 wont, and when they had sung, perhaps, a thousand ditties, fitter to
 please by their words than by any excellence of musical art, the king
 bade Neifile sing one on her own account. And promptly and
 graciously, with voice clear and blithe, thus Neifile sang:</p><div3 who="neifile" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p09970008" /><l>In prime of maidenhood, and fair and feat</l>
<l>'Mid spring's fresh foison chant I merrily:</l>
<l>Thanks be to Love and to my fancies sweet.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p09970009" /><l>As o'er the grassy mead I, glancing, fare,</l>
<l>I mark it white and yellow and vermeil dight</l>
<l>With flowers, the thorny rose, the lily white:</l>
<l>And all alike to his face I compare,</l>
<l>Who, loving, hath me ta'en, and me shall e'er</l>
<l>Hold bounden to his will, sith I am she</l>
<l>That in his will findeth her joy complete.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p09970010" /><l>Whereof if so it be that I do find</l>
<l>Any that I most like to him approve,</l>
<l>That pluck I straight and kiss with words of love,</l>
<l>Discovering all, as best I may, my mind;</l>
<l>Yea, all my heart's desire; and then entwined</l>
<l>I set it in the chaplet daintily,</l>
<l>And with my yellow tresses bind and pleat.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p09970011" /><l>And as mine eyes do drink in the delight</l>
<l>Which the flower yields them, even so my mind,</l>
<l>Fired with his sweet love, doth such solace find,</l>
<l>As he himself were present to the sight:</l>
<l>But never word of mine discover might</l>
<l>That which the flower's sweet smell awakes in me:</l>
<l>Witness the true tale that my sighs repeat.</l></lg><pb n="312" /><lg><milestone id="p09970012" /><l>For from my bosom gentle and hot they fly,</l>
<l>Not like the gusty sighs that others heave,</l>
<l>Whenas they languish and do sorely grieve;</l>
<l>And to my love incontinent they hie:</l>
<l>Whereof when he is ware, he, by and by,</l>
<l>To meward hasting, cometh suddenly,</l>
<l>When: <q direct="unspecified">Lest I faint,</q> I cry, <q direct="unspecified">come, I entreat.</q></l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p09970013" />The king and all the ladies did not a little commend Neifile's
 song; after which, as the night was far spent, the king bade all go to
 rest until the morrow.</p></div2></div1>