<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov0306"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03060001" />Ricciardo Minutolo loves the wife of Filippello Fighinolfi,
 and knowing her to be jealous, makes her believe that
 his own wife is to meet Filippello at a bagnio on the
 ensuing day; whereby she is induced to go thither,
 where, thinking to have been with her husband, she
 discovers that she has tarried with Ricciardo.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03060002" />When Elisa had quite done, the queen, after some commendation
	of Zima's sagacity, bade Fiammetta follow with a story. Whereto
	Fiammetta, all smiles, responded: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, with all my heart;</q>
	and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03060003" />Richly though our city abounds, as in all things else, so also in
	instances to suit every topic, yet I am minded to journey some
	distance thence, and, like Elisa, to tell you something of what goes
	on in other parts of the world: wherefore pass we to Naples, where
	you shall hear how one of these sanctified that shew themselves so
	shy of love, was by the subtlety of her lover brought to taste of the
	fruit before she had known the flowers of love; whereby at one and
	the same time you may derive from the past counsel of prudence for
	the future, and present delectation.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p03060004" />In the very ancient city of Naples, which for loveliness has not
 its superior or perhaps its equal in Italy, there once lived a young
 man, renowned alike for noble blood and the splendour of his vast
 wealth, his name Ricciardo Minutolo. He was mated with a very
 fair and loving wife; but nevertheless he became enamoured of a
 lady who in the general opinion vastly surpassed in beauty every other
 lady in Naples. Catella--such was the lady's name--was married to
 <pb n="210" />a young man, likewise of gentle blood, Filippello Fighinolfi by name,
 whom she, most virtuous of ladies, loved and held dear above all else
 in the world. <milestone id="p03060005" />Being thus enamoured of Catella, Ricciardo Minutolo
 left none of those means untried whereby a lady's favour and love
 are wont to be gained, but for all that he made no way towards the
 attainment of his heart's desire: whereby he fell into a sort of despair,
 and witless and powerless to loose himself from his love, found life
 scarce tolerable, and yet knew not how to die. <milestone id="p03060006" />While in this frame
 he languished, it befell one day that some ladies that were of kin to
 him counselled him earnestly to be quit of such a love, whereby he
 could but fret himself to no purpose, seeing that Catella cared for
 nought in the world save Filippello, and lived in such a state of
 jealousy on his account that never a bird flew but she feared lest it
 should snatch him from her. <milestone id="p03060007" />So soon as Ricciardo heard of Catella's
 jealousy, he forthwith began to ponder how he might make it
 subserve his end. He feigned to have given up his love for Catella
 as hopeless, and to have transferred it to another lady, in whose
 honour he accordingly began to tilt and joust and do all that he
 had been wont to do in honour of Catella. <milestone id="p03060008" />Nor was it long before
 well-nigh all the Neapolitans, including Catella herself, began to
 think that he had forgotten Catella, and was to the last degree
 enamoured of the other lady. In this course he persisted, until the
 opinion was so firmly rooted in the minds of all that even Catella
 laid aside a certain reserve which she had used towards him while
 she deemed him her lover, and, coming and going, greeted him in
 friendly, neighbourly fashion, like the rest. <milestone id="p03060009" />Now it so befell that
 during the hot season, when, according to the custom of the
 Neapolitans, many companies of ladies and gentlemen went down to
 the sea-coast to recreate themselves and breakfast and sup, Ricciardo,
 knowing that Catella was gone thither with her company, went
 likewise with his, but, making as if he were not minded to stay
 there, he received several invitations from the ladies of Catella's
 company before he accepted any. <milestone id="p03060010" />When the ladies received him,
 they all with one accord, including Catella, began to rally him on
 his new love, and he furnished them with more matter for talk
 by feigning a most ardent passion. At length most of the ladies
 being gone off, one hither, another thither, as they do in such places,
 leaving Catella and a few others with Ricciardo, he tossed at Catella
 <pb n="211" />a light allusion to a certain love of her husband Filippello, which
 threw her at once into such a fit of jealousy, that she inly burned
 with a vehement desire to know what Ricciardo meant. <milestone id="p03060011" />For a
 while she kept her own counsel; then, brooking no more suspense,
 she adjured Ricciardo, by the love he bore the lady whom most he
 loved, to expound to her what he had said touching Filippello. <milestone id="p03060012" />He
 answered thus: <q direct="unspecified">You have adjured me by her to whom I dare
 not deny aught that you may ask of me; my riddle therefore I will
 presently read you, provided you promise me that neither to him nor
 to any one else will you impart aught of what I shall relate to you,
 until you shall have ocular evidence of its truth; which, so you desire
 it, I will teach you how you may obtain.</q> 
<milestone id="p03060013" />The lady accepted his
 terms, which rather confirmed her belief in his veracity, and swore
 that she would not tell a soul. They then drew a little apart, that
 they might not be overheard by the rest, and Ricciardo thus began:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam, did I love you, as I once did, I should not dare to tell
 you aught that I thought might cause you pain; but, now that that
 love is past, I shall have the less hesitation in telling you the truth.
 <milestone id="p03060014" />Whether Filippello ever resented the love which I bore you, or
 deemed that it was returned by you, I know not: whether it were
 so or no, he certainly never shewed any such feeling to me; <milestone id="p03060015" />but
 so it is that now, having waited, perhaps, until, as he supposes, I am
 less likely to be on my guard, he shews a disposition to serve me
 as I doubt he suspects that I served him; that is to say, he would
 fain have his pleasure of my wife, whom for some time past he has,
 as I discover, plied with messages through most secret channels. She
 has told me all, and has answered him according to my instructions:
 <milestone id="p03060016" />but only this morning, just before I came hither, I found a woman
 in close parley with her in the house, whose true character and
 purpose I forthwith divined; so I called my wife, and asked what the
 woman wanted. <milestone id="p03060017" />Whereto she answered: ''Tis this persecution
 by Filippello which thou hast brought upon me by the encouraging
 answers that thou wouldst have me give him: he now tells me that
 he is most earnestly desirous to know my intentions, and that, should
 I be so minded, he would contrive that I should have secret access
 to a bagnio in this city, and he is most urgent and instant that I
 should consent. And hadst thou not, wherefore I know not, bidden
 me keep the affair afoot, I would have dismissed him in such a
 <pb n="212" />sort that my movements would have been exempt from his prying
 observation for ever. <milestone id="p03060018" />Upon this I saw that the affair was going
 too far; I determined to have no more of it, and to let you know
 it, that you may understand how he requites your whole-hearted
 faith, which brought me of late to the verge of death. <milestone id="p03060019" />And that
 you may not suppose that these are but empty words and idle tales,
 but may be able, should you so desire, to verify them by sight and
 touch, I caused my wife to tell the woman who still waited her
 answer, that she would be at the bagnio to-morrow about none,
 during the siesta: with which answer the woman went away well
 content. <milestone id="p03060020" />Now you do not, I suppose, imagine that I would send
 her thither; but if I were in your place, he should find me there
 instead of her whom he thinks to find there; and when I had been
 some little time with him, I would give him to understand with
 whom he had been, and he should have of me such honour as he
 deserved. Whereby, I doubt not, he would be put to such shame
 as would at one and the same time avenge both the wrong which
 he has done to you and that which he plots against me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03060021" />Catella, as is the wont of the jealous, hearkened to Ricciardo's words
 without so much as giving a thought to the speaker or his wiles,
 inclined at once to credit his story, and began to twist certain antecedent
 matters into accord with it; then, suddenly kindling with
 wrath, she answered, that to the bagnio she would certainly go;
 'twould cause her no great inconvenience, and if he should come, she
 would so shame him that he should never again set eyes on woman
 but his ears would tingle. <milestone id="p03060022" />Satisfied by what he heard, that his
 stratagem was well conceived, and success sure, Ricciardo added much
 in corroboration of his story, and having thus confirmed her belief
 in it, besought her to keep it always close, whereto she pledged
 her faith.</p><p><milestone id="p03060023" />Next morning Ricciardo hied him to the good woman that kept
 the bagnio to which he had directed Catella, told her the enterprise
 which he had in hand, and prayed her to aid him therein so far as
 she might be able. The good woman, who was much beholden to
 him, assured him that she would gladly do so, and concerted with
 him all that was to be said and done. <milestone id="p03060024" />She had in the bagnio a room
 which was very dark, being without any window to admit the light.
 This room, by Ricciardo's direction, she set in order, and made up a
 <pb n="213" />bed there as well as she could, into which bed Ricciardo got, as soon
 as he had breakfasted, and there awaited Catella's coming.</p><p><milestone id="p03060025" />Now Catella, still giving more credence to Ricciardo's story than
 it merited, had gone home in the evening in a most resentful mood,
 and Filippello, returning home the same evening with a mind greatly
 preoccupied, was scarce as familiar with her as he was wont to be.
 <milestone id="p03060026" />Which she marking, grew yet more suspicious than before, and said
 to herself: <q direct="unspecified">Doubtless he is thinking of the lady of whom he expects
 to take his pleasure to-morrow, as most assuredly he shall not;</q> and
 so, musing and meditating what she should say to him after their
 rencounter at the bagnio, she spent the best part of the night. <milestone id="p03060027" />But--to
 shorten my story--upon the stroke of none Catella, taking with
 her a single attendant, but otherwise adhering to her original intention,
 hied her to the bagnio which Ricciardo had indicated; and finding
 the good woman there, asked her whether Filippello had been there
 that day. <milestone id="p03060028" />Primed by Ricciardo, the good woman asked her, whether
 she were the lady that was to come to speak with him; <milestone id="p03060029" />to which she
 answered in the affirmative. 
<milestone id="p03060030" /><q direct="unspecified">Go to him, then,</q> said the good
 woman. <milestone id="p03060031" />And so Catella, in quest of that which she would gladly
 not have found, was shewn to the chamber where Ricciardo was,
 and having entered without uncovering her head, closed the door
 behind her. Overjoyed to see her, Ricciardo sprang out of bed, took
 her in his arms, and said caressingly: <q direct="unspecified">Welcome, my soul.</q>
 <milestone id="p03060032" />Catella, dissembling, for she was minded at first to counterfeit another
 woman, returned his embrace, kissed him, and lavished endearments
 upon him; saying, the while, not a word, lest her speech should
 betray her. The darkness of the room, which was profound, was
 equally welcome to both; nor were they there long enough for their
 eyes to recover power. Ricciardo helped Catella on to the bed,
 where, with no word said on either side in a voice that might be
 recognized, they lay a long while, much more to the solace and
 satisfaction of the one than of the other party. <milestone id="p03060033" />Then, Catella,
 deeming it high time to vent her harboured resentment, burst forth
 in a blaze of wrath on this wise: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! how wretched is the lot
 of women, how misplaced of not a few the love they bear their
 husbands! Ah, woe is me! for eight years have I loved thee more
 dearly than my life; and now I find that thou, base miscreant that
 thou art, dost nought but burn and languish for love of another
 <pb n="214" />woman! <milestone id="p03060034" />Here thou hast been--with whom, thinkest thou? Even
 with her whom thou hast too long deluded with thy false blandishments,
 making pretence to love her while thou art enamoured of
 another. 'Tis I, Catella, not the wife of Ricciardo, false traitor
 that thou art; list if thou knowest my voice; 'tis I indeed! Ah!
 would we were but in the light!--it seems to me a thousand years
 till then--that I might shame thee as thou deservest, vile, pestilent
 dog that thou art! <milestone id="p03060035" />Alas! woe is me! such love as I have borne so
 many years--to whom? To this faithless dog, that, thinking to have a
 strange woman in his embrace, has in the brief while that I have
 been with him here lavished upon me more caresses and endearments
 than during all the forepast time that I have been his! <milestone id="p03060036" />A lively
 spark indeed art thou to-day, renegade dog, that shewest thyself
 so limp and enervate and impotent at home! But, God be praised,
 thou hast tilled thine own plot, and not another's, as thou didst believe.
 <milestone id="p03060037" />No wonder that last night thou heldest aloof from me; thou wast
 thinking of scattering thy seed elsewhere, and wast minded to shew
 thyself a lusty knight when thou shouldst join battle. But praise be
 to God and my sagacity, the water has nevertheless taken its proper
 course. <milestone id="p03060038" />Where is thy answer, culprit? Hast thou nought to say?
 Have my words struck thee dumb? God's faith! I know not why I
 forbear to pluck thine eyes out with my fingers! Thou thoughtest
 to perpetrate this treason with no small secrecy; but, by God, one is
 as knowing as another; thy plot has failed; I had better hounds on
 thy trail than thou didst think for.</q> 
<milestone id="p03060039" />Ricciardo, inly delighted by her
 words, made no answer, but embraced and kissed her more than
 ever, and overwhelmed her with his endearments. So she continued
 her reproaches, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Ay, thou thinkest to cajole me with thy
 feigned caresses, wearisome dog that thou art, and so to pacify and
 mollify me; but thou art mistaken. I shall never be mollified, until
 I have covered thee with infamy in the presence of all our kinsfolk
 and friends and neighbours. <milestone id="p03060040" />Am I not, miscreant, as fair as the wife
 of Ricciardo Minutolo? Am I not as good a lady as she? Why
 dost not answer, vile dog? Wherein has she the advantage of me?
 Away with thee! touch me not; thou hast done feats of arms more
 than enough for to-day. <milestone id="p03060041" />Well I know that, now that thou knowest
 who I am, thou wilt wreak thy will on me by force: but by God's
 grace I will yet disappoint thee. I know not why I forbear to send
 <pb n="215" />for Ricciardo, who loved me more than himself and yet was never
 able to boast that he had a single glance from me; nor know I why
 'twere wrong to do so. Thou thoughtest to have his wife here, and
 'tis no fault of thine that thou hadst her not: so, if I had him, thou
 couldst not justly blame me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03060042" />Enough had now been said: the lady's mortification was extreme;
 and, as she ended, Ricciardo bethought him that, if he suffered her,
 thus deluded, to depart, much evil might ensue. He therefore
 resolved to make himself known, and disabuse her of her error. So,
 taking her in his arms, and clipping her so close that she could not
 get loose, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Sweet my soul, be not wroth: that which,
 while artlessly I loved, I might not have, Love has taught me to
 compass by guile: know that I am thy Ricciardo.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03060043" />At these words and the voice, which she recognized, Catella
 started, and would have sprung out of the bed; which being
 impossible, she essayed a cry; but Ricciardo laid a hand upon her
 mouth, and closed it, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, that which is done can
 never be undone, though you should cry out for the rest of your
 days, and should you in such or any other wise publish this matter to
 any, two consequences will ensue. <milestone id="p03060044" />In the first place (and this is a
 point which touches you very nearly) your honour and fair fame will
 be blasted; for, however you may say that I lured you hither by
 guile, I shall deny it, and affirm, on the contrary, that I induced you
 to come hither by promises of money and gifts, and that 'tis but
 because you are vexed that what I gave you did not altogether come
 up to your expectations, that you make such a cry and clamour; and
 you know that folk are more prone to believe evil than good, and
 therefore I am no less likely to be believed than you. <milestone id="p03060045" />The further
 consequence will be mortal enmity between your husband and me, and
 the event were as like to be that I killed him as that he killed me:
 which if I did, you would never more know joy or peace. Wherefore,
 heart of my body, do not at one and the same time bring dishonour
 upon yourself and set your husband and me at strife and in jeopardy
 of our lives. <milestone id="p03060046" />You are not the first, nor will you be the last to be
 beguiled; nor have I beguiled you to rob you of aught, but for excess
 of love that I bear, and shall ever bear, you, being your most lowly
 vassal. And though it is now a great while that I, and what I have
 and can and am worth, are yours, yet I am minded that so it shall be
 <pb n="216" />henceforth more than ever before. Your discretion in other matters
 is not unknown to me, and I doubt not 'twill be equally manifest
 in this.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03060047" />Ricciardo's admonitions were received by Catella with many a
 bitter tear; but though she was very wroth and very sad at heart,
 yet Ricciardo's true words so far commanded the assent of her
 reason, that she acknowledged that 'twas possible they might be
 verified by the event. Wherefore she made answer: 
<milestone id="p03060048" /><q direct="unspecified">Ricciardo,
 I know not how God will grant me patience to bear the villainy and
 knavery which thou hast practised upon me; and though in this
 place, to which simplicity and excess of jealousy guided my steps, I
 raise no cry, rest assured that I shall never be happy, until in one way
 or another I know myself avenged of that which thou hast done to
 me. Wherefore unhand me, let me go: thou hast had thy desire of
 me, and hast tormented me to thy heart's content: 'tis time to release
 me; let me go, I pray thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p03060049" />But Ricciardo, seeing that she was
 still much ruffled in spirit, was resolved not to let her go, until he
 had made his peace with her. So he addressed himself to soothe
 her; and by dint of most dulcet phrases and entreaties and adjurations
 he did at last prevail with her to give him her pardon; nay, by
 joint consent, they tarried there a great while to the exceeding great
 delight of both. <milestone id="p03060050" />Indeed the lady, finding her lover's kisses smack
 much better than those of her husband, converted her asperity into
 sweetness, and from that day forth cherished a most tender love for
 Ricciardo; whereof, using all circumspection, they many a time had
 solace. God grant us solace of ours.</p></div2>