<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0202"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02020001" />Rinaldo d'Asti is robbed, arrives at Castel Guglielmo,
 and is entertained by a widow lady; his property is
 restored to him, and he returns home safe and sound.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02020002" />The ladies and the young men, especially Filostrato, laughed
	inordinately at Neifile's narrative of Martellino's misadventures.
	Then Filostrato, who sate next Neifile, received the queen's command
	to follow her, and promptly thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02020003" />Fair ladies, 'tis on my mind to tell you a story in which are
 mingled things sacred and passages of adverse fortune and love,
 which to hear will perchance be not unprofitable, more especially to
 travellers in love's treacherous lands; of whom if any fail to say St.
 Julian's paternoster, it often happens that, though he may have a
 good bed, he is ill lodged.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02020004" />Know, then, that in the time of the Marquis Azzo da Ferrara, a
 merchant, Rinaldo d'Asti by name, having disposed of certain affairs
 which had brought him to Bologna, set his face homeward, and
 having left Ferrara behind him was on his way to Verona, when he
 fell in with some men that looked like merchants, but were in truth
 robbers and men of evil life and condition, whose company he
      imprudently joined, riding and conversing with them. <milestone id="p02020005" />They, perceiving
 that he was a merchant, and judging that he must have
 money about him, complotted to rob him on the first opportunity;
 and to obviate suspicion they played the part of worthy and reputable
 men, their discourse of nought but what was seemly and honourable
 and leal, their demeanour at once as respectful and as cordial as they
 could make it; so that he deemed himself very lucky to have met
 with them, being otherwise alone save for a single mounted servant.
 <pb n="74" />
      <milestone id="p02020006" />Journeying
 thus, they conversed, after the desultory manner of travellers,
 of divers matters, until at last they fell a talking of the prayers which
 men address to God, and one of the robbers--there were three of
 them--said to Rinaldo: <q direct="unspecified">And you, gentle sir, what is your wonted
 orison when you are on your travels?</q> 
<milestone id="p02020007" />Rinaldo answered: <q direct="unspecified">Why,
 to tell the truth, I am a man unskilled, unlearned in such matters,
 and few prayers have I at my command, being one that lives in the
 good old way and lets two soldi count for twenty-four deniers;
 nevertheless it has always been my custom in journeying to say of a
 morning, as I leave the inn, a paternoster and an avemaria for the
 souls of the father and mother of St. Julian, after which I pray God
 and St. Julian to provide me with a good inn for the night. <milestone id="p02020008" />And
 many a time in the course of my life have I met with great perils by
 the way, and evading them all have found comfortable quarters for
 the night: whereby my faith is assured, that St. Julian, in whose
 honour I say my paternoster, has gotten me this favour of God; nor
 should I look for a prosperous journey and a safe arrival at night, if
 I had not said it in the morning.</q> 
<milestone id="p02020009" />Then said his interrogator:
 <q direct="unspecified">And did you say it this morning?</q> 
<milestone id="p02020010" />Whereto Rinaldo answered, <q direct="unspecified">Troth, did I,</q> 
<milestone id="p02020011" />which caused the other, who by this time knew
 what course matters would take, to say to himself: <q direct="unspecified">'Twill prove
 to have been said in the nick of time; for if we do not miscarry, I
 take it thou wilt have but a sorry lodging.</q> 
<milestone id="p02020012" />Then turning to
 Rinaldo he said: <q direct="unspecified">I also have travelled much, and never a prayer
 have I said, though I have heard them much commended by many;
 nor has it ever been my lot to find other than good quarters for the
 night; it may be that this very evening you will be able to determine
 which of us has the better lodging, you that have said the paternoster,
 or I that have not said it. True, however, it is that in its stead I
 am accustomed to say the 'Dirupisti,' or the 'Intemerata,' or the
 'De profundis,' which, if what my grandmother used to say is to be
 believed, are of the greatest efficacy.</q> 
<milestone id="p02020013" />So, talking of divers matters,
 and ever on the look-out for time and place suited to their evil
 purpose, they continued their journey, until towards evening, some
 distance from Castel Guglielmo, as they were about to ford a stream,
 these three ruffians, profiting by the lateness of the hour, and the
 loneliness and straitness of the place, set upon Rinaldo and robbed
 him, and leaving him afoot and in his shirt, said by way of adieu:
 <pb n="75" /><q direct="unspecified">Go now, and see if thy St. Julian will provide thee with good
 lodging to-night; our saint, we doubt not, will do as much by us;</q>
 and so crossing the stream, they went their way. <milestone id="p02020014" />Rinaldo's servant,
 coward that he was, did nothing to help his master when he saw him
 attacked, but turned his horse's head, and was off at a smart pace;
 nor did he draw rein until he was come to Castel Guglielmo; where,
 it being now evening, he put up at an inn and gave himself no
 further trouble. <milestone id="p02020015" />Rinaldo, left barefoot, and stripped to his shirt,
 while the night closed in very cold and snowy, was at his wits' end,
 and shivering so that his teeth chattered in his head, began to peer
 about, if haply he might find some shelter for the night, that so
 he might not perish with the cold; but, seeing none (for during a
 recent war the whole country had been wasted by fire), he set off for
 Castel Guglielmo, quickening his pace by reason of the cold.
 Whether his servant had taken refuge in Castel Guglielmo or
 elsewhere, he knew not, but he thought that, could he but enter
 the town, God would surely send him some succour. <milestone id="p02020016" />However,
 dark night overtook him while he was still about a mile from the
 castle; so that on his arrival he found the gates already locked and
 the bridges raised, and he could not pass in. <milestone id="p02020017" />Sick at heart, disconsolate
 and bewailing his evil fortune, he looked about for some
 place where he might ensconce himself, and at any rate find shelter
 from the snow. And by good luck he espied a house, built with a
 balcony a little above the castle-wall, under which balcony he
 purposed to shelter himself until daybreak. Arrived at the spot, he
 found beneath the balcony a postern, which, however, was locked;
 and having gathered some bits of straw that lay about, he placed
 them in front of the postern, and there in sad and sorrowful plight
 took up his quarters, with many a piteous appeal to St. Julian, whom
 he reproached for not better rewarding the faith which he reposed
 in him. <milestone id="p02020018" />St. Julian, however, had not abandoned him, and in due
 time provided him with a good lodging.</p><p><milestone id="p02020019" />There was in the castle a widow lady of extraordinary beauty
 (none fairer) whom Marquis Azzo loved as his own life, and kept
 there for his pleasure. She lived in the very same house beneath
 the balcony of which Rinaldo had posted himself. <milestone id="p02020020" />Now it chanced
 that that very day the Marquis had come to Castel Guglielmo to
 pass the night with her, and had privily caused a bath to be made
 <pb n="76" />ready, and a supper suited to his rank, in the lady's own house.
 The arrangements were complete; and only the Marquis was stayed
 for, when a servant happened to present himself at the castle-gate,
 bringing tidings for the Marquis which obliged him suddenly to take
 horse. He therefore sent word to the lady that she must not wait
 for him, and forthwith took his departure. <milestone id="p02020021" />The lady, somewhat
 disconsolate, found nothing better to do than to get into the bath
 which had been intended for the Marquis, sup and go to bed: so
 into the bath she went. <milestone id="p02020022" />The bath was close to the postern on the
 other side of which hapless Rinaldo had ensconced himself, and thus
 the mournful and quavering music which Rinaldo made as he
 shuddered in the cold, and which seemed rather to proceed from a
 stork's beak than from the mouth of a human being, was audible to
 the lady in the bath. She therefore called her maid, and said to
 her: <q direct="unspecified">Go up and look out over the wall and down at the postern,
 and mark who is there, and what he is, and what he does there.</q>
 <milestone id="p02020023" />The maid obeyed, and, the night being fine, had no difficulty in
 making out Rinaldo as he sate there, barefoot, as I have said, and in
 his shirt, and trembling in every limb. So she called out to him,
 to know who he was. <milestone id="p02020024" />Rinaldo, who could scarcely articulate for
 shivering, told as briefly as he could, who he was, and how and why
 he came to be there; which done, he began piteously to beseech
 her not, if she could avoid it, to leave him there all night to perish of
 cold. <milestone id="p02020025" />The maid went back to her mistress full of pity for Rinaldo,
 and told her all she had seen and heard. The lady felt no less pity
 for Rinaldo; and bethinking her that she had the key of the postern
 by which the Marquis sometimes entered when he paid her a secret
 visit, she said to the maid: <q direct="unspecified">Go, and let him in softly; here is
 this supper, and there will be none to eat it; and we can very well
 put him up for the night.</q> 
<milestone id="p02020026" />Cordially commending her mistress's
 humanity, the maid went and let Rinaldo in, and brought him to the
 lady, who, seeing that he was all but dead with cold, said to him:
 <q direct="unspecified">Quick, good man, get into that bath, which is still warm.</q>
 <milestone id="p02020027" />Gladly he did so, awaiting no second invitation, and was so much
 comforted by its warmth that he seemed to have passed from death
 to life. The lady provided him with a suit of clothes, which
 had been worn by her husband shortly before his death, and which,
 when he had them on, looked as if they had been made for him. So
 <pb n="77" />he recovered heart, and, while he awaited the lady's commands, gave
 thanks to God and St. Julian for delivering him from a woful night
 and conducting him, as it seemed, to comfortable quarters.</p><p><milestone id="p02020028" />The lady meanwhile took a little rest, after which she had a
 roaring fire put in one of her large rooms, whither presently she
 came, and asked her maid how the good man did. <milestone id="p02020029" />The maid
 replied: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, he has put on the clothes, in which he shews
 to advantage, having a handsome person, and seeming to be a worthy
 man, and well-bred.</q> 
<milestone id="p02020030" /><q direct="unspecified">Go, call him then,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">tell him
 to come hither to the fire, and we will sup; for I know that he has
 not supped.</q> 
<milestone id="p02020031" />Rinaldo, on entering the room and seeing the lady,
 took her to be of no small consequence. He therefore made her a
 low bow, and did his utmost to thank her worthily for the service
 she had rendered him. <milestone id="p02020032" />His words pleased her no less than his
 person, which accorded with what the maid had said: so she made
 him heartily welcome, installed him at his ease by her side before the
 fire, and questioned him of the adventure which had brought him
 thither. Rinaldo detailed all the circumstances, <milestone id="p02020033" />of which the lady
 had heard somewhat when Rinaldo's servant made his appearance at
 the castle. She therefore gave entire credence to what he said, and
 told him what she knew about his servant, and how he might easily
 find him on the morrow. <milestone id="p02020034" />She then bade set the table, which done,
 Rinaldo and she washed their hands and sate down together to sup.
 <milestone id="p02020035" />Tall he was and comely of form and feature, debonair and gracious
 of mien and manner, and in his lusty prime. The lady had eyed
 him again and again to her no small satisfaction, and, her wantonness
 being already kindled for the Marquis, who was to have come
 to lie with her, she had let Rinaldo take the vacant place in her
 mind. So when supper was done, and they were risen from the
 table, she conferred with her maid, whether, after the cruel trick
 played upon her by the Marquis, it were not well to take the good
 gift which Fortune had sent her. <milestone id="p02020036" />The maid knowing the bent of
 her mistress's desire, left no word unsaid that might encourage her
 to follow it. Wherefore the lady, turning towards Rinaldo, who
 was standing where she had left him by the fire, began thus: 
<milestone id="p02020037" /><q direct="unspecified">So!
 Rinaldo, why still so pensive? Will nothing console you for the
 loss of a horse and a few clothes? Take heart, put a blithe face on
 it, you are at home; nay more, let me tell you that, seeing you in
 <pb n="78" />those clothes which my late husband used to wear, and taking you
 for him, I have felt, not once or twice, but perhaps a hundred times
 this evening, a longing to throw my arms round you and kiss you;
 and, in faith, I had so done, but that I feared it might displease you.</q>
 <milestone id="p02020038" />Rinaldo, hearing these words, and marking the flame which shot
 from the lady's eyes, and being no laggard, came forward with open
 arms, and confronted her and said: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, I am not unmindful
 that I must ever acknowledge that to you I owe my life, in regard
 of the peril whence you rescued me. If then there be any way in
 which I may pleasure you, churlish indeed were I not to devise it.
 So you may even embrace and kiss me to your heart's content, and
 I will embrace and kiss you with the best of good wills.</q> There
 needed no further parley. <milestone id="p02020039" />The lady, all aflame with amorous desire,
 forthwith threw herself into his arms, and straining him to her
 bosom with a thousand passionate embraces, gave and received a
 thousand kisses before they sought her chamber. There with all
 speed they went to bed, nor did day surprise them until again and
 again and in full measure they had satisfied their desire. <milestone id="p02020040" />With the
 first streaks of dawn they rose, for the lady was minded that none
 should surmise aught of the affair. So, having meanly habited
 Rinaldo, and replenished his purse, she enjoined him to keep the
 secret, shewed him the way to the castle, where he was to find his
 servant, and let him out by the same postern by which he had
 entered. <milestone id="p02020041" />When it was broad day the gates were opened, and
 Rinaldo, passing himself off as a traveller from distant parts, entered
 the castle, and found his servant. Having put on the spare suit
 which was in his valise, he was about to mount the servant's horse,
 when, as if by miracle, there were brought into the castle the three
 gentlemen of the road who had robbed him the evening before,
 having been taken a little while after for another offence. Upon
 their confession Rinaldo's horse was restored to him, as were also his
 clothes and money; so that he lost nothing except a pair of garters,
 of which the robbers knew not where they had bestowed them.
 <milestone id="p02020042" />Wherefore Rinaldo, giving thanks to God and St. Julian, mounted
 his horse, and returned home safe and sound, and on the morrow the
 three robbers kicked heels in the wind.</p></div2>