<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0909"><head>Novel IX</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09090001" />Two young men ask counsel of Solomon; the one, how he
 is to make himself beloved, the other, how he is to reduce
 an unruly wife to order. The King bids the one to
 love, and the other to go to the Bridge of Geese.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09090002" />None now remained to tell save the queen, unless she were
      minded to infringe Dioneo's privilege. Wherefore, when the ladies
      had laughed their fill over the misfortunes of Biondello, thus gaily
      the queen began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09090003" />Observe we, lovesome ladies, the order of things
      with a sound mind, and we shall readily perceive that we women are
      one and all subjected by Nature and custom and law unto man, by
      him to be ruled and governed at his discretion; wherefore she, that
      would fain enjoy quietude and solace and comfort with the man to
      whom she belongs, ought not only to be chaste but lowly, patient
      and obedient: the which is the discreet wife's chief and most precious
      possession.  <milestone id="p09090004" />And if the laws, which in all matters have regard unto
      the common weal, and use and wont or custom (call it what you
      will), a power very great and to be had in awe, should not suffice to
      school us thereto; yet abundantly clear is the witness of Nature,
      which has fashioned our frames delicate and sensitive, and our spirits
      timorous and fearful, and has decreed that our bodily strength shall
      be slight, our voices tunable, and our movements graceful; which
      qualities do all avouch that we have need of others' governance.
       <milestone id="p09090005" />And whoso has need of succour and governance ought in all reason
      to be obedient and submissive and reverent towards his governor.
      And whom have we to govern and succour us save men? 'Tis then
      our bounden duty to give men all honour and submit ourselves unto
      them: from which rule if any deviate, I deem her most deserving
      not only of grave censure but of severe chastisement.  <milestone id="p09090006" />Which
      <pb n="303" />reflections,
      albeit they are not new to me, I am now led to make by
      what but a little while ago Pampinea told us touching the perverse
      wife of Talano, on whom God bestowed that chastisement which
      the husband had omitted; and accordingly it jumps with my judgment
      that all such women as deviate from the graciousness, kindliness
      and compliancy, which Nature and custom and law prescribe, merit,
      as I said, stern and severe chastisement.  <milestone id="p09090007" />Wherefore, as a salutary
      medicine for the healing of those of us who may be afflicted with
      this disease, I am minded to relate to you that which was once
      delivered by Solomon by way of counsel in such a case. Which let
      none that stands not in need of such physic deem to be meant for
      her, albeit a proverb is current among men; to wit:</p><p><q type="proverb" direct="unspecified">	Good steed, bad steed, alike need the rowel's prick,
	Good wife, bad wife, alike demand the stick.</q>
    </p><p><milestone id="p09090008" />Which whoso should construe as a merry conceit would find you all
      ready enough to acknowledge its truth. But even in its moral
      significance I say that it ought to command assent.  <milestone id="p09090009" />For women are
      all by nature apt to be swayed and to fall; and therefore, for the
      correction of the wrong-doing of such as transgress the bounds
      assigned to them, there is need of the stick punitive; and also for the
      maintenance of virtue in others, that they transgress not these
      appointed bounds, there is need of the stick auxiliary and deterrent.
      However, to cut short this preachment, and to come to that which I
      purpose to tell you, I say:</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09090010" />That the bruit of the incomparable renown of the prodigious
 wisdom of Solomon, as also of the exceeding great liberality with
 which he accorded proof thereof to all that craved such assurance,
 being gone forth over well-nigh all the earth, many from divers parts
 were wont to resort to him for counsel in matters of most pressing
 and arduous importance; among whom was a young man, Melisso
 by name, a very wealthy nobleman, who was, as had been his fathers
 before him, of Lazistan, and there dwelt.  <milestone id="p09090011" />And as Melisso fared
 toward Jerusalem, on his departure from Antioch he fell in with
 another young man, Giosefo by name, who was going the same way,
 and with whom, after the manner of travellers, he entered into converse.
  <milestone id="p09090012" />Melisso, having learned from Giosefo, who and whence he
 was, asked him whither he went, and on what errand: whereupon <pb n="304" />Giosefo
 made an answer that he was going to seek counsel of Solomon,
 how he should deal with his wife, who had not her match among
 women for unruliness and perversity, insomuch that neither entreaties
 nor blandishments nor aught else availed him to bring her to a better
 frame. And thereupon he in like manner asked Melisso whence he
 was, and whither he was bound, and on what errand:  <milestone id="p09090013" />whereto:
 <q direct="unspecified">Of Lazistan, I,</q> replied Melisso, <q direct="unspecified">and like thyself in evil plight;
 for albeit I am wealthy and spend my substance freely in hospitably
 entertaining and honourably entreating my fellow-citizens, yet for
 all that, passing strange though it be to think upon, I find never a
 soul to love me; and therefore I am bound to the self-same place as
 thou, to be advised how it may come to pass that I be beloved.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09090014" />So the two men fared on together, and being arrived at Jerusalem,
 were, by the good offices of one of Solomon's barons, ushered
 into his presence, and Melisso having briefly laid his case before the
 King, was answered in one word: <q direct="unspecified">Love.</q>  <milestone id="p09090015" />Which said, Melisso
 was forthwith dismissed, and Giosefo discovered the reason of his
 coming. To whom Solomon made no answer but: <q direct="unspecified">Get thee
 to the Bridge of Geese.</q> Whereupon Giosefo was likewise promptly
 ushered out of the King's presence, and finding Melisso awaiting
 him, told him what manner of answer he had gotten.  <milestone id="p09090016" />Which
 utterances of the King the two men pondered, but finding therein
 nought that was helpful or relevant to their need, they doubted
 the King had but mocked them, and set forth upon their homeward
 journey.</p><p>Now when they had been some days on the road, they came to
 a river, which was spanned by a fine bridge, and a great caravan of
 sumpter mules and horses being about to cross, they must needs
 tarry, until the caravan had passed by.  <milestone id="p09090017" />The more part of which
 had done so, when it chanced that a mule turned sulky, as we know
 they will not seldom do, and stood stock still; wherefore a muleteer
 took a stick and fell a beating the mule therewith, albeit at first with
 no great vigour, to urge the mule forward.  <milestone id="p09090018" />The mule, however,
 swerving, now to this, now to the other side of the bridge, and sometimes
 facing about, utterly refused to go forward. Whereat the
 muleteer, wroth beyond measure, fell a belabouring him with the stick
 now on the head, now on the flanks, and anon on the croup, never
 so lustily, but all to no purpose.  <milestone id="p09090019" />Which caused Melisso and Giosefo
 <pb n="305" />ofttimes
 to say to him: <q direct="unspecified">How now, caitiff? What is this thou
 doest? Wouldst kill the beast? Why not try if thou canst not
 manage him kindly and gently? He would start sooner so than for
 this cudgelling of thine.</q>  <milestone id="p09090020" />To whom: <q direct="unspecified">You know your horses,</q>
 replied the muleteer, <q direct="unspecified">and I know my mule: leave me to deal with
 him.</q> Which said, he resumed his cudgelling of the mule, and laid
 about him on this side and on that to such purpose that he started
 him; and so the honours of the day rested with the muleteer.  <milestone id="p09090021" />Now,
 as the two young men were leaving the bridge behind them, Giosefo
 asked a good man that sate at its head what the bridge was called,
 and was answered: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, 'tis called the Bridge of Geese.</q>  <milestone id="p09090022" />Which
 Giosefo no sooner heard than he called to mind Solomon's words,
 and turning to Melisso: <q direct="unspecified">Now, comrade, I warrant thee I may
 yet find Solomon's counsel sound and good, for that I knew not how
 to beat my wife is abundantly clear to me; and this muleteer has
 shewn me what I have to do.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09090023" />Now some days afterwards they arrived at Antioch, where
 Giosefo prevailed upon Melisso to tarry with him and rest a day or
 two; and meeting with but a sorry welcome on the part of his wife,
 he told her to take her orders as to supper from Melisso, who, seeing
 that such was Giosefo's will, briefly gave her his instructions; which
 the lady, as had been her wont, not only did not obey, but contravened
 in almost every particular.  <milestone id="p09090024" />Which Giosefo marking: <q direct="unspecified">Wast
 thou not told,</q> quoth he angrily, <q direct="unspecified">after what fashion thou wast to
 order the supper?</q>  <milestone id="p09090025" />Whereto: <q direct="unspecified">So!</q> replied the lady haughtily:
 <q direct="unspecified">what means this? If thou hast a mind to sup, why take not thy
 supper? No matter what I was told, 'tis thus I saw fit to order it.
 If it like thee, so be it: if not, 'tis thine affair.</q>  <milestone id="p09090026" />Melisso heard the
 lady with surprise and inward disapprobation: Giosefo retorted:
 <q direct="unspecified">Ay, wife, thou art still as thou wast used to be; but I will make
 thee mend thy manners.</q> Then, turning to Melisso: <q direct="unspecified">Friend,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">thou wilt soon prove the worth of Solomon's counsel:
 but, prithee, let it not irk thee to look on, and deem that what I shall
 do is but done in sport; and if thou shouldst be disposed to stand in
 my way, bear in mind how we were answered by the muleteer,
 when we pitied his mule.</q>  <milestone id="p09090027" /><q direct="unspecified">I am in thy house,</q> replied Melisso,
 <q direct="unspecified">and thy pleasure is to me law.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09090028" />Thereupon Giosefo took a stout cudgel cut from an oak sapling, <pb n="306" />and
 hied him into the room whither the lady had withdrawn from
 the table in high dudgeon, seized her by the hair, threw her on to
 the floor at his feet, and fell a beating her amain with the cudgel.
  <milestone id="p09090029" />The lady at first uttered a shriek or two, from which she passed to
 threats; but seeing that, for all that, Giosefo slackened not, by the
 time she was thoroughly well thrashed, she began to cry him mercy,
 imploring him not to kill her, and adding that henceforth his will
 should be to her for law.  <milestone id="p09090030" />But still Giosefo gave not over, but with
 ever fresh fury dealt her mighty swingeing blows, now about the
 ribs, now on the haunches, now over the shoulders; nor had he
 done with the fair lady, until, in short, he had left never a bone or
 other part of her person whole, and he was fairly spent.  <milestone id="p09090031" />Then,
 returning to Melisso: <q direct="unspecified">To-morrow,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">we shall see
 whether 'Get thee to the Bridge of Geese' will prove to have been
 sound advice or no.</q> And so, having rested a while, and then washed
 his hands, he supped with Melisso.  <milestone id="p09090032" />With great pain the poor lady
 got upon her feet and laid herself on her bed, and having there taken
 such rest as she might, rose betimes on the morrow, and craved to
 know of Giosefo what he was minded to have to breakfast.  <milestone id="p09090033" />Giosefo,
 laughing with Melisso over the message, gave her his directions, and
 when in due time they came to breakfast, they found everything
 excellently ordered according as it had been commanded: for which
 cause the counsel, which they had at first failed to understand, now
 received their highest commendation.</p><p><milestone id="p09090034" />Some few days later Melisso, having taken leave of Giosefo,
 went home, and told a wise man the counsel he had gotten from
 Solomon. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">And no truer or sounder advice could
 he have given thee,</q> quoth the sage: <q direct="unspecified">thou knowest that thou
 lovest never a soul, and that the honours thou payest and the services
 thou renderest to others are not prompted by love of them, but by
 love of display. Love, then, as Solomon bade thee, and thou shalt
 be loved.</q>  <milestone id="p09090035" />On such wise was the unruly chastised; and the young
 man, learning to love, was beloved.</p></div2>