<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov0408"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04080001" />Girolamo loves Salvestra: yielding to his mother's prayers
 he goes to Paris; he returns to find Salvestra
 married; he enters her house by stealth, lays himself
 by her side, and dies; he is borne to the church,
 where Salvestra lays herself by his side, and dies.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04080002" />When Emilia's story was done, Neifile at a word
	from the king thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04080003" />Some there are, noble ladies, who, methinks, deem
	themselves to be wiser than the rest of the world, and are in fact less
	so; and by consequence presume to measure their wit against not
	only the counsels of men but the nature of things; which presumption
	has from time to time been the occasion of most grievous mishaps;
	but nought of good was ever seen to betide thereof. <milestone id="p04080004" />And
	as there is nought in nature that brooks to be schooled or thwarted
	so ill as love, the quality of which is such that it is more likely to die
	out of its own accord than to be done away of set purpose, I am
	minded to tell you a story of a lady, who, while she sought to be
	more wise than became her, and than she was, and indeed than the
	nature of the matter, wherein she studied to shew her wisdom, allowed,
	thinking to unseat Love from the heart that he had occupied, and
	wherein perchance the stars had established him, did in the end
	banish at one and the same time Love and life from the frame of
	her son.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04080005" />Know, then, that, as 'tis related by them of old time, there was
 once in our city a very great and wealthy merchant, Leonardo
 Sighieri by name, who had by his lady a son named Girolamo, after
 whose birth he departed this life, leaving his affairs in meet and due
 order; and well and faithfully were they afterwards administered in
 <pb n="314" />the interest of the boy by his mother and guardians. 
<milestone id="p04080006" />As he grew
 up, consorting more frequently with the neighbours' children than
 any others of the quarter, he made friends with a girl of his own
 age that was the daughter of a tailor; and in course of time this
 friendship ripened into a love so great and vehement, that Girolamo
 was ever ill at ease when he saw her not; nor was her love for him
 a whit less strong than his for her. <milestone id="p04080007" />Which his mother perceiving
 would not seldom chide him therefor and chastise him. And as
 Girolamo could not give it up, she confided her distress to his
 guardians, speaking--for by reason of her boy's great wealth she
 thought to make, as it were, an orange-tree out of a bramble--on
 this wise: 
<milestone id="p04080008" /><q direct="unspecified">This boy of ours, who is now scarce fourteen years
 old, is so in love with a daughter of one of our neighbours, a
 tailor--Salvestra
 is the girl's name--that, if we part them not, he will, peradventure,
 none else witting, take her to wife some day, and I shall
 never be happy again; or, if he see her married to another, he will
 pine away; <milestone id="p04080009" />to prevent which, methinks, you would do well to send
 him away to distant parts on the affairs of the shop; for so, being
 out of sight she will come at length to be out of mind, and then we
 can give him some well-born girl to wife.</q> 
<milestone id="p04080010" />Whereto the guardians
 answered, that 'twas well said, and that it should be so done to the
 best of their power: so they called the boy into the shop, and one
 of them began talking to him very affectionately on this wise:
 <milestone id="p04080011" /><q direct="unspecified">My son, thou art now almost grown up; 'twere well thou shouldst
 now begin to learn something for thyself of thy own affairs: wherefore
 we should be very well pleased if thou wert to go stay at Paris
 a while, where thou wilt see how we trade with not a little of thy
 wealth, besides which thou wilt there become a much better, finer,
 and more complete gentleman than thou couldst here, and when
 thou hast seen the lords and barons and seigneurs that are there in
 plenty, and hast acquired their manners, thou canst return hither.</q>
 <milestone id="p04080012" />The boy listened attentively, and then answered shortly that he
 would have none of it, for he supposed he might remain at Florence
 as well as another. Whereupon the worthy men plied him with fresh
 argument, but were unable to elicit other answer from him, and
 told his mother so. <milestone id="p04080013" />Whereat she was mightily incensed, and gave
 him a great scolding, not for his refusing to go to Paris, but for his
 love; which done, she plied him with soft, wheedling words, and
 <pb n="315" />endearing expressions and gentle entreaties that he would be pleased
 to do as his guardians would have him; whereby at length she prevailed
 so far, that he consented to go to Paris for a year and no more;
 and so 'twas arranged. <milestone id="p04080014" />To Paris accordingly our ardent lover went,
 and there under one pretext or another was kept for two years. He
 returned more in love than ever, to find his Salvestra married to a
 good youth that was a tent-maker; whereat his mortification knew
 no bounds. <milestone id="p04080015" />But, seeing that what must be must be, he sought to
 compose his mind; and, having got to know where she lived, he
 took to crossing her path, according to the wont of young men in
 love, thinking that she could no more have forgotten him than he
 her. 'Twas otherwise, however; she remembered him no more
 than if she had never seen him; or, if she had any recollection of
 him, she dissembled it: <milestone id="p04080016" />whereof the young man was very soon ware,
 to his extreme sorrow. Nevertheless he did all that he could to
 recall himself to her mind; but, as thereby he seemed to be nothing
 advantaged, he made up his mind, though he should die for it, to
 speak to her himself. <milestone id="p04080017" />So, being instructed as to her house by a neighbour,
 he entered it privily one evening when she and her husband
 were gone to spend the earlier hours with some neighbours, and hid
 himself in her room behind some tent-cloths that were stretched
 there, and waited till they were come back, and gone to bed, and he
 knew the husband to be asleep. Whereupon he got him to the
 place where he had seen Salvestra lie down, and said as he gently
 laid his hand upon her bosom: <q direct="unspecified">O my soul, art thou yet asleep?</q>
 <milestone id="p04080018" />The girl was awake, and was on the point of uttering a cry, when
 he forestalled her, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Hush! for God's sake. I am thy
 Girolamo.</q> 
<milestone id="p04080019" />Whereupon she, trembling in every limb: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but
 for God's sake, Girolamo, begone: 'tis past, the time of our childhood,
 when our love was excusable. Thou seest I am married;
 wherefore 'tis no longer seemly that I should care for any other man
 than my husband, <milestone id="p04080020" />and so by the one God, I pray thee, begone; for,
 if my husband were to know that thou art here, the least evil that
 could ensue would be that I should never more be able to live with
 him in peace or comfort, whereas, having his love, I now pass my
 days with him in tranquil happiness.</q> 
<milestone id="p04080021" />Which speech caused the
 young man grievous distress; but 'twas in vain that he reminded
 her of the past, and of his love that distance had not impaired, and
 therewith mingled many a prayer and the mightiest protestations.
 <pb n="316" />
<milestone id="p04080022" />Wherefore, yearning for death, he besought her at last that she would
 suffer him to lie a while beside her till he got some heat, for he was
 chilled through and through, waiting for her, and promised her that
 he would say never a word to her, nor touch her, and that as soon
 as he was a little warmed he would go away. 
<milestone id="p04080023" />On which terms
 Salvestra, being not without pity for him, granted his request. So
 the young man lay down beside her, and touched her not; but,
 gathering up into one thought the love he had so long borne her,
 the harshness with which she now requited it, and his ruined hopes,
 resolved to live no longer, and in a convulsion, without a word, and
 with fists clenched, expired by her side.</p><p><milestone id="p04080024" />After a while the girl, marvelling at his continence, and fearing
 lest her husband should awake, broke silence, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Nay, but,
 Girolamo, why goest thou not?</q> 
<milestone id="p04080025" />But, receiving no answer, she
 supposed that he slept. Wherefore, reaching forth her hand to
 arouse him, she touched him and found him to her great surprise
 cold as ice; and touching him again and again somewhat rudely, and
 still finding that he did not stir, she knew that he was dead. Her
 grief was boundless, and 'twas long before she could bethink her how
 to act. <milestone id="p04080026" />But at last she resolved to sound her husband's mind as to
 what should be done in such a case without disclosing that 'twas his
 own. So she awakened him, and told him how he was then bested,
 as if it were the affair of another, and then asked him, if such a thing
 happened to her, what course he would take. 
<milestone id="p04080027" />The good man
 answered that he should deem it best to take the dead man privily
 home, and there leave him, bearing no grudge against the lady, who
 seemed to have done no wrong. 
<milestone id="p04080028" /><q direct="unspecified">And even so,</q> said his wife, <q direct="unspecified">it
 is for us to do;</q> and taking his hand, she laid it on the corpse.
 Whereat he started up in consternation, and struck a light, and without
 further parley with his wife, clapped the dead man's clothes
 upon him, and forthwith (confident in his own innocence) raised
 him on his shoulders, and bore him to the door of his house, where
 he set him down and left him.</p><p><milestone id="p04080029" />Day came, and the dead man being found before his own door,
 there was a great stir made, particularly by his mother; the body
 was examined with all care from head to foot, and, no wound or trace
 of violence being found on it, the physicians were on the whole of
 opinion that, as the fact was, the man had died of grief. So the corpse
 was borne to a church, and thither came the sorrowing mother and
 <pb n="317" />other ladies, her kinswomen and neighbours, and began to wail and
 mourn over it without restraint after our Florentine fashion. 
<milestone id="p04080030" />And
 when the wailing had reached its height, the good man, in whose
 house the death had occurred, said to Salvestra: <q direct="unspecified">Go wrap a
 mantle about thy head, and hie thee to the church, whither Girolamo
 has been taken, and go about among the women and list what
 they say of this matter, and I will do the like among the men, that
 we may hear if aught be said to our disadvantage.</q> 
<milestone id="p04080031" />The girl
 assented, for with tardy tenderness she now yearned to look on him
 dead, whom living she would not solace with a single kiss, and so to
 the church she went. <milestone id="p04080032" />Ah! how marvellous to whoso ponders it, is
 the might of Love, and how unsearchable his ways! That heart,
 which, while Fortune smiled on Girolamo, had remained sealed to
 him, opened to him now that he was fordone, and, kindling anew
 with all its old flame, melted with such compassion that no sooner
 saw she his dead face, as there she stood wrapped in her mantle,
 than, edging her way forward through the crowd of women, she
 stayed not till she was beside the corpse; and there, uttering a piercing
 shriek, she threw herself upon the dead youth, and as her face
 met his, and before she might drench it with her tears, grief that had
 reft life from him had even so reft it from her.</p><p><milestone id="p04080033" />The women strove to comfort her, and bade her raise herself a
 little, for as yet they knew her not; then, as she did not arise, they
 would have helped her, but found her stiff and stark, and so, raising
 her up, they in one and the same moment saw her to be Salvestra
 and dead. Whereat all the women that were there, overborne by
 a redoubled pity, broke forth in wailing new and louder far than
 before. <milestone id="p04080034" />From the church the bruit spread itself among the men,
 and reached the ears of Salvestra's husband, who, deaf to all that
 offered comfort or consolation, wept a long while; after which he
 told to not a few that were there what had passed in the night
 between the youth and his wife; and so 'twas known of all how
 they came to die, to the common sorrow of all. 
<milestone id="p04080035" />So they took the
 dead girl, and arrayed her as they are wont to array the dead, and
 laid her on the same bed beside the youth, and long time they
 mourned her: then were they both buried in the same tomb, and
 thus those, whom love had not been able to wed in life, were wedded
 by death in indissoluble union.</p></div2>