<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="neifile" id="nov1001"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00010001" />A knight in the service of the King of Spain deems
 himself ill requited. Wherefore the King, by most
 cogent proof, shews him that the blame rests not with
 him, but with the knight's own evil fortune; after
 which, he bestows upon him a noble gift.</p></argument><div3 who="neifile" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00010002" />Highly graced, indeed, do I deem myself, honourable my ladies,
 that our king should have given to me the precedence in a matter so
 arduous to tell of as magnificence: for, as the sun irradiates all the
 heaven with his glory and beauty, even so does magnificence enhance
 the purity and the splendour of every other virtue. I shall therefore
 tell you a story, which, to my thinking, is not a little pretty; and
 which, assuredly, it must be profitable to call to mind.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00010003" />You are to know, then, that, among other honourable knights
 that from days of old even until now have dwelt in our city, one, and
 perchance the worthiest of all, was Messer Ruggieri de' Figiovanni.
  <milestone id="p00010004" />Who, being wealthy and magnanimous, reflecting on the customs and
 manner of life of Tuscany, perceived that by tarrying there he was
 like to find little or no occasion of shewing his mettle, and accordingly
 resolved to pass some time at the court of Alfonso, King of Spain,
 who for the fame of his high qualities was without a peer among the
 potentates of his age. So, being well provided with arms and horses
 and retinue suitable to his rank, he hied him to Spain, where he was
 graciously received by the King.  <milestone id="p00010005" />There tarrying accordingly, Messer
 Ruggieri very soon, as well by the splendid style in which he lived
 as by the prodigious feats of arms that he did, gave folk to know his
 high desert.</p><p>Now, having tarried there some while, and observed the King's
 <pb n="315" />ways with much care, and how he would grant castles, cities, or
 baronies, to this, that, or the other of his subjects, he deemed that
 the King shewed therein but little judgment, seeing that he would
 give them to men that merited them not. And for that nought was
 given to him, he, knowing his merit, deemed himself gravely injured
 in reputation; wherefore he made up his mind to depart the realm,
 and to that end craved license of the King;  <milestone id="p00010006" />which the King granted
 him, and therewith gave him one of the best and finest mules that
 was ever ridden, a gift which Messer Ruggieri, as he had a long
 journey to make, did not a little appreciate.  <milestone id="p00010007" />The King then bade
 one of his discreet domestics contrive, as best he might, to ride with
 Messer Ruggieri on such wise that it might not appear that he did
 so by the King's command, and charge his memory with whatever
 Messer Ruggieri might say of him, so that he might be able to repeat
 it; which done, he was on the very next morning to bid Ruggieri
 return to the King forthwith.  <milestone id="p00010008" />The King's agent was on the
 alert, and no sooner was Ruggieri out of the city, than without any
 manner of difficulty he joined his company, giving out that he was
 going towards Italy.  <milestone id="p00010009" />As thus they rode, talking of divers matters,
 Messer Ruggieri being mounted on the mule given him by the
 King: <q direct="unspecified">Methinks,</q> quoth the other, it being then hard upon
 tierce, <q direct="unspecified">that 'twere well to give the beasts a voidance;</q>  <milestone id="p00010010" />and by and
 by, being come to a convenient place, they voided all the beasts save
 the mule. Then, as they continued their journey, the squire
 hearkening attentively to the knight's words, they came to a river,
 and while there they watered the beasts, the mule made a voidance
 in the stream. Whereat: <q direct="unspecified">Ah, foul fall thee, beast,</q> quoth
 Messer Ruggieri, <q direct="unspecified">that art even as thy master, that gave thee to me!</q>
  <milestone id="p00010011" />Which remark, as also many another that fell from Ruggieri as they
 rode together throughout the day, the squire stored in his memory;
 but never another word did he hear Ruggieri say touching the King,
 that was not laudatory to the last degree.</p><p><milestone id="p00010012" />On the morrow, when they were gotten to horse, and had set
 their faces towards Tuscany, the squire apprised Ruggieri of the
 King's command, and thereupon Ruggieri turned back.  <milestone id="p00010013" />On his
 arrival the King, having already heard what he had said touching the
 mule, gave him gladsome greeting, and asked him wherefore he had
 likened him to the mule, or rather the mule to him.  <milestone id="p00010014" />Whereto
 <pb n="316" />Messer Ruggieri answered frankly: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, I likened you to the
 mule, for that, as you bestow your gifts where 'tis not meet, and
 where meet it were, bestow them not, so the mule where 'twas meet,
 voided not, and where 'twas not meet, voided.</q>  <milestone id="p00010015" /><q direct="unspecified">Messer Ruggieri,</q>
 replied the King, <q direct="unspecified">'tis not because I have not discerned in you a
 knight most good and true, for whose desert no gift were too great,
 that I have not bestowed on you such gifts as I have bestowed upon
 many others, who in comparison of you are nothing worth: the
 fault is none of mine but solely of your fortune, which would not
 suffer me; and that this which I say is true, I will make abundantly
 plain to you.</q>  <milestone id="p00010016" /><q direct="unspecified">My lord,</q> returned Messer Ruggieri, <q direct="unspecified">mortified
 am I, not that you gave me no gift, for thereof I had no desire, being
 too rich, but that you made no sign of recognition of my desert;
 however, I deem your explanation sound and honourable, and
 whatever you shall be pleased that I should see, that gladly will I,
 albeit I believe you without attestation.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00010017" />The King then led him into one of the great halls, in which, by
 his preordinance, were two chests closed under lock and key, and, not
 a few others being present, said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Messer Ruggieri, one of
 these chests contains my crown, sceptre and orb, with many a fine
 girdle, buckle, ring, and whatever else of jewellery I possess; the
 other is full of earth: choose then, and whichever you shall choose,
 be it yours; thereby you will discover whether 'tis due to me or to
 your fortune that your deserts have lacked requital.</q>  <milestone id="p00010018" />Such being the
 King's pleasure, Messer Ruggieri chose one of the chests, which at
 the King's command being opened and found to be that which
 contained the earth: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Messer Ruggieri,</q> quoth the King
 with a laugh, <q direct="unspecified">your own eyes may warrant you of the truth of what
 I say touching Fortune; but verily your merit demands that I take
 arms against her in your cause.  <milestone id="p00010019" />I know that you are not minded to
 become a Spaniard, and therefore I shall give you neither castle nor
 city; but that chest, which Fortune denied you, I bestow on you in
 her despite, that you may take it with you to your own country, and
 there with your neighbours justly vaunt yourself of your deserts,
 attested by my gifts.</q>  <milestone id="p00010020" />Messer Ruggieri took the chest, and having
 thanked the King in a manner befitting such a gift, returned therewith,
 well pleased, to Tuscany.</p></div2>