<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filomena" id="nov0303"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03030001" />Under cloak of confession and a most spotless conscience,
 a lady, enamoured of a young man, induces a booby
 friar unwittingly to provide a means to the entire
 gratification of her passion.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03030002" />When Pampinea had done, and several of the company had
	commended the hardihood and wariness of the groom, as also the
	wisdom of the King, the queen, turning to Filomena, bade her follow
	suit: wherefore with manner debonair Filomena thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="filomena" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03030003" />The story which I shall tell you is of a trick which was actually
 played by a fair lady upon a booby religious, and which every layman
 should find the more diverting that these religious, being, for the
 most part, great blockheads and men of odd manners and habits, do
 nevertheless credit themselves with more ability and knowledge in
 all kinds than fall to the lot of the rest of the world; whereas, in
 truth, they are far inferior, and so, not being able, like others, to
 provide their own sustenance, are prompted by sheer baseness to fly
 thither for refuge where they may find provender, like pigs. <milestone id="p03030004" />Which
 story, sweet my ladies, I shall tell you, not merely that thereby I may
 continue the sequence in obedience to the queen's behest, but also to
 the end that I may let you see that even the religious, in whom we
 in our boundless credulity repose exorbitant faith, may be, and sometimes
 are, made--not to say by men--even by some of us women
 the sport of their sly wit.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p03030005" />In our city, where wiles do more abound than either love or
 faith, there dwelt, not many years ago, a gentlewoman richly
 endowed (none more so) by nature with physical charms, as also
 with gracious manners, high spirit and fine discernment. Her name
 <pb n="190" />I know, but will not disclose it, nor yet that of any other who
 figures in this story, because there yet live those who might take
 offence thereat, though after all it might well be passed off with a
 laugh. <milestone id="p03030006" />High-born and married to an artificer of woollen fabrics, she
 could not rid her mind of the disdain with which, by reason of his
 occupation, she regarded her husband; for no man, however wealthy,
 so he were of low condition, seemed to her worthy to have a gentlewoman
 to wife; and seeing that for all his wealth he was fit for
 nothing better than to devise a blend, set up a warp, or higgle about
 yarn with a spinster, she determined to dispense with his embraces,
 save so far as she might find it impossible to refuse them; and to find
 her satisfaction elsewhere with one that seemed to her more meet to
 afford it than her artificer of woollens. <milestone id="p03030007" />In this frame of mind she
 became enamoured of a man well worthy of her love and not yet
 past middle age, insomuch that, if she saw him not in the day, she
 must needs pass an unquiet night. The gallant, meanwhile, remained
 fancy-free, for he knew nought of the lady's case; and she, being
 apprehensive of possible perils to ensue, was far too circumspect to
 make it known to him either by writing or by word of mouth of
 any of her female friends. <milestone id="p03030008" />Then she learned that he had much to
 do with a religious, a simple, clownish fellow, but nevertheless, as
 being a man of most holy life, reputed by almost everybody a most
 worthy friar, and decided that she could not find a better intermediary
 between herself and her lover than this same friar. So,
 having matured her plan, she hied her at a convenient time to the
 convent where the friar abode, and sent for him, saying, that, if he
 so pleased, she would be confessed by him. <milestone id="p03030009" />The friar, who saw at
 a glance that she was a gentlewoman, gladly heard her confession;
 which done, she said: <q direct="unspecified">My father, I have yet a matter to confide
 to you, in which I must crave your aid and counsel. <milestone id="p03030010" />Who my
 kinsfolk and husband are, I wot you know, for I have myself told
 you. My husband loves me more dearly than his life, and being
 very wealthy, he can well and does forthwith afford me whatever I
 desire. Wherefore, as he loves me, even so I love him more dearly
 than myself; nor was there ever yet wicked woman that deserved
 the fire so richly as should I, were I guilty--I speak not of acts, but
 of so much as a single thought of crossing his will or tarnishing his
 honour. <milestone id="p03030011" />Now a man there is--his name, indeed, I know not, but
 <pb n="191" />he seems to me to be a gentleman, and, if I mistake not, he is much
 with you--a fine man and tall, his garb dun and very decent, who,
 the bent of my mind being, belike, quite unknown to him, would
 seem to have laid siege to me, insomuch that I cannot shew
 myself at door or casement, or quit the house, but forthwith he
 presents himself before me; indeed I find it passing strange that he
 is not here now; whereat I am sorely troubled, because, when men
 so act, unmerited reproach will often thereby be cast upon honest
 women. <milestone id="p03030012" />At times I have been minded to inform my brothers of
 the matter; but then I have bethought me that men sometimes
 frame messages in such a way as to evoke untoward answers, whence
 follow high words; and so they proceed to rash acts: wherefore, to
 obviate trouble and scandal, I have kept silence, and by preference
 have made you my confidant, both because you are the gentleman's
 friend, and because it befits your office to censure such behaviour
 not only in friends but in strangers. <milestone id="p03030013" />And so I beseech you for the
 love of our only Lord God to make him sensible of his fault, and
 pray him to offend no more in such sort. Other ladies there are in
 plenty, who may, perchance, be disposed to welcome such advances,
 and be flattered to attract his fond and assiduous regard, which to
 me, who am in no wise inclined to encourage it, is but a most
 grievous molestation.</q></p><p>Having thus spoken, the lady bowed her head as if she were ready
 to weep. <milestone id="p03030014" />The holy friar was at no loss to apprehend who it was of
 whom she spoke; he commended her virtuous frame, firmly believing
 that what she said was true, and promised to take such action that
 she should not again suffer the like annoyance; nor, knowing that
 she was very wealthy, did he omit to extol works of charity and
 almsgiving, at the same time opening to her his own needs. 
<milestone id="p03030015" /><q direct="unspecified">I
 make my suit to you,</q> said she, <q direct="unspecified">for the love of God; and if your
 friend should deny what I have told you, tell him roundly that 'twas
 from me you had it, and that I made complaint to you thereof.</q>
 <milestone id="p03030016" />So, her confession ended and penance imposed, bethinking her of the
 hints which the friar had dropped touching almsgiving, she slipped
 into his hand as many coins as it would hold, praying him to say
 masses for the souls of her dead. She then rose and went home.</p><p><milestone id="p03030017" />Not long afterwards the gallant paid one of his wonted visits to
 the holy friar. They conversed for a while of divers topics, and
 <pb n="192" />then the friar took him aside, and very courteously reproved him for
 so haunting and pursuing the lady with his gaze, as from what
 she had given him to understand, he supposed was his wont. <milestone id="p03030018" />The
 gallant, who had never regarded her with any attention, and very
 rarely passed her house, was amazed, and was about to clear himself,
 when the friar closed his mouth, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Now away with this
 pretence of amazement, and waste not words in denial, for 'twill not
 avail thee. I have it not from the neighbours; she herself, bitterly
 complaining of thy conduct, told it me. <milestone id="p03030019" />I say not how ill this
 levity beseems thee; but of her I tell thee so much as this, that, if
 I ever knew woman averse to such idle philandering, she is so;
 and therefore for thy honour's sake, and that she be no more vexed,
 I pray thee refrain therefrom, and let her be in peace.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030020" />The gallant,
 having rather more insight than the holy friar, was not slow to
 penetrate the lady's finesse; he therefore made as if he were rather
 shame-stricken, promised to go no further with the matter, and hied
 him straight from the friar to the lady's house, where she was always
 posted at a little casement to see if he were passing by. <milestone id="p03030021" />As she saw
 him come, she shewed him so gay and gracious a mien that he could
 no longer harbour any doubt that he had put the true construction
 upon what he had heard from the friar; and thenceforth, to his own
 satisfaction and the immense delight and solace of the lady, he
 omitted not daily to pass that way, being careful to make it appear
 as if he came upon other business. <milestone id="p03030022" />'Twas thus not long before the
 lady understood that she met with no less favour in his eyes than he
 in hers; and being desirous to add fuel to his flame, and to assure him
 of the love she bore him, as soon as time and occasion served, she
 returned to the holy friar, and having sat herself down at his feet in
 the church, fell a weeping. The friar asked her in a soothing tone
 what her new trouble might be. <milestone id="p03030023" />Whereto the lady answered:
 <q direct="unspecified">My father, 'tis still that accursed friend of thine, of whom I made
 complaint to you some days ago, and who would now seem to have
 been born for my most grievous torment, and to cause me to do that
 by reason whereof I shall never be glad again, nor venture to place
 myself at your feet.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030024" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> said the friar; <q direct="unspecified">has he not forborne
 to annoy thee?</q> 
<milestone id="p03030025" /><q direct="unspecified">Not he, indeed,</q> said the lady; <q direct="unspecified">on the
 contrary, 'tis my belief that, since I complained to you of him, he
 has, as if in despite, being offended, belike, that I did so, passed my
 <pb n="193" />house seven times for once that he did so before. 
<milestone id="p03030026" />Nay, would to
 God he were content to pass and fix me with his eyes; but he is
 waxed so bold and unabashed that only yesterday he sent a woman
 to me at home with his compliments and cajoleries, and, as if I had
 not purses and girdles enough, he sent me a purse and a girdle;
 whereat I was, as I still am, so wroth, that, had not conscience first,
 and then regard for you, weighed with me, I had flown into a frenzy
 of rage. However, I restrained myself, and resolved neither to do
 nor to say aught without first letting you know it. <milestone id="p03030027" />Nor only so;
 but, lest the woman who brought the purse and girdle, and to whom
 I at first returned them, shortly bidding her begone and take them
 back to the sender, should keep them and tell him that I had accepted
 them, as I believe they sometimes do, I recalled her and had them
 back, albeit 'twas in no friendly spirit that I received them from her
 hand; and I have brought them to you, that you may return them
 to him and tell him that I stand in no need of such gifts from him,
 because, thanks be to God and my husband, I have purses and girdles
 enough to smother him in. <milestone id="p03030028" />And if after this he leave me not alone,
 I pray you as my father to hold me excused if, come what may, I
 tell it to my husband and brothers; for much liefer had I that he
 suffer indignity, if so it must be, than that my fair fame should be
 sullied on his account: that holds good, friar.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030029" />Weeping bitterly
 as she thus ended, she drew from under her robe a purse of very fine
 and ornate workmanship and a dainty and costly little girdle, and
 threw them into the lap of the friar, who, fully believing what she
 said, manifested the utmost indignation as he took them, and said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Daughter, that by these advances thou shouldst be moved to anger, I
 deem neither strange nor censurable; but I am instant with thee to
 follow my advice in the matter. <milestone id="p03030030" />I chid him some days ago, and ill
 has he kept the promise that he made me; for which cause and this
 last feat of his I will surely make his ears so tingle that he will give
 thee no more trouble; wherefore, for God's sake, let not thyself be
 so overcome by wrath as to tell it to any of thy kinsfolk; which
 might bring upon him a retribution greater than he deserves. Nor
 fear lest thereby thy fair fame should suffer; for I shall ever be thy
 most sure witness before God and men that thou art innocent.</q>
 <milestone id="p03030031" />The lady made a shew of being somewhat comforted: then, after a
 pause--for well she knew the greed of him and his likes--she said:
 <pb n="194" /><q direct="unspecified">Of late, Sir, by night, the spirits of divers of my kinsfolk have
 appeared to me in my sleep, and methinks they are in most grievous
 torment; alms, alms, they crave, nought else, especially my mother,
 who seems to be in so woful and abject a plight that 'tis pitiful
 to see. <milestone id="p03030032" />Methinks 'tis a most grievous torment to her to see the
 tribulation which this enemy of God has brought upon me. I would
 therefore have you say for their souls the forty masses of St. Gregory
 and some of your prayers, that God may deliver them from this
 purging fire.</q> So saying she slipped a florin into the hand of the
 holy friar, <milestone id="p03030033" />who took it gleefully, and having with edifying words and
 many examples fortified her in her devotion, gave her his benediction,
 and suffered her to depart.</p><p>The lady gone, the friar, who had still no idea of the trick that
 had been played upon him, sent for his friend; who was no sooner
 come than he gathered from the friar's troubled air that he had news
 of the lady, and waited to hear what he would say. <milestone id="p03030034" />The friar
 repeated what he had said before, and then broke out into violent
 and heated objurgation on the score of the lady's latest imputation.
 The gallant, who did not as yet apprehend the friar's drift, gave but
 a very faint denial to the charge of sending the purse and girdle, in
 order that he might not discredit the lady with the friar, if, perchance,
 she had given him the purse and girdle. <milestone id="p03030035" />Whereupon the friar exclaimed
 with great heat: <q direct="unspecified">How canst thou deny it, thou wicked
 man? Why, here they are; she brought them to me in tears with
 her own hand. Look at them, and say if thou knowest them not.</q>
<milestone id="p03030036" /> The gallant now feigned to be much ashamed, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Why,
 yes, indeed, I do know them; I confess that I did wrong; and I
 swear to you that, now I know her character, you shall never hear
 word more of this matter.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030037" />Many words followed; and then the
 blockheadly friar gave the purse and girdle to his friend, after which
 he read him a long lecture, besought him to meddle no more with
 such matters, and on his promising obedience dismissed him.</p><p><milestone id="p03030038" />Elated beyond measure by the assurance which he now had of
 the lady's love, and the beautiful present, the gallant, on leaving the
 friar, hied him straight to a spot whence he stealthily gave the lady
 to see that he had both her gifts: whereat the lady was well content,
 the more so as her intrigue seemed ever to prosper more and more.
 She waited now only for her husband's departure from home to
 <pb n="195" />crown her enterprise with success. Nor was it long before occasion
 required that her husband should go to Genoa. <milestone id="p03030039" />The very morning
 that he took horse and rode away she hied her to the holy friar, and
 after many a lamentation she said to him betwixt her sobs: <q direct="unspecified">My
 father, now at last I tell you out and out that I can bear my suffering
 no longer. I promised you some days ago to do nought in this
 matter without first letting you know it; I am now come to crave
 release from that promise; and that you may believe that my
 lamentations and complaints are not groundless, I will tell you how
 this friend of yours, who should rather be called a devil let loose
 from hell, treated me only this very morning, a little before matins.
 <milestone id="p03030040" />As ill-luck would have it, he learned, I know not how, that yesterday
 morning my husband went to Genoa, and so this morning at the
 said hour he came into my garden, and got up by a tree to the
 window of my bedroom, which looks out over the garden, and had
 already opened the casement, and was about to enter the room, when
 I suddenly awoke, and got up and uttered a cry, and should have
 continued to cry out, had not he, who was still outside, implored my
 mercy for God's sake and yours, telling me who he was. So, for
 love of you I was silent, and naked as I was born, ran and shut the
 window in his face, and he--bad luck to him--made off, I suppose,
 for I saw him no more. <milestone id="p03030041" />Consider now if such behaviour be seemly
 and tolerable: I for my part am minded to put up with no more of
 it; indeed I have endured too much already for love of you.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03030042" />Wroth beyond measure was the friar, as he heard her thus speak,
 nor knew he what to say, except that he several times asked her if
 she were quite certain that it was no other than he. 
<milestone id="p03030043" /><q direct="unspecified">Holy name
 of God!</q> replied the lady, <q direct="unspecified">as if I did not yet know him from
 another! He it was, I tell you; and do you give no credence to his
 denial.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030044" /><q direct="unspecified">Daughter,</q> said then the friar, <q direct="unspecified">there is here nought
 else to say but that this is a monstrous presumption and a most
 heinous offence; and thou didst well to send him away as thou didst.
 <milestone id="p03030045" />But seeing that God has preserved thee from shame, I would implore
 thee that, as thou hast twice followed my advice, thou do so likewise
 on this occasion, and making no complaint to any of thy kinsfolk,
 leave it to me to try if I can control this devil that has slipt his chain,
 whom I supposed to be a saint; and if I succeed in weaning him from
 this insensate folly, well and good; and if I fail, thenceforth I give
 <pb n="196" />thee leave, with my blessing, to do whatsoever may commend itself
 to thy own judgment.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030046" /><q direct="unspecified">Lo now,</q> answered the lady, <q direct="unspecified">once
 again I will not vex or disobey you; but be sure that you so order
 matters that he refrain from further annoyance, as I give you my
 word that never will I have recourse to you again touching this
 matter.</q> Then, without another word, and with a troubled air, she
 took leave of him. <milestone id="p03030047" />Scarcely was she out of the church when the
 gallant came up. The friar called him, took him aside, and gave him
 the affront in such sort as 'twas never before given to any man,
 reviling him as a disloyal and perjured traitor. The gallant, who by
 his two previous lessons had been taught how to value the friar's
 censures, listened attentively, and sought to draw him out by ambiguous
 answers. <q direct="unspecified">Wherefore this wrath, Sir?</q> he began. <q direct="unspecified">Have I
 crucified Christ?</q> 
<milestone id="p03030048" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, mark the fellow's effrontery!</q> retorted
 the friar: <q direct="unspecified">list to what he says! He talks, forsooth, as if 'twere
 a year or so since, and his villanies and lewdnesses were clean gone from
 his memory for lapse of time. Between matins and now hast thou
 forgotten this morning's outrage? Where wast thou this morning
 shortly before daybreak?</q> 
<milestone id="p03030049" /><q direct="unspecified">Where was I?</q> rejoined the gallant;
 <q direct="unspecified">that know not I. 'Tis indeed betimes that the news has reached
 you.</q> 
<milestone id="p03030050" /><q direct="unspecified">True indeed it is,</q> said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">that the news has
 reached
 me: I suppose that, because the husband was not there, thou never
 doubtedst that thou wouldst forthwith be received by the lady with
 open arms. Ah! the gay gallant! the honourable gentleman! he
 is now turned prowler by night, and breaks into gardens, and climbs
 trees! <milestone id="p03030051" />Dost thou think by sheer importunity to vanquish the virtue
 of this lady, that thou escaladest her windows at night by the trees?
 She dislikes thee of all things in the world, and yet thou must still
 persist. Well indeed hast thou laid my admonitions to heart, to say
 nothing of the many proofs which she has given thee of her disdain!
 <milestone id="p03030052" />But I have yet a word for thee: hitherto, not that she bears thee
 any love, but that she has yielded to my urgent prayers, she has kept
 silence as to thy misdeeds: she will do so no more: I have given her
 leave to act as she may think fit, if thou givest her any further
 annoyance. And what wilt thou do if she informs her brothers?</q>
 <milestone id="p03030053" />The gallant, now fully apprised of what it imported him to know,
 was profuse in promises, whereby as best he might he reassured the
 friar, and so left him. The very next night, as soon as the matin
 <pb n="197" />hour was come, he entered the garden, climbed up the tree, found the
 window open, entered the chamber, and in a trice was in the embrace
 of his fair lady. <milestone id="p03030054" />Anxiously had she expected him, and blithely did she
 now greet him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">All thanks to master friar that he so well
 taught thee the way hither.</q> Then, with many a jest and laugh at
 the simplicity of the asinine friar, and many a flout at distaff-fuls and
 combs and cards, they solaced themselves with one another to their
 no small delight. <milestone id="p03030055" />Nor did they omit so to arrange matters that
 they were well able to dispense with master friar, and yet pass many
 another night together with no less satisfaction: to which goal I
 pray that I, and all other Christian souls that are so minded, may be
 speedily guided of God in His holy mercy.</p></div2>