<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="emilia" id="nov0206"><head>Novel VI</head><argument>      <p><milestone id="p02060001" />Madam Beritola loses two sons, is found with two kids
	on an island, goes thence to Lunigiana, where
	one of her sons takes service with her master,
	and lies with his daughter, for which he is put in
	prison. Sicily rebels against King Charles, the son
	is recognised by the mother, marries the master's
	daughter, and, his brother being discovered, is reinstated
	in great honour.</p>
    </argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02060002" />The ladies and the young men alike had many a hearty laugh
      over Fiammetta's narrative of Andreuccio's adventures, which ended,
      Emilia, at the queen's command, thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="emilia" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02060003" />Grave and grievous are the vicissitudes with which Fortune
      makes us acquainted, and as discourse of such matter serves to
      awaken our minds, which are so readily lulled to sleep by her
      flatteries, I deem it worthy of attentive hearing by all, whether
      they enjoy her favour or endure her frown, in that it ministers
      counsel to the one sort and consolation to the other. <milestone id="p02060004" />Wherefore,
      albeit great matters have preceded it, I mean to tell you a story, not
      less true than touching, of adventures whereof the issue was indeed
      felicitous, but the antecedent bitterness so long drawn out that scarce
      can I believe that it was ever sweetened by ensuing happiness.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02060005" />Dearest ladies, you must know that after the death of the
      Emperor Frederic II. the crown of Sicily passed to Manfred; whose
      favour was enjoyed in the highest degree by a gentleman of Naples,
      Arrighetto Capece by name, who had to wife Madonna Beritola
      Caracciola, a fair and gracious lady, likewise a Neapolitan. <milestone id="p02060006" />Now
      <pb n="105" />when Manfred was conquered and slain by King Charles I. at
      Benevento, and the whole realm transferred its allegiance to the
      conqueror, Arrighetto, who was then governor of Sicily, no sooner
      received the tidings than he prepared for instant flight, knowing that
      little reliance was to be placed on the fleeting faith of the Sicilians,
      and not being minded to become a subject of his master's enemy.
      <milestone id="p02060007" />But the Sicilians having intelligence of his plans, he and many other
      friends and servants of King Manfred were surprised, taken prisoners
      and delivered over to King Charles, to whom the whole island was
      soon afterwards surrendered. <milestone id="p02060008" />In this signal reversal of the wonted
      course of things Madam Beritola, knowing not what was become
      of Arrighetto, and from the past ever auguring future evil, lest she
      should suffer foul dishonour, abandoned all that she possessed, and with
      a son of, perhaps, eight years, Giusfredi by name, being also pregnant,
      fled in a boat to Lipari, where she gave birth to another male child,
      whom she named Outcast. Then with her sons and a hired nurse
      she took ship for Naples, intending there to rejoin her family.
      <milestone id="p02060009" />Events, however, fell out otherwise than she expected; for by stress
      of weather the ship was carried out of her course to the desert
      island of Ponza,<note>The largest, now inhabited, of a group of islets in
	the
	Gulf of Gaeta.</note> where they put in to a little bay until such time
      as they might safely continue their voyage. <milestone id="p02060010" />Madam Beritola
      landed with the rest on the island, and, leaving them all, sought out
      a lonely and secluded spot, and there abandoned herself to melancholy
      brooding on the loss of her dear Arrighetto. While thus she spent
      her days in solitary preoccupation with her grief it chanced that a
      galley of corsairs swooped down upon the island, and, before either
      the mariners or any other folk were aware of their peril, made
      an easy capture of them all and sailed away; <milestone id="p02060011" />so that, when Madam
      Beritola, her wailing for that day ended, returned, as was her wont,
      to the shore to solace herself with the sight of her sons, she found
      none there. At first she was lost in wonder, then with a sudden
      suspicion of the truth she bent her eyes seaward, and there saw the
 galley still at no great distance, towing the ship in her wake. Thus
 apprehending beyond all manner of doubt that she had lost her sons
 as well as her husband, and that, alone, desolate and destitute, she
 might not hope that any of her lost ones would ever be restored to
 <pb n="106" />her, she fell down on the shore in a swoon with the names of her
 husband and sons upon her lips. <milestone id="p02060012" />None was there to administer cold
 water or aught else that might recall her truant powers; her animal
 spirits might even wander whithersoever they would at their sweet
 will: strength, however, did at last return to her poor exhausted
 frame, and therewith tears and lamentations, as, plaintively repeating
 her sons' names, she roamed in quest of them from cavern to cavern.
 <milestone id="p02060013" />Long time she sought them thus; but when she saw that her labour
 was in vain, and that night was closing in, hope, she knew not why,
 began to return, and with it some degree of anxiety on her own
 account. Wherefore she left the shore and returned to the cavern
 where she had been wont to indulge her plaintive mood. <milestone id="p02060014" />She
 passed the night in no small fear and indescribable anguish; the new
 day came, and, as she had not supped, she was fain after tierce to
 appease her hunger, as best she could, by a breakfast of herbs: this
 done, she wept and began to ruminate on her future way of life.
 <milestone id="p02060015" />While thus engaged, she observed a she-goat come by and go into
 an adjacent cavern, and after a while come forth again and go into
 the wood: thus roused from her reverie she got up, went into the
 cavern from which the she-goat had issued, and there saw two kids,
 which might have been born that very day, and seemed to her the
 sweetest and the most delicious things in the world: and, having,
 by reason of her recent delivery, milk still within her, she took them
 up tenderly, and set them to her breast. <milestone id="p02060016" />They, nothing loath,
 sucked at her teats as if she had been their own dam; and thenceforth
 made no distinction between her and the dam. Which caused
 the lady to feel that she had found company in the desert; and so,
 living on herbs and water, weeping as often as she bethought her
 of her husband and sons and her past life, she disposed herself to
 live and die there, and became no less familiar with the she-goat
 than with her young.</p><p><milestone id="p02060017" />The gentle lady thus leading the life of a wild creature, it
 chanced that after some months stress of weather brought a Pisan
 ship to the very same bay in which she had landed. The ship lay
 there for several days, <milestone id="p02060018" />having on board a gentleman, Currado de'
 Malespini by name (of the same family as the Marquis), who with
 his noble and most devout lady was returning home from a pilgrimage,
 having visited all the holy places in the realm of Apulia. 
<milestone id="p02060019" />To
 <pb n="107" />beguile the tedium of the sojourn Currado with his lady, some
 servants and his dogs, set forth one day upon a tour through the
 island. As they neared the place where Madam Beritola dwelt,
 Currado's dogs on view of the two kids, which, now of a fair size,
 were grazing, gave chase. The kids, pursued by the dogs, made
 straight for Madam Beritola's cavern. <milestone id="p02060020" />She, seeing what was toward,
 started to her feet, caught up a stick, and drove the dogs back.
 Currado and his lady coming up after the dogs, gazed on Madam
 Beritola, now tanned and lean and hairy, with wonder, which she
 more than reciprocated. <milestone id="p02060021" />At her request Currado called off the
 dogs; and then he and his lady besought her again and again to
 say who she was and what she did there. So she told them all
 about herself, her rank, her misfortunes, and the savage life which
 she was minded to lead. <milestone id="p02060022" />Currado, who had known Arrighetto
 Capece very well, was moved to tears by compassion, and exhausted
 all his eloquence to induce her to change her mind, offering to escort
 her home, or to take her to live with him in honourable estate as his
 sister until God should vouchsafe her kindlier fortune. <milestone id="p02060023" />The lady
 declining all his offers, Currado left her with his wife, whom he bade
 see that food was brought thither, and let Madam Beritola, who was
 all in rags, have one of her own dresses to wear, and do all that she
 could to persuade her to go with them. <milestone id="p02060024" />So the gentle lady stayed
 with Madam Beritola, and after condoling with her at large on her
 misfortunes had food and clothing brought to her, and with the
 greatest difficulty in the world prevailed upon her to eat and dress
 herself. At last, after much beseeching, she induced her to depart
 from her oft-declared intention never to go where she might meet
 any that knew her, and accompany them to Lunigiana, taking with
 her the two kids and the dam, which latter had in the meantime
 returned, and to the gentle lady's great surprise had greeted
 Madam Beritola with the utmost affection. <milestone id="p02060025" />So with the return
 of fair weather Madam Beritola, taking with her the dam and the
 two kids, embarked with Currado and his lady on their ship, being
 called by them--for her true name was not to be known of
 all--Cavriuola;<note>I. e. she-goat.</note> and the wind holding
 fair, they speedily reached the
 mouth of the Magra,<note>Between Liguria and Tuscany.</note> and landing
 hied
 them to Currado's castle;
 <pb n="108" />

<milestone id="p02060026" />where Madam Beritola abode with Currado's lady in the quality of
 her maid, serving her well and faithfully, wearing widow's weeds,
 and feeding and tending her kids with assiduous and loving care.</p><p><milestone id="p02060027" />The corsairs, who, not espying Madam Beritola, had left her at
 Ponza when they took the ship on which she had come thither,
 had made a course to Genoa, taking with them all the other folk.
 On their arrival the owners of the galley shared the booty, and so
 it happened that as part thereof Madam Beritola's nurse and her two
 boys fell to the lot of one Messer Guasparrino d'Oria, who sent all
 three to his house, being minded to keep them there as domestic
 slaves. <milestone id="p02060028" />The nurse, beside herself with grief at the loss of her
 mistress and the woful plight in which she found herself and her
 two charges, shed many a bitter tear. <milestone id="p02060029" />But, seeing that they were
 unavailing, and that she and the boys were slaves together, she,
 having, for all her low estate, her share of wit and good sense, made
 it her first care to comfort them; then, regardful of the condition
 to which they were reduced, she bethought her, that, if the lads were
 recognised, 'twould very likely be injurious to them. So, still hoping
 that some time or another Fortune would change her mood, and
 they be able, if living, to regain their lost estate, she resolved to let
 none know who they were, until she saw a fitting occasion; and
 accordingly, whenever she was questioned thereof by any, she gave
 them out as her own children. <milestone id="p02060030" />The name of the elder she changed
 from Giusfredi to Giannotto di Procida; the name of the younger
 she did not think it worth while to change. She spared no pains
 to make Giusfredi understand the reason why she had changed his
 name, and the risk which he might run if he were recognised.
 This she impressed upon him not once only but many times; and
 the boy, who was apt to learn, followed the instructions of the wise
 nurse with perfect exactitude.</p><p><milestone id="p02060031" />So the two boys, ill clad and worse shod, continued with the
 nurse in Messer Guasparrino's house for two years, patiently performing
 all kinds of menial offices. <milestone id="p02060032" />But Giannotto, being now
 sixteen years old, and of a spirit that consorted ill with servitude,
 brooked not the baseness of his lot, and dismissed himself from
 Messer Guasparrino's service by getting aboard a galley bound
 for Alexandria, and travelled far and wide, and fared never the
 better. In the course of his wanderings he learned that his father,
 <pb n="109" />whom he had supposed to be dead, was still living, but kept in prison
 under watch and ward by King Charles. <milestone id="p02060033" />He was grown a tall
 handsome young man, when, perhaps three or four years after he
 had given Messer Guasparrino the slip, weary of roaming and all
 but despairing of his fortune, he came to Lunigiana, and by chance
 took service with Currado Malespini, who found him handy, and
 was well-pleased with him. <milestone id="p02060034" />His mother, who was in attendance
 on Currado's lady, he seldom saw, and never recognised her, nor
 she him; so much had time changed both from their former aspect
 since they last met. <milestone id="p02060035" />While Giannotto was thus in the service of
 Currado, it fell out by the death of Niccol&#242; da Grignano that his
 widow, Spina, Currado's daughter, returned to her father's house.
 Very fair she was and loveable, her age not more than sixteen years,
 and so it was that she saw Giannotto with favour, and he her, and
 both fell ardently in love with one another. <milestone id="p02060036" />Their passion was
 early gratified; but several months elapsed before any detected its
 existence. Wherefore, growing overbold, they began to dispense with
 the precautions which such an affair demanded. <milestone id="p02060037" />So one day, as
 they walked with others through a wood, where the trees grew fair
 and close, the girl and Giannotto left the rest of the company some
 distance behind, and, thinking that they were well in advance, found
 a fair pleasaunce girt in with trees and carpeted with abundance of
 grass and flowers, and fell to solacing themselves after the manner
 of lovers. <milestone id="p02060038" />Long time they thus dallied, though such was their
 delight that all too brief it seemed to them, and so it befell that they
 were surprised first by the girl's mother and then by Currado.
 Pained beyond measure by what he had seen, Currado, without
 assigning any cause, had them both arrested by three of his servants
 and taken in chains to one of his castles; where in a frenzy of
 passionate wrath he left them, resolved to put them to an ignominious
 death. <milestone id="p02060039" />The girl's mother was also very angry, and deemed her
 daughter's fall deserving of the most rigorous chastisement, but,
 when by one of Currado's chance words she divined the doom which
 he destined for the guilty pair, she could not reconcile herself to
 it, and hasted to intercede with her angry husband, beseeching him
 to refrain the impetuous wrath which would hurry him in his
 old age to murder his daughter and imbrue his hands in the
 blood of his servant, and vent it in some other way, as by close
 <pb n="110" />confinement and duress, whereby the culprits should be brought to
 repent them of their fault in tears. <milestone id="p02060040" />Thus, and with much more
 to the like effect, the devout lady urged her suit, and at length
 prevailed upon her husband to abandon his murderous design.
 Wherefore, he commanded that the pair should be confined in
 separate prisons, and closely guarded, and kept short of food and
 in sore discomfort, until further order; which was accordingly done;
 <milestone id="p02060041" />and the life which the captives led, their endless tears, their fasts of
 inordinate duration, may be readily imagined.</p><p>Giannotto and Spina had languished in this sorry plight for full
 a year, entirely ignored by Currado, when in concert with Messer
 Gian di Procida, King Peter of Arragon raised a rebellion<note>The Sicilian
 Vespers, Easter, 1282.</note> in the island
 of Sicily, and wrested it from King Charles, whereat Currado, being a
 Ghibelline, was overjoyed. <milestone id="p02060042" />Hearing the tidings from one of his warders,
 Giannotto heaved a great sigh, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, fourteen years have I
 been a wanderer upon the face of the earth, looking for no other than
 this very event; and now, that my hopes of happiness may be for ever
 frustrate, it has come to pass only to find me in prison, whence I
 may never think to issue alive.</q> 
<milestone id="p02060043" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> said the warder; <q direct="unspecified">what
 signify to thee these doings of these mighty monarchs? What part
 hadst thou in Sicily?</q> 
<milestone id="p02060044" />Giannotto answered: <q direct="unspecified">'Tis as if my heart
 were breaking when I bethink me of my father and what part he had
 in Sicily. I was but a little lad when I fled the island, but yet I
 remember him as its governor in the time of King Manfred.</q>
 <milestone id="p02060045" /><q direct="unspecified">And who then was thy father?</q> demanded the warder. 
<milestone id="p02060046" /><q direct="unspecified">His
 name,</q> rejoined Giannotto, <q direct="unspecified">I need no longer scruple to disclose,
 seeing that I find myself in the very strait which I hoped to avoid by
 concealing it. He was and still is, if he live, Arrighetto Capece;
 and my name is not Giannotto but Giusfredi; and I doubt not but,
 were I once free, and back in Sicily, I might yet hold a very honourable
 position in the island.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02060047" />The worthy man asked no more questions, but, as soon as he found
 opportunity, told what he had learned to Currado; who, albeit he
 made light of it in the warder's presence, repaired to Madam Beritola,
 and asked her in a pleasant manner, whether she had had by Arrighetto
 a son named Giusfredi. The lady answered, in tears, that, if
 <pb n="111" />the elder of her two sons were living, such would be his name, and
 his age twenty-two years. <milestone id="p02060048" />This inclined Currado to think that
 Giannotto and Giusfredi were indeed one and the same; and it
 occurred to him, that, if so it were, he might at once shew himself
 most merciful and blot out his daughter's shame and his own by
 giving her to him in marriage; wherefore he sent for Giannotto
 privily, and questioned him in detail touching his past life. And
 finding by indubitable evidence that he was indeed Giusfredi, son of
 Arrighetto Capece, he said to him: 
<milestone id="p02060049" /><q direct="unspecified">Giannotto, thou knowest the
 wrong which thou hast done me in the person of my daughter, what
 and how great it is, seeing that I used thee well and kindly, and thou
 shouldst therefore, like a good servant, have shewn thyself jealous
 of my honour, and zealous in my interest; and many there are who,
 hadst thou treated them as thou hast treated me, would have caused
 thee to die an ignominious death; which my clemency would not
 brook. <milestone id="p02060050" />But now, as it is even so as thou sayst, and thou art of
 gentle blood by both thy parents, I am minded to put an end to thy
 sufferings as soon as thou wilt, releasing thee from the captivity in
 which thou languishest, and setting thee in a happy place, and reinstating
 at once thy honour and my own. <milestone id="p02060051" />Thy intimacy with Spina--albeit
 shameful to both--was yet prompted by love. Spina, as
 thou knowest, is a widow, and her dower is ample and secure. What
 her breeding is, and her father's and her mother's, thou knowest:
 of thy present condition I say nought. Wherefore, when thou wilt,
 I am consenting, that, having been with dishonour thy friend, she
 become with honour thy wife, and that, so long as it seem good to
 thee, thou tarry here with her and me as my son.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02060052" />Captivity had wasted Giannotto's flesh, but had in no degree
 impaired the generosity of spirit which he derived from his ancestry,
 or the whole-hearted love which he bore his lady. <milestone id="p02060053" />So, albeit he
 ardently desired that which Currado offered, and knew that he was
 in Currado's power, yet, even as his magnanimity prompted, so,
 unswervingly, he made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Currado, neither ambition nor
 cupidity nor aught else did ever beguile me to any treacherous
 machination against either thy person or thy property. <milestone id="p02060054" />Thy daughter
 I loved, and love and shall ever love, because I deem her worthy of
 my love; and, if I dealt with her after a fashion which to the
 mechanic mind seems hardly honourable, I did but commit that fault
 <pb n="112" />which is ever congenial to youth, which can never be eradicated so
 long as youth continues, and which, if the aged would but remember
 that they were once young and would measure the delinquencies
 of others by their own and their own by those of others, would not
 be deemed so grave as thou and many others depict it; and what
 I did, I did as a friend, not as an enemy. <milestone id="p02060055" />That which thou offerest
 I have ever desired, and should long ago have sought, had I supposed
 that thou wouldst grant it, and 'twill be the more grateful to me in
 proportion to the depth of my despair. <milestone id="p02060056" />But if thy intent be not such
 as thy words import, feed me not with vain hopes, but send me back
 to prison there to suffer whatever thou mayst be pleased to inflict; nor
 doubt that even as I love Spina, so for love of her shall I ever love
 thee, though thou do thy worst, and still hold thee in reverent
 regard.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02060057" />Currado marvelled to hear him thus speak, and being assured of
 his magnanimity and the fervour of his love, held him the more dear;
 wherefore he rose, embraced and kissed him, and without further
 delay bade privily bring thither Spina, who left her prison wasted and
 wan and weak, and so changed that she seemed almost another
 woman than of yore, even as Giannotto was scarce his former self.
 Then and there in Currado's presence they plighted their troth
 according to our custom of espousals; <milestone id="p02060058" />and some days afterwards
 Currado, having in the meantime provided all things meet for their
 convenience and solace, yet so as that none should surmise what had
 happened, deemed it now time to gladden their mothers with the
 news. So he sent for his lady and Cavriuola, and thus, addressing first
 Cavriuola, he spoke: <q direct="unspecified">What would you say, madam, were I to
 restore you your elder son as the husband of one of my daughters?</q>
 <milestone id="p02060059" />Cavriuola answered: <q direct="unspecified">I should say, that, were it possible for you
 to strengthen the bond which attaches me to you, then assuredly you
 had so done, in that you restored to me that which I cherish more
 tenderly than myself, and in such a guise as in some measure to renew
 within me the hope which I had lost: more I could not say.</q> And
 so, weeping, she was silent. <milestone id="p02060060" />Then, turning to his lady, Currado said:
 <q direct="unspecified">And thou, madam, what wouldst thou think if I were to present
 thee with such a son-in-law?</q> 
<milestone id="p02060061" /><q direct="unspecified">A son-in-law,</q> she answered,
 <q direct="unspecified">that was not of gentle blood, but a mere churl, so he pleased you,
 would well content me.</q> 
<milestone id="p02060062" /><q direct="unspecified">So!</q> returned Currado; <q direct="unspecified">I hope within
 a few days to gladden the hearts of both of you.</q></p><pb n="113" /><p><milestone id="p02060063" />He waited only until the two young folk had recovered their
 wonted mien, and were clad in a manner befitting their rank. Then,
 addressing Giusfredi, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Would it not add to thy joy to see
 thy mother here?</q> 
<milestone id="p02060064" /><q direct="unspecified">I dare not hope,</q> returned Giusfredi, <q direct="unspecified">that she
 has survived calamities and sufferings such as hers; but were it so,
 great indeed would be my joy, and none the less that by her counsel
 I might be aided to the recovery (in great measure) of my lost heritage
 in Sicily.</q> 
<milestone id="p02060065" />Whereupon Currado caused both the ladies to come
 thither, and presented to them the bride. The gladness with which
 they both greeted her was a wonder to behold, and no less great was
 their wonder at the benign inspiration that had prompted Currado to
 unite her in wedlock with Giannotto, <milestone id="p02060066" />whom Currado's words caused
 Madam Beritola to survey with some attention. A hidden spring of
 memory was thus touched; she recognised in the man the lineaments
 of her boy, and awaiting no further evidence she ran with open arms
 and threw herself upon his neck. No word did she utter, for very
 excess of maternal tenderness and joy; but, every avenue of sense
 closed, she fell as if bereft of life within her son's embrace. 
<milestone id="p02060067" />Giannotto,
 who had often seen her in the castle and never recognised her,
 marvelled not a little, but nevertheless it at once flashed upon him
 that 'twas his mother, and blaming himself for his past inadvertence
 he took her in his arms and wept and tenderly kissed her. 
<milestone id="p02060068" />With gentle
 solicitude Currado's lady and Spina came to her aid, and restored her
 suspended animation with cold water and other remedies. She then
 with many tender and endearing words kissed him a thousand times
 or more, which tokens of her love he received with a look of reverential
 acknowledgment. <milestone id="p02060069" />Thrice, nay a fourth time were these glad
 and gracious greetings exchanged, and joyful indeed were they that
 witnessed them, and hearkened while mother and son compared their
 past adventures. Then Currado, who had already announced his new
 alliance to his friends, and received their felicitations, proceeded to
 give order for the celebration of the event with all becoming gaiety
 and splendour. As he did so, Giusfredi said to him: 
<milestone id="p02060070" /><q direct="unspecified">Currado, you
 have long given my mother honourable entertainment, and on me
 you have conferred many boons; wherefore, that you may fill up the
 measure of your kindness, 'tis now my prayer that you be pleased to
 gladden my mother and my marriage feast and me with the presence
 of my brother, now in servitude in the house of Messer Guasparrino
 <pb n="114" />d'Oria, who, as I have already told you, made prize of both him and
 me; and that then you send some one to Sicily, who shall make himself
 thoroughly acquainted with the circumstances and condition of
 the country, and find out how it has fared with my father Arrighetto,
 whether he be alive or dead, and if alive, in what circumstances, and
 being thus fully informed, return to us with the tidings.</q> 
<milestone id="p02060071" />Currado
 assented, and forthwith sent most trusty agents both to Genoa and to
 Sicily. So in due time an envoy arrived at Genoa, and made instant
 suit to Guasparrino on Currado's part for the surrender of Outcast and
 the nurse, setting forth in detail all that had passed between Currado
 and Giusfredi and his mother. <milestone id="p02060072" />Whereat Messer Guasparrino was
 mightily astonished, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Of a surety there is nought that, being
 able, I would not do to pleasure Currado; and true it is that I have
 had in my house for these fourteen years the boy whom thou dost now
 demand of me, and his mother, and gladly will I surrender them; but
 tell Currado from me to beware of excessive credulity, and to put no
 faith in the idle tales of Giannotto, or Giusfredi, as thou sayst he
 calls himself, who is by no means so guileless as he supposes.</q></p><p><milestone id="p02060073" />Then, having provided for the honourable entertainment of the
 worthy envoy, he sent privily for the nurse, and cautiously sounded
 her as to the affair. The nurse had heard of the revolt of Sicily, and
 had learned that Arrighetto was still alive. She therefore banished
 fear, and told Messer Guasparrino the whole story, and explained to
 him the reasons why she had acted as she had done. 
<milestone id="p02060074" />Finding that
 what she said accorded very well with what he had learned from
 Currado's envoy, he inclined to credit the story, and most astutely
 probing the matter in divers ways, and always finding fresh grounds
 for confidence, he reproached himself for the sorry manner in which
 he had treated the boy, and by way of amends gave him one of his
 own daughters, a beautiful girl of eleven years, to wife with a dowry
 suited to Arrighetto's rank, <milestone id="p02060075" />and celebrated their nuptials with great
 festivity. He then brought the boy and girl, Currado's envoy, and the
 nurse in a well-armed galliot to Lerici, being there met by Currado,
 who had a castle not far off, where great preparations had been made
 for their entertainment: and thither accordingly he went with his
 whole company. 
<milestone id="p02060076" />What cheer the mother had of her son, the brothers
 of one another, and all the three of the faithful nurse; what cheer
 Messer Guasparrino and his daughter had of all, and all of them, and
 <pb n="115" />what cheer all had of Currado and his lady and their sons and their
 friends, words may not describe; wherefore, my ladies, I leave it to
 your imagination. And that their joy might be full, God, who, when
 He gives, gives most abundantly, added the glad tidings that Arrighetto
 Capece was alive and prosperous. <milestone id="p02060077" />For, when in the best of spirits the
 ladies and gentlemen had sat them down to feast, and they were yet
 at the first course, the envoy from Sicily arrived, and among other
 matters reported, that, no sooner had the insurrection broken out in the
 island than the people hied them in hot haste to the prison where
 Arrighetto was kept in confinement by King Charles, and despatching
 the guards, brought him forth, and knowing him to be a capital
 enemy to King Charles made him their captain, and under his command
 fell upon and massacred the French. <milestone id="p02060078" />Whereby he had won
 the highest place in the favour of King Peter, who had granted him
 restitution of all his estates and honours, so that he was now both
 prosperous and mighty. The envoy added that Arrighetto had
 received him with every token of honour, had manifested the utmost
 delight on hearing of his lady and son, of whom no tidings had reached
 him since his arrest, and had sent, to bring them home, a brigantine
 with some gentlemen aboard, whose arrival might hourly be expected.</p><p><milestone id="p02060079" />The envoy, and the good news which he brought, were heartily
 welcome; and presently Currado, with some of his friends, encountered
 the gentlemen who came for Madam Beritola and Giusfredi, and
 saluting them cordially invited them to his feast, which was not yet
 half done. <milestone id="p02060080" />Joy unheard-of was depicted on the faces of the lady, of
 Giusfredi, and of all the rest as they greeted them; nor did they on
 their part take their places at the table before, as best they might,
 they had conveyed to Currado and his lady Arrighetto's greetings and
 grateful acknowledgments of the honour which they had conferred
 upon his lady and his son, and had placed Arrighetto, to the uttermost
 of his power, entirely at their service. <milestone id="p02060081" />Then, turning to Messer
 Guasparrino, of whose kindness Arrighetto surmised nothing, they
 said that they were very sure that, when he learned the boon which
 Outcast had received at his hands, he would pay him the like and an
 even greater tribute of gratitude. This speech ended, they feasted
 most joyously with the brides and bridegrooms. <milestone id="p02060082" />So passed the day,
 the first of many which Currado devoted to honouring his son-in-law
 and his other intimates, both kinsfolk and friends. The time of
 <pb n="116" />festivity ended, Madam Beritola and Giusfredi and the rest felt that
 they must leave: so, taking Spina with them, they parted, not
 without many tears, from Currado and his lady and Guasparrino, and
 went aboard the brigantine, <milestone id="p02060083" />which, wafted by a prosperous wind,
 soon brought them to Sicily. At Palermo they were met by
 Arrighetto, who received them all, ladies and sons alike, with such
 cheer as it were vain to attempt to describe. There it is believed
 that they all lived long and happily and in amity with God, being
 not unmindful of the blessings which He had conferred upon them.</p></div2>