<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0501"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05010001" />Cimon, by loving, waxes wise, wins his wife Iphigenia by
 capture on the high seas, and is imprisoned at Rhodes.
 He is delivered by Lysimachus; and the twain capture
 Cassandra and recapture Iphigenia in the hour of their
 marriage. They flee with their ladies to Crete, and
 having there married them, are brought back to their
 homes.</p></argument><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05010002" />Many stories, sweet my ladies, occur to me as meet for me to
 tell by way of ushering in a day so joyous as this will be: of which
 one does most commend itself to my mind, because not only has it
 one of those happy endings of which to-day we are in quest, but
 'twill enable you to understand how holy, how mighty and how
 salutary are the forces of Love, which not a few, witting not what
 they say, do most unjustly reprobate and revile: which, if I err not,
 should to you, for that I take you to be enamoured, be indeed
 welcome.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p05010003" />Once upon a time, then, as we have read in the ancient histories
 of the Cypriotes, there was in the island of Cyprus a very great
 noble named Aristippus, a man rich in all worldly goods beyond all
 other of his countrymen, and who might have deemed himself
 incomparably blessed, but for a single sore affliction that Fortune had
 allotted him. <milestone id="p05010004" />Which was that among his sons he had one, the best
 grown and handsomest of them all, that was well-nigh a hopeless
 imbecile. His true name was Galesus; but, as neither his tutor's
 pains, nor his father's coaxing or chastisement, nor any other method
 had availed to imbue him with any tincture of letters or manners, <pb n="3" />but
 he still remained gruff and savage of voice, and in his bearing
 liker to a beast than to a man, all, as in derision, were wont to call
 him Cimon, which in their language signifies the same as <q direct="unspecified">bestione</q>
 (brute)<note>One of the augmentative forms of bestia.</note> in ours. 
<milestone id="p05010005" />The father, grieved beyond measure to see his
 son's life thus blighted, and having abandoned all hope of his recovery,
 nor caring to have the cause of his mortification ever before his
 eyes, bade him betake him to the farm, and there keep with his
 husbandmen. To Cimon the change was very welcome, because
 the manners and habits of the uncouth hinds were more to his taste
 than those of the citizens. <milestone id="p05010006" />So to the farm Cimon hied him, and
 addressed himself to the work thereof; and being thus employed, he
 chanced one afternoon as he passed, staff on shoulder, from one
 domain to another, to enter a plantation, the like of which for beauty
 there was not in those parts, and which was then--for 'twas the
 month of May--a mass of greenery; <milestone id="p05010007" />and, as he traversed it, he
 came, as Fortune was pleased to guide him, to a meadow girt in with
 trees exceeding tall, and having in one of its corners a fountain most
 fair and cool, beside which he espied a most beautiful girl lying
 asleep on the green grass, clad only in a vest of such fine stuff that it
 scarce in any measure veiled the whiteness of her flesh, and below the
 waist nought but an apron most white and fine of texture; and
 likewise at her feet there slept two women and a man, her slaves.
 <milestone id="p05010008" />No sooner did Cimon catch sight of her, than, as if he had never
 before seen form of woman, he stopped short, and leaning on his
 cudgel, regarded her intently, saying never a word, and lost in admiration.
 And in his rude soul, which, despite a thousand lessons, had
 hitherto remained impervious to every delight that belongs to urbane
 life, he felt the awakening of an idea, that bade his gross and coarse
 mind acknowledge, that this girl was the fairest creature that had ever
 been seen by mortal eye. <milestone id="p05010009" />And thereupon he began to distinguish
 her several parts, praising her hair, which shewed to him as gold, her
 brow, her nose and mouth, her throat and arms, and above all her
 bosom, which was as yet but in bud, and as he gazed, he changed
 of a sudden from a husbandman into a judge of beauty, and desired
 of all things to see her eyes, which the weight of her deep slumber
 kept close shut, and many a time he would fain have awakened <pb n="4" />her,
 that he might see them. <milestone id="p05010010" />But so much fairer seemed she to
 him than any other woman that he had seen, that he doubted
 she must be a goddess; and as he was not so devoid of sense but
 that he deemed things divine more worthy of reverence than things
 mundane, he forbore, and waited until she should awake of her
 own accord; and though he found the delay overlong, yet,
 enthralled by so unwonted a delight, he knew not how to be
 going. <milestone id="p05010011" />However, after he had tarried a long while, it so befell
 that Iphigenia--such was the girl's name--her slaves still sleeping,
 awoke, and raised her head, and opened her eyes, and seeing
 Cimon standing before her, leaning on his staff, was not a little
 surprised, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Cimon, what seekest thou in this wood at
 this hour?</q> 
<milestone id="p05010012" />For Cimon she knew well, as indeed did almost all the
 country-side, by reason alike of his uncouth appearance as of the rank
 and wealth of his father. To Iphigenia's question he answered never
 a word; but as soon as her eyes were open, nought could he do but
 intently regard them, for it seemed to him that a soft influence
 emanated from them, which filled his soul with a delight that he had
 never before known. <milestone id="p05010013" />Which the girl marking began to misdoubt
 that by so fixed a scrutiny his boorish temper might be prompted to
 some act that should cause her dishonour: wherefore she roused her
 women, and got up, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Keep thy distance, Cimon, in God's
 name.</q> 
<milestone id="p05010014" />Whereto Cimon made answer: <q direct="unspecified">I will come with thee.</q>
 <milestone id="p05010015" />And, albeit the girl refused his escort, being still in fear of him, she
 could not get quit of him; but he attended her home; after which
 he hied him straight to his father's house, and announced that he was
 minded on no account to go back to the farm: which intelligence was
 far from welcome to his father and kinsmen; but nevertheless they
 suffered him to stay, and waited to see what might be the reason or
 his change of mind. <milestone id="p05010016" />So Cimon, whose heart, closed to all teaching,
 love's shaft, sped by the beauty of Iphigenia, had penetrated, did now
 graduate in wisdom with such celerity as to astonish his father and
 kinsmen, and all that knew him. <milestone id="p05010017" />He began by requesting his father
 to let him go clad in the like apparel, and with, in all respects, the
 like personal equipment as his brothers: which his father very gladly
 did. <milestone id="p05010018" />Mixing thus with the gallants, and becoming familiar with the
 manners proper to gentlemen, and especially to lovers, he very soon,
 to the exceeding great wonder of all, not only acquired the rudiments <pb n="5" />of
 letters, but waxed most eminent among the philosophic wits.
 <milestone id="p05010019" />After which (for no other cause than the love he bore to Iphigenia)
 he not only modulated his gruff and boorish voice to a degree of
 smoothness suitable to urbane life, but made himself accomplished in
 singing and music; in riding also and in all matters belonging to
 war, as well by sea as by land, he waxed most expert and hardy. <milestone id="p05010020" />And
 in sum (that I go not about to enumerate each of his virtues in
 detail) he had not completed the fourth year from the day of his
 first becoming enamoured before he was grown the most gallant, and
 courteous, ay, and the most perfect in particular accomplishments, of
 the young cavaliers that were in the island of Cyprus. <milestone id="p05010021" />What then,
 gracious ladies, are we to say of Cimon? Verily nought else but
 that the high faculties, with which Heaven had endowed his noble
 soul, invidious Fortune had bound with the strongest of cords, and
 circumscribed within a very narrow region of his heart; all which
 cords Love, more potent than Fortune, burst and brake in pieces;
 <milestone id="p05010022" />and then with the might, wherewith he awakens dormant powers, he
 brought them forth of the cruel obfuscation, in which they lay, into
 clear light, plainly shewing thereby, whence he may draw, and
 whither he may guide, by his beams the souls that are subject to
 his sway.</p><p><milestone id="p05010023" />Now, albeit by his love for Iphigenia Cimon was betrayed, as
 young lovers very frequently are, into some peccadillos, yet Aristippus,
 reflecting that it had turned him from a booby into a man, not
 only bore patiently with him, but exhorted him with all his heart to
 continue steadfast in his love <milestone id="p05010024" />And Cimon, who still refused to be
 called Galesus, because 'twas as Cimon that Iphigenia had first
 addressed him, being desirous to accomplish his desire by honourable
 means, did many a time urge his suit upon her father, Cipseus, that
 he would give her him to wife: whereto Cipseus always made the
 same answer, to wit, that he had promised her to Pasimondas, a
 young Rhodian noble, and was not minded to break faith with him.
 <milestone id="p05010025" />However, the time appointed for Iphigenia's wedding being come,
 and the bridegroom having sent for her, Cimon said to himself:
 'Tis now for me to shew thee, O Iphigenia, how great is my love
 for thee: 'tis by thee that I am grown a man, nor doubt I, if I
 shall have thee, that I shall wax more glorious than a god, and verily
 thee will I have, or die. <milestone id="p05010026" />Having so said, he privily enlisted in his
 <pb n="6" />cause
 certain young nobles that were his friends, and secretly fitted
 out a ship with all equipment meet for combat, and put to sea on the
 look-out for the ship that was to bear Iphigenia to Rhodes and her
 husband. And at length, when her father had done lavishing
 honours upon her husband's friends, Iphigenia embarked, and, the
 mariners shaping their course for Rhodes, put to sea. <milestone id="p05010027" />Cimon was on
 the alert, and overhauled them the very next day, and standing on
 his ship's prow shouted amain to those that were aboard Iphigenia's
 ship: <q direct="unspecified">Bring to; strike sails, or look to be conquered and sunk in
 the sea.</q> 
<milestone id="p05010028" />Then, seeing that the enemy had gotten their arms above
 deck, and were making ready to make a fight of it, he followed up his
 words by casting a grapnel upon the poop of the Rhodians, who were
 making great way; and having thus made their poop fast to his prow,
 he sprang, fierce as a lion, reckless whether he were followed or no,
 on to the Rhodians' ship, making, as it were, no account of them,
 and animated by love, hurled himself, sword in hand, with prodigious
 force among the enemy, and cutting and thrusting right and left,
      slaughtered them like sheep; <milestone id="p05010029" />insomuch that the Rhodians, marking
 the fury of his onset, threw down their arms, and as with one voice
 did all acknowledge themselves his prisoners. <milestone id="p05010030" />To whom Cimon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Gallants,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'twas neither lust of booty nor enmity to
 you that caused me to put out from Cyprus to attack you here with
 force of arms on the high seas. <milestone id="p05010031" />Moved was I thereto by that which
 to gain is to me a matter great indeed, which peaceably to yield me
 is to you but a slight matter; for 'tis even Iphigenia, whom more
 than aught else I love; whom, as I might not have her of her father
 in peaceable and friendly sort, Love has constrained me to take from
 you in this high-handed fashion and by force of arms; <milestone id="p05010032" />to whom I
 mean to be even such as would have been your Pasimondas: wherefore
 give her to me, and go your way, and God's grace go with
 you.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05010033" />Yielding rather to force than prompted by generosity, the Rhodians
 surrendered Iphigenia, all tears, to Cimon; who, marking her tears,
 said to her: <q direct="unspecified">Grieve not, noble lady; thy Cimon am I, who, by my
 long love, have established a far better right to thee than Pasimondas
 by the faith that was plighted to him.</q> 
<milestone id="p05010034" />So saying, he sent her aboard
 his ship, whither he followed her, touching nought that belonged to
 the Rhodians, and suffering them to go their way. 
<milestone id="p05010035" />To have gotten <pb n="7" />so
 dear a prize made him the happiest man in the world, but for a
 time 'twas all he could do to assuage her grief: then, after taking
 counsel with his comrades, he deemed it best not to return to Cyprus
 for the present: and so, by common consent they shaped their course
 for Crete, where most of them, and especially Cimon, had alliances
 of old or recent date, and friends not a few, whereby they deemed
 that there they might tarry with Iphigenia in security. <milestone id="p05010036" />But Fortune,
 that had accorded Cimon so gladsome a capture of the lady, suddenly
 proved fickle, and converted the boundless joy of the enamoured
 gallant into woeful and bitter lamentation. <milestone id="p05010037" />'Twas not yet full four
 hours since Cimon had parted from the Rhodians, when with the
 approach of night, that night from which Cimon hoped such joyance
 as he had never known, came weather most turbulent and tempestuous,
 which wrapped the heavens in cloud, and swept the sea with scathing
 blasts; whereby 'twas not possible for any to see how the ship was
 to be worked or steered, or to steady himself so as to do any duty upon
 her deck. <milestone id="p05010038" />Whereat what grief was Cimon's, it boots not to ask.
 Indeed it seemed to him that the gods had granted his heart's desire
 only that it might be harder for him to die, which had else been to
 him but a light matter. <milestone id="p05010039" />Not less downcast were his comrades; but
 most of all Iphigenia, who, weeping bitterly and shuddering at every
 wave that struck the ship, did cruelly curse Cimon's love and censure
 his rashness, averring that this tempest was come upon them for no
 other cause than that the gods had decreed, that, as 'twas in despite
 of their will that he purposed to espouse her, he should be frustrate of
 his presumptuous intent, and having lived to see her expire, should
 then himself meet a woeful death.</p><p><milestone id="p05010040" />While thus and yet more bitterly they bewailed them, and the
 mariners were at their wits' end, as the gale grew hourly more violent,
 nor knew they, nor might conjecture, whither they went, they drew
 nigh the island of Rhodes, albeit that Rhodes it was they wist not,
 and set themselves, as best and most skilfully they might, to run the
 ship aground. <milestone id="p05010041" />In which enterprise Fortune favoured them, bringing
 them into a little bay, where, shortly before them, was arrived the
 Rhodian ship that Cimon had let go. Nor were they sooner ware
 that 'twas Rhodes they had made, than day broke, and, the sky thus
 brightening a little, they saw that they were about a bow-shot from
 the ship that they had released on the preceding day. 
<milestone id="p05010042" />Whereupon <pb n="8" />Cimon,
 vexed beyond measure, being apprehensive of that which in
 fact befell them, bade make every effort to win out of the bay, and
 let Fortune carry them whither she would, for nowhere might they be
 in worse plight than there. <milestone id="p05010043" />So might and main they strove to bring
 the ship out, but all in vain: the violence of the gale thwarted them
 to such purpose as not only to preclude their passage out of the bay but
 to drive them, willing nilling, ashore. <milestone id="p05010044" />Whither no sooner were they
 come, than they were recognized by the Rhodian mariners, who were
 already landed. Of whom one ran with all speed to a farm hard by,
 whither the Rhodian gallants were gone, and told them that Fortune
 had brought Cimon and Iphigenia aboard their ship into the same
 bay to which she had guided them. <milestone id="p05010045" />Whereat the gallants were overjoyed,
 and taking with them not a few of the farm-servants, hied
 them in hot haste to the shore, where, Cimon and his men being
 already landed with intent to take refuge in a neighbouring wood,
 they took them all (with Iphigenia) and brought them to the farm.
 Whence, pursuant to an order of the Senate of Rhodes, to which, so
 soon as he received the news, Pasimondas made his complaint, Cimon
 and his men were all marched off to prison by Lysimachus, chief
 magistrate of the Rhodians for that year, who came down from the
 city for the purpose with an exceeding great company of men at
 arms. <milestone id="p05010046" />On such wise did our hapless and enamoured Cimon lose his
 so lately won Iphigenia before he had had of her more than a kiss
 or two. <milestone id="p05010047" />Iphigenia was entertained and comforted of the annoy,
 occasioned as well by her recent capture as by the fury of the sea, by
 not a few noble ladies of Rhodes, with whom she tarried until the
 day appointed for her marriage. <milestone id="p05010048" />In recompense of the release of the
 Rhodian gallants on the preceding day the lives of Cimon and his
 men were spared, notwithstanding that Pasimondas pressed might
 and main for their execution; and instead they were condemned to
 perpetual imprisonment: wherein, as may be supposed, they abode in
 dolorous plight, and despaired of ever again knowing happiness.</p><p>However, it so befell that, Pasimondas accelerating his nuptials to
 the best of his power, <milestone id="p05010049" />Fortune, as if repenting her that in her haste
 she had done Cimon so evil a turn, did now by a fresh disposition of
 events compass his deliverance. Pasimondas had a brother, by name
 Hormisdas, his equal in all respects save in years, who had long
 been contract to marry Cassandra, a fair and noble damsel of <pb n="9" />Rhodes,
 of whom Lysimachus was in the last degree enamoured;
 but owing to divers accidents the marriage had been from time to
 time put off. <milestone id="p05010050" />Now Pasimondas, being about to celebrate his nuptials
 with exceeding great pomp, bethought him that he could not do
 better than, to avoid a repetition of the pomp and expense, arrange, if
 so he might, that his brother should be wedded on the same day
 with himself. So, having consulted anew with Cassandra's kinsfolk,
 and come to an understanding with them, he and his brother and
 they conferred together, and agreed that on the same day that
 Pasimondas married Iphigenia, Hormisdas should marry Cassandra.
 <milestone id="p05010051" />Lysimachus, getting wind of this arrangement, was mortified beyond
 measure, seeing himself thereby deprived of the hope which he cherished
 of marrying Cassandra himself, if Hormisdas should not forestall
 him. <milestone id="p05010052" />But like a wise man he concealed his chagrin, and cast about
 how he might frustrate the arrangement: to which end he saw no
 other possible means but to carry Cassandra off. <milestone id="p05010053" />It did not escape
 him that the office which he held would render this easily feasible,
 but he deemed it all the more dishonourable than if he had not held
 the office; but, in short, after much pondering, honour yielded place
 to love, and he made up his mind that, come what might, he would
 carry Cassandra off. <milestone id="p05010054" />Then, as he took thought what company he
 should take with him, and how he should go about the affair, he
 remembered Cimon, whom he had in prison with his men, and it
 occurred to him that he could not possibly have a better or more trusty
 associate in such an enterprise than Cimon. <milestone id="p05010055" />Wherefore the same night
 he caused Cimon to be brought privily to him in his own room, and
 thus addressed him: <q direct="unspecified">Cimon, as the gods are most generous and
 liberal to bestow their gifts on men, so are they also most sagacious
 to try their virtue; and those whom they find to be firm and steadfast
 in all circumstances they honour, as the most worthy, with the
 highest rewards. <milestone id="p05010056" />They have been minded to be certified of thy
 worth by better proofs than thou couldst afford them, as long as thy
 life was bounded by thy father's house amid the superabundant wealth
 which I know him to possess: wherefore in the first place they so
 wrought upon thee with the shrewd incitements of Love that from an
 insensate brute, as I have heard, thou grewest to be a man; since
 when, it has been and is their intent to try whether evil fortune and
 harsh imprisonment may avail to change thee from the temper that <pb n="10" />was
 thine when for a short while thou hadst joyance of the prize
 thou hadst won. <milestone id="p05010057" />And so thou prove the same that thou wast then,
 they have in store for thee a boon incomparably greater than aught
 that they vouchsafed thee before: what that boon is, to the end thou
 mayst recover heart and thy wonted energies, I will now explain to
 thee. <milestone id="p05010058" />Pasimondas, exultant in thy misfortune and eager to compass thy
 death, hastens to the best of his power his nuptials with thy Iphigenia;
 that so he may enjoy the prize that Fortune, erstwhile smiling, gave
 thee, and forthwith, frowning, reft from thee. Whereat how sore
 must be thy grief, if rightly I gauge thy love, I know by my own
 case, seeing that his brother Hormisdas addresses himself to do me on
 the same day a like wrong in regard of Cassandra, whom I love more
 than aught else in the world. <milestone id="p05010059" />Nor see I that Fortune has left us
 any way of escape from this her unjust and cruel spite, save what we
 may make for ourselves by a resolved spirit and the might of our
 right hands: take we then the sword, and therewith make we, each,
 prize of his lady, thou for the second, I for the first time: for so thou
 value the recovery, I say not of thy liberty, for without thy lady I doubt
 thou wouldst hold it cheap, but of thy lady, the gods have placed it in
 thine own hands, if thou art but minded to join me in my enterprise.</q></p><p><milestone id="p05010060" />These words restored to Cimon all that he had lost of heart and
 hope, nor pondered he long, before he replied: <q direct="unspecified">Lysimachus, comrade
 stouter or more staunch than I thou mightst not have in such
 an enterprise, if such indeed it be as thou sayst: wherefore lay upon
 me such behest as thou shalt deem meet, and thou shalt marvel to
 witness the vigour of my performance.</q> 
<milestone id="p05010061" />Whereupon Lysimachus:
 <q direct="unspecified">On the third day from now,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">their husbands' houses
 will be newly entered by the brides, and on the same day at even we
 too will enter them in arms, thou with thy men, and I with some of
 mine, in whom I place great trust, and forcing our way among the
 guests and slaughtering all that dare to oppose us, will bear the ladies
 off to a ship which I have had privily got ready.</q> 
<milestone id="p05010062" />Cimon approved
 the plan, and kept quiet in prison until the appointed time; 
<milestone id="p05010063" />which being come, the nuptials were celebrated with great pomp and
 magnificence, that filled the houses of the two brothers with festal
 cheer. <milestone id="p05010064" />Then Lysimachus having made ready all things meet, and fired
 Cimon and his men and his own friends for the enterprise by a long
 harangue, disposed them in due time, all bearing arms under their
 <pb n="11" />cloaks,
 in three companies; and having privily despatched one company
 to the port, that, when the time should come to embark, he might
 meet with no let, he marched with the other two companies to the
 house of Pasimondas, posted the one company at the gate, that, being
 entered, they might not be shut in or debarred their egress, and, with
 the other company and Cimon, ascended the stairs, <milestone id="p05010065" />and gained the
 saloon, where the brides and not a few other ladies were set at several
 tables to sup in meet order: whereupon in they rushed, and overthrew
 the tables and seized each his own lady, and placed them in
 charge of their men, whom they bade bear them off forthwith to the
 ship that lay ready to receive them. <milestone id="p05010066" />Whereupon the brides and the
 other ladies and the servants with one accord fell a sobbing and
 shrieking, insomuch that a confused din and lamentation filled the
 whole place. <milestone id="p05010067" />Cimon, Lysimachus and their band, none withstanding,
 but all giving way before them, gained the stairs, which they were
 already descending when they encountered Pasimondas, who, carrying
 a great staff in his hand, was making in the direction of the noise;
 but one doughty stroke of Cimon's sword sufficed to cleave his skull
 in twain, and lay him dead at Cimon's feet, <milestone id="p05010068" />and another stroke
 disposed of hapless Hormisdas, as he came running to his brother's
 aid. Some others who ventured to approach them were wounded
 and beaten off by the retinue. <milestone id="p05010069" />So forth of the house, that reeked
 with blood and resounded with tumult and lamentation and woe,
 sped Simon and Lysimachus with all their company, and without any
 let, in close order, with their fair booty in their midst, made good
 their retreat to the ship; whereon with the ladies they one and all
 embarked, for the shore was now full of armed men come to rescue
 the ladies, and, the oarsmen giving way, put to sea elate. 
<milestone id="p05010070" />Arrived at
 Crete, they met with a hearty welcome on the part of their many
 friends and kinsfolk; and, having married their ladies, they made
 greatly merry, and had gladsome joyance of their fair booty. Their
 doings occasioned, both in Cyprus and in Rhodes, no small stir and
 commotion, which lasted for a long while: but in the end, by the
 good offices of their friends and kinsfolk in both islands, 'twas so
 ordered as that after a certain term of exile Cimon returned with
 Iphigenia to Cyprus, and in like manner Lysimachus returned with
 Cassandra to Rhodes; and long and blithely thereafter lived they,
 each well contented with his own wife in his own land.</p></div2>