<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0406"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04060001" />Andreuola loves Gabriotto: she tells him a dream that
 she has had; he tells her a dream of his own, ana
 dies suddenly in her arms. While she and her maia
 are carrying his corpse to his house, they are taken
 by the Signory. She tells how the matter stands, is
 threatened with violence by the Podest&#224;, but will not
 brook it. Her father hears how she is bested; and,
 her innocence being established, causes her to be set
 at large; but she, being minded to tarry no longer in
 the world, becomes a nun.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04060002" />Glad indeed were the ladies to have heard
	Filomena's story, for
	that, often though they had heard the song sung, they had never
	yet, for all their enquiries, been able to learn the occasion upon
	which it was made. When 'twas ended, Pamfilo received the
	king's command to follow suit, and thus spoke:</p></div3><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04060003" />By the dream
	told in the foregoing story I am prompted to relate one in which
	two dreams are told, dreams of that which was to come, as Lisabetta's
	was of that which had been, and which were both fulfilled
	almost as soon as they were told by those that had dreamed them.
	<milestone id="p04060004" />Wherefore, loving ladies, you must know that 'tis the common
	experience of mankind to have divers visions during sleep; and albeit
	the sleeper, while he sleeps, deems all alike most true, but, being
	awake, judges some of them to be true, others to be probable, and
	others again to be quite devoid of truth, yet not a few are found to
	have come to pass. <milestone id="p04060005" />For which cause many are as sure of every
	<pb n="303" />dream as of aught that they see in their waking hours, and so, as
	their dreams engender in them fear or hope, are sorrowful or joyous.
	And on the other hand there are those that credit no dream, until
	they see themselves fallen into the very peril whereof they were
	forewarned. Of whom I approve neither sort, for in sooth neither are
	all dreams true, nor all alike false. <milestone id="p04060006" />That they are not all true, there
	is none of us but may many a time have proved; and that they are
	not all alike false has already been shewn in Filomena's story, and
	shall also, as I said before, be shewn in mine. <milestone id="p04060007" />Wherefore I deem
	that in a virtuous course of life and conduct there is no need to fear
	aught by reason of any dream that is contrary thereto, or on that
	account to give up any just design; and as for crooked and sinister
	enterprises, however dreams may seem to favour them, and flatter
	the hopes of the dreamer with auspicious omens, none should trust
	them: rather should all give full credence to such as run counter
	thereto. But come we to the story.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04060008" />In the city of Brescia there lived of yore a gentleman named
 Messer Negro da Ponte Carraro, who with other children had a
 very fair daughter, Andreuola by name, who, being unmarried,
 chanced to fall in love with a neighbour, one Gabriotto, a man of
 low degree, but goodly of person and debonair, and endowed with
 all admirable qualities; <milestone id="p04060009" />and aided and abetted by the housemaid, the
 girl not only brought it to pass that Gabriotto knew that he was
 beloved of her, but that many a time to their mutual delight he
 came to see her in a fair garden belonging to her father. And that
 nought but death might avail to sever them from this their gladsome
 love, they became privily man and wife; and, while thus they
 continued their clandestine intercourse, it happened that one night,
 while the girl slept, she saw herself in a dream in her garden with
 Gabriotto, who to the exceeding great delight of both held her in his
 arms; <milestone id="p04060010" />and while thus they lay, she saw issue from his body somewhat
 dark and frightful, the shape whereof she might not discern;
 which, as she thought, laid hold of Gabriotto, and in her despite
 with prodigious force reft him from her embrace, and bore him with
 it underground, so that both were lost to her sight for evermore:
 <milestone id="p04060011" />whereby stricken with sore and inexpressible grief, she awoke; and
 albeit she was overjoyed to find that 'twas not as she had dreamed,
 yet a haunting dread of what she had seen in her vision entered her
 <pb n="304" />soul. Wherefore, Gabriotto being minded to visit her on the ensuing
 night, she did her best endeavour to dissuade him from coming; but
 seeing that he was bent upon it, lest he should suspect somewhat,
 she received him in her garden, <milestone id="p04060012" />where, having culled roses many,
 white and red--for 'twas summer--she sat herself down with him
 at the base of a most fair and lucent fountain. There long and
 joyously they dallied, and then Gabriotto asked her wherefore she
 had that day forbade his coming. Whereupon the lady told him
 her dream of the night before, and the doubt and fear which it had
 engendered in her mind. <milestone id="p04060013" />Whereat Gabriotto laughed, and said that
 'twas the height of folly to put any faith in dreams, for that they
 were occasioned by too much or too little food, and were daily seen
 to be, one and all, things of nought, adding: 
<milestone id="p04060014" /><q direct="unspecified">Were I minded to
 give heed to dreams, I should not be here now, for I, too, had a
 dream last night, which was on this wise: Methought I was in
 a fair and pleasant wood, and there, a hunting, caught a she-goat as
 beautiful and loveable as any that ever was seen, and, as it seemed to
 me, whiter than snow, which in a little while grew so tame and
 friendly that she never stirred from my side. 
<milestone id="p04060015" />All the same so jealous
 was I lest she should leave me, that, meseemed, I had set a collar of
 gold around her neck, and held her by a golden chain. 
<milestone id="p04060016" />And presently
 meseemed that, while the she-goat lay at rest with her head in my
 lap, there came forth, I knew not whence, a greyhound bitch, black
 as coal, famished, and most fearsome to look upon; which made
 straight for me, and for, meseemed, I offered no resistance, set her
 muzzle to my breast on the left side and gnawed through to the
 heart, which, meseemed, she tore out to carry away with her.
 <milestone id="p04060017" />Whereupon ensued so sore a pain that it brake my sleep, and as I
 awoke I laid my hand to my side to feel if aught were amiss there;
 but finding nothing I laughed at myself that I had searched. But
 what signifies it all? Visions of the like sort, ay, and far more
 appalling, have I had in plenty, and nought whatever, great or small,
 has come of any of them. So let it pass, and think we how we may
 speed the time merrily.</q></p><p><milestone id="p04060018" />What she heard immensely enhanced the already great dread
 which her own dream had inspired in the girl; but, not to vex
 Gabriotto, she dissembled her terror as best she might. But, though
 she made great cheer, embracing and kissing him, and receiving his
 <pb n="305" />embraces and kisses, yet she felt a doubt, she knew not why, and
 many a time, more than her wont, she would gaze upon his face,
 and ever and anon her glance would stray through the garden to
 see if any black creature were coming from any quarter. 
<milestone id="p04060019" />While
 thus they passed the time, of a sudden Gabriotto heaved a great
 sigh, and embracing her, said: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! my soul, thy succour! for
 I die.</q> And so saying, he fell down upon the grassy mead. 
<milestone id="p04060020" />Whereupon
 the girl drew him to her, and laid him on her lap, and all
 but wept, and said: <q direct="unspecified">O sweet my lord, what is't that ails thee?</q>
 <milestone id="p04060021" />But Gabriotto was silent, and gasping sore for breath, and bathed
 in sweat, in no long time departed this life.</p><p><milestone id="p04060022" />How grievous was the distress of the girl, who loved him more
 than herself, you, my ladies, may well imagine. With many a tear
 she mourned him, and many times she vainly called him by his
 name; but when, having felt his body all over, and found it cold in
 every part, she could no longer doubt that he was dead, knowing not
 what to say or do, she went, tearful and woebegone, to call the
 maid, to whom she had confided her love, and shewed her the
 woeful calamity that had befallen her. <milestone id="p04060023" />Piteously a while they wept
 together over the dead face of Gabriotto, and then the girl said to
 the maid: <q direct="unspecified">Now that God has reft him from me, I have no
 mind to linger in this life; but before I slay myself, I would we
 might find apt means to preserve my honour, and the secret of our
 love, and to bury the body from which the sweet soul has fled.</q>
 <milestone id="p04060024" /><q direct="unspecified">My daughter,</q> said the maid, <q direct="unspecified">speak not of slaying thyself, for
 so wouldst thou lose in the other world, also, him that thou hast
 lost here; seeing that thou wouldst go to hell, whither, sure I am,
 his soul is not gone, for a good youth he was; far better were it to
 put on a cheerful courage, and bethink thee to succour his soul with
 thy prayers or pious works, if perchance he have need thereof by
 reason of any sin that he may have committed. 
<milestone id="p04060025" />We can bury him
 readily enough in this garden, nor will any one ever know; for
 none knows that he ever came hither; and if thou wilt not have
 it so, we can bear him forth of the garden, and leave him there;
 and on the morrow he will be found, and carried home, and buried
 by his kinsfolk.</q> 
<milestone id="p04060026" />The girl, heavy-laden though she was with
 anguish, and still weeping, yet gave ear to the counsels of her maid,
 and rejecting the former alternative, made answer to the latter on
 <pb n="306" />this wise: <q direct="unspecified">Now God forbid that a youth so dear, whom I have
 so loved and made my husband, should with my consent be buried
 like a dog, or left out there in the street. He has had my tears, and
 so far as I may avail, he shall have the tears of his kinsfolk, and
 already wot I what we must do.</q> 
<milestone id="p04060027" />And forthwith she sent the maid
 for a piece of silken cloth, which she had in one of her boxes; and
 when the maid returned with it, they spread it on the ground, and
 laid Gabriotto's body thereon, resting the head upon a pillow. She
 then closed the eyes and mouth, shedding the while many a tear,
 wove for him a wreath of roses, and strewed upon him all the roses
 that he and she had gathered; which done, she said to the maid:
 <milestone id="p04060028" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis but a short way hence to the door of his house; so thither we
 will bear him, thou and I, thus as we have dight him, and will lay
 him at the door. Day will soon dawn, and they will take him up;
 and, though 'twill be no consolation to them, I, in whose arms he
 died, shall be glad of it.</q> 
<milestone id="p04060029" />So saying, she burst once more into a
 torrent of tears, and fell with her face upon the face of the dead, and
 so long time she wept. Then, yielding at last to the urgency of her
 maid, for day was drawing nigh, she arose, drew from her finger the
 ring with which she had been wedded to Gabriotto, and set it on
 his finger, saying with tears: 
<milestone id="p04060030" /><q direct="unspecified">Dear my lord, if thy soul be witness
 of my tears, or if, when the spirit is fled, aught of intelligence or
 sense still lurk in the body, graciously receive the last gift of her
 whom in life thou didst so dearly love.</q> Which said, she swooned,
 and fell upon the corpse; 
<milestone id="p04060031" />but, coming after a while to herself, she
 arose; and then she and her maid took the cloth whereon the body
 lay, and so bearing it, quitted the garden, and bent their steps towards
 the dead man's house. As thus they went, it chanced that certain
 of the Podest&#224;'s guard, that for some reason or another were abroad
 at that hour, met them, and arrested them with the corpse. 
<milestone id="p04060032" />Andreuola,
 to whom death was more welcome than life, no sooner knew
 them for the officers of the Signory than she frankly said: <q direct="unspecified">I know
 you, who you are, and that flight would avail me nothing: I am
 ready to come with you before the Signory, and to tell all there is to
 tell; but let none of you presume to touch me, so long as I obey
 you, or to take away aught that is on this body, if he would not that
 I accuse him.</q> And so, none venturing to lay hand upon either her
 person or the corpse, she entered the palace.</p><pb n="307" /><p><milestone id="p04060033" />So soon as the Podest&#224; was apprised of the affair, he arose,
 had
 her brought into his room, and there made himself conversant with
 the circumstances: and certain physicians being charged to inquire
 whether the good man had met his death by poison or otherwise, all
 with one accord averred that 'twas not by poison, but that he was
 choked by the bursting of an imposthume near the heart. 
<milestone id="p04060034" />Which
 when the Podest&#224; heard, perceiving that the girl's guilt could but
 be slight, he sought to make a pretence of giving what it was not
 lawful for him to sell her, and told her that he would set her at
 liberty, so she were consenting to pleasure him; 
<milestone id="p04060035" />but finding that he
 did but waste his words he cast aside all decency, and would have
 used force. Whereupon Andreuola, kindling with scorn, waxed
 exceeding brave, and defended herself with a virile energy, and with
 high and contumelious words drove him from her.</p><p><milestone id="p04060036" />When 'twas broad day, the affair reached the ears of Messer
 Negro, who, half dead with grief, hied him with not a few of his
 friends to the palace; where, having heard all that the Podest&#224; had
 to say, he required him peremptorily to give him back his daughter.
 <milestone id="p04060037" />The Podest&#224;, being minded rather to be his own accuser, than that
 he should be accused by the girl of the violence that he had meditated
 towards her, began by praising her and her constancy, and in proof
 thereof went on to tell what he had done; he ended by saying, that,
 marking her admirable firmness, he had fallen mightily in love with
 her, and so, notwithstanding she had been wedded to a man of low
 degree, he would, if 'twere agreeable to her and to her father, Messer
 Negro, gladly make her his wife. <milestone id="p04060038" />While they thus spoke, Andreuola
 made her appearance, and, weeping, threw herself at her father's feet,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">My father, I wot I need not tell you the story of my
 presumption, and the calamity that has befallen me, for sure I am
 that you have heard it and know it; wherefore, with all possible
 humility I crave your pardon of my fault, to wit, that without your
 knowledge I took for my husband him that pleased me best. 
<milestone id="p04060039" />And
 this I crave, not that my life may be spared, but that I may die as
 your daughter and not as your enemy;</q> and so, weeping, she fell at
 his feet. 
<milestone id="p04060040" />Messer Negro, now an old man, and naturally kindly and
 affectionate, heard her not without tears, and weeping raised her
 tenderly to her feet, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Daughter mine, I had much liefer
 had it that thou hadst had a husband that I deemed a match for thee;
 <pb n="308" />and in that thou hadst taken one that pleased thee I too had been
 pleased; but thy concealing thy choice from me is grievous to me
 by reason of thy distrust of me, and yet more so, seeing that thou
 hast lost him before I have known him. 
<milestone id="p04060041" />But as 'tis even so, to his
 remains be paid the honour which, while he lived for thy contentment,
 I had gladly done him as my son-in-law.</q> Then, turning to
 his sons and kinsmen, he bade them order Gabriotto's obsequies with
 all pomp and honourable circumstance.</p><p><milestone id="p04060042" />Meanwhile the young man's kinsmen and kinswomen, having
 heard the news, had flocked thither, bringing with them almost all the
 rest of the folk, men and women alike, that were in the city. And so
 his body, resting on Andreuola's cloth, and covered with her roses,
 was laid out in the middle of the courtyard, and there was mourned
 not by her and his kinsfolk alone, but publicly by well-nigh all the
 women of the city, and not a few men; and shouldered by some of
 the noblest of the citizens, as it had been the remains of no plebeian
 but of a noble, was borne from the public courtyard to the tomb
 with exceeding great pomp.</p><p><milestone id="p04060043" />Some days afterwards, as the Podest&#224; continued to urge his suit,
 Messer Negro would have discussed the matter with his daughter;
 but, as she would hear none of it, and he was minded in this matter
 to defer to her wishes, she and her maid entered a religious house of
 great repute for sanctity, where in just esteem they lived long time
 thereafter.</p></div2>