<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0204"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p02040001" />Landolfo Ruffolo is reduced to poverty, turns corsair, is
 captured by Genoese, is shipwrecked, escapes on a
 chest full of jewels, and, being cast ashore at Corfu,
 is hospitably entertained by a woman, and returns
 home wealthy.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02040002" />When Pampinea had brought her story to this glorious conclusion,
 Lauretta, who sate next her, delayed not, but thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p02040003" />Most gracious ladies, the potency of Fortune is never, methinks,
 more conspicuous than when she raises one, as in Pampinea's story
 we have seen her raise Alessandro, from abject misery to regal state.
      <milestone id="p02040004" />And such being the limits which our theme henceforth imposes on
 our invention, I shall feel no shame to tell a story wherein reverses
 yet greater are compensated by a sequel somewhat less dazzling.
 Well I know that my story, being compared with its predecessor,
 will therefore be followed with the less interest; but, failing of
 necessity, I shall be excused.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p02040005" />Scarce any part of Italy is reputed so delectable as the sea-coast
 between Reggio and Gaeta; and in particular the slope which overlooks
 the sea by Salerno, and which the dwellers there call the Slope
 of Amalfi, is studded with little towns, gardens and fountains, and
 peopled by men as wealthy and enterprising in mercantile affairs as
 are anywhere to be found; in one of which towns, to wit, Ravello,
 rich as its inhabitants are to-day, there was formerly a merchant,
 who surpassed them all in wealth, Landolfo Ruffolo by name, who
 yet, not content with his wealth, but desiring to double it, came
      nigh to lose it all and his own life to boot. <milestone id="p02040006" />Know, then, that this
 man, having made his calculations, as merchants are wont, bought a
 <pb n="88" />great ship, which, entirely at his own expense, he loaded with divers
 sorts of merchandise, and sailed to Cyprus. <milestone id="p02040007" />There he found several
 other ships, each laden with just such a cargo as his own, and was
 therefore fain to dispose of his goods at a very cheap rate, insomuch
 that he might almost as well have thrown them away, and was
 brought to the verge of ruin. <milestone id="p02040008" />Mortified beyond measure to find
 himself thus reduced in a short space of time from opulence to something
 like poverty, he was at his wits' end, and rather than go home
 poor, having left home rich, he was minded to retrieve his losses by
 piracy or die in the attempt. <milestone id="p02040009" />So he sold his great ship, and with the
 price and the proceeds of the sale of his merchandise bought a light
 bark such as corsairs use, and having excellently well equipped her
 with the armament and all things else meet for such service, took to
 scouring the seas as a rover, preying upon all folk alike, but more
 particularly upon the Turk.</p><p><milestone id="p02040010" />In this enterprise he was more favoured by Fortune than in
 his trading adventures. A year had scarce gone by before he had
 taken so many ships from the Turk that not only had he recovered
 the fortune which he had lost in trade, but was well on the way
 to doubling it. <milestone id="p02040011" />The bitter memory of his late losses taught him
 sobriety; he estimated his gains and found them ample; and lest
 he should have a second fall, he schooled himself to rest content
 with them, and made up his mind to return home without attempting
 to add to them. <milestone id="p02040012" />Shy of adventuring once more in trade, he
 refrained from investing them in any way, but shaped his course
 for home, carrying them with him in the very same bark in which
 he had gotten them. <milestone id="p02040013" />He had already entered the Archipelago when
 one evening a contrary wind sprang up from the south-east, bringing
 with it a very heavy sea, in which his bark could not well have lived.
 He therefore steered her into a bay under the lee of one of the
 islets, and there determined to await better weather. <milestone id="p02040014" />As he lay
 there two great carracks of Genoa, homeward-bound from Constantinople,
 found, not without difficulty, shelter from the tempest
 in the same bay. The masters of the carracks espied the bark, and
 found out to whom she belonged: the fame of Landolfo and his
 vast wealth had already reached them, and had excited their natural
 cupidity and rapacity. They therefore determined to capture the
 bark, which lay without means of escape. <milestone id="p02040015" />Part of their men, well
 <pb n="89" />armed with cross-bows and other weapons, they accordingly sent
 ashore, so posting them that no one could leave the bark without
 being exposed to the bolts; the rest took to their boats, and rowed
 up to the side of Landolfo's little craft, which in a little time, with
 little trouble and no loss or risk, they captured with all aboard
 her. They then cleared the bark of all she contained, allowing
 Landolfo, whom they set aboard one of the carracks, only a pitiful
 doublet, and sunk her. <milestone id="p02040016" />Next day the wind shifted, and the carracks
 set sail on a westerly course, which they kept prosperously enough
 throughout the day; but towards evening a tempest arose, and the
 sea became very boisterous, so that the two ships were parted one
 from the other. <milestone id="p02040017" />And such was the fury of the gale that the ship,
 aboard which was poor, hapless Landolfo, was driven with prodigious
 force upon a shoal off the island of Cephalonia, and broke up and
 went to pieces like so much glass dashed against a wall. Wherefore
 the unfortunate wretches that were aboard her, launched amid the
 floating merchandise and chests and planks with which the sea was
 strewn, did as men commonly do in such a case; and though the night
 was of the murkiest and the sea rose and fell in mountainous surges,
 such as could swim sought to catch hold of whatever chance brought
 in their way. <milestone id="p02040018" />Among whom hapless Landolfo, who only the day
 before had again and again prayed for death, rather than he should
 return home in such poverty, now, seeing death imminent, was
 afraid; and, like the rest, laid hold of the first plank that came to
 hand, in the hope that, if he could but avoid immediate drowning,
 God would in some way aid his escape. Gripping the beam with
 his legs as best he might, while wind and wave tossed him hither
 and thither, he contrived to keep himself afloat until broad day:
 <milestone id="p02040019" />when, looking around him, he discerned nothing but clouds and sea
 and a chest, which, borne by the wave, from time to time drew
 nigh him to his extreme terror, for he apprehended it might strike
 against the plank, and do him a mischief; and ever, as it came near
 him, he pushed it off with all the little force he had in his hand.
 <milestone id="p02040020" />But, as it happened, a sudden gust of wind swept down upon the
 sea, and struck the chest with such force that it was driven against
 the plank on which Landolfo was, and upset it, and Landolfo went
 under the waves. Swimming with an energy begotten rather of
 fear than of strength, he rose to the surface only to see the plank
 <pb n="90" />so far from him that, doubting he could not reach it, he made for
 the chest, which was close at hand; and resting his breast upon the
 lid, he did what he could to keep it straight with his arms. <milestone id="p02040021" />In this
 manner, tossed to and fro by the sea, without tasting food, for not
 a morsel had he with him, and drinking more than he cared for,
 knowing not where he was, and seeing nothing but the sea, he
 remained all that day, and the following night. <milestone id="p02040022" />The next day, as
 the will of God, or the force of the wind so ordered, more like a
 sponge than aught else, but still with both hands holding fast by
 the edges of the chest, as we see those do that clutch aught to save
 themselves from drowning, he was at length borne to the coast of
 the island of Corfu, where by chance a poor woman was just then
 scrubbing her kitchen-ware with sand and salt-water to make it
 shine. The woman caught sight of him as he drifted shorewards,
 but making out only a shapeless mass, was at first startled, and
 shrieked and drew back. <milestone id="p02040023" />Landolfo was scarce able to see, and
 uttered no sound, for his power of speech was gone. However,
 when the sea brought him close to the shore, she distinguished the
 shape of the chest, and gazing more intently, she first made out the
 arms strained over the chest, and then discerned the face and divined
 the truth. <milestone id="p02040024" />So, prompted by pity, she went out a little way into the
 sea, which was then calm, took him by the hair of the head, and
 drew him to land, chest and all. Then, not without difficulty she
 disengaged his hands from the chest, which she set on the head of
 a little girl, her daughter, that was with her, carried him home like
 a little child, and set him in a bath, where she chafed and laved him
 with warm water, until, the vital heat and some part of the strength
 which he had lost being restored, she saw fit to take him out and
 regale him with some good wine and comfits. Thus for some days
 she tended him as best she could, until he recovered his strength, and
 knew where he was. <milestone id="p02040025" />Then, in due time, the good woman, who
 had kept his chest safe, gave it back to him, and bade him try his
 fortune.</p><p><milestone id="p02040026" />Landolfo could not recall the chest, but took it when she brought
 it to him, thinking that, however slight its value, it must suffice for
 a few days' charges. He found it very light, and quite lost hope;
 but when the good woman was out of doors, he opened it to see
 what was inside, and found there a great number of precious stones,
 <pb n="91" />some set, others unset. Having some knowledge of such matters,
 he saw at a glance that the stones were of great value; wherefore,
 feeling that he was still not forsaken by God, he praised His name,
 and quite recovered heart. <milestone id="p02040027" />But, having in a brief space of time
 been twice shrewdly hit by the bolts of Fortune, he was apprehensive
 of a third blow, and deemed it meet to use much circumspection in
 conveying his treasure home; so he wrapped it up in rags as best
 he could, telling the good woman that he had no more use for the
 chest, but she might keep it if she wished, and give him a sack in
 exchange. <milestone id="p02040028" />This the good woman readily did; and he, thanking
 her as heartily as he could for the service she had rendered him,
 threw his sack over his shoulders, and, taking ship, crossed to
 Brindisi. Thence he made his way by the coast as far as Trani,
 where he found some of his townsfolk that were drapers, to whom
 he narrated all his adventures except that of the chest. They in
 charity gave him a suit of clothes, and lent him a horse and their
 escort as far as Ravello, whither, he said, he was minded to return.
 <milestone id="p02040029" />There, thanking God for bringing him safe home, he opened his sack,
 and examining its contents with more care than before, found the
 number and fashion of the stones to be such that the sale of them
 at a moderate price, or even less, would leave him twice as rich as
 when he left Ravello. <milestone id="p02040030" />So, having disposed of his stones, he sent a
 large sum of money to Corfu in recompense of the service done him
 by the good woman who had rescued him from the sea, and also to
 his friends at Trani who had furnished him with the clothes; the
 residue he retained, and, making no more ventures in trade, lived
 and died in honourable estate.</p></div2>