<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="elissa" id="nov0404"><head>Novel IV</head><argument><p><milestone id="p04040001" />Gerbino, in breach of the plighted faith of his grandfather,
 King Guglielmo, attacks a ship of the King of Tunis
 to rescue thence his daughter. She being slain by
 those aboard the ship, he slays them, and afterwards
 he is beheaded.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04040002" />Lauretta, her story ended, kept silence; and the king brooded
 as in deep thought, while one or another of the company deplored
 the sad fate of this or the other of the lovers, or censured Ninette's
 wrath, or made some other comment. At length, however, the
 king roused himself, and raising his head, made sign to Elisa that
 'twas now for her to speak. So, modestly, Elisa thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="elissa" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p04040003" />Gracious ladies, not a few there are that believe that Love looses no
	shafts save when he is kindled by the eyes, contemning their opinion
	that hold that passion may be engendered by words; whose error
	will be abundantly manifest in a story which I purpose to tell you;
	wherein you may see how mere rumour not only wrought mutual
	love in those that had never seen one another, but also brought both
	to a miserable death.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p04040004" />Guglielmo, the Second,<note>First, according to the now accepted
	reckoning. He reigned from 1154
	to 1166.</note> as the Sicilians compute, King of Sicily,
      had two children, a son named Ruggieri, and a daughter named
      Gostanza. Ruggieri died before his father, and left a son named
      Gerbino; who, being carefully trained by his grandfather, grew up a
      most goodly gallant, and of great renown in court and camp, 
      <milestone id="p04040005" />and
      that not only within the borders of Sicily, but in divers other parts
      <pb n="292" />of the world, among them Barbary, then tributary to the King of
      Sicily. And among others, to whose ears was wafted the bruit of
      Gerbino's magnificent prowess and courtesy, was a daughter of the
      King of Tunis, who, by averment of all that had seen her, was a
      creature as fair and debonair, and of as great and noble a spirit as
      Nature ever formed. <milestone id="p04040006" />To hear tell of brave men was her delight, and
      what she heard, now from one, now from another, of the brave deeds
      of Gerbino she treasured in her mind so sedulously, and pondered
      them with such pleasure, rehearsing them to herself in imagination,
      that she became hotly enamoured of him, and there was none
      of whom she talked, or heard others talk, so gladly. <milestone id="p04040007" />Nor, on the
      other hand, had the fame of her incomparable beauty and other
      excellences failed to travel, as to other lands, so also to Sicily, where,
      falling on Gerbino's ears, it gave him no small delight, to such effect
      that he burned for the lady no less vehemently than she for him.
      <milestone id="p04040008" />Wherefore, until such time as he might, upon some worthy occasion,
      have his grandfather's leave to go to Tunis, yearning beyond measure
      to see her, he charged every friend of his, that went thither, to give
      her to know, as best he might, his great and secret love for her, and
      to bring him tidings of her. Which office one of the said friends
      discharged with no small address; for, having obtained access to her,
      after the manner of merchants, by bringing jewels for her to look at,
      he fully apprised her of Gerbino's passion, and placed him, and all
      that he possessed, entirely at her disposal. <milestone id="p04040009" />The lady received both
      messenger and message with gladsome mien, made answer that she
      loved with equal ardour, and in token thereof sent Gerbino one of
      her most precious jewels. Gerbino received the jewel with extreme
      delight, and sent her many a letter and many a most precious gift by
      the hand of the same messenger; and 'twas well understood between
      them that, should Fortune accord him opportunity, he should see
      and know her.</p><p><milestone id="p04040010" />On this footing the affair remained somewhat longer than was
 expedient; and so, while Gerbino and the lady burned with mutual
 love, it befell that the King of Tunis gave her in marriage to the
 King of Granada;<note>An anachronism; the Moorish kingdom of Granada not
 having been
 founded until 1238.</note> whereat she was wroth beyond measure, for that
 <pb n="293" />she was not only going into a country remote from her lover, but, as
 she deemed, was severed from him altogether; and so this might not
 come to pass, gladly, could she but have seen how, would she have
 left her father and fled to Gerbino. <milestone id="p04040011" />In like manner, Gerbino, on
 learning of the marriage, was vexed beyond measure, and was ofttimes
 minded, could he but find means to win to her husband by
 sea, to wrest her from him by force. <milestone id="p04040012" />Some rumour of Gerbino's love,
 and of his intent, reached the King of Tunis, who, knowing his
 prowess and power, took alarm, and as the time drew nigh for
 conveying the lady to Granada, sent word of his purpose to King
 Guglielmo, and craved his assurance that it might be carried into
 effect without let or hindrance on the part of Gerbino, or any one
 else. <milestone id="p04040013" />The old King had heard nothing of Gerbino's love affair, and
 never dreaming that 'twas on such account that the assurance was
 craved, granted it without demur, and in pledge thereof sent the
 King of Tunis his glove. Which received, the King made ready
 a great and goodly ship in the port of Carthage, and equipped
 her with all things meet for those that were to man her, and
 with all appointments apt and seemly for the reception of his
 daughter, and awaited only fair weather to send her therein to
 Granada. <milestone id="p04040014" />All which the young lady seeing and marking, sent
 one of her servants privily to Palermo, bidding him greet the
 illustrious Gerbino on her part, and tell him that a few days
 would see her on her way to Granada; wherefore 'twould now appear
 whether, or no, he were really as doughty a man as he was reputed,
 and loved her as much as he had so often protested. 
<milestone id="p04040015" />The servant
 did not fail to deliver her message exactly, and returned to Tunis,
 leaving Gerbino, who knew that his grandfather, King Guglielmo,
 had given the King of Tunis the desired assurance, at a loss how to
 act. But prompted by love, and goaded by the lady's words and
 loath to seem a craven, he hied him to Messina; and having there
 armed two light galleys, and manned them with good men and true,
 he put to sea, and stood for Sardinia, deeming that the lady's ship must
 pass that way. <milestone id="p04040016" />Nor was he far out in his reckoning; for he had
 not been there many days, when the ship, sped by a light breeze, hove
 in sight not far from the place where he lay in wait for her. Whereupon
 Gerbino said to his comrades: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, if you be as good
 men and true as I deem you, there is none of you but must have felt, if
 <pb n="294" />he feel not now, the might of love; for without love I deem no
 mortal capable of true worth or aught that is good; and if you are
 or have been in love, 'twill be easy for you to understand that which
 I desire. <milestone id="p04040017" />I love, and 'tis because I love that I have laid this travail
 upon you; and that which I love is in the ship that you see before
 you, which is fraught not only with my beloved, but with immense
 treasures, which, if you are good men and true, we, so we but play
 the man in fight, may with little trouble make our own; nor for
 my share of the spoils of the victory demand I aught but a lady,
 whose love it is that prompts me to take arms: all else I freely cede
 to you from this very hour. Forward, then; attack we this ship;
 success should be ours, for God favours our enterprise, nor lends her
 wind to evade us.</q> 
<milestone id="p04040018" />Fewer words might have sufficed the illustrious
 Gerbino; for the rapacious Messinese that were with him were
 already bent heart and soul upon that to which by his harangue he
 sought to animate them. So, when he had done, they raised a
 mighty shout, so that 'twas as if trumpets did blare, and caught up
 their arms, and smiting the water with their oars, overhauled the
 ship. <milestone id="p04040019" />The advancing galleys were observed while they were yet a
 great way off by the ship's crew, who, not being able to avoid the
 combat, put themselves in a posture of defence. Arrived at close
 quarters, the illustrious Gerbino bade send the ship's masters aboard
 the galleys, unless they were minded to do battle. 
<milestone id="p04040020" />Certified of the
 challenge, and who they were that made it, the Saracens answered
 that 'twas in breach of the faith plighted to them by their assailants'
 king that they were thus attacked, and in token thereof displayed
 King Guglielmo's glove, averring in set terms that there should be
 no surrender either of themselves or of aught that was aboard the
 ship without battle. 
<milestone id="p04040021" />Gerbino, who had observed the lady standing
 on the ship's poop, and seen that she was far more beautiful than he
 had imagined, burned with a yet fiercer flame than before, and to
 the display of the glove made answer, that, as he had no falcons there
 just then, the glove booted him not; wherefore, so they were not
 minded to surrender the lady, let them prepare to receive battle.
 <milestone id="p04040022" />Whereupon, without further delay, the battle began on both sides
 with a furious discharge of arrows and stones; on which wise it was
 long protracted to their common loss; <milestone id="p04040023" />until at last Gerbino, seeing
 that he gained little advantage, took a light bark which they had
 <pb n="295" />brought from Sardinia, and having fired her, bore down with her,
 and both the galleys, upon the ship. Whereupon the Saracens,
 seeing that they must perforce surrender the ship or die, caused the
 King's daughter, who lay beneath the deck weeping, to come up on
 deck, and led her to the prow, and shouting to Gerbino, while the
 lady shrieked alternately <q direct="unspecified">mercy</q> and <q direct="unspecified">succour,</q> opened her veins
 before his eyes, and cast her into the sea, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Take her; we
 give her to thee on such wise as we can, and as thy faith has merited.</q>
 <milestone id="p04040024" />Maddened to witness this deed of barbarism, Gerbino, as if courting
 death, recked no more of the arrows and the stones, but drew alongside
 the ship, and, despite the resistance of her crew, boarded her;
 and as a famished lion ravens amongst a herd of oxen, and tearing
 and rending, now one, now another, gluts his wrath before he appeases
 his hunger, so Gerbino, sword in hand, hacking and hewing on all
 sides among the Saracens, did ruthlessly slaughter not a few of them;
 till, as the burning ship began to blaze more fiercely, he bade the
 seamen take thereout all that they might by way of guerdon, which
 done, he quitted her, having gained but a rueful victory over his
 adversaries. <milestone id="p04040025" />His next care was to recover from the sea the body of
 the fair lady, whom long and with many a tear he mourned: and
 so he returned to Sicily, and gave the body honourable sepulture in
 Ustica, an islet that faces, as it were, Trapani, and went home the
 saddest man alive.</p><p><milestone id="p04040026" />When these tidings reached the King of Tunis, he sent to King
 Guglielmo ambassadors, habited in black, who made complaint
 of the breach of faith and recited the manner of its occurrence.
 Which caused King Guglielmo no small chagrin; and seeing not
 how he might refuse the justice they demanded, he had Gerbino
 arrested, and he himself, none of his barons being able by any
 entreaty to turn him from his purpose, sentenced him to forfeit his
 head, and had it severed from his body in his presence, preferring
 to suffer the loss of his only grandson than to gain the reputation of
 a faithless king. <milestone id="p04040027" />And so, miserably, within the compass of a few
 brief days, died the two lovers by woeful deaths, as I have told you,
 and without having known any joyance of their love.</p></div2>