<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="fiammetta" id="nov0606"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06060001" />Michele Scalza proves to certain young men that the
Baronci are the best gentlemen in the world and the Maremma, and wins a
supper.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06060002" />The ladies were still laughing over Giotto's
	ready retort, when the queen charged Fiammetta to follow suit; wherefore thus Fiammetta
	began:</p></div3><div3 who="fiammetta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06060003" />Pamfilo's mention of the
	Baronci, who to you, Damsels, are perchance not so well known as to him, has brought to my
	mind a story in which 'tis shewn how great is their nobility; and, for that it involves no
	deviation from our rule of discourse, I am minded to tell it you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p06060004" />'Tis no long time
since there dwelt in our city a young man,
 Michele Scalza by name, the
pleasantest and merriest fellow in the
 world, and the best furnished with
quaint stories: for which reason
 the Florentine youth set great store on
having him with them when
 they forgathered in company. <milestone id="p06060005" />Now it so befell
that one day, he
 being with a party of them at Mont' Ughi, they fell a
disputing
 together on this wise; to wit, who were the best gentlemen and
of
 the longest descent in Florence. One said, the Uberti, another, the
Lamberti, or some other family, according to the predilection of the
speaker. <milestone id="p06060006" />Whereat Scalza began to smile, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Now out
 upon you, out
upon you, blockheads that ye are: ye know not what
 ye say. The best
gentlemen and of longest descent in all the world
 and the Maremma (let
alone Florence) are the Baronci by the
 common consent of all
phisopholers,<note>In the Italian fisofoli: an
evidently intentional distortion.</note> and all that know them as I
 do;
and lest you should otherwise conceive me, I say that 'tis of
 your
neighbours the Baronci<note>Villani, Istorie
Fiorentine, iv.
 cap.
 ix., and Dante,
Paradiso, xvi. 104,
 spell the name Barucci.</note> of
Santa Maria Maggiore that I speak.</q>
 <pb n="88" /><milestone id="p06060007" />Whereupon the young men,
who had looked for somewhat else from
 him, said derisively: <q direct="unspecified">Thou dost
but jest with us; as if we did not
 know the Baronci as well as thou!</q>
<milestone id="p06060008" />Quoth Scalza: <q direct="unspecified">By the Gospels
 I jest not, but speak sooth; and if there
is any of you will wager a
 supper to be given to the winner and six good
fellows whom he
 shall choose, I will gladly do the like, and--what is
more--I will
 abide by the decision of such one of you as you may
choose.</q> <milestone id="p06060009" />Then
 said one of them whose name was Neri Mannini: <q direct="unspecified">I am
ready to
 adventure this supper;</q> and so they agreed together that Piero
di
 Fiorentino, in whose house they were, should be judge, and hied them
to him followed by all the rest, eager to see Scalza lose, and triumph
 in
his discomfiture, and told Piero all that had been said. <milestone id="p06060010" />Piero, who
 was a
young man of sound sense, heard what Neri had to say; and
 then turning to
Scalza: <q direct="unspecified">And how,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">mayst thou make
 good what thou
averrest?</q> <milestone id="p06060011" /><q direct="unspecified">I will demonstrate it,</q> returned
 Scalza, <q direct="unspecified">by
reasoning so cogent that not only you, but he that denies
 it shall
acknowledge that I say sooth. <milestone id="p06060012" />You know, and so they were
 saying but now,
that the longer men's descent, the better is their
 gentility, and I say
that the Baronci are of longer descent, and thus
 better gentlemen than any
other men. If, then, I prove to you that
 they are of longer descent than
any other men, without a doubt the
 victory in this dispute will rest with
me. <milestone id="p06060013" />Now you must know that
 when God made the Baronci, He was but a novice
in His art, of
 which, when He made the rest of mankind, He was already
master.
 <milestone id="p06060014" />And to assure yourself that herein I say sooth, you have but to
consider
 the Baronci, how they differ from the rest of mankind, who all
have faces well composed and duly proportioned, whereas of the
 Baronci you
will see one with a face very long and narrow, another
 with a face
inordinately broad, one with a very long nose, another
 with a short one,
one with a protruding and upturned chin, and
 great jaws like an ass's; and
again there will be one that has one eye
 larger than its fellow, or set on
a lower plane; so that their faces
 resemble those that children make when
they begin to learn to draw.
 <milestone id="p06060015" />Whereby, as I said, 'tis plainly manifest
that, when God made them,
 He was but novice in His art; and so they are of
longer descent
 than the rest of mankind, and by consequence better
gentlemen.</q>
 <milestone id="p06060016" />By which entertaining argument Piero, the judge, and Neri
who had
 wagered the supper, and all the rest, calling to mind the
Baronci's
 <pb n="89" />ugliness, were so tickled, that they fell a laughing,
and averred that
 Scalza was in the right, and that he had won the wager,
and that
 without a doubt the Baronci were the best gentlemen, and of the
longest descent, not merely in Florence, but in the world and the
 Maremma
to boot. <milestone id="p06060017" />Wherefore 'twas not without reason that
 Pamfilo, being minded to
declare Messer Forese's ill-favouredness,
 said that he would have been
hideous beside a Baroncio.</p></div2>