<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="dioneo" id="nov0810"><head>Novel X</head><argument><p><milestone id="p08100001" />A Sicilian woman cunningly conveys from a merchant that
 which he has brought to Palermo; he, making a shew
 of being come back thither with far greater store of
 goods than before, borrows money of her, and leaves
 her in lieu thereof water and tow.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08100002" />How much in divers passages the queen's story moved the ladies
 to laughter, it boots not to ask: none was there in whose eyes the
 tears stood not full a dozen times for excess of merriment. However,
 it being ended, and Dioneo witting that 'twas now his turn,
 thus spake he:</p></div3><div3 who="dioneo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p08100003" />Gracious ladies, 'tis patent to all that wiles are
 diverting in the degree of the wiliness of him that is by them
 beguiled. Wherefore, albeit stories most goodly have been told by
 you all, I purpose to relate one which should afford you more
 pleasure than any that has been told, seeing that she that was
 beguiled was far more cunning in beguiling others than any of the
 beguiled of whom you have spoken.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p08100004" />There was, and perhaps still is, a custom in all maritime
 countries that have ports, that all merchants arriving there with
 merchandise, should, on discharging, bring all their goods into a
 warehouse, called in many places <q direct="unspecified">dogana,</q> and maintained by
 the state, or the lord of the land; <milestone id="p08100005" />where those that are assigned
 to that office allot to each merchant, on receipt of an invoice of
 all his goods and the value thereof, a room in which he stores
 his goods under lock and key; whereupon the said officers of the
 dogana enter all the merchant's goods to his credit in the book
 of the dogana, and afterwards make him pay duty thereon, or on
 such part as he withdraws from the warehouse. <milestone id="p08100006" />By which book of
 <pb n="251" />the dogana the brokers not seldom find out the sorts and quantities
 of the merchandise that is there, and also who are the owners
 thereof, with whom, as occasion serves, they afterwards treat of
 exchanges, barters, sales and other modes of disposing of the goods.
 <milestone id="p08100007" />Which custom obtained, as in many other places, so also at Palermo
 in Sicily, where in like manner there were and are not a few women,
 fair as fair can be, but foes to virtue, who by whoso knows them not
 would be reputed great and most virtuous ladies. 
<milestone id="p08100008" />And being given
 not merely to fleece but utterly to flay men, they no sooner espy a
 foreign merchant in the city, than they find out from the book of
 the dogana how much he has there and what he is good for; and
 then by caressing and amorous looks and gestures, and words of
 honeyed sweetness, they strive to entice and allure the merchant to
 their love, and not seldom have they succeeded, and wrested from
 him great part or the whole of his merchandise; and of some they
 have gotten goods and ship and flesh and bones, so delightsomely
 have they known how to ply the shears.</p><p><milestone id="p08100009" />Now 'tis not long since one of our young Florentines, Niccol&#242; da
 Cignano by name, albeit he was called Salabaetto, arrived there,
 being sent by his masters with all the woollen stuffs that he had not
 been able to dispose of at Salerno fair, which might perhaps be
 worth five hundred florins of gold; and having given the invoice to
 the officers of the dogana and stored the goods, Salabaetto was in no
 hurry to get them out of bond, but took a stroll or two about the
 city for his diversion. <milestone id="p08100010" />And as he was fresh-complexioned and fair
 and not a little debonair, it so befell that one of these ladies that
 plied the shears, and called herself Jancofiore, began to ogle him.
 Whereof he taking note, and deeming that she was a great lady,
 supposed that she was taken by his good looks, and cast about how
 he might manage this amour with all due discretion; wherefore,
 saying nought to a soul, he began to pass to and fro before her house.
 <milestone id="p08100011" />Which she observing, occupied herself for a few days in inflaming
 his passion, and then affecting to be dying of love for him, sent
 privily to him a woman that she had in her service, and who was an
 adept in the arts of the procuress. She, after not a little palaver,
 told him, while the tears all but stood in her eyes, that for his handsome
 person and winsome air her mistress was so enamoured of him,
 that she found no peace by day or by night; and therefore, if 'twere
 <pb n="252" />agreeable to him, there was nought she desired so much as to meet
 him privily at a bagnio: whereupon she drew a ring from her purse,
 and gave it him by way of token from her mistress. <milestone id="p08100012" />Overjoyed as
 ne'er another to hear such good news, Salabaetto took the ring, and,
 after drawing it across his eyes and kissing it, put it on his finger,
 and told the good woman that, if Madonna Jancofiore loved him,
 she was well requited, for that he loved her more dearly than himself,
 and that he was ready to meet her wherever and whenever she might
 see fit. <milestone id="p08100013" />With which answer the procuress hied her back to her
 mistress, and shortly afterwards Salabaetto was informed that he was
 to meet the lady at a certain bagnio at vespers of the ensuing day.</p><p>So, saying nought to a soul of the matter, he hied him punctually
 at the appointed hour to the bagnio, and found that it had been taken
 by the lady; <milestone id="p08100014" />nor had he long to wait before two female slaves made
 their appearance, bearing on their heads, the one a great and goodly
 mattress of wadding, and the other a huge and well-filled basket; and
 having laid the mattress on a bedstead in one of the rooms of the bagnio,
 they covered it with a pair of sheets of the finest fabric, bordered with
 silk, and a quilt of the whitest Cyprus buckram, with two
 daintily-embroidered
 pillows. The slaves then undressed and got into the
 bath, which they thoroughly washed and scrubbed: <milestone id="p08100015" />whither soon
 afterwards the lady, attended by other two female slaves, came,
 and made haste to greet Salabaetto with the heartiest of cheer; and
 when, after heaving many a mighty sigh, she had embraced and
 kissed him: <q direct="unspecified">I know not,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">who but thou could have
 brought me to this, such a fire hast thou kindled in my soul, little
 dog of a Tuscan!</q> 
<milestone id="p08100016" />Whereupon she was pleased that they should
 undress, and get into the bath, and two of the slaves with them;
 which, accordingly, they did; and she herself, suffering none other to
 lay a hand upon him, did with wondrous care wash Salabaetto from
 head to foot with soap perfumed with musk and cloves; after which
 she let the slaves wash and shampoo herself. <milestone id="p08100017" />The slaves then
 brought two spotless sheets of finest texture, which emitted such a
 scent of roses, that 'twas as if there was nought there but roses, in
 one of which having wrapped Salabaetto, and in the other the lady,
 they bore them both to bed, where, the sheets in which they were
 enfolded being withdrawn by the slaves as soon as they had done
 sweating, they remained stark naked in the others. <milestone id="p08100018" />The slaves then
 <pb n="253" />took from the basket cruets of silver most goodly, and full, this of
 rose-water, that of water of orange-blossom, a third of water of
 jasmine-blossom, and a fourth of nanfa<note>Neither the Vocab. degli
 Accad. della Crusca nor the Riccbezze attempts
 to define the precise nature of this scent, which Fanfani identifies with
 that
 of the orange-blossom.</note> water, wherewith they
 sprinkled them: after which, boxes of comfits and the finest wines
 being brought forth, they regaled them a while. <milestone id="p08100019" />To Salabaetto 'twas
 as if he were in Paradise; a thousand times he scanned the lady,
 who was indeed most beautiful; and he counted each hour as
 a hundred years until the slaves should get them gone, and he find
 himself in the lady's arms.</p><p><milestone id="p08100020" />At length, by the lady's command, the slaves departed, leaving a
 lighted torch in the room, and then the lady and Salabaetto embraced,
 and to Salabaetto's prodigious delight, for it seemed to him that she
 was all but dissolved for love of him, tarried there a good while.
 <milestone id="p08100021" />However, the time came when the lady must needs rise: so she
 called the slaves, with whose help they dressed, regaled them again
 for a while with wine and comfits, and washed their faces and hands
 with the odoriferous waters. Then as they were going, quoth the
 lady to Salabaetto: <q direct="unspecified">If it be agreeable to thee, I should deem it a
 very great favour if thou wouldst come to-night to sup and sleep
 with me.</q> <milestone id="p08100022" />Salabaetto, who, captivated by her beauty and her
 studied graciousness, never doubted but he was dear to her as her
 very heart, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, there is nought you can
 desire but is in the last degree agreeable to me; wherefore to-night
 and ever 'tis my purpose to do whatsoever you may be pleased to
 command.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100023" />So home the lady hied her, and having caused a brave
 shew to be made in her chamber with her dresses and other paraphernalia,
 and a grand supper to be prepared, awaited Salabaetto;
 who, being come there as soon as 'twas dark, had of her a gladsome
 welcome, and was regaled with an excellent and well-served supper.
 <milestone id="p08100024" />After which, they repaired to the chamber, where he was saluted by
 a wondrous sweet odour of aloe-wood, and observed that the bed
 was profusely furnished with birds,<note>I. e. with a sort of
 musical
 boxes in the shape of birds.</note> after the fashion of Cyprus, and
 that not a few fine dresses were hanging upon the pegs. Which
 circumstances did, one and all, beget in him the belief that this must
 <pb n="254" />be a great and wealthy lady; and, though he had heard a hint or
 two to the contrary touching her life, he would by no means credit
 them; nor, supposing that she had perchance taken another with
 guile, would he believe that the same thing might befall him. So to
 his exceeding great solace, he lay with her that night, and ever grew
 more afire for her. <milestone id="p08100025" />On the morrow, as she was investing him with
 a fair and dainty girdle of silver, with a goodly purse attached:
 <q direct="unspecified">Sweet my Salabaetto,</q> quoth she, <q direct="unspecified">prithee forget me not; even
 as my person, so is all that I have at thy pleasure, and all that
 I can at thy command.</q></p><p>Salabaetto then embraced and kissed her, and so bade her adieu,
 and betook him to the place where the merchants were wont to congregate.
 <milestone id="p08100026" />And so it befell that he, continuing to consort with her
 from time to time, and being never a denier the poorer thereby,
 disposed of his merchandise for ready money and at no small profit;
 <milestone id="p08100027" />whereof not by him but by another the lady was forthwith advised.
 And Salabaetto being come to see her one evening, she greeted him
 gaily and gamesomely, and fell a kissing and hugging him, and made
 as if she were so afire for love of him that she was like to die thereof
 in his arms; and offered to give him two most goodly silver cups
 that she had, which Salabaetto would not accept, having already had
 from her (taking one time with another) fully thirty florins of gold,
 while he had not been able to induce her to touch so much as a groat
 of his money. <milestone id="p08100028" />But when by this shew of passion and generosity
 she had thoroughly kindled his flame, in came, as she had arranged,
 one of her slaves, and spoke to her; whereupon out of the room she
 went, and after a while came back in tears, and threw herself prone
 on the bed, and set up the most dolorous lamentation that ever
 woman made. <milestone id="p08100029" />Whereat Salabaetto wondering, took her in his arms,
 and mingled his tears with hers, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! heart of my
 body! what ails thee thus of a sudden? Wherefore art thou so
 distressed? Ah! tell me the reason, my soul.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100030" />The lady allowed
 him to run on in this strain for a good while, and then: <q direct="unspecified">Alas!
 sweet my lord,</q> quoth she, 
<milestone id="p08100031" /><q direct="unspecified">I know not either what to do or what
 to say. I have but now received a letter from Messina, in which my
 brother bids me sell, if need be, all that I have here, and send him
 without fail within eight days a thousand florins of gold: otherwise
 he will forfeit his head. I know not how to come by them so soon:
 <pb n="255" />had I but fifteen days, I would make a shift to raise them in a quarter
 where I might raise a much larger sum, or I would sell one of our
 estates; but, as this may not be, would I had been dead or e'er this
 bad news had reached me!</q> Which said, affecting to be utterly
 broken-hearted, she ceased not to weep.</p><p><milestone id="p08100032" />Salabaetto, the ardour of whose passion had in great measure
 deprived him of the sagacity which the circumstances demanded,
 supposed that the tears were genuine enough, and the words even
 more so. Wherefore: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I could not furnish
 you with a thousand, but if five hundred florins of gold would suffice,
 they are at your service, if you think you could repay them within
 fifteen days; and you may deem yourself in luck's way, for 'twas
 only yesterday that I sold my woollens, which had I not done, I
 could not have lent you a groat.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100033" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas!</q> returned the lady,
 <q direct="unspecified">then thou hast been in straits for money? Oh! why didst thou
 not apply to me? Though I have not a thousand at my command,
 I could have given thee quite a hundred, nay indeed two hundred
 florins. By what thou hast said thou hast made me hesitate to accept
 the service that thou proposest to render me.</q> <milestone id="p08100034" />Which words fairly
 delivered Salabaetto into the lady's hands, insomuch that: <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q>
 quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">I would not have you decline my help for such a scruple;
 for had my need been as great as yours, I should certainly have
 applied to you.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100035" />Quoth then the lady: <q direct="unspecified">Ah! Salabaetto mine,
 well I wot that the love thou bearest me is a true and perfect love,
 seeing that, without waiting to be asked, thou dost so handsomely
 come to my aid with so large a sum of money. And albeit I was
 thine without this token of thy love, yet, assuredly, it has made me
 thine in an even greater degree; nor shall I ever forget that 'tis to
 thee I owe my brother's life. 
<milestone id="p08100036" />But God knows I take thy money
 from thee reluctantly, seeing that thou art a merchant, and 'tis by
 means of money that merchants conduct all their affairs; but, as
 necessity constrains me, and I have good hope of speedily repaying
 thee, I will even take it, and by way of security, if I should find no
 readier method, I will pawn all that I have here.</q> Which said, she
 burst into tears, and fell upon Salabaetto, pressing her cheek upon
 his.</p><p><milestone id="p08100037" />Salabaetto tried to comfort her; and having spent the night with
 her, on the morrow, being minded to shew himself her most devoted
 <pb n="256" />servant, brought her, without awaiting any reminder, five hundred
 fine florins of gold: which she, laughing at heart while the tears
 streamed from her eyes, took, Salabaetto trusting her mere promise
 of repayment. <milestone id="p08100038" />Now that the lady had gotten the money, the
 complexion of affairs began to alter; and whereas Salabaetto had
 been wont to have free access to her, whenever he was so minded,
 now for one reason or another he was denied admittance six times
 out of seven; nor did she greet him with the same smile, or shower
 on him the same caresses, or do him the same cheer as of yore. 
<milestone id="p08100039" />So
 a month, two months, passed beyond the time when he was to have
 been repaid his money; and when he demanded it, he was put off
 with words. 
<milestone id="p08100040" />Whereby Salabaetto, being now ware of the cheat
 which his slender wit had suffered the evil-disposed woman to put
 upon him, and also that, having neither writing nor witness against
 her, he was entirely at her mercy in regard of his claim, and being,
 moreover, ashamed to lodge any complaint with any one, as well
 because he had been forewarned of her character, as because he
 dreaded the ridicule to which his folly justly exposed him, was
 chagrined beyond measure, and inly bewailed his simplicity. 
<milestone id="p08100041" />And
 his masters having written to him, bidding him change the money
 and remit it to them, he, being apprehensive that, making default as
 he must, he should, if he remained there, be detected, resolved to
 depart; and having taken ship, he repaired, not, as he should have
 done, to Pisa, but to Naples; 
<milestone id="p08100042" />where at that time resided our gossip,
 Pietro dello Canigiano, treasurer of the Empress of Constantinople,
 a man of great sagacity and acuteness, and a very great friend of
 Salabaetto and his kinsfolk; to whom trusting in his great discretion,
 Salabaetto after a while discovered his distress, telling him what he
 had done, and the sorry plight in which by consequence he stood,
 and craving his aid and counsel, that he might the more readily find
 means of livelihood there, for that he was minded never to go back
 to Florence. <milestone id="p08100043" />Impatient to hear of such folly: <q direct="unspecified">'Twas ill done of
 thee,</q> quoth Canigiano, <q direct="unspecified">thou hast misbehaved thyself, wronged thy
 masters, and squandered an exorbitant sum in lewdness; however,
 'tis done, and we must consider of the remedy.</q> And indeed, like
 the shrewd man that he was, he had already bethought him what
 was best to be done; and forthwith he imparted it to Salabaetto.
 Which expedient Salabaetto approving, resolved to make the adven<pb n="257" />ture;
 <milestone id="p08100044" />and having still a little money, and being furnished with a loan
 by Canigiano, he provided himself with not a few bales well and
 closely corded, and bought some twenty oil-casks, which he filled,
 and having put all on shipboard, returned to Palermo. There he
 gave the invoice of the bales, as also of the oil-casks, to the officers of
 the dogana, and having them all entered to his credit, laid them up
 in the store-rooms, saying that he purposed to leave them there until
 the arrival of other merchandise that he expected.</p><p><milestone id="p08100045" />Which Jancofiore learning, and being informed that the merchandise,
 that he had brought with him, was worth fully two thousand
 florins of gold, or even more, besides that which he expected, which
 was valued at more than three thousand florins of gold, bethought her
 that she had not aimed high enough, and that 'twere well to refund
 him the five hundred, if so she might make the greater part of the
 five thousand florins her own. Wherefore she sent for him, 
<milestone id="p08100046" />and
 Salabaetto, having learned his lesson of cunning, waited on her.
 Feigning to know nought of the cargo he had brought with him, she
 received him with marvellous cheer, and began: <q direct="unspecified">Lo, now, if thou
 wast angry with me because I did not repay thee thy money in due
 time:</q> 
<milestone id="p08100047" />but Salabaetto interrupted her, saying with a laugh:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam, 'tis true I was a little vexed, seeing that I would have
 plucked out my heart to pleasure you; but listen, and you shall learn
 the quality of my displeasure. <milestone id="p08100048" />Such and so great is the love I bear
 you, that I have sold the best part of all that I possess, whereby I
 have already in this port merchandise to the value of more than two
 thousand florins, and expect from the Levant other goods to the
 value of above three thousand florins, and mean to set up a warehouse
 in this city, and live here, to be ever near you, for that I deem myself
 more blessed in your love than any other lover that lives.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100049" />Whereupon:
 <q direct="unspecified">Harkye, Salabaetto,</q> quoth the lady, <q direct="unspecified">whatever advantages
 thee is mighty grateful to me, seeing that I love thee more
 than my very life, and right glad am I that thou art come back with
 intent to stay, for I hope to have many a good time with thee; but
 something I must say to thee by way of excuse, for that, whilst thou
 wast thinking of taking thy departure, there were times when thou
 wast disappointed of seeing me, and others when thou hadst not as
 gladsome a welcome as thou wast wont to have, and therewithal I
 kept not the time promised for the repayment of thy money. 
<milestone id="p08100050" />Thou
 <pb n="258" />must know that I was then in exceeding great trouble and tribulation,
 and whoso is thus bested, love he another never so much, cannot
 greet him with as gladsome a mien, or be as attentive to him, as he
 had life; 
<milestone id="p08100051" />and thou must further know that 'tis by no means an easy
 matter for a lady to come by a thousand florins of gold: why, 'tis
 every day a fresh lie, and never a promise kept; and so we in our
 turn must needs lie to others; and 'twas for this cause, and not for
 any fault of mine, that I did not repay thee thy money; 
<milestone id="p08100052" />however, I
 had it but a little while after thy departure, and had I known whither
 to send it, be sure I would have remitted it to thee; but, as that I
 wist not, I have kept it safe for thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100053" />She then produced a purse, in
 which were the very same coins that he had brought her, and placed
 it in his hand, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Count and see if there are five hundred
 there.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100054" />'Twas the happiest moment Salabaetto had yet known, as,
 having told them out, and found the sum exact, he made answer:
 <q direct="unspecified">Madam, I know that you say sooth, and what you have done
 abundantly proves it; wherefore, and for the love I bear you, I
 warrant you there is no sum you might ask of me on any occasion of
 need, with which, if 'twere in my power, I would not accommodate
 you; whereof, when I am settled here, you will be able to assure
 yourself.</q></p><p><milestone id="p08100055" />Having thus in words reinstated himself as her lover, he proceeded
 to treat her as his mistress, whereto she responded, doing all that was
 in her power to pleasure and honour him, and feigning to be in the
 last degree enamoured of him. 
<milestone id="p08100056" />But Salabaetto, being minded to
 requite her guile with his own, went to her one evening, being bidden
 to sup and sleep with her, with an aspect so melancholy and dolorous,
 that he shewed as he had lief give up the ghost. Jancofiore, as she
 embraced and kissed him, demanded of him the occasion of his
 melancholy. 
<milestone id="p08100057" />Whereto he, having let her be instant with him a
 good while, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">I am undone, for that the ship, having
 aboard her the goods that I expected, has been taken by the corsairs
 of Monaco, and held to ransom in ten thousand florins of gold, of
 which it falls to me to pay one thousand, and I have not a denier, for
 the five hundred thou repaidst me I sent forthwith to Naples to buy
 stuffs for this market, <milestone id="p08100058" />and were I to sell the merchandise I have here,
 as 'tis not now the right time to sell, I should scarce get half the
 value; nor am I as yet so well known here as to come by any to
 <pb n="259" />help me at this juncture, and so what to do or what to say I know
 not; but this I know that, if I send not the money without delay,
 my merchandise will be taken to Monaco, and I shall never touch
 aught of it again.</q> 
<milestone id="p08100059" />Whereat the lady was mightily annoyed, being
 apprehensive of losing all, and bethought her how she might prevent
 the goods going to Monaco: wherefore: <q direct="unspecified">God knows,</q> quoth
 she, <q direct="unspecified">that for the love I bear thee I am not a little sorry for thee:
 but what boots it idly to distress oneself? Had I the money, God
 knows I would lend it thee forthwith, but I have it not. 
<milestone id="p08100060" />One,
 indeed, there is that accommodated me a day or two ago with five
 hundred florins that I stood in need of, but he requires a heavy
 usance, not less than thirty on the hundred, and if thou shouldst
 have recourse to him, good security must be forthcoming. Now for
 my part I am ready, so I may serve thee, to pledge all these dresses,
 and my person to boot, for as much as he will lend thee thereon; but
 how wilt thou secure the balance?</q></p><p><milestone id="p08100061" />Salabaetto divined the motive that prompted her thus to accommodate
 him, and that she was to lend the money herself; which suiting
 his purpose well, he first of all thanked her, and then said that, being
 constrained by necessity, he would not stand out against exorbitant
 terms, <milestone id="p08100062" />adding that, as to the balance, he would secure it upon the
 merchandise that he had at the dogana by causing it to be entered in
 the name of the lender; but that he must keep the key of the storerooms,
 as well that he might be able to shew the goods, if requested,
 as to make sure that none of them should be tampered with or
 changed or exchanged. <milestone id="p08100063" />The lady said that this was reasonable, and
 that 'twas excellent security. So, betimes on the morrow, the lady
 sent for a broker, in whom she reposed much trust, and having talked
 the matter over with him, gave him a thousand florins of gold, which
 the broker took to Salabaetto, and thereupon had all that Salabaetto
 had at the dogana entered in his name; they then had the script and
 counterscript made out, and, the arrangement thus concluded, went
 about their respective affairs. <milestone id="p08100064" />Salabaetto lost no time in getting
 aboard a bark with his five hundred florins of gold, and being come
 to Naples, sent thence a remittance which fully discharged his obligation
 to his masters that had entrusted him with the stuffs: he also
 paid all that he owed to Pietro dello Canigiano and all his other
 creditors, and made not a little merry with Canigiano over the trick
 <pb n="260" />he had played the Sicilian lady. He then departed from Naples, and
 being minded to have done with mercantile affairs, betook him to
 Ferrara.</p><p><milestone id="p08100065" />Jancofiore, surprised at first by Salabaetto's disappearance from
 Palermo, waxed after a while suspicious; and, when she had waited
 fully two months, seeing that he did not return, she caused the broker
 to break open the store-rooms. <milestone id="p08100066" />And trying first of all the casks, she
 found them full of sea-water, save that in each there was perhaps a
 hog's-head of oil floating on the surface. Then undoing the bales,
 she found them all, save two that contained stuffs, full of tow, and
 in short their whole contents put together were not worth more than
 two hundred florins. <milestone id="p08100067" />Wherefore Jancofiore, knowing herself to
 have been outdone, regretted long and bitterly the five hundred
 florins of gold that she had refunded, and still more the thousand that
 she had lent, repeating many a time to herself: Who with a Tuscan
 has to do, Had need of eyesight quick and true. Thus, left with the
 loss and the laugh against her, she discovered that there were others
 as knowing as she.</p></div2>