<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov1003"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p00030001" />Mitridanes, holding Nathan in despite by reason of his
 courtesy, journeys with intent to kill him, and falling
 in with him unawares, is advised by him how to
 compass his end. Following his advice, he finds him
 in a copse, and recognizing him, is shame-stricken,
 and becomes his friend.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00030002" />Verily like to a miracle seemed it to all to hear that a prelate
 had
 done aught with magnificence; but when the ladies had made an end
 of their remarks, the king bade Filostrato follow suit; and forthwith
 Filostrato began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p00030003" />Noble ladies, great was the magnificence of the
 King of Spain, and perchance a thing unheard-of the magnificence
 of the Abbot of Cluny; but peradventure 'twill seem not a whit less
 marvellous to you to hear of one who, to shew liberality towards
 another, did resolve artfully to yield to him his blood, nay, his very
 life, for which the other thirsted, and had so done, had the other
 chosen to take them, as I shall shew you in a little story.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p00030004" />Beyond all question, if we may believe the report of certain
 Genoese, and other folk that have been in those regions, there dwelt
 of yore in the parts of Cathay one Nathan, a man of noble lineage
 and incomparable wealth.  <milestone id="p00030005" />Who, having a seat hard by a road, by
 which whoso would travel from the West eastward, or from the East
 westward, must needs pass, and being magnanimous and liberal, and
 zealous to approve himself such in act, did set on work cunning
 artificers not a few, and cause one of the finest and largest and most
 luxurious palaces that ever were seen, to be there builded and
 furnished in the goodliest manner with all things meet for the
 reception and honourable entertainment of gentlemen.  <milestone id="p00030006" />And so,
 <pb n="323" />keeping a great array of excellent servants, he courteously and
 hospitably did the honours of his house to whoso came and went: in
 which laudable way of life he persevered, until not only the East, but
 well-nigh all the West had heard his fame;  <milestone id="p00030007" />which thus, what time
 he was well-stricken in years, albeit not for that cause grown weary
 of shewing courtesy, reached the ears of one Mitridanes, a young man
 of a country not far distant. Who, knowing himself to be no less
 wealthy than Nathan, grew envious of the renown that he had of his
 good deeds, and resolved to obliterate, or at least to obscure it, by a
 yet greater liberality.  <milestone id="p00030008" />So he had built for himself a palace like that
 of Nathan, of which he did the honours with a lavish courtesy that
 none had ever equalled, to whoso came or went that way; and verily
 in a short while he became famous enough.</p><p><milestone id="p00030009" />Now it so befell that on a day when the young man was all alone
 in the courtyard of the palace, there came in by one of the gates a
 poor woman, who asked of him an alms, and had it; but, not content
 therewith, came again to him by the second gate, and asked another
 alms, and had it, and after the like sort did even unto the twelfth
 time; but, she returning for the thirteenth time: <q direct="unspecified">My good
 woman,</q> quoth Mitridanes, <q direct="unspecified">thou art not a little pertinacious in thy
 begging:</q> howbeit he gave her an alms.  <milestone id="p00030010" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Ah!
 the wondrous liberality of Nathan!</q> quoth the beldam: <q direct="unspecified">thirty-two
 gates are there to his palace, by every one of which I have entered,
 and asking alms of him, was never--for aught he shewed--recognized,
 or refused, and here, though I have entered as yet by but
 thirteen gates, I am recognized and reprimanded.</q> And therewith
 she departed, and returned no more.  <milestone id="p00030011" />Mitridanes, who accounted
 the mention of Nathan's fame an abatement of his own, was kindled
 by her words with a frenzy of wrath, and began thus to commune
 with himself: Alas! when shall I attain to the grandeur of
 Nathan's liberality, to say nought of transcending it, as I would fain,
 seeing that in the veriest trifles I cannot approach him? Of a surety
 my labour is in vain, if I rid not the earth of him: which, since old
 age relieves me not of him, I must forthwith do with mine own
 hands.  <milestone id="p00030012" />And in the flush of his despite up he started, and giving
 none to know of his purpose, got to horse with a small company,
 and after three days arrived at the place where Nathan abode; and
 having enjoined his comrades to make as if they were none of his,
 <pb n="324" />and knew him not, and to go quarter themselves as best they might
 until they had his further orders, he, being thus alone, towards
 evening came upon Nathan, also alone, at no great distance from
 his splendid palace. Nathan was recreating himself by a walk, and
 was very simply clad; so that Mitridanes, knowing him not, asked
 him if he could shew him where Nathan dwelt.  <milestone id="p00030013" /><q direct="unspecified">My son,</q> replied
 Nathan gladsomely, <q direct="unspecified">that can none in these parts better than I;
 wherefore, so it please thee, I will bring thee thither.</q> 
      <milestone id="p00030014" />The young
 man replied that 'twould be mighty agreeable to him, but that, if so
 it might be, he had a mind to be neither known nor seen by Nathan.
 <q direct="unspecified">And herein also,</q> returned Nathan, <q direct="unspecified">since 'tis thy pleasure, I will
 gratify thee.</q>  <milestone id="p00030015" />Whereupon Mitridanes dismounted, and with Nathan,
 who soon engaged him in delightsome discourse, walked to the
 goodly palace. Arrived there Nathan caused one of his servants
 take the young man's horse, and drawing close to him, bade him
 in a whisper to see to it without delay that none in the house should
 tell the young man that he was Nathan: and so 'twas done.</p><p><milestone id="p00030016" />Being come into the palace, Nathan quartered Mitridanes in a
 most goodly chamber, where none saw him but those whom he had
 appointed to wait upon him; and he himself kept him company,
 doing him all possible honour.  <milestone id="p00030017" />Of whom Mitridanes, albeit he
 reverenced him as a father, yet, being thus with him, forbore not to
 ask who he was. Whereto Nathan made answer: <q direct="unspecified">I am a petty
 servant of Nathan: old as I am, I have been with him since my
 childhood, and never has he advanced me to higher office than this
 wherein thou seest me: wherefore, howsoever other folk may praise
 him, little cause have I to do so.</q>  <milestone id="p00030018" />Which words afforded Mitridanes
 some hope of carrying his wicked purpose into effect with more of
 plan and less of risk than had otherwise been possible. By and by
 Nathan very courteously asked him who he was, and what business
 brought him thither; offering him such counsel and aid as he might
 be able to afford him.  <milestone id="p00030019" />Mitridanes hesitated a while to reply: but
 at last he resolved to trust him, and when with no little circumlocution
 he had demanded of him fidelity, counsel and aid, he fully
 discovered to him who he was, and the purpose and motive of his
 coming thither.  <milestone id="p00030020" />Now, albeit to hear Mitridanes thus unfold his
 norrid design caused Nathan no small inward commotion, yet 'twas
 not long before courageously and composedly he thus made answer:
 <pb n="325" /><q direct="unspecified">Noble was thy father, Mitridanes, and thou art minded to shew
 thyself not unworthy of him by this lofty emprise of thine, to wit,
 of being liberal to all comers: and for that thou art envious of
 Nathan's merit I greatly commend thee; for were many envious
 for a like cause, the world, from being a most wretched, would soon
 become a happy place.  <milestone id="p00030021" />Doubt not that I shall keep secret the
 design which thou hast confided to me, for the furtherance whereof
 'tis good advice rather than substantial aid that I have to offer thee.
 Which advice is this.  <milestone id="p00030022" />Hence, perhaps half a mile off, thou mayst
 see a copse, in which almost every morning Nathan is wont to walk,
 taking his pleasure, for quite a long while: 'twill be an easy matter
 for thee to find him there, and deal with him as thou mayst be
 minded.  <milestone id="p00030023" />Now, shouldst thou slay him, thou wilt get thee home with
 less risk of let, if thou take not the path by which thou camest
 hither, but that which thou seest issue from the copse on the left,
 for, though 'tis somewhat more rough, it leads more directly to thy
 house, and will be safer for thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030024" />Possessed of this information, Mitridanes, when Nathan had left
 him, privily apprised his comrades, who were likewise lodged in the
 palace, of the place where they were to await him on the ensuing
 day; which being come, Nathan, inflexibly determined to act in all
 respects according to the advice which he had given Mitridanes,
 hied him forth to the copse unattended, to meet his death.  <milestone id="p00030025" />Mitridanes,
 being risen, took his bow and sword, for other arms he had
 none with him, mounted his horse, and rode to the copse, through
 which, while he was yet some way off, he saw Nathan passing, quite
 alone. And being minded, before he fell upon him, to see his face
 and hear the sound of his voice, as, riding at a smart pace, he came
 up with him, he laid hold of him by his head-gear, exclaiming:
 <q direct="unspecified">Greybeard, thou art a dead man.</q>  <milestone id="p00030026" />Whereto Nathan answered
 nought but: <q direct="unspecified">Then 'tis but my desert.</q>  <milestone id="p00030027" />But Mitridanes, hearing
 the voice, and scanning the face, forthwith knew him for the same
 man that had welcomed him heartily, consorted with him familiarly,
 and counselled him faithfully; whereby his wrath presently subsided,
 and gave place to shame. Wherefore, casting away the sword that
 he held drawn in act to strike, he sprang from his horse, and weeping,
 threw himself at Nathan's feet, saying:  <milestone id="p00030028" /><q direct="unspecified">Your liberality, dearest
 father, I acknowledge to be beyond all question, seeing with what
 craft you did plot your coming hither to yield me your life, for
 <pb n="326" />which, by mine own avowal, you knew that I, albeit cause I had
 none, did thirst. But God, more regardful of my duty than I
 myself, has now, in this moment of supreme stress, opened the eyes
 of my mind, that wretched envy had fast sealed.  <milestone id="p00030029" />The prompter
 was your compliance, the greater is the debt of penitence that I owe
 you for my fault; wherefore wreak even such vengeance upon me
 as you may deem answerable to my transgression.</q>  <milestone id="p00030030" />But Nathan
 raised Mitridanes to his feet, and tenderly embraced him, saying:
 <q direct="unspecified">My son, thy enterprise, howsoever thou mayst denote it, whether
 evil or otherwise, was not such that thou shouldst crave, or I give,
 pardon thereof; for 'twas not in malice but in that thou wouldst
 fain have been reputed better than I that thou ensuedst it.  <milestone id="p00030031" />Doubt
 then no more of me; nay, rest assured that none that lives bears
 thee such love as I, who know the loftiness of thy spirit, bent not
 to heap up wealth, as do the caitiffs, but to dispense in bounty thine
 accumulated store.  <milestone id="p00030032" />Think it no shame that to enhance thy reputation
 thou wouldst have slain me; nor deem that I marvel thereat.
 To slay not one man, as thou wast minded, but countless multitudes,
 to waste whole countries with fire, and to raze cities to the ground
 has been well-nigh the sole art, by which the mightiest emperors and
 the greatest kings have extended their dominions, and by consequence
 their fame. Wherefore, if thou, to increase thy fame, wouldst fain
 have slain me, 'twas nothing marvellous or strange, but wonted.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030033" />Whereto Mitridanes made answer, not to excuse his wicked
 design, but to commend the seemly excuse found for it by Nathan,
 whom at length he told how beyond measure he marvelled that
 Nathan had not only been consenting to the enterprise, but had
 aided him therein by his counsel. But Nathan answered:  <milestone id="p00030034" /><q direct="unspecified">Liefer
 had I, Mitridanes, that thou didst not marvel either at my consent
 or at my counsel, for that, since I was my own master and of a mind
 to that emprise whereon thou art also bent, never a soul came to my
 house, but, so far as in me lay, I gave him all that he asked of me.
  <milestone id="p00030035" />Thou camest, lusting for my life; and so, when I heard thee crave
 it of me, I forthwith, that thou mightst not be the only guest to
 depart hence ill content, resolved to give it thee; and to that end I
 gave thee such counsel as I deemed would serve thee both to the
 taking of my life and the preservation of thine own. Wherefore
 yet again I bid thee, nay, I entreat thee, if so thou art minded, to
 take it for thy satisfaction: I know not how I could better bestow
 <pb n="327" />it.  <milestone id="p00030036" />I have had the use of it now for some eighty years, and
 pleasure and solace thereof; and I know that, by the course of
 Nature and the common lot of man and all things mundane, it can
 continue to be mine for but a little while; and so I deem that 'twere
 much better to bestow it, as I have ever bestowed and dispensed my
 wealth, than to keep it, until, against my will, it be reft from me by
 Nature.  <milestone id="p00030037" />'Twere but a trifle, though 'twere a hundred years: how
 insignificant, then, the six or eight years that are all I have to give!
 Take it, then, if thou hadst lief, take it, I pray thee; for, long as
 I have lived here, none have I found but thee to desire it; nor know
 I when I may find another, if thou take it not, to demand it of me.
  <milestone id="p00030038" />And if, peradventure, I should find one such, yet I know that the
 longer I keep it, the less its worth will be; wherefore, ere it be thus
 cheapened, take it, I implore thee.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030039" />Sore shame-stricken, Mitridanes made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Now God
 forefend that I should so much as harbour, as but now I did, such a
 thought, not to say do such a deed, as to wrest from you a thing
 so precious as your life, the years whereof, so far from abridging, I
 would gladly supplement with mine own.</q>  <milestone id="p00030040" /><q direct="unspecified">So then,</q> rejoined
 Nathan promptly, <q direct="unspecified">thou wouldst, if thou couldst, add thy years to
 mine, and cause me to serve thee as I never yet served any man, to
 wit, to take from thee that which is thine, I that never took aught
	from a soul!</q> <milestone id="p00030041" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, that would I,</q> returned Mitridanes.  
<milestone id="p00030042" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q>
 quoth Nathan, <q direct="unspecified">do as I shall bid thee. Thou art young: tarry
 here in my house, and call thyself Nathan; and I will get me to
 thy house, and ever call myself Mitridanes.</q>  <milestone id="p00030043" />Whereto Mitridanes
 made answer: <q direct="unspecified">Were I but able to discharge this trust, as you
 have been and are, scarce would I hesitate to accept your offer; but,
 as too sure am I that aught that I might do would but serve to
 lower Nathan's fame, and I am not minded to mar that in another
 which I cannot mend in myself, accept it I will not.</q></p><p><milestone id="p00030044" />After which and the like interchange of delectable discourse,
 Nathan and Mitridanes, by Nathan's desire, returned to the palace;
 where Nathan for some days honourably entreated Mitridanes, and
 by his sage counsel confirmed and encouraged him in his high and
 noble resolve; after which, Mitridanes, being minded to return
 home with his company, took his leave of Nathan, fully persuaded
 that 'twas not possible to surpass him in liberality.</p></div2>