<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0308"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03080001" />Ferondo, having taken a certain powder, is interred for
 dead; is disinterred by the abbot, who enjoys his wife;
 is put in prison and taught to believe that he is in
 purgatory; is then resuscitated, and rears as his own
 a boy begotten by the abbot upon his wife.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03080002" />Ended Emilia's long story, which to none was the less pleasing
	for its length, but was deemed of all the ladies brief in regard of the
	number and variety of the events therein recounted, a gesture of
	the queen sufficed to convey her behest to Lauretta, and cause her
	thus to begin:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03080003" /><q direct="unspecified">Dearest ladies, I have it in mind to tell you a true
	  story, which wears far more of the aspect of a lie than of that which
	  it really was: 'tis brought to my recollection by that which we
	  have heard of one being bewailed and buried in lieu of another. My
	  story then is of one that, living, was buried for dead, and after believed
	  with many others that he came out of the tomb not as one that had
	  not died but as one risen from the dead; whereby he was venerated
	  as a saint who ought rather to have been condemned as a criminal.</q></p></div3><p><milestone id="p03080004" />Know then that there was and still is in Tuscany an abbey,
 situate, as we see not a few, in a somewhat solitary spot, wherein the
 office of abbot was held by a monk, who in all other matters ordered
 his life with great sanctity, save only in the commerce with women,
 and therein knew so well how to cloak his indulgence, that scarce any
 there were that so much as suspected--not to say detected it--so
 holy and just was he reputed in all matters. <milestone id="p03080005" />Now the abbot consorted
 much with a very wealthy contadino, Ferondo by name, a
 man coarse and gross beyond measure, whose friendship the abbot
 only cared for because of the opportunities which it afforded of
 <pb n="233" />deriving amusement from his simplicity; and during their intercourse
 the abbot discovered that Ferondo had a most beautiful wife; of
 whom he became so hotly enamoured that he could think of nought
 else either by day or by night. <milestone id="p03080006" />But learning that, however simple
 and inept in all other matters, Ferondo shewed excellent good sense
 in cherishing and watching over this wife of his, he almost despaired.
 However, being very astute, he prevailed so far with Ferondo, that he
 would sometimes bring his wife with him to take a little recreation
 in the abbey-garden, where he discoursed to them with all lowliness
 of the blessedness of life eternal, and the most pious works of many
 men and women of times past, insomuch that the lady conceived a
 desire to confess to him, and craved and had Ferondo's leave therefor.
 <milestone id="p03080007" />So, to the abbot's boundless delight, the lady came and seated herself
 at his feet to make her confession, whereto she prefixed the following
 exordium: 
<milestone id="p03080008" /><q direct="unspecified">If God, Sir, had given me a husband, or had not permitted
 me to have one, perchance 'twould be easy for me, under your
 guidance, to enter the way, of which you have spoken, that leads to
 life eternal. But, considering what manner of man Ferondo is, and
 his stupidity, I may call myself a widow, while yet I am married in
 that, so long as he lives, I may have no other husband; and he,
 fool that he is, is without the least cause so inordinately jealous of
 me that 'tis not possible but that my life with him be one of perpetual
 tribulation and woe. <milestone id="p03080009" />Wherefore, before I address myself to make
 further confession, I in all humility beseech you to be pleased to give
 me some counsel of this matter, for here or nowhere is to be found
 the source of the amelioration of my life, and if it be not found,
 neither confession nor any other good work will be of any avail.</q>
 <milestone id="p03080010" />The abbot was overjoyed to hear her thus speak, deeming that
 Fortune had opened a way to the fulfilment of his heart's desire.
 Wherefore he said: <q direct="unspecified">My daughter, I doubt not that 'tis a great
 affliction to a lady, fair and delicate as you are, to have a fool for a
 husband, and still more so that he should be jealous: and as your
 husband is both the one and the other, I readily credit what you say
 of your tribulation. <milestone id="p03080011" />But, to come to the point, I see no resource or
 remedy in this case, save this only, that Ferondo be cured of his
 jealousy. The medicine that shall cure him I know very well how
 to devise, but it behoves you to keep secret what I am about to tell
 you.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080012" /><q direct="unspecified">Doubt not of it, my father,</q> said the lady; <q direct="unspecified">for I had
 <pb n="234" />rather suffer death than tell any aught that you forbade me to tell.
 But the medicine, how is it to be devised?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080013" /><q direct="unspecified">If we would have
 him cured,</q> replied the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">it can only be by his going to
 purgatory.</q>
 <milestone id="p03080014" /><q direct="unspecified">And how may that be?</q> returned the lady; <q direct="unspecified">can he go
 thither while he yet lives?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080015" /><q direct="unspecified">He must die,</q> answered the abbot;
 <q direct="unspecified">and so he will go thither; and when he has suffered pain enough to
 be cured of his jealousy, we have certain prayers with which we will
 supplicate God to restore him to life, and He will do so.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080016" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q>
 said the lady; <q direct="unspecified">am I to remain a widow?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080017" /><q direct="unspecified">Yes,</q> replied the
 abbot, <q direct="unspecified">for a certain time, during which you must be very careful
 not to let yourself be married to another, because 'twould offend God,
 and when Ferondo was restored to life, you would have to go back to
 him, and he would be more jealous than ever.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080018" /><q direct="unspecified">Be it so then,</q>
 said the lady; <q direct="unspecified">if he be but cured of his jealousy, and so I be not
 doomed to pass the rest of my days in prison, I shall be content: do
 as you think best.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080019" /><q direct="unspecified">And so will I,</q> said the abbot; <q direct="unspecified">but what
 reward shall I have for such a service?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080020" /><q direct="unspecified">My father,</q> said the
 lady, <q direct="unspecified">what you please; so only it be in my power. But what may
 the like of me do that may be acceptable to a man such as you?'
<milestone id="p03080021" /> <q direct="unspecified">Madam,</q> replied the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">'tis in your power to do no less for
 me than I am about to do for you: as that which I am minded to do
 will ensure your comfort and consolation, so there is that which you
 may do which will be the deliverance and salvation of my life.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080022" /><q direct="unspecified">If
 so it be,</q> said the lady, <q direct="unspecified">I shall not be found wanting.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080023" /><q direct="unspecified">In that
 case,</q> said the abbot, <q direct="unspecified">you will give me your love, and gratify my
 passion for you, with which I am all afire and wasting away.</q>
 <milestone id="p03080024" />Whereto the lady, all consternation, replied: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! my father, what
 is this you crave? I took you for a holy man; now does it beseem
 holy men to make such overtures to ladies that come to them for
 counsel?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080025" /><q direct="unspecified">Marvel not, fair my soul,</q> returned the abbot; 
	<q direct="unspecified">hereby
	  is my holiness in no wise diminished, for holiness resides in the
	  soul, and this which I ask of you is but a sin of the flesh. But, however
	  it may be, such is the might of your bewitching beauty, that
	  love constrains me thus to act. And, let me tell you, good cause
	  have you to vaunt you of your beauty more than other women, in
	  that it delights the saints, who are used to contemplate celestial
	  beauties; <milestone id="p03080026" />whereto I may add that, albeit I am an abbot, yet I am a
	  man even as others, and, as you see, not yet old. Nor need this
	  <pb n="235" />matter seem formidable to you, but rather to be anticipated with
	  pleasure, for, while Ferondo is in purgatory, I shall be your nightly
	  companion, and will give you such solace as he should have given you;
	  nor will it ever be discovered by any, for all think of me even as you
	  did a while ago, or even more so. <milestone id="p03080027" />Reject not the grace that God
	  accords you; for 'tis in your power to have, and, if you are wise and
	  follow my advice, you shall have that which women not a few desire
	  in vain to have. And moreover I have jewels fair and rare, which I
	  am minded shall be yours and none other's. Wherefore, sweet my
	  hope, deny me not due guerdon of the service which I gladly render
	  you.</q></q>
    </p><p><milestone id="p03080028" />The lady, her eyes still downcast, knew not how to deny him,
 and yet scrupled to gratify him: wherefore the abbot, seeing that
 she had hearkened and hesitated to answer, deemed that she was
 already half won, and following up what he had said with much more
 to the like effect, did not rest until he had persuaded her that she
 would do well to comply: and so with some confusion she told him
 that she was ready to obey his every behest; but it might not be until
 Ferondo was in purgatory. <milestone id="p03080029" />The abbot, well content, replied: 
<q direct="unspecified">And
 we will send him thither forthwith: do but arrange that he come
 hither to stay with me to-morrow or the day after.</q> Which said, he
 slipped a most beautiful ring on her finger, and dismissed her.
 Pleased with the gift, and expecting more to come, the lady rejoined
 her attendants, with whom she forthwith fell a talking marvellous
 things of the abbot's sanctity, and so went home with them.</p><p><milestone id="p03080030" />Some few days after, Ferondo being come to the abbey, the abbot
 no sooner saw him than he resolved to send him to purgatory. <milestone id="p03080031" />So he
 selected from among his drugs a powder of marvellous virtue, which
 he had gotten in the Levant from a great prince, who averred that
 'twas wont to be used by the Old Man of the Mountain, when he
 would send any one to or bring him from his paradise, and that,
 without doing the recipient any harm, 'twould induce in him, according
 to the quantity of the dose, a sleep of such duration and quality that,
 while the efficacy of the powder lasted, none would deem him to be
 alive.<note>By the Old Man of the Mountain is meant the head of the
 confraternity
 of hashish-eaters (Assassins), whose chief stronghold was at Alamut in
 Persia (1090-1256). Cf. Marco Polo, ed. Yule, I. cap. xxiii.</note>
 Whereof he took enough to cause a three days' sleep, and
 <pb n="236" />gave it to Ferondo in his cell in a beaker that had still some wine in
 it, so that he drank it unwittingly: after which he took Ferondo to
 the cloister, and there with some of his monks fell to making merry
 with him and his ineptitudes. <milestone id="p03080032" />In no long time, however, the
 powder so wrought, that Ferondo was seized in the head with a fit
 of somnolence so sudden and violent that he slept as he stood, and
 sleeping fell to the ground. <milestone id="p03080033" />The abbot put on an agitated air, caused
 him to be untrussed, sent for cold water, and had it sprinkled on his
 face, and applied such other remedies as if he would fain call back
 life and sense banished by vapours of the stomach, or some other
 intrusive force; but, as, for all that he and his monks did, Ferondo
 did not revive, they, after feeling his pulse and finding there no
 sign of life, one and all pronounced him certainly dead. Wherefore
 they sent word to his wife and kinsfolk, who came forthwith, and
 mourned a while; after which Ferondo in his clothes was by the
 abbot's order laid in a tomb. <milestone id="p03080034" />The lady went home, saying that
 nothing should ever part her from a little son that she had borne
 Ferondo; and so she occupied herself with the care of her son and
 Ferondo's estate. <milestone id="p03080035" />At night the abbot rose noiselessly, and with the
 help of a Bolognese monk, in whom he reposed much trust, and who
 was that very day arrived from Bologna, got Ferondo out of the
 tomb, and bore him to a vault, which admitted no light, having been
 made to serve as a prison for delinquent monks; and having stripped
 him of his clothes, and habited him as a monk, they laid him on a
 truss of straw, and left him there until he should revive. Expecting
 which event, and instructed by the abbot how he was then to act,
 the Bolognese monk (none else knowing aught of what was afoot)
 kept watch by the tomb.</p><p><milestone id="p03080036" />The day after, the abbot with some of his monks paid a pastoral
 visit to the lady's house, where he found her in mourning weeds and
 sad at heart; and, after administering a little consolation, he gently
 asked her to redeem her promise. Free as she now felt herself, and
 hampered neither by Ferondo nor by any other, the lady, who had
 noticed another beautiful ring on the abbot's finger, promised immediate
 compliance, and arranged with the abbot that he should visit
 her the very next night. <milestone id="p03080037" />So, at nightfall, the abbot donned Ferondo's
 clothes, and, attended by his monk, paid his visit, and lay with her
 until matins to his immense delight and solace, and so returned to
 <pb n="237" />the abbey; and many visits he paid her on the same errand; whereby
 some that met him, coming or going that way, supposed that 'twas
 Ferondo perambulating those parts by way of penance; and fables
 not a few passed from mouth to mouth of the foolish rustics, and
 sometimes reached the ears of the lady, who was at no loss to account
 for them.</p><p><milestone id="p03080038" />As for Ferondo, when he revived, 'twas only to find himself he
 knew not where, while the Bolognese monk entered the tomb, gibbering
 horribly, and armed with a rod, wherewith, having laid hold of
 Ferondo, he gave him a severe thrashing. 
<milestone id="p03080039" />Blubbering and bellowing
 for pain, Ferondo could only ejaculate: <q direct="unspecified">Where am I?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080040" /><q direct="unspecified">In purgatory,</q> replied the monk. 
<milestone id="p03080041" /><q direct="unspecified">How?</q> returned Ferondo, <q direct="unspecified">am I dead then?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080042" />and the monk assuring him that 'twas even so, he
 fell a bewailing his own and his lady's and his son's fate, after the
 most ridiculous fashion in the world. <milestone id="p03080043" />The monk brought him
 somewhat to eat and drink. Of which when Ferondo caught sight,
 <q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> said he, <q direct="unspecified">dead folk eat then, do they?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080044" /><q direct="unspecified">They do,</q>
 replied the monk; <q direct="unspecified">and this, which I bring thee, is what the lady
 that was thy wife sent this morning to the church by way of alms
 for masses for thy soul; and God is minded that it be assigned to
 thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080045" /><q direct="unspecified">Now God grant her a happy year,</q> said Ferondo; <q direct="unspecified">dearly
 I loved her while I yet lived, and would hold her all night long in
 my arms, and cease not to kiss her, ay, and would do yet more to her,
 when I was so minded.</q> Whereupon he fell to eating and drinking
 with great avidity, and finding the wine not much to his taste, he
 said: <q direct="unspecified">Now God do her a mischief! Why gave she not the priest
 of the wine that is in the cask by the wall?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080046" />When he had done
 eating, the monk laid hold of him again, and gave him another sound
 thrashing with the rod. 
<milestone id="p03080047" />Ferondo bellowed mightily, and then cried
 out: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! why servest thou me so?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080048" /><q direct="unspecified">God,</q> answered the monk, <q direct="unspecified">has decreed that thou be so served twice a day.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080049" /><q direct="unspecified">For why?</q> said Ferondo. 
<milestone id="p03080050" /><q direct="unspecified">Because,</q> returned the monk, <q direct="unspecified">thou wast
 jealous, notwithstanding thou hadst to wife a woman that has not her
 peer in thy countryside.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080051" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas,</q> said Ferondo, <q direct="unspecified">she was indeed
 all that thou sayst, ay, and the sweetest creature too,--no comfit so
 honeyed--but I knew not that God took it amiss that a man should
 be jealous, or I had not been so.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080052" /><q direct="unspecified">Of that,</q> replied the monk,
 <q direct="unspecified">thou shouldst have bethought thee while thou wast there, and have
 <pb n="238" />amended thy ways; and should it fall to thy lot ever to return thither,
 be sure that thou so lay to heart the lesson that I now give thee, that
 thou be no more jealous.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080053" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> said Ferondo; <q direct="unspecified">dead folk sometimes
 return to earth, do they?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080054" /><q direct="unspecified">They do,</q> replied the monk; <q direct="unspecified">if God so will.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080055" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> said Ferondo; <q direct="unspecified">if I ever return, I will
 be the best husband in the world; never will I beat her or scold her,
 save for the wine that she has sent me this morning, and also for
 sending me never a candle, so that I have had perforce to eat in the
 dark.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080056" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay,</q> said the monk, <q direct="unspecified">she sent them, but they were burned
 at the masses.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080057" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh!</q> said Ferondo, <q direct="unspecified">I doubt not you say true;
 and, of a surety, if I ever return, I will let her do just as she likes.
 But tell me, who art thou that entreatest me thus?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080058" /><q direct="unspecified">Late of
 Sardinia I,</q> answered the monk, <q direct="unspecified">dead too; and, for that I gave
 my lord much countenance in his jealousy, doomed by God for
 my proper penance to entreat thee thus with food and drink and
 thrashings, until such time as He may ordain otherwise touching
 thee and me.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080059" /><q direct="unspecified">And are we two the only folk here?</q> inquired
 Ferondo. 
<milestone id="p03080060" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, there are thousands beside,</q> answered the monk;
 <q direct="unspecified">but thou canst neither see nor hear them, nor they thee.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080061" /><q direct="unspecified">And how far,</q> said Ferondo, <q direct="unspecified">may we be from our country?</q> 
<milestone id="p03080062" /><q direct="unspecified">Oh! ho!</q> returned the monk, <q direct="unspecified">why, 'tis some miles clean out of
 shitrange.</q>
 <milestone id="p03080063" /><q direct="unspecified">I'faith,</q> said Ferondo, <q direct="unspecified">that is far indeed: methinks we
 must be out of the world.</q></p><p><milestone id="p03080064" />In such a course, alternately beaten, fed and amused with idle
 tales, was Ferondo kept for ten months, while the abbot, to his great
 felicity, paid many a visit to the fair lady, and had the jolliest time in
 the world with her. But, as misfortunes will happen, the lady
 conceived, which fact, as soon as she was aware of it, she imparted to
 the abbot; whereupon both agreed that Ferondo must without delay
 be brought back from purgatory to earth and her, and be given to
 understand that she was with child of him. <milestone id="p03080065" />So the very next night
 the abbot went to the prison, and in a disguised voice pronounced
 Ferondo's name, and said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Ferondo, be of good cheer, for
 God is minded that thou return to earth; and on thy return thou
 shalt have a son by thy lady, and thou shalt call him Benedetto;
 because 'tis in answer to the prayers of thy holy abbot and thy lady,
 and for love of St. Benedict, that God accords thee this grace.</q>
 <milestone id="p03080066" />Whereat Ferondo was overjoyed, and said: <q direct="unspecified">It likes me well.
 <pb n="239" />God give a good year to Master Lord God, and the abbot, and St.
 Benedict, and my cheese-powdered, honey-sweet wife.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080067" />Then, in
 the wine that he sent him, the abbot administered enough of the
 powder to cause him to sleep for four hours; and so, with the aid of
 the monk, having first habited him in his proper clothes, he privily
 conveyed him back to the tomb in which he had been buried. <milestone id="p03080068" />On
 the morrow at daybreak Ferondo revived, and perceiving through a
 chink in the tomb a glimmer of light, to which he had been a
 stranger for full ten months, he knew that he was alive, and began
 to bellow: <q direct="unspecified">Let me out, let me out:</q> then, setting his head to
 the lid of the tomb, he heaved amain; whereby the lid, being insecure,
 started; and he was already thrusting it aside, when the monks,
 matins being now ended, ran to the spot and recognized Ferondo's
 voice, and saw him issue from the tomb; by which unwonted event
 they were all so affrighted that they took to flight, and hied them to
 the abbot: <milestone id="p03080069" />who, rising as if from prayer, said: <q direct="unspecified">Sons, be not
 afraid; take the cross and the holy water, and follow me, and let us
 see what sign of His might God will vouchsafe us.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080070" />And so
 he led the way to the tomb; beside which they found Ferondo
 standing, deathly pale by reason of his long estrangement from the
 light. On sight of the abbot he ran and threw himself at his feet,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">My father, it has been revealed to me that 'tis to your
 prayers and those of St. Benedict and my lady that I owe my release
 from purgatorial pain, and restoration to life; wherefore 'tis my
 prayer that God give you a good year and good calends, to-day and
 all days.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080071" /><q direct="unspecified">Laud we the power of God!</q> said the abbot. <q direct="unspecified">Go
 then, son, as God has restored thee to earth, comfort thy wife, who,
 since thou didst depart this life, has been ever in tears, and mayst thou
 live henceforth in the love and service of God.</q> 
<milestone id="p03080072" /><q direct="unspecified">Sir,</q> answered
 Ferondo, <q direct="unspecified">'tis well said; and, for the doing, trust me that, as soon as
 I find her, I shall kiss her, such is the love I bear her.</q> So saying,
 he went his way; <milestone id="p03080073" />and the abbot, left alone with his monks, made
 as if he marvelled greatly at the affair, and caused devoutly chant
 the Miserere. So Ferondo returned to his hamlet, where all that
 saw him fleeing, as folk are wont to flee from spectacles of horror,
 he called them back, asseverating that he was risen from the tomb.
 His wife at first was no less timorous: <milestone id="p03080074" />but, as folk began to take heart
 of grace, perceiving that he was alive, they plied him with many
 <pb n="240" />questions, all which he answered as one that had returned with ripe
 experience, and gave them tidings of the souls of their kinsfolk, and
 told of his own invention the prettiest fables of the purgatorial state,
 and in full folkmoot recounted the revelation vouchsafed him by the
 mouth of Ragnolo Braghiello<note>Derisively for Agnolo Gabriello (the
 h having merely the effect of
 preserving the hardness of the g before i), 
i.e. Angel Gabriel.</note> before his resuscitation.</p><p><milestone id="p03080075" />Thus was Ferondo reinstated in his property and reunited to his
 wife, who, being pregnant, as he thought, by himself, chanced by
 the time of her delivery to countenance the vulgar error that the
 woman must bear the infant in the womb for exactly nine months,
 and gave birth to a male child, who was named Benedetto Ferondi.
 <milestone id="p03080076" />Ferondo's return from purgatory, and the report he brought thence,
 immeasurably enhanced the fame of the abbot's holiness. So
 Ferondo, cured of his jealousy by the thrashings which he had gotten
 for it, verified the abbot's prediction, and never offended the lady
 again in that sort. Wherefore she lived with him, as before, in all
 outward seemliness; albeit she failed not, as occasion served, to forgather
 with the holy abbot, who had so well and sedulously served
 her in her especial need.</p></div2>