<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="conclusion" who="author" id="d06conclu"><head>Conclusion</head><p><milestone id="p06970001" />Immense was the delight and
diversion which this story afforded
 to all the company alike, and great
and general was the laughter over
 Fra Cipolla, and more especially at his
pilgrimage, and the relics, as
 well those that he had but seen as those
that he had brought back
 with him. Which being ended, the queen, taking
note that therewith
 the close of her sovereignty was come, stood up, took
off the
 crown, and set it on Dioneo's head, saying with a laugh: <milestone id="p06970002" /><q direct="unspecified">'Tis
time, Dioneo, that thou prove the weight of the burden of having
 ladies to
govern and guide. Be thou king then; and let thy rule
 be such that, when
'tis ended, we may have cause to commend it.</q>
 <milestone id="p06970003" />Dioneo took the crown,
and laughingly answered: <q direct="unspecified">Kings worthier
 far than I you may well have
seen many a time ere now--I speak
 of the kings in chess; but let me have
of you that obedience which
 is due to a true king, and of a surety I will
give you to taste of that
 solace, without which perfection of joy there
may not be in any
 festivity. But enough of this: I will govern as best I
may.</q> <milestone id="p06970004" />Then,
 as was the wont, he sent for the seneschal, and gave him
particular
 instruction how to order matters during the term of his
sovereignty,
 which done, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Noble ladies, such and so diverse has
been
 our discourse of the ways of men and their various fortunes, that
but for the visit that we had a while ago from Madam Licisca, who
 by what
she said has furnished me with matter of discourse for
 to-morrow, I doubt
I had been not a little put to it to find a theme.
 <milestone id="p06970005" />You heard how she said
that there was not a woman in her neighbourhood
 whose husband had her
virginity; adding that well she knew
 <pb n="107" />how many and what manner
of tricks they, after marriage, played
 their husbands. <milestone id="p06970006" />The first count we
may well leave to the girls
 whom it concerns; the second, methinks, should
prove a diverting
 topic: wherefore I ordain that, taking our cue from
Madam Licisca,
 we discourse to-morrow of the tricks that, either for love
or for their
 deliverance from peril, ladies have heretofore played their
husbands,
 and whether they were by the said husbands detected or no.</q>
<milestone id="p06970007" />To
 discourse of such a topic some of the ladies deemed unmeet for them,
and besought the king to find another theme. But the king made
 answer:
<milestone id="p06970008" /><q direct="unspecified">Ladies, what manner of theme I have prescribed I know
 as well as you,
nor was I to be diverted from prescribing it by that
 which you now think
to declare unto me, for I wot the times are
 such that, so only men and
women have a care to do nought that is
 unseemly, 'tis allowable to them to
discourse of what they please.
 <milestone id="p06970009" />For in sooth, as you must know, so out of
joint are the times that
 the judges have deserted the judgment-seat, the
laws are silent, and
 ample licence to preserve his life as best he may is
accorded to each
 and all. <milestone id="p06970010" />Wherefore, if you are somewhat less strict of
speech than is
 your wont, not that aught unseemly in act may follow, but
that you
 may afford solace to yourselves and others, I see not how you can
be
 open to reasonable censure on the part of any. <milestone id="p06970011" />Furthermore, nought
that has been said from the first day to the present moment has,
 methinks,
in any degree sullied the immaculate honour of your
 company, nor, God
helping us, shall aught ever sully it. <milestone id="p06970012" />Besides,
 who is there that knows
not the quality of your honour? which
 were proof, I make no doubt, against
not only the seductive influence
 of diverting discourse, but even the
terror of death. <milestone id="p06970013" />And,
 to tell you the truth, whoso wist that you refused
to discourse of
 these light matters for a while, would be apt to suspect
that 'twas
 but for that you had yourselves erred in like sort. <milestone id="p06970014" />And truly
a
 goodly honour would you confer upon me, obedient as I have ever
 been to
you, if after making me your king and your lawgiver, you
 were to refuse to
discourse of the theme which I prescribe. <milestone id="p06970015" />Away,
 then, with this scruple
fitter for low minds than yours, and let each
 study how she may give us a
goodly story, and Fortune prosper her
 therein.</q></p><p><milestone id="p06970016" />So spake the
king, and the ladies, hearkening, said that, even as
 he would, so it
should be: whereupon he gave all leave to do as they
 <pb n="108" />might be
severally minded until the supper-hour. <milestone id="p06970017" />The sun was still
 quite high in
the heaven, for they had not enlarged in their discourse:
 wherefore,
Dioneo with the other gallants being set to play
 at dice, Elisa called the
other ladies apart, and said: <milestone id="p06970018" /><q direct="unspecified">There is a
 nook hard by this place, where
I think none of you has ever been:
 'tis called the Ladies' Vale: whither,
ever since we have been here,
 I have desired to take you, but time meet I
have not found until today,
 when the sun is still so high: if, then, you
are minded to visit
 it, I have no manner of doubt that, when you are
there, you will be
 very glad you came.</q> <milestone id="p06970019" />The ladies answered that they
were ready,
 and so, saying nought to the young men, they summoned one of
their maids, and set forth; nor had they gone much more than a
 mile, when
they arrived at the Vale of Ladies. They entered it by
 a very strait
gorge, through which there issued a rivulet, clear as
 crystal, and a
sight, than which nought more fair and pleasant,
 especially at that time
when the heat was great, could be imagined,
 met their eyes. <milestone id="p06970020" />Within the
valley, as one of them afterwards told
 me, was a plain about half-a-mile
in circumference, and so exactly
 circular that it might have been
fashioned according to the compass,
 though it seemed a work of Nature's
art, not man's: 'twas girdled
 about by six hills of no great height, each
crowned with a palace
 that shewed as a goodly little castle. <milestone id="p06970021" />The slopes of
the hills were
 graduated from summit to base after the manner of the
successive
 tiers, ever abridging their circle, that we see in our
theatres; <milestone id="p06970022" />and as
 many as fronted the southern rays were all planted so
close with
 vines, olives, almond-trees, cherry-trees, fig-trees and other
fruit-bearing
 trees not a few, that there was not a hand's-breadth of
vacant space. <milestone id="p06970023" />Those that fronted the north were in like manner
 covered
with copses of oak saplings, ashes and other trees, as green
 and straight
as might be. <milestone id="p06970024" />Besides which, the plain, which was shut
 in on all sides save
that on which the ladies had entered, was full of
 firs, cypresses, and
bay-trees, with here and there a pine, in order
 and symmetry so meet and
excellent as had they been planted by an
 artist, the best that might be
found in that kind; wherethrough,
 even when the sun was in the zenith,
scarce a ray of light might
 reach the ground, which was all one lawn of
the finest turf, pranked
 with the hyacinth and divers other flowers. <milestone id="p06970025" />Add
to which--nor was
 there aught there more delightsome--a rivulet that,
issuing from one
 <pb n="109" />of the gorges between two of the hills,
descended over ledges of
 living rock, making, as it fell, a murmur most
gratifying to the ear,
 and, seen from a distance, shewed as a spray of
finest, powdered
 quick-silver, <milestone id="p06970026" />and no sooner reached the little plain,
than 'twas
 gathered into a tiny channel, by which it sped with great
velocity
 to the middle of the plain, where it formed a diminutive lake,
like
 the fishponds that townsfolk sometimes make in their gardens, when
they have occasion for them. <milestone id="p06970027" />The lake was not so deep but that a
 man might
stand therein with his breast above the water; and so
 clear, so pellucid
was the water that the bottom, which was of
 the finest gravel, shewed so
distinct, that one, had he wished, who
 had nought better to do, might have
counted the stones. Nor was it
 only the bottom that was to be seen, but
such a multitude of fishes,
 glancing to and fro, as was at once a delight
and a marvel to behold.
 <milestone id="p06970028" />Bank it had none, but its margin was the lawn, to
which it imparted
 a goodlier freshness. So much of the water as it might
not contain
 was received by another tiny channel, through which, issuing
from
 the vale, it glided swiftly to the plain below.</p><p><milestone id="p06970029" />To which
pleasaunce the damsels being come surveyed it with
 roving glance, and
finding it commendable, and marking the lake
 in front of them, did, as
'twas very hot, and they deemed themselves
 secure from observation,
resolve to take a bath. <milestone id="p06970030" />So, having bidden
 their maid wait and keep watch
over the access to the vale, and give
 them warning, if haply any should
approach it, they all seven undressed
 and got into the water, which to the
whiteness of their flesh
 was even such a veil as fine glass is to the
vermeil of the rose. <milestone id="p06970031" />They,
 being thus in the water, the clearness of which
was thereby in no
 wise affected, did presently begin to go hither and
thither after the
 fish, which had much ado where to bestow themselves so
as to
 escape out of their hands. <milestone id="p06970032" />In which diversion they spent some time,
and caught a few, and then they hied them out of the water and
 dressed
them again, and bethinking them that 'twas time to return
 to the palace,
they began slowly sauntering thither, dilating much as
 they went upon the
beauty of the place, albeit they could not extol
 it more than they had
already done. <milestone id="p06970033" />'Twas still quite early when
 they reached the palace, so
that they found the gallants yet at play
 where they had left them. To whom
quoth Pampinea with a
 smile: <q direct="unspecified">We have stolen a march upon you
to-day.</q> <milestone id="p06970034" /><q direct="unspecified">So,</q>
 <pb n="110" />replied Dioneo, <q direct="unspecified">'tis with you do
first and say after?</q> <milestone id="p06970035" /><q direct="unspecified">Ay, my
 lord,</q> returned Pampinea, and told
him at large whence they came,
 and what the place was like, and how far
'twas off, and what they
 had done. <milestone id="p06970036" />What she said of the beauty of the spot
begat in the king
 a desire to see it: wherefore he straightway ordered
supper, whereof
 when all had gaily partaken, the three gallants parted
from the ladies
 and hied them with their servants to the vale, where none
of them
 had ever been before, and, having marked all its beauties,
extolled it
 as scarce to be matched in all the world. <milestone id="p06970037" />Then, as the hour
was
 very late, they did but bathe, and as soon as they had resumed their
clothes, returned to the ladies, whom they found dancing a carol to
 an air
that Fiammetta sang, which done, they conversed of the
 Ladies' Vale,
waxing eloquent in praise thereof: <milestone id="p06970038" />insomuch that the
 king called the
seneschal, and bade him have some beds made ready
 and carried thither on
the morrow, that any that were so minded
 might there take their siesta. <milestone id="p06970039" />He
then had lights and wine and
 comfits brought; and when they had taken a
slight refection, he
 bade all address them to the dance. So at his behest
Pamfilo led a
 dance, and then the king, turning with gracious mien to
Elisa:
 <milestone id="p06970040" /><q direct="unspecified">Fair damsel,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">'twas thou to-day didst me this
honour
 of the crown; and 'tis my will that thine to-night be the honour
or
 the song; wherefore sing us whatsoever thou hast most lief.</q>
<milestone id="p06970041" /><q direct="unspecified">That gladly will I,</q> replied Elisa smiling; and thus with dulcet
voice began:</p><div3 who="elissa" type="song"><lg><milestone id="p06970042" /><l>If of thy talons,
Love, be quit I may,</l>
<l>I deem it scarce can be</l>
<l>But other fangs
I may elude for aye.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p06970043" /><l>Service I took with thee, a tender
maid,</l>
<l>In thy war thinking perfect peace to find,</l>
<l>And all my
arms upon the ground I laid,</l>
<l>Yielding myself to thee with trustful
mind:</l>
<l>Thou, harpy-tyrant, whom no faith may bind,</l>
<l>Eftsoons
didst swoop on me,</l>
<l>And with thy cruel claws mad'st me thy
prey.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p06970044" /><l>Then thy poor captive, bound with many a
chain,</l>
<l>Thou tookst, and gav'st to him, whom fate did
call</l>
<l>Hither my death to be; for that in pain</l>
<pb n="111" />
<l>And
bitter tears I waste away, his thrall:</l>
<l>Nor heave I e'er a sigh, or
tear let fall,</l>
<l>So harsh a lord is he,</l>
<l>That him inclines a jot
my grief to allay.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p06970045" /><l>My prayers upon the idle air are
spent:</l>
<l>He hears not, will not hear; wherefore in vain</l>
<l>The
more each hour my soul doth her torment;</l>
<l>Nor may I die, albeit to
die were gain.</l>
<l>Ah! Lord, have pity of my bitter pain!</l>
<l>Help
have I none but thee;</l>
<l>Then take and bind and at my feet him
lay.</l></lg><lg><milestone id="p06970046" /><l>But if thou wilt not, do my soul but loose</l>
<l>From
hope, that her still binds with triple chain.</l>
<l>Sure, O my Lord, this
prayer thou'lt not refuse:</l>
<l>The which so thou to grant me do but
deign,</l>
<l>I look my wonted beauty to regain,</l>
<l>And banish
misery</l>
<l>With roses white and red bedecked and
gay.</l></lg></div3><p><milestone id="p06970047" />So with a most piteous sigh ended Elisa her song,
whereat all
 wondered exceedingly, nor might any conjecture wherefore she
so
 sang. <milestone id="p06970048" />But the king, who was in a jolly humour, sent for Tindaro,
 and
bade him out with his cornemuse, and caused them tread many a
 measure
thereto, until, no small part of the night being thus spent,
 he gave leave
to all to betake them to rest.</p></div2>