<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0506"><head>Novel VI</head><argument><p><milestone id="p05060001" /> Gianni di Procida, being found with a damsel that he
 loves, and who had been given to King Frederic, is
 bound with her to a stake, so to be burned. He is
 recognized by Ruggieri dell' Oria, is delivered, and
 marries her.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p05060002" /> Neifile's story, with which the ladies were greatly delighted,
 being ended, the queen called for one from Pampinea; who forthwith
 raised her noble countenance, and thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p> <milestone id="p05060003" />Mighty
 indeed, gracious ladies, are the forces of Love, and great are the
 labours and excessive and unthought-of the perils which they induce
 lovers to brave; as is manifest enough by what we have heard
 to-day and on other occasions: howbeit I mean to shew you the
 same once more by a story of an enamoured youth.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p05060004" />Hard by Naples is the island of Ischia, in which there dwelt
 aforetime with other young damsels one, Restituta by name, daughter
 of one Marin Bolgaro, a gentleman of the island. Very fair was
 she, and blithe of heart, and by a young gallant, Gianni by name,
 of the neighbouring islet of Procida, was beloved more dearly than
 life, and in like measure returned his love.  <milestone id="p05060005" />Now, not to mention his
 daily resort to Ischia to see her, there were times not a few when
 Gianni, not being able to come by a boat, would swim across from
 Procida by night, that he might have sight, if of nought else, at
 least of the walls of her house.  <milestone id="p05060006" />And while their love burned thus
 fervently, it so befell that one summer's day, as the damsel was all
 alone on the seashore, picking her way from rock to rock, detaching,
 as she went, shells from their beds with a knife, she came to a recess
 among the rocks, where for the sake, as well of the shade as of the
 comfort afforded by a spring of most cool water that was there,
 <pb n="37" />some Sicilian gallants, that were come from Naples, had put in with
 their felucca.  <milestone id="p05060007" />Who, having taken note of the damsel, that she was
 very fair, and that she was not yet ware of them, and was alone,
 resolved to capture her, and carry her away; nor did they fail to
 give effect to their resolve;  <milestone id="p05060008" />but, albeit she shrieked amain, they laid
 hands on her, and set her aboard their boat, and put to sea. Arrived
 at Calabria, they fell a wrangling as to whose the damsel should be,
 and in brief each claimed her for his own: wherefore, finding no
 means of coming to an agreement, and fearing that worse might
 befall them, and she bring misfortune upon them, they resolved with
 one accord to give her to Frederic, King of Sicily, who was then a
 young man, and took no small delight in commodities of that
 quality; and so, being come to Palermo, they did.</p><p><milestone id="p05060009" />Marking her beauty, the King set great store by her; but as she
 was somewhat indisposed, he commanded that, till she was stronger,
 she should be lodged and tended in a very pretty villa that was in
 one of his gardens, which he called Cuba; and so 'twas done.  <milestone id="p05060010" />The
 purloining of the damsel caused no small stir in Ischia, more especially
 because 'twas impossible to discover by whom she had been
 carried off.  <milestone id="p05060011" />But Gianni, more concerned than any other, despairing
 of finding her in Ischia, and being apprised of the course the felucca
 had taken, equipped one himself, and put to sea, and in hot haste
 scoured the whole coast from Minerva to Scalea in Calabria, making
 everywhere diligent search for the damsel, and in Scalea learned
 that she had been taken by Sicilian mariners to Palermo.  <milestone id="p05060012" />Whither,
 accordingly, he hied him with all speed; and there after long search
 discovering that she had been given to the King, who kept her at
 Cuba, he was sore troubled, insomuch that he now scarce ventured
 to hope that he should ever set eyes on her, not to speak of having
 her for his own, again.  <milestone id="p05060013" />But still, holden by Love, and seeing that
 none there knew him, he sent the felucca away, and tarried there,
 and frequently passing by Cuba, he chanced one day to catch sight
 of her at a window, and was seen of her, to their great mutual
 satisfaction.  <milestone id="p05060014" />And Gianni, taking note that the place was lonely,
 made up to her, and had such speech of her as he might, and being
 taught by her after what fashion he must proceed, if he would have
 further speech of her, he departed, but not till he had made himself
 thoroughly acquainted with the configuration of the place;  <milestone id="p05060015" />and
 <pb n="38" />having waited until night was come and indeed far spent, he returned
 thither, and though the ascent was such that 'twould scarce have
 afforded lodgment to a woodpecker, won his way up and entered the
 garden, where, finding a pole, he set it against the window which
 the damsel had pointed out as hers, and thereby swarmed up easily
 enough.</p><p><milestone id="p05060016" />The damsel had aforetime shewn herself somewhat distant
 towards him, being careful of her honour, but now deeming it
 already lost, she had bethought her that there was none to whom
 she might more worthily give herself than to him; and reckoning
 upon inducing him to carry her off, she had made up her mind to
 gratify his every desire; and to that end had left the window open
 that his ingress might be unimpeded.  <milestone id="p05060017" />So, finding it open, Gianni
 softly entered, lay down beside the damsel, who was awake,  <milestone id="p05060018" />and
 before they went further, opened to him all her mind, beseeching
 him most earnestly to take her thence, and carry her off. Gianni
 replied that there was nought that would give him so much pleasure,
 and that without fail, upon leaving her, he would make all needful
 arrangements for bringing her away when he next came.  <milestone id="p05060019" />Whereupon
 with exceeding great delight they embraced one another, and
 plucked that boon than which Love has no greater to bestow; and
 having so done divers times, they unwittingly fell asleep in one
 another's arms.</p><p><milestone id="p05060020" />Now towards daybreak the King, who had been greatly charmed
 with the damsel at first sight, happened to call her to mind, and
 feeling himself fit, resolved, notwithstanding the hour, to go lie with
 her a while;  <milestone id="p05060021" />and so, attended by a few of his servants, he hied him
 privily to Cuba. Having entered the house, he passed (the door
 being softly opened) into the room in which he knew the damsel
 slept. A great blazing torch was borne before him, and so, as he
 bent his glance on the bed, he espied the damsel and Gianni lying
 asleep, naked and in one another's arms.  <milestone id="p05060022" />Whereat he was seized
 with a sudden and vehement passion of wrath, insomuch that, albeit
 he said never a word, he could scarce refrain from slaying both of
 them there and then with a dagger that he had with him.  <milestone id="p05060023" />Then,
 bethinking him that 'twere the depth of baseness in any man--not
 to say a king--to slay two naked sleepers, he mastered himself, and
 determined to do them to death in public and by fire. Wherefore,
 <pb n="39" />turning to a single companion that he had with him, he said:
 <q direct="unspecified">What thinkest thou of this base woman, in whom I had placed
 my hope?</q> And then he asked whether he knew the gallant, that
 had presumed to enter his house to do him such outrage and despite.
  <milestone id="p05060024" />Whereto the other replied that he minded not ever to have seen
 him.  <milestone id="p05060025" />Thereupon the King hied him out of the room in a rage,
 and bade take the two lovers, naked as they were, and bind them,
 and, as soon as 'twas broad day, bring them to Palermo, and bind
 them back to back to a stake in the piazza, there to remain until
 tierce, that all might see them, after which they were to be burned,
 as they had deserved. And having so ordered, he went back to
 Palermo, and shut himself up in his room, very wroth.</p><p><milestone id="p05060026" />No sooner was he gone than there came unto the two lovers folk
 not a few, who, having awakened them, did forthwith ruthlessly take
 and bind them: whereat, how they did grieve and tremble for
 their lives, and weep and bitterly bewail their fate, may readily be
 understood.</p><p><milestone id="p05060027" />Pursuant to the King's commandment they were brought to
 Palermo, and bound to a stake in the piazza; and before their eyes
 faggots and fire were made ready to burn them at the hour appointed
 by the King.  <milestone id="p05060028" />Great was the concourse of the folk of Palermo, both
 men and women, that came to see the two lovers, the men all agog
 to feast their eyes on the damsel, whom they lauded for shapeliness
 and loveliness, and no less did the women commend the gallant,
 whom in like manner they crowded to see, for the same qualities.
  <milestone id="p05060029" />Meanwhile the two hapless lovers, both exceeding shamefast, stood
 with bent heads bitterly bewailing their evil fortune, and momently
 expecting their death by the cruel fire.  <milestone id="p05060030" />So they awaited the time
 appointed by the King; but their offence being bruited abroad, the
 tidings reached the ears of Ruggieri dell' Oria, a man of peerless
 worth, and at that time the King's admiral, who, being likewise
 minded to see them, came to the place where they were bound, and
 after gazing on the damsel and finding her very fair, turned to look
 at the gallant, whom with little trouble he recognized, and drawing
 nearer to him, he asked him if he were Gianni di Procida.  <milestone id="p05060031" />Gianni
 raised his head, and recognizing the admiral, made answer: <q direct="unspecified">My
 lord, he, of whom you speak, I was; but I am now as good as no
 more.</q>  <milestone id="p05060032" />The admiral then asked him what it was that had brought
 <pb n="40" />him to such a pass. Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Love and the King's wrath,</q>
 quoth Gianni.  <milestone id="p05060033" />The admiral induced him to be more explicit, and
 having learned from him exactly how it had come about, was turning
 away, when Gianni called him back, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Oh! my lord, if so
 it may be, procure me one favour of him by whose behest I thus
 stand here.</q> <milestone id="p05060034" /><q direct="unspecified">What favour?</q> demanded Ruggieri. <q direct="unspecified">I see,</q>
 returned Gianni, <q direct="unspecified">that die I must, and that right soon. I crave,
 then, as a favour, that, whereas this damsel and I, that have loved one
 another more dearly than life, are here set back to back, we may be
 set face to face, that I may have the consolation of gazing on her
 face as I depart.</q>  <milestone id="p05060035" />Ruggieri laughed as he replied: <q direct="unspecified">With all my
 heart. I will so order it that thou shalt see enough of her to tire or
 her.</q>  <milestone id="p05060036" />He then left him and charged the executioners to do nothing
 more without further order of the King; and being assured of their
 obedience, he hied him forthwith to the King, to whom, albeit he
 found him in a wrathful mood, he spared not to speak his mind,
 saying: <q direct="unspecified">Sire, wherein have they wronged thee, those two young
 folk, whom thou hast ordered to be burned down there in the
 piazza?</q>  <milestone id="p05060037" />The King told him. Whereupon Ruggieri continued:
 <q direct="unspecified">Their offence does indeed merit such punishment, but not at thy
 hands, and if misdeeds should not go unpunished, services should not
 go unrewarded; nay, may warrant indulgence and mercy. Knowest
 thou who they are whom thou wouldst have burned?</q>  <milestone id="p05060038" />The King
 signified that he did not. Whereupon Ruggieri: <q direct="unspecified">But I,</q> quoth
 he, <q direct="unspecified">am minded that thou shouldst know them, to the end that thou
 mayst know with what discretion thou surrenderest thyself to a
 transport of rage.  <milestone id="p05060039" />The young man is the son of Landolfo di
 Procida, brother of Messer Gianni di Procida, to whom thou owest
 it that thou art lord and king of this island. The damsel is a
 daughter of Marin Bolgaro, whose might alone to-day prevents
 Ischia from throwing off thy yoke.  <milestone id="p05060040" />Moreover, these young folk
 have long been lovers, and 'tis for that the might of Love constrained
 them, and not that they would do despite to thy lordship, that they
 have committed this offence, if indeed 'tis meet to call that an
 offence which young folk do for Love's sake. Wherefore, then,
 wouldst thou do them to death, when thou shouldst rather do them
 all cheer, and honour them with lordly gifts?</q>  <milestone id="p05060041" />The King gave ear
 to Ruggieri's words, and being satisfied that he spoke sooth, repented
 <pb n="41" />him, not only of his evil purpose, but of what he had already done,
 and forthwith gave order to loose the two young folk from the
 stake, and bring them before him; and so 'twas done.  <milestone id="p05060042" />And having
 fully apprised himself of their case, he saw fit to make them amends
 of the wrong he had done them with honours and largess. Wherefore
 he caused them to be splendidly arrayed, and being assured that
 they were both minded to wed, he himself gave Gianni his bride,
 and loading them with rich presents, sent them well content back to
 Ischia, where they were welcomed with all festal cheer, and lived
 long time thereafter to their mutual solace and delight.</p></div2>