<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0602"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p06020001" />Cisti, a baker, by an apt speech gives Messer Geri
Spina to know that he has by inadvertence asked that of him which he should
not.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06020002" />All the ladies and the men alike having greatly
	commended Madonna Oretta's apt saying, the queen bade Pampinea follow suit, and thus she
	began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p06020003" />Fair ladies, I cannot myself determine whether Nature or Fortune be the
	more at fault, the one in furnishing a noble soul with a vile body, or the other in
	allotting a base occupation to a body endowed with a noble soul, whereof we may have seen
	an example, among others, in our fellow-citizen, Cisti; whom, furnished though he was with
	a most lofty soul, Fortune made a baker. <milestone id="p06020004" />And verily I should
	curse Nature and Fortune alike, did I not know that Nature is most discreet, and that
	Fortune, albeit the foolish imagine her blind, has a thousand eyes. 
	<milestone id="p06020005" />For 'tis, I suppose, that, being wise above a little, they do as mortals
	ofttimes do, who, being uncertain as to their future, provide against contingencies by
	burying their most precious treasures in the basest places in their houses, as being the
	least likely to be suspected; whence, in the hour of their greatest need, they bring them
	forth, the base place having kept them more safe than the dainty chamber would have
	done. <milestone id="p06020006" />And so these two arbitresses of the world not seldom hide
	their most precious commodities in the obscurity of the crafts that are reputed most base,
	that thence being brought to light they may shine with a brighter splendour. 
	<milestone id="p06020007" />Whereof how in a trifling matter Cisti, the baker, gave proof, restoring
	the eyes of the mind to Messer Geri Spina, whom the story of his wife, Madonna Oretta, has
	brought to my recollection, I am minded to shew you in a narrative which shall be of the
	briefest.</p></div3><pb n="77" /><p><milestone id="p06020008" />I say then that Pope Boniface, with whom
Messer Geri Spina
 stood very high in favour and honour, having sent divers
of his
 courtiers to Florence as ambassadors to treat of certain matters of
great
 moment, and they being lodged in Messer Geri's house, where he

treated with them of the said affairs of the Pope, 'twas, for some
 reason
or another, the wont of Messer Geri and the ambassadors of
 the Pope to
pass almost every morning by Santa Maria Ughi, where
 Cisti, the baker, had
his bakehouse, and plied his craft in person.
 <milestone id="p06020009" />Now, albeit Fortune had
allotted him a very humble occupation, she
 had nevertheless prospered him
therein to such a degree that he was
 grown most wealthy, and without ever
aspiring to change it for
 another, lived in most magnificent style, having
among his other good
 things a cellar of the best wines, white and red,
that were to be found
 in Florence, or the country parts; <milestone id="p06020010" />and marking
Messer Geri and the
 ambassadors of the Pope pass every morning by his
door, he bethought
 him that, as 'twas very hot, 'twould be a very
courteous thing to give
 them to drink of his good wine; but comparing his
rank with that
 of Messer Geri, he deemed it unseemly to presume to invite
him,
 and cast about how he might lead Messer Geri to invite himself.
 <milestone id="p06020011" />So,
wearing always the whitest of doublets and a spotless apron, that
 denoted
rather the miller than the baker, he let bring, every morning
 about the
hour that he expected Messer Geri and the ambassadors to
 pass by his door,
a spick-and-span bucket of fresh and cool spring
 water, and a small
Bolognese flagon of his good white wine, and two
 beakers that shone like
silver, so bright were they: <milestone id="p06020012" />and there down
 he sat him, as they came by,
and after hawking once or twice, fell a
 drinking his wine with such gusto
that 'twould have raised a thirst
 in a corpse. <milestone id="p06020013" />Which Messer Geri having
observed on two successive
 mornings, said on the third: <q direct="unspecified">What is't,
Cisti? Is't good?</q>
 <milestone id="p06020014" />Whereupon Cisti jumped up, and answered: <q direct="unspecified">Ay, Sir,
good it is;
 but in what degree I might by no means make you understand,
unless
 you tasted it.</q> <milestone id="p06020015" />Messer Geri, in whom either the heat of the
weather,
 or unwonted fatigue, or, perchance, the gusto with which he had

seen Cisti drink, had bred a thirst, turned to the ambassadors and
 said
with a smile: <q direct="unspecified">Gentlemen, 'twere well to test the quality of
 this worthy
man's wine: it may be such that we shall not repent
 us.</q> And so in a
body they came up to where Cisti stood; <milestone id="p06020016" />who,
 having caused a goodly bench
to be brought out of the bakehouse,
 <pb n="78" />bade them be seated, and to
their servants, who were now coming
 forward to wash the beakers, said:
<q direct="unspecified">Stand back, comrades, and
 leave this office to me, for I know as well
how to serve wine as to
 bake bread; and expect not to taste a drop
yourselves.</q> <milestone id="p06020017" />Which said,
 he washed four fine new beakers with his own
hands, and having
 sent for a small flagon of his good wine, he heedfully
filled the
 beakers, and presented them to Messer Geri and his companions;

who deemed the wine the best that they had drunk for a great while.
 So
Messer Geri, having praised the wine not a little, came there to
 drink
every morning with the ambassadors as long as they tarried
 with
him.</p><p><milestone id="p06020018" />Now when the ambassadors had received their
cong&#232;, and were
 about to depart, Messer Geri
gave a grand banquet, to which he bade
 some of the most honourable of the
citizens, and also Cisti, who could
 by no means be induced to come.
<milestone id="p06020019" />However, Messer Geri bade one
 of his servants go fetch a flask of Cisti's
wine, and serve half a beaker
 thereof to each guest at the first course.
The servant, somewhat
 offended, perhaps, that he had not been suffered to
taste any of the
 wine, took with him a large flask, <milestone id="p06020020" />which Cisti no sooner
saw, than:
 <q direct="unspecified">Son,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">Messer Geri does not send thee to
me</q>: <milestone id="p06020021" />and
 often as the servant affirmed that he did, he could get no
other answer:
 wherewith he was fain at last to return to Messer Geri.
<q direct="unspecified">Go, get
 thee back,</q> said Messer Geri, <q direct="unspecified">and tell him that I do send
thee
 to him, and if he answers thee so again, ask him, to whom then
 I
send thee.</q> <milestone id="p06020022" />So the servant came back, and said: <q direct="unspecified">Cisti, Messer
 Geri
does, for sure, send me to thee.</q> <milestone id="p06020023" /><q direct="unspecified">Son,</q> answered Cisti,

<q direct="unspecified">Messer
 Geri does, for sure, not send thee to me.</q> <milestone id="p06020024" /><q direct="unspecified">To whom
then,</q> said
 the servant, <q direct="unspecified">does he send me?</q> <milestone id="p06020025" /><q direct="unspecified">To Arno,</q>
returned Cisti.
 <milestone id="p06020026" />Which being reported by the servant to Messer Geri, the
eyes of
 his mind were straightway opened, and: <q direct="unspecified">Let me see,</q> quoth
he
 to the servant, <q direct="unspecified">what flask it is thou takest there.</q> And when he

had seen it: <q direct="unspecified">Cisti says sooth,</q> he added; and having sharply
 chidden
him, he caused him take with him a suitable flask, <milestone id="p06020027" />which
 when Cisti saw:
<q direct="unspecified">Now know I,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">that 'tis indeed Messer
 Geri that sends
thee to me,</q> and blithely filled it. <milestone id="p06020028" />And having
 replenished the rundlet
that same day with wine of the same quality,
 he had it carried with due
care to Messer Geri's house, and followed
 after himself; where finding
Messer Geri he said: <q direct="unspecified">I would not
 <pb n="79" />have you think, Sir, that I
was appalled by the great flask your servant
 brought me this morning;
'twas but that I thought you had forgotten
 that which by my little beakers
I gave you to understand, when you
 were with me of late; to wit, that this
is no table wine; and so
 wished this morning to refresh your memory. <milestone id="p06020029" />Now,
however, being
 minded to keep the wine no longer, I have sent you all I
have of it,
 to be henceforth entirely at your disposal.</q> <milestone id="p06020030" />Messer Geri
set great
 store by Cisti's gift, and thanked him accordingly, and ever
made
 much of him and entreated him as his friend.</p></div2>