<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="pampinea" id="nov0302"><head>Novel II</head><argument><p><milestone id="p03020001" />A groom lies with the wife of King Agilulf, who learns
 the fact, keeps his own counsel, finds out the groom
 and shears him. The shorn shears all his fellows,
 and so comes safe out of the scrape.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03020002" />Filostrato's story, which the ladies had received now with
	blushes now with laughter, being ended, the queen bade Pampinea
	follow suit. Which behest Pampinea smilingly obeyed, and thus
	began:</p></div3><div3 who="pampinea" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p03020003" />Some there are whose indiscretion is such that they must needs
	evince that they are fully cognizant of that which it were best
	they should not know, and censuring the covert misdeeds of others,
	augment beyond measure the disgrace which they would fain diminish.
	The truth whereof, fair ladies, I mean to shew you in the contrary
	case, wherein appears the astuteness of one that held, perhaps, an even
	lower place than would have been Masetto's in the esteem of a
	doughty king.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p03020004" />Agilulf, King of the Lombards, who like his predecessors made
 the city of Pavia in Lombardy the seat of his government, took
 to wife Theodelinde, the widow of Authari, likewise King of the
 Lombards, a lady very fair, wise and virtuous, but who was
      unfortunate in her lover. <milestone id="p03020005" />For while the Lombards prospered in
 peace under the wise and firm rule of King Agilulf, it so befell
 that one of the Queen's grooms, a man born to very low estate,
 but in native worth far above his mean office, and moreover not
 a whit less tall and goodly of person than the King, became
 inordinately enamoured of her. <milestone id="p03020006" />And as, for all his base condition,
 he had sense enough to recognize that his love was in the last
 <pb n="185" />degree presumptuous, he disclosed it to none, nay, he did not even
 venture to tell her the tale by the mute eloquence of his eyes.
 <milestone id="p03020007" />And albeit he lived without hope that he should ever be able to
 win her favour, yet he inwardly gloried that he had fixed his
 affections in so high a place; and being all aflame with passion,
 he shewed himself zealous beyond any of his comrades to do whatever
 he thought was likely to please the Queen. <milestone id="p03020008" />Whereby it came
 about, that, when the Queen had to take horse, she would mount
 the palfrey that he groomed rather than any other; and when she
 did so, he deemed himself most highly favoured, and never quitted
 her stirrup, esteeming himself happy if he might but touch her
 clothes. <milestone id="p03020009" />But as 'tis frequently observed that love waxes as hope
 wanes, so was it with this poor groom, insomuch that the burden
 of this great hidden passion, alleviated by no hope, was most grievous
 to bear, and from time to time, not being able to shake it off, he
 purposed to die. <milestone id="p03020010" />And meditating on the mode, he was minded
 that it should be of a kind to make it manifest that he died for the
 love which he had borne and bore to the Queen, and also to afford
 him an opportunity of trying his fortune whether his desire might
 in whole or in part be gratified. <milestone id="p03020011" />He had no thought of speaking
 to the Queen, nor yet of declaring his love to her by letter, for he
 knew that 'twould be vain either to speak or to write; but he
 resolved to try to devise some means whereby he might lie with
 the Queen; which end might in no other way be compassed than
 by contriving to get access to her in her bedroom; which could
 only be by passing himself off as the King, who, as he knew, did
 not always lie with her. <milestone id="p03020012" />Wherefore, that he might observe the
 carriage and dress of the King as he passed to her room, he contrived
 to conceal himself for several nights in a great hall of the
 King's palace which separated the King's room from that of the
 Queen: and on one of these nights he saw the King issue from
 his room, wrapped in a great mantle, with a lighted torch in one
 hand and a wand in the other, and cross the hall, and, saying
 nothing, tap the door of the Queen's room with the wand once
 or twice; whereupon the door was at once opened and the torch
 taken from his hand. <milestone id="p03020013" />Having observed the King thus go and
 return, and being bent on doing likewise, he found means to come
 by a mantle like that which he had seen the King wear, and also
 <pb n="186" />a torch and a wand: he then took a warm bath, and having
 thoroughly cleansed himself, that the smell of the foul straw might
 not offend the lady, or discover to her the deceit, he in this guise
 concealed himself as he was wont in the great hall. <milestone id="p03020014" />He waited
 only until all were asleep, and then, deeming the time come to
 accomplish his purpose, or by his presumption clear a way to the death
 which he coveted, he struck a light with the flint and steel which he
 had brought with him; and having kindled his torch and wrapped
 himself close in his mantle, he went to the door of the Queen's
 room, and tapped on it twice with his wand. <milestone id="p03020015" />The door was opened
 by a very drowsy chambermaid, who took the torch and put it out
 of sight; whereupon without a word he passed within the curtain,
 laid aside the mantle, and got into the bed where the Queen lay
 asleep. <milestone id="p03020016" />Then, taking her in his arms and straining her to him
 with ardour, making as if he were moody, because he knew that,
 when the King was in such a frame, he would never hear aught,
 in such wise, without word said either on his part or on hers,
 he had more than once carnal cognizance of the Queen. Loath
 indeed was he to leave her, but, fearing lest by too long tarrying
 his achieved delight might be converted into woe, he rose, resumed
 the mantle and the light, and leaving the room without a word,
 returned with all speed to his bed. <milestone id="p03020017" />He was hardly there when the
 King got up and entered the Queen's room; whereat she wondered
 not a little; but, reassured by the gladsome greeting which he gave
 her as he got into bed, she said: <q direct="unspecified">My lord, what a surprise is this
 to-night! 'Twas but now you left me after an unwonted measure
 of enjoyment, and do you now return so soon? consider what you
 do.</q> 
<milestone id="p03020018" />From these words the King at once inferred that the Queen
 had been deceived by some one that had counterfeited his person
 and carriage; but, at the same time, bethinking himself that, as
 neither the Queen nor any other had detected the cheat, 'twas
 best to leave her in ignorance, he wisely kept silence. Which
 many a fool would not have done, but would have said: <q direct="unspecified">Nay,
 'twas not I that was here. Who was it that was here? How
 came it to pass? Who came hither?</q> 
<milestone id="p03020019" />Whereby in the sequel
 he might have caused the lady needless chagrin, and given her
 occasion to desire another such experience as she had had; and
 so have brought disgrace upon himself by uttering that, from which,
 <pb n="187" />unuttered, no shame could have resulted. 
<milestone id="p03020020" />Wherefore, betraying
 little, either by his mien or by his words, of the disquietude which
 he felt, the King replied: <q direct="unspecified">Madam, seem I such to you that you
 cannot suppose that I should have been with you once, and returned
 to you immediately afterwards?</q> 
<milestone id="p03020021" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, not so, my lord,</q> returned
 the lady, <q direct="unspecified">but none the less I pray you to look to your health.</q>
 <milestone id="p03020022" />Then said the King: <q direct="unspecified">And I am minded to take your advice;
 wherefore, without giving you further trouble I will leave you.</q>
 <milestone id="p03020023" />So, angered and incensed beyond measure by the trick which, he
 saw, had been played upon him, he resumed his mantle and quitted
 the room with the intention of privily detecting the offender,
 deeming that he must belong to the palace, and that, whoever he
 might be, he could not have quitted it. <milestone id="p03020024" />So, taking with him a
 small lantern which shewed only a glimmer of light, he went into
 the dormitory which was over the palace-stables and was of great
 length, insomuch that well-nigh all the men-servants slept there
 in divers beds, and arguing that, by whomsoever that of which the
 Queen spoke was done, his heart and pulse could not after such
 a strain as yet have ceased to throb, he began cautiously with one
 of the head-grooms, and so went from bed to bed feeling at the
 heart of each man to see if it was thumping. <milestone id="p03020025" />All were asleep,
 save only he that had been with the Queen, who, seeing the King
 come, and guessing what he sought to discover, began to be mightily
 afraid, insomuch that to the agitation which his late exertion had
 communicated to his heart, terror now added one yet more violent;
 nor did he doubt that, should the King perceive it, he would kill
 him. <milestone id="p03020026" />Divers alternatives of action thronged his mind; but at last,
 observing that the King was unarmed, he resolved to make as if
 he were asleep, and wait to see what the King would do. So,
 having tried many and found none that he deemed the culprit, the
 King came at last to the culprit himself, and marking the thumping
 of his heart, said to himself: This is he. <milestone id="p03020027" />But being minded to afford
 no clue to his ulterior purpose, he did no more than with a pair of
 scissors which he had brought with him shear away on one side
 of the man's head a portion of his locks, which, as was then the
 fashion, he wore very long, that by this token he might recognize
 him on the morrow; and having so done, he departed and returned
 to his room. <milestone id="p03020028" />The groom, who was fully sensible of what the King
 <pb n="188" />had done, and being a shrewd fellow understood very well to what
 end he was so marked, got up without a moment's delay; and,
 having found a pair of scissors--for, as it chanced, there were several
 pairs there belonging to the stables for use in grooming the horses--he
 went quietly through the dormitory and in like manner sheared
 the locks of each of the sleepers just above the ear; which done
 without disturbing any, he went back to bed.</p><p><milestone id="p03020029" />On the morrow, as soon as the King was risen, and before the
 gates of the palace were opened, he summoned all his men-servants to
 his presence, and, as they stood bareheaded before him, scanned them
 closely to see whether the one whom he had sheared was there; and
 observing with surprise that the more part of them were all sheared
 in the same manner, said to himself: Of a surety this fellow, whom
 I go about to detect, evinces, for all his base condition, a high degree
 of sense. <milestone id="p03020030" />Then, recognising that he could not compass his end
 without causing a bruit, and not being minded to brave so great a
 dishonour in order to be avenged upon so petty an offender, he was
 content by a single word of admonition to shew him that his offence
 had not escaped notice. Wherefore turning to them all, he said:
 <q direct="unspecified">He that did it, let him do it no more, and get you hence in God's
 peace.</q> 
<milestone id="p03020031" />Another would have put them to the strappado, the question,
 the torture, and thereby have brought to light that which one should
 rather be sedulous to cloak; and having so brought it to light, would,
 however complete the retribution which he exacted, have not
 lessened but vastly augmented his disgrace, and sullied the fair fame
 of his lady. Those who heard the King's parting admonition
 wondered, and made much question with one another, what the
 King might have meant to convey by it; but 'twas understood by
 none but him to whom it referred: who was discreet enough never to
 reveal the secret as long as the King lived, or again to stake his life
 on such a venture.</p></div2>