<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="filostrato" id="nov0903"><head>Novel III</head><argument><p><milestone id="p09030001" />Master Simone, at the instance of Bruno and Buffalmacco
 and Nello, makes Calandrino believe that he is with
 child. Calandrino, accordingly, gives them capons and
 money for medicines, and is cured without being
 delivered.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09030002" />When Elisa had ended her story, and all had given thanks to
 God that He had vouchsafed the young nun a happy escape from
 the fangs of her envious companions, the queen bade Filostrato follow
 suit; and without expecting a second command, thus Filostrato
 began:</p></div3><div3 who="filostrato" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p09030003" />Fairest my ladies, the uncouth judge from the Marches, or
 whom I told you yesterday, took from the tip of my tongue a story
 of Calandrino, which I was on the point of narrating: and as nought
 can be said of him without mightily enhancing our jollity, albeit not
 a little has already been said touching him and his comrades, I will
 now give you the story which I had meant yesterday to give you.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p09030004" />Who they were, this Calandrino and the others that I am to tell of
 in this story, has already been sufficiently explained; wherefore,
 without more ado, I say that one of Calandrino's aunts having died,
 leaving him two hundred pounds in petty cash, Calandrino gave out
 that he was minded to purchase an estate, and, as if he had had ten
 thousand florins of gold to invest, engaged every broker in Florence
 to treat for him, the negotiation always falling through, as soon as
 the price was named.  <milestone id="p09030005" />Bruno and Buffalmacco, knowing what was
 afoot, told him again and again that he had better give himself a
 jolly time with them than go about buying earth as if he must needs
 make pellets;<note>I.e. bolts of clay for the cross-bow.</note> but
 so far were they from effecting their purpose,
 <pb n="275" />that they could not even prevail upon him to give them a single
 meal.  <milestone id="p09030006" />Whereat as one day they grumbled, being joined by a comrade
 of theirs, one Nello, also a painter, they all three took counsel how
 they might wet their whistle at Calandrino's expense; and, their
 plan being soon concerted, the next morning Calandrino was scarce
 gone out, when Nello met him, saying: <q direct="unspecified">Good day, Calandrino:</q>
  <milestone id="p09030007" />whereto Calandrino replied: <q direct="unspecified">God give thee a good day and a
 good year.</q> Nello then drew back a little, and looked him steadily
 in the face, until: <q direct="unspecified">What seest thou to stare at?</q> quoth Calandrino.
  <milestone id="p09030008" /><q direct="unspecified">Hadst thou no pain in the night?</q> returned Nello; <q direct="unspecified">thou
 seemest not thyself to me.</q> Which Calandrino no sooner heard,
 than he began to be disquieted, and:  <milestone id="p09030009" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas! How sayst thou?</q>
 quoth he. <q direct="unspecified">What tak'st thou to be the matter with me?</q>  <milestone id="p09030010" /><q direct="unspecified">Why,
 as to that I have nothing to say,</q> returned Nello; <q direct="unspecified">but thou
 seemest to be quite changed: perchance 'tis not what I suppose;</q>
 and with that he left him.</p><p><milestone id="p09030011" />Calandrino, anxious, though he could not in the least have said
 why, went on; and soon Buffalmacco, who was not far off, and had
 observed him part from Nello, made up to him, and greeted him,
 asking him if he was not in pain. <q direct="unspecified">I cannot say,</q> replied Calandrino;
 <q direct="unspecified">'twas but now that Nello told me that I looked quite changed:
 can it be that there is aught the matter with me?</q> <q direct="unspecified">Aught?</q>
  <milestone id="p09030012" />quoth Buffalmacco, <q direct="unspecified">ay, indeed, there might be a trifle the matter
 with thee. Thou look'st to be half dead, man.</q>  <milestone id="p09030013" />Calandrino now
 began to think he must have a fever. And then up came Bruno;
 and the first thing he said was: <q direct="unspecified">Why, Calandrino, how ill thou
 look'st! thy appearance is that of a corpse. How dost thou feel?</q>
  <milestone id="p09030014" />To be thus accosted by all three left no doubt in Calandrino's mind
 that he was ill, and so: <q direct="unspecified">What shall I do?</q> quoth he, in a great
 fright.  <milestone id="p09030015" /><q direct="unspecified">My advice,</q> replied Bruno, <q direct="unspecified">is that thou go home and
 get thee to bed and cover thee well up, and send thy water to
 Master Simone, who, as thou knowest, is such a friend of ours. He
 will tell thee at once what thou must do; and we will come to see
 thee, and will do aught that may be needful.</q>  <milestone id="p09030016" />And Nello then
 joining them, they all three went home with Calandrino, who, now
 quite spent, went straight to his room, and said to his wife: <q direct="unspecified">Come
 now, wrap me well up; I feel very ill.</q>  <milestone id="p09030017" />And so he laid himself on
 the bed, and sent a maid with his water to Master Simone, who had
 then his shop in the Mercato Vecchio, at the sign of the pumpkin.
 <pb n="276" />Whereupon quoth Bruno to his comrades: <q direct="unspecified">You will stay here
 with him, and I will go hear what the doctor has to say, and if need
 be, will bring him hither.</q>  <milestone id="p09030018" /><q direct="unspecified">Prithee, do so, my friend,</q> quoth
 Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">and bring me word how it is with me, for I feel as
 how I cannot say in my inside.</q>  <milestone id="p09030019" />So Bruno hied him to Master
 Simone, and before the maid arrived with the water, told him what
 was afoot. The Master, thus primed, inspected the water, and then
 said to the maid: <q direct="unspecified">Go tell Calandrino to keep himself very warm,
 and I will come at once, and let him know what is the matter with
 him, and what he must do.</q>  <milestone id="p09030020" />With which message the maid was
 scarce returned, when the Master and Bruno arrived, and the Master,
 having seated himself beside Calandrino, felt his pulse, and by and by,
 in the presence of his wife, said: <q direct="unspecified">Harkye, Calandrino, I speak to
 thee as a friend, and I tell thee that what is amiss with thee is just
 that thou art with child.</q>  <milestone id="p09030021" />Whereupon Calandrino cried out querulously:
 <q direct="unspecified">Woe's me! 'Tis thy doing, Tessa, for that thou must
 needs be uppermost: I told thee plainly what would come of it.</q>
  <milestone id="p09030022" />Whereat the lady, being not a little modest, coloured from brow to
 neck, and with downcast eyes, withdrew from the room, saying
 never a word by way of answer.  <milestone id="p09030023" />Calandrino ran on in the same
 plaintive strain: <q direct="unspecified">Alas! woe's me! What shall I do? How shall
 I be delivered of this child? What passage can it find? Ah! I see
 only too plainly that the lasciviousness of this wife of mine has been
 the death of me: God make her as wretched as I would fain be
 happy!  <milestone id="p09030024" />Were I as well as I am not, I would get me up and thrash
 her, till I left not a whole bone in her body, albeit it does but serve
 me right for letting her get the upper place; but if I do win through
 this, she shall never have it again; verily she might pine to death for
 it, but she should not have it.</q></p><p><milestone id="p09030025" />Which to hear, Bruno and Buffalmacco and Nello were like to
 burst with suppressed laughter, and Master Scimmione<note>I.e.
 great
 ape: with a play on Simone.</note> laughed so
 frantically, that all his teeth were ready to start from his jaws.  <milestone id="p09030026" />However,
 at length, in answer to Calandrino's appeals and entreaties for
 counsel and succour: <q direct="unspecified">Calandrino,</q> quoth the Master, <q direct="unspecified">thou
 mayst dismiss thy fears, for, God be praised, we were apprised of thy
 state in such good time that with but little trouble, in the course of a
 few days, I shall set thee right; but 'twill cost a little.</q>  <milestone id="p09030027" /><q direct="unspecified">Woe's
 <pb n="277" />me,</q> returned Calandrino, <q direct="unspecified">be it so, Master, for the love of God:
 I have here two hundred pounds, with which I had thoughts of buying
 an estate: take them all, all, if you must have all, so only I may escape
 being delivered, for I know not how I should manage it, seeing that
 women, albeit 'tis much easier for them, do make such a noise in
 the hour of their labour, that I misdoubt me, if I suffered so, I should
 die before I was delivered.</q>  <milestone id="p09030028" /><q direct="unspecified">Disquiet not thyself,</q> said the
 doctor:
 <q direct="unspecified">I will have a potion distilled for thee; of rare virtue it is, and not
 a little palatable, and in the course of three days 'twill purge thee of
 all, and leave thee in better fettle than a fish; but thou wilt do well
 to be careful thereafter, and commit no such indiscretions again.
  <milestone id="p09030029" />Now to make this potion we must have three pair of good fat
 capons, and, for divers other ingredients, thou wilt give one of thy
 friends here five pounds in small change to purchase them, and thou
 wilt have everything sent to my shop, and so, please God, I will
 send thee this distilled potion to-morrow morning, and thou wilt
 take a good beakerful each time.</q>  <milestone id="p09030030" />Whereupon: <q direct="unspecified">Be it as you
 bid, Master mine,</q> quoth Calandrino, and handing Bruno five
 pounds, and money enough to purchase three pair of capons, he
 begged him, if it were not too much trouble, to do him the service
 to buy these things for him.  <milestone id="p09030031" />So away went the doctor, and made a
 little decoction by way of draught, and sent it him. Bruno bought
 the capons and all else that was needed to furnish forth the feast,
 with which he and his comrades and the doctor regaled them.
  <milestone id="p09030032" />Calandrino drank of the decoction for three mornings, after which
 he had a visit from his friends and the doctor, who felt his pulse, and
 then: <q direct="unspecified">Beyond a doubt, Calandrino,</q> quoth he, <q direct="unspecified">thou art cured,
 and so thou hast no more occasion to keep indoors, but needst have
 no fear to do whatever thou hast a mind to.</q>  <milestone id="p09030033" />Much relieved,
 Calandrino got up, and resumed his accustomed way of life, and,
 wherever he found any one to talk to, was loud in praise of
 Master Simone for the excellent manner in which he had cured
 him, causing him in three days without the least suffering to
 be quit of his pregnancy. And Bruno and Buffalmacco and
 Nello were not a little pleased with themselves that they had so
 cleverly got the better of Calandrino's niggardliness, albeit Monna
 Tessa, who was not deceived, murmured not a little against her
 husband.</p></div2>