<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="lauretta" id="nov0108"><head>Novel VIII</head><argument><p><milestone id="p01080001" />Guglielmo Borsiere by a neat retort sharply censures
 avarice in Messer Ermino de' Grimaldi.</p></argument><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01080002" />Next Filostrato was seated Lauretta, who, when the praises
 bestowed on Bergamino's address had ceased, knowing that it was
 now her turn to speak, waited not for the word of command, but
 with a charming graciousness thus began:</p></div3><div3 who="lauretta" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01080003" />The last novel, dear gossips, prompts me to relate how a worthy
 man, likewise a jester, reprehended not without success the greed
 of a very wealthy merchant; and though the burden of my story
 is not unlike the last, yet, perchance, it may not on that account
 be the less appreciated by you, because it has a happy termination.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p01080004" />Know then that in Genoa there dwelt long ago a gentleman,
 who was known as Messer Ermino de' Grimaldi, and whose wealth,
 both in lands and money, was generally supposed to be far in excess
 of that of any other burgher then in Italy; <milestone id="p01080005" />and as in wealth he was
 without a rival in Italy, so in meanness and avarice there was not
 any in the entire world, however richly endowed with those qualities,
 whom he did not immeasurably surpass, insomuch that, not only
 did he keep a tight grip upon his purse when honour was to be done
 to another, but in his personal expenditure, even upon things meet
 and proper, contrary to the general custom of the Genoese, whose
 wont is to array themselves nobly, he was extremely penurious, as
 also in his outlay upon his table. <milestone id="p01080006" />Wherefore, not without just cause,
 folk had dropped his surname de' Grimaldi, and called him instead
 Messer Ermino Avarizia. <milestone id="p01080007" />While thus by thrift his wealth waxed
 greater and greater, it so chanced that there came to Genoa a jester
 of good parts, a man debonair and ready of speech, his name
 Guglielmo Borsiere, whose like is not to be found to-day, when
 <pb n="57" />jesters (to the great reproach be it spoken of those that claim the
 name and reputation of gentlemen) are rather to be called asses,
 being without courtly breeding, and formed after the coarse pattern
 of the basest of churls. <milestone id="p01080008" />And whereas in the days of which I speak
 they made it their business, they spared no pains, to compose quarrels,
 to allay heart-burnings, between gentlemen, or arrange marriages, or
 leagues of amity, ministering meanwhile relief to jaded minds and
 solace to courts by the sprightly sallies of their wit, and with keen
 sarcasm, like fathers, censuring churlish manners, being also satisfied
 with very trifling guerdons; <milestone id="p01080009" />nowadays all their care is to spend their
 time in scandal-mongering, in sowing discord, in saying, and (what
 is worse) in doing in the presence of company things churlish and
 flagitious, in bringing accusations, true or false, of wicked, shameful
 or flagitious conduct against one another; and in drawing gentlemen
 into base and nefarious practices by sinister and insidious arts. 
<milestone id="p01080010" />And
 by these wretched and depraved lords he is held most dear and best
 rewarded whose words and deeds are the most atrocious, to the
 great reproach and scandal of the world of to-day; whereby it is
 abundantly manifest that virtue has departed from the earth, leaving
 a degenerate generation to wallow in the lowest depths of vice.</p><p><milestone id="p01080011" />But reverting to the point at which I started, wherefrom under
 stress of just indignation I have deviated somewhat further than I
 intended, I say that the said Guglielmo was had in honour, and was
 well received by all the gentlemen of Genoa; and tarrying some
 days in the city, heard much of the meanness and avarice of Messer
 Ermino, and was curious to see him. <milestone id="p01080012" />Now Messer Ermino had
 heard that this Guglielmo Borsiere was a man of good parts, and,
 notwithstanding his avarice, having in him some sparks of good
 breeding, received him with words of hearty greeting and a gladsome
 mien, and conversed freely with him and of divers matters, and so
 conversing, took him with other Genoese that were of his company
 to a new and very beautiful house which he had built, 
<milestone id="p01080013" />and after
 shewing him over the whole of it, said to him: <q direct="unspecified">Now, Messer
 Guglielmo, you have seen and heard many things; could you suggest
 to me something, the like of which has not hitherto been seen,
 which I might have painted here in the saloon of this house?</q> 
<milestone id="p01080014" />To
 which ill-judged question Guglielmo replied: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, it would not, I
 think, be in my power to suggest anything the like of which has
 <pb n="58" />never been seen, unless it were a sneeze or something similar; but
 if it so please you, I have something to suggest, which, I think, you
 have never seen.</q> 
<milestone id="p01080015" /><q direct="unspecified">Prithee, what may that be?</q> said Messer
 Ermino, not expecting to get the answer which he got. 
<milestone id="p01080016" />For
 Guglielmo replied forthwith: <q direct="unspecified">Paint Courtesy here;</q> 
<milestone id="p01080017" />which Messer
 Ermino had no sooner heard, than he was so stricken with shame
 that his disposition underwent a complete change, and he said:
 <q direct="unspecified">Messer Guglielmo, I will see to it that Courtesy is here painted
 in such wise that neither you nor any one else shall ever again have
 reason to tell me that I have not seen or known that virtue.</q> 
<milestone id="p01080018" />And
 henceforward (so enduring was the change wrought by Guglielmo's
 words) there was not in Genoa, while he lived, any gentleman so
 liberal and so gracious and so lavish of honour both to strangers and
 to his fellow-citizens as Messer Ermino de' Grimaldi</p></div2>