<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div2 type="novella" who="panfilo" id="nov0101"><head>Novel I</head><argument><p><milestone id="p01010001" />Ser Ciappelletto cheats a holy friar by a false confession,
	and dies; and, having lived as a very bad man,
	is, on his death, reputed a saint, and called San
	Ciappelletto.</p></argument><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01010002" />A seemly thing it is, dearest ladies, that whatever we do, it be
      begun
      in the holy and awful name of Him who was the maker of all. Wherefore,
      as it falls to me to lead the way in this your enterprise of storytelling,
      I intend to begin with one of His wondrous works, that, by
      hearing thereof, our hopes in Him, in whom is no change, may be
      established, and His name be by us forever lauded. <milestone id="p01010003" />'Tis manifest
      that, as things temporal are all doomed to pass and perish, so within
      and without they abound with trouble and anguish and travail, and
      are subject to infinite perils; nor, save for the especial grace of God,
      should we, whose being is bound up with and forms part of theirs,
      have either the strength to endure or the wisdom to combat their
      adverse influences. <milestone id="p01010004" />By which grace we are visited and penetrated
      (so we must believe) not by reason of any merit of our own, but
      solely out of the fulness of God's own goodness, and in answer to the
      prayers of those who, being mortal like ourselves, did faithfully
      observe His ordinances during their lives, and are now become
      blessed for ever with Him in heaven. To whom, as to advocates
      taught by experience all that belongs to our frailty, we, not daring,
      perchance, to present our petitions in the presence of so great a Judge,
      make known our requests for such things as we deem expedient for
      us. <milestone id="p01010005" />And of His mercy richly abounding to usward we have further
      proof herein, that, no keenness of mortal vision being able in any
      degree to penetrate the secret counsels of the Divine mind, it
      some<pb n="23" />times,
      perchance, happens, that, in error of judgment, we make one
      our advocate before His Majesty, who is banished from His presence
      in eternal exile, and yet He to whom nothing is hidden, having
      regard rather to the sincerity of our prayers than to our ignorance or
      the banishment of the intercessor, hears us no less than if the intercessor
      were in truth one of the blest who enjoy the light of His
      countenance. <milestone id="p01010006" />Which the story that I am about to relate may serve
      to make apparent; apparent, I mean, according to the standard of
      the judgment of man, not of God.</p></div3><p><milestone id="p01010007" />The story goes, then, that Musciatto Franzesi, a great and
      wealthy merchant, being made a knight in France, and being to
      attend Charles Sansterre, brother of the King of France, when he
      came into Tuscany at the instance and with the support of Pope
      Boniface, found his affairs, as often happens to merchants, to be
      much involved in divers quarters, and neither easily nor suddenly to
      be adjusted; wherefore he determined to place them in the hands of
      commissioners, and found no difficulty except as to certain credits
      given to some Burgundians, for the recovery of which he doubted
      whether he could come by a competent agent; <milestone id="p01010008" />for well he knew
      that the Burgundians were violent men and ill-conditioned and
      faithless; nor could he call to mind any man so bad that he could
      with confidence oppose his guile to theirs. <milestone id="p01010009" />After long pondering
      the matter, he recollected one Ser Ciapperello da Prato, who much
      frequented his house in Paris. Who being short of stature and very
      affected, the French who knew not the meaning of Cepparello,<note>The
	diminutive of ceppo, stump or log: more commonly written
	cepperello (cf. p. 32) or ceppatello. The form ciapperello
	seems to be found only here.</note> 
      but supposed that it meant the same as Cappello, i. e. garland, in their
      vernacular, called him not Cappello, but Ciappelletto by reason of his
      diminutive size; and as Ciappelletto he was known everywhere,
      whereas few people knew him as Ciapperello. <milestone id="p01010010" />Now Ciappelletto's
      manner of life was thus. He was by profession a notary, and his
      pride was to make false documents; he would have made them as
      often as he was asked, and more readily without fee than another
      at a great price; few indeed he made that were not false, and great
      was his shame when they were discovered. <milestone id="p01010011" />False witness he bore,
      solicited or unsolicited, with boundless delight; and, as oaths were in
      <pb n="24" />those days had in very great respect in France, he, scrupling not to
      forswear himself, corruptly carried the day in every case in which he
      was summoned faithfully to attest the truth. <milestone id="p01010012" />He took inordinate
      delight, and bestirred himself with great zeal, in fomenting ill-feeling,
      enmities, dissensions between friends, kinsfolk and all other folk;
      and the more calamitous were the consequences the better he was
      pleased. <milestone id="p01010013" />Set him on murder, or any other foul crime, and he never
      hesitated, but went about it with alacrity; he had been known on
      more than one occasion to inflict wounds or death by preference
      with his own hands. <milestone id="p01010014" />He was a profuse blasphemer of God and His
      saints, and that on the most trifling occasions, being of all men the
      most irascible. He was never seen at church, held all the sacraments
      vile things, and derided them in language of horrible ribaldry.
      On the other hand he resorted readily to the tavern and other
      places of evil repute, and frequented them. He was as fond of
      women as a dog is of the stick: in the use against nature he had
      not his match among the most abandoned. He would have pilfered
      and stolen as a matter of conscience, as a holy man would make an
      oblation. Most gluttonous he was and inordinately fond of his
      cups, whereby he sometimes brought upon himself both shame and
      suffering. He was also a practised gamester and thrower of false
      dice. <milestone id="p01010015" />But why enlarge so much upon him? Enough that he was,
      perhaps, the worst man that ever was born.</p><p>The rank and power of Musciatto Franzesi had long been this
 reprobate's mainstay, serving in many instances to secure him considerate
 treatment on the part of the private persons whom he
 frequently, and the court which he unremittingly, outraged. <milestone id="p01010016" />So
 Musciatto, having bethought him of this Ser Cepparello, with whose
 way of life he was very well acquainted, judged him to be the very
 sort of person to cope with the guile of the Burgundians. He therefore
 sent for him, and thus addressed him: <milestone id="p01010017" /><q direct="unspecified">Ser Ciappelletto, I am,
 as thou knowest, about to leave this place for good; and among
 those with whom I have to settle accounts are certain Burgundians,
 very wily knaves; nor know I the man whom I could more fitly
 entrust with the recovery of my money than thyself. Wherefore, as
 thou hast nothing to do at present, if thou wilt undertake this
 business, I will procure thee the favour of the court, and give thee a
 reasonable part of what thou shalt recover.</q> <milestone id="p01010018" />Ser Ciappelletto, being
 <pb n="25" />out of employment, and by no means in easy circumstances, and
 about to lose Musciatto, so long his mainstay and support, without
 the least demur, for in truth he had hardly any choice, made his
 mind up and answered that he was ready to go. So the bargain was
 struck. <milestone id="p01010019" />Armed with the power of attorney and the royal letters
 commendatory, Ser Ciappelletto took leave of Messer Musciatto and
 hied him to Burgundy, where he was hardly known to a soul. He
 set about the business which had brought him thither, the recovery
 of the money, in a manner amicable and considerate, foreign to his
 nature, as if he were minded to reserve his severity to the last.
 <milestone id="p01010020" />While thus occupied, he was frequently at the house of two
 Florentine usurers, who treated him with great distinction out of
 regard for Messer Musciatto; and there it so happened that he fell
 sick. The two brothers forthwith placed physicians and servants in
 attendance upon him, and omitted no means meet and apt for the
 restoration of his health. <milestone id="p01010021" />But all remedies proved unavailing; for
 being now old, and having led, as the physicians reported, a disorderly
 life, he went daily from bad to worse like one stricken with a
 mortal disease. This greatly disconcerted the two brothers; <milestone id="p01010022" />and one
 day, hard by the room in which Ser Ciappelletto lay sick, they began
 to talk about him; saying one to the other: <milestone id="p01010023" /><q direct="unspecified">What shall we do
 with this man? We are hard bested indeed on his account. If we
 turn him out of the house, sick as he is, we shall not only incur grave
 censure, but shall evince a signal want of sense; for folk must know
 the welcome we gave him in the first instance, the solicitude with
 which we have had him treated and tended since his illness, during
 which time he could not possibly do aught to displease us, and yet
 they would see him suddenly turned out of our house sick unto
 death. <milestone id="p01010024" />On the other hand he has been so bad a man that he is sure
 not to confess or receive any of the Church's sacraments; and dying
 thus unconfessed, he will be denied burial in church, but will be cast out
 into some ditch like a dog; <milestone id="p01010025" />nay, 'twill be all one if he do confess, for
 such and so horrible have been his crimes that no friar or priest either
 will or can absolve him; and so, dying without absolution, he will
 still be cast out into the ditch. <milestone id="p01010026" />In which case the folk of these parts,
 who reprobate our trade as iniquitous and revile it all day long, and
 would fain rob us, will seize their opportunity, and raise a tumult,
 and make a raid upon our houses, crying: 'A way with these Lombard
 <pb n="26" />dogs, whom the Church excludes from her pale;' and will certainly
 strip us of our goods, and perhaps take our lives also; so that in any
 case we stand to lose if this man die.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01010027" />Ser Ciappelletto, who, as we said, lay close at hand while they
	thus spoke, and whose hearing was sharpened, as is often the case,
	by his malady, overheard all that they said about him. So he called
	them to him, and said to them: <q direct="unspecified">I would not have you disquiet
	  yourselves in regard of me, or apprehend loss to befall you by my
	  death. I have heard what you have said of me and have no doubt
	  that 'twould be as you say, if matters took the course you anticipate;
	  but I am minded that it shall be otherwise. <milestone id="p01010028" />I have committed so
	  many offences against God in the course of my life, that one more in
	  the hour of my death will make no difference whatever to the account.
	  <milestone id="p01010029" />So seek out and bring hither the worthiest and most holy friar you
	  can find, and leave me to settle your affairs and mine upon a sound
	  and solid basis, with which you may rest satisfied.</q> <milestone id="p01010030" />The two brothers
	had not much hope of the result, but yet they went to a friary and
	asked for a holy and discreet man to hear the confession of a Lombard
	that was sick in their house, and returned with an aged man of just
	and holy life, very learned in the Scriptures, and venerable and held
	in very great and especial reverence by all the citizens. <milestone id="p01010031" />As soon as
	he had entered the room where Ser Ciappelletto was lying, and had
	taken his place by his side, he began gently to comfort him: then he
	asked him how long it was since he was confessed. <milestone id="p01010032" />Whereto Ser
	Ciappelletto, who had never been confessed, answered: <q direct="unspecified">Father, it
	  is my constant practice to be confessed at least once a week, and
	  many a week I am confessed more often; but true it is, that, since I
	  have been sick, now eight days, I have made no confession, so sore
	  has been my affliction.</q> <milestone id="p01010033" /><q direct="unspecified">Son,</q> said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">thou hast well
	  done,
	  and well for thee, if so thou continue to do; as thou dost confess
	  so often, I see that my labour of hearkening and questioning will be
	  slight.</q> <milestone id="p01010034" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay but, master friar,</q> said Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">say not
	  so; I have not confessed so often but that I would fain make a
	  general confession of all my sins that I have committed, so far as
	  I can recall them, from the day of my birth to the present time;
	  and therefore I pray you, my good father, to question me precisely in
	  every particular just as if I had never been confessed. <milestone id="p01010035" />And spare me
	  not by reason of my sickness, for I had far rather do despite to my
	  <pb n="27" />flesh than, sparing it, risk the perdition of my soul, which my Saviour
	  redeemed with His precious blood.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01010036" />The holy man was mightily delighted with these words, which
	seemed to him to betoken a soul in a state of grace. He therefore
	signified to Ser Ciappelletto his high approval of this practice; and
	then began by asking him whether he had ever sinned carnally with
	a woman. <milestone id="p01010037" />Whereto Ser Ciappelletto answered with a sigh: <q direct="unspecified">My
	  father, I scruple to tell you the truth in this matter, fearing lest I sin
	  in vain-glory.</q> <milestone id="p01010038" /><q direct="unspecified">Nay, but,</q> said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">speak boldly; none
	  ever sinned by telling the truth, either in confession or otherwise.</q>
	<milestone id="p01010039" /><q direct="unspecified">Then,</q> said Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">as you bid me speak boldly, I will
	  tell you the truth of this matter. I am virgin even as when I issued
	  from my mother's womb.</q> <milestone id="p01010040" /><q direct="unspecified">Now God's blessing on thee,</q> said the
	friar, <q direct="unspecified">well done; and the greater is thy merit in that, hadst thou
	  so willed, thou mightest have done otherwise far more readily than
	  we who are under constraint of rule.</q> <milestone id="p01010041" />He then proceeded to ask,
	whether he had offended God by gluttony. Whereto Ser Ciappelletto,
	heaving a heavy sigh, answered that he had frequently so offended;
	for, being wont to fast not only in Lent like other devout persons, but
	at least three days in every week, taking nothing but bread and water,
	he had quaffed the water with as good a gusto and as much enjoyment,
	more particularly when fatigued by devotion or pilgrimage, as great
	drinkers quaff their wine; and oftentimes he had felt a craving for
	such dainty dishes of herbs as ladies make when they go into the
	country, and now and again he had relished his food more than
	seemed to him meet in one who fasted, as he did, for devotion.
	<milestone id="p01010042" /><q direct="unspecified">Son,</q> said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">these sins are natural and very trifling; and
	  therefore I would not have thee burden thy conscience too much
	  with them. There is no man, however holy he may be, but must
	  sometimes find it pleasant to eat after a long fast and to drink after
	  exertion.</q> <milestone id="p01010043" /><q direct="unspecified">O, my father,</q> said Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">say not this to
	  comfort me. You know well that I know, that the things which are
	  done in the service of God ought to be done in perfect purity of
	  an unsullied spirit; and whoever does otherwise sins.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010044" />The friar,
	well content, replied: <q direct="unspecified">Glad I am that thou dost think so, and I
	  am mightily pleased with thy pure and good conscience which therein
	  appears; but tell me: hast thou sinned by avarice, coveting more
	  than was reasonable, or withholding more than was right?</q> <milestone id="p01010045" /><q direct="unspecified">My
	  <pb n="28" />father,</q> replied Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">I would not have you disquiet
	  yourself, because I am in the house of these usurers: no part have
	  I in their concerns; nay, I did but come here to admonish and
	  reprehend them, and wean them from this abominable traffic; and
	  so, I believe, I had done, had not God sent me this visitation. <milestone id="p01010046" />But
	  you must know, that my father left me a fortune, of which I dedicated
	  the greater part to God; and since then for my own support and the
	  relief of Christ's poor I have done a little trading, whereof I have desired
	  to make gain; and all that I have gotten I have shared with God's
	  poor, reserving one half for my own needs and giving the other half
	  to them; and so well has my Maker prospered me, that I have ever
	  managed my affairs to better and better account.</q> <milestone id="p01010047" /><q direct="unspecified">Well done,</q>
	said the friar; <q direct="unspecified">but how? hast thou often given way to anger?</q>
	<milestone id="p01010048" /><q direct="unspecified">Often indeed, I assure you,</q> said Ser Ciappelletto. <q direct="unspecified">And who
	  could refrain therefrom, seeing men doing frowardly all day long,
	  breaking the commandments of God and recking nought of His
	  judgments? <milestone id="p01010049" />Many a time in the course of a single day I had rather
	  be dead than alive, to see the young men going after vanity, swearing
	  and forswearing themselves, haunting taverns, avoiding the churches,
	  and in short walking in the way of the world rather than in God's
	  way.</q> <milestone id="p01010050" /><q direct="unspecified">My son,</q> said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">this is a righteous wrath; nor
	  could I find occasion therein to lay a penance upon thee. But did
	  anger ever by any chance betray thee into taking human life, or
	  affronting or otherwise wronging any?</q> <milestone id="p01010051" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas,</q> replied Ser
	Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">alas, sir, man of God though you seem to me, how
	  come you to speak after this manner? If I had had so much
	  as the least thought of doing any of the things of which you speak,
	  should I believe, think you, that I had been thus supported or
	  God? These are the deeds of robbers and such like evil men, to
	  whom I have ever said, when any I saw: 'Go, God change your
	  heart.'</q> <milestone id="p01010052" />Said then the friar: <q direct="unspecified">Now, my son, as thou hopest to
	  be blest of God, tell me, hast thou never borne false witness against
	  any, or spoken evil of another, or taken the goods of another without
	  his leave?</q> <milestone id="p01010053" /><q direct="unspecified">Yes, master friar,</q> answered Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">most
	  true it is that I have spoken evil of another; for I had once a neighbour
	  who without the least excuse in the world was ever beating his
	  wife, and so great was my pity of the poor creature, whom, when he
	  was in his cups, he would thrash as God alone knows how, that once I
	  <pb n="29" />spoke evil of him to his wife's kinsfolk.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010054" /><q direct="unspecified">Well, well,</q> said the
	friar, <q direct="unspecified">thou tellest me thou hast been a merchant; hast thou ever
	  cheated any, as merchants use to do?</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010055" /><q direct="unspecified">I'faith, yes, master friar,</q>
	said Ser Ciappelletto; <q direct="unspecified">but I know not who he was; only that he
	  brought me some money which he owed me for some cloth that
	  I had sold him, and I put it in a box without counting it, where
	  a month afterwards I found four farthings more than there should
	  have been, which I kept for a year to return to him, but not seeing
	  him again, I bestowed them in alms for the love of God.</q> <milestone id="p01010056" /><q direct="unspecified">This,</q>
	said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">was a small matter; and thou didst well to bestow
	  them as thou didst.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010057" />The holy friar went on to ask him many
	other questions, to which he made answer in each case in this sort.
	Then, as the friar was about to give him absolution, Ser Ciappelletto
	interposed: <q direct="unspecified">Sir, I have yet a sin to confess.</q> <milestone id="p01010058" /><q direct="unspecified">What?</q> asked the
	friar. <q direct="unspecified">I remember,</q> he said, <q direct="unspecified">that I once caused my servant to
	  sweep my house on a Saturday after none; and that my observance
	  of Sunday was less devout than it should have been.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010059" /><q direct="unspecified">O, my son,</q>
	said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">this is a light matter.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010060" /><q direct="unspecified">No,</q> said Ser Ciappelletto,
	<q direct="unspecified">say not a light matter; for Sunday is the more to be had in honour
	  because on that day our Lord rose from the dead.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010061" />Then said the
	holy friar: <q direct="unspecified">Now is there aught else that thou hast done?</q>
	<milestone id="p01010062" /><q direct="unspecified">Yes, master friar,</q> replied Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">once by inadvertence
	  I spat in the church of God.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010063" />At this the friar began to smile, and
	said: <q direct="unspecified">My son, this is not a matter to trouble about; we, who are
	  religious, spit there all day long.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010064" /><q direct="unspecified">And great impiety it is when
	  you so do,</q> replied Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">for there is nothing that
	  is so worthy to be kept from all impurity as the holy temple in which
	  sacrifice is offered to God.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010065" />More he said in the same strain, which I
	pass over; and then at last he began to sigh, and by and by to weep
	bitterly, as he was well able to do when he chose. 
	<milestone id="p01010066" />And the friar demanding: 
	<q direct="unspecified">My son, why weepest thou?</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010067" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas, master friar,</q> 
	answered Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">a sin yet remains, which I have
	  never confessed, such shame were it to me to tell it; and as often as
	  I call it to mind, I weep as you now see me weep, being well assured
	  that God will never forgive me this sin.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010068" />Then said the holy friar:
	<q direct="unspecified">Come, come, son, what is this that thou sayst? If all the sins of
	  all the men, that ever were or ever shall be, as long as the world shall
	  endure, were concentrated in one man, so great is the goodness of
	  <pb n="30" />God that He would freely pardon them all, were he but penitent and
	  contrite as I see thou art, and confessed them: wherefore tell me thy
	  sin with a good courage.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010069" />Then said Ser Ciappelletto, still weeping
	bitterly: <q direct="unspecified">Alas, my father, mine is too great a sin, and scarce can
	  I believe, if your prayers do not co-operate, that God will ever grant
	  me His pardon thereof.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010070" /><q direct="unspecified">Tell it with a good courage,</q> said the
	friar; <q direct="unspecified">I promise thee to pray God for thee.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010071" />Ser Ciappelletto,
	however, continued to weep, and would not speak, for all the friar's
	encouragement. When he had kept him for a good while in suspense,
	he heaved a mighty sigh, and said: <q direct="unspecified">My father, as you promise me
	  to pray God for me, I will tell it you. Know, then, that once, when I
	  was a little child, I cursed my mother;</q> and having so said he began
	again to weep bitterly. 
	<milestone id="p01010072" /><q direct="unspecified">O, my son,</q> said the friar, <q direct="unspecified">does this seem
	  to thee so great a sin? Men curse God all day long, and He pardons
	  them freely, if they repent them of having so done; and thinkest
	  thou He will not pardon thee this? Weep not, be comforted, for
	  truly, hadst thou been one of them that set Him on the Cross, with
	  the contrition that I see in thee, thou wouldst not fail of His pardon.</q>
	<milestone id="p01010073" /><q direct="unspecified">Alas! my father,</q> rejoined Ser Ciappelletto, <q direct="unspecified">what is this you
	  say? To curse my sweet mother that carried me in her womb
	  for nine months day and night, and afterwards on her shoulder
	  more than a hundred times! Heinous indeed was my offence;
	  'tis too great a sin; nor will it be pardoned, unless you pray God
	  for me.</q></p><p><milestone id="p01010074" />The friar now perceiving that Ser Ciappelletto had nothing more
	to say, gave him absolution and his blessing, reputing him for a most
	holy man, fully believing that all that he had said was true. And
	who would not have so believed, hearing him so speak at the point
	of death? 
	<milestone id="p01010075" />Then, when all was done, he said: <q direct="unspecified">Ser Ciappelletto,
	  if God so will, you will soon be well; but should it so come to pass
	  that God call your blessed soul to Himself in this state of grace, is
	  it well pleasing to you that your body be buried in our convent?</q>
	<milestone id="p01010076" /><q direct="unspecified">Yea, verily, master friar,</q> replied Ser Ciappelletto; <q direct="unspecified">there would
	  I be, and nowhere else, since you have promised to pray God for
	  me; besides which I have ever had a special devotion to your order.
	  Wherefore I pray you, that, on your return to your convent, you
	  cause to be sent me that very Body of Christ, which you consecrate
	  in the morning on the altar; because (unworthy though I be) I
	  <pb n="31" />purpose with your leave to take it, and afterwards the holy and
	  extreme unction, that, though I have lived as a sinner, I may die
	  at any rate as a Christian.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010077" />The holy man said that he was greatly
	delighted, that it was well said of Ser Ciappelletto, and that
	he would cause the Host to be forthwith brought to him; and
	so it was.</p><p><milestone id="p01010078" />The two brothers, who much misdoubted Ser Ciappelletto's power
	to deceive the friar, had taken their stand on the other side of a
	wooden partition which divided the room in which Ser Ciappelletto
	lay from another, and hearkening there they readily heard and understood
	what Ser Ciappelletto said to the friar; and at times could
	scarce refrain their laughter as they followed his confession; and
	now and again they said one to another: 
	<milestone id="p01010079" /><q direct="unspecified">What manner of man
	  is this, whom neither age nor sickness, nor fear of death, on the
	  threshold of which he now stands, nor yet of God, before whose
	  judgment-seat he must soon appear, has been able to turn from his
	  wicked ways, that he die not even as he has lived?</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010080" />But seeing that
	his confession had secured the interment of his body in church, they
	troubled themselves no further. 
	<milestone id="p01010081" />Ser Ciappelletto soon afterwards
	communicated, and growing immensely worse, received the extreme
	unction, and died shortly after vespers on the same day on which he
	had made his good confession. 
	<milestone id="p01010082" />So the two brothers, having from
	his own moneys provided the wherewith to procure him honourable
	sepulture, and sent word to the friars to come at even to observe the
	usual vigil, and in the morning to fetch the corpse, set all things
	in order accordingly. 
	<milestone id="p01010083" />The holy friar who had confessed him, hearing
	that he was dead, had audience of the prior of the friary; a chapter
	was convened and the assembled brothers heard from the confessor's
	own mouth how Ser Ciappelletto had been a holy man, as had
	appeared by his confession, and were exhorted to receive the body
	with the utmost veneration and pious care, as one by which there
	was good hope that God would work many miracles. 
	<milestone id="p01010084" />To this the
	prior and the rest of the credulous confraternity assenting, they went
	in a body in the evening to the place where the corpse of Ser
	Ciappelletto lay, and kept a great and solemn vigil over it; and in
	the morning they made a procession habited in their surplices and
	copes, with books in their hands and crosses in front; and chanting
	as they went, they fetched the corpse and brought it back to their
	<pb n="32" />church with the utmost pomp and solemnity, being followed by
	almost all the folk of the city, men and women alike. 
	<milestone id="p01010085" />So it was laid
	in the church, and then the holy friar who had heard the confession
	got up in the pulpit and began to preach marvellous things of Ser
	Ciappelletto's life, his fasts, his virginity, his simplicity and
	guilelessness and holiness; narrating among other matters that of which
	Ser Ciappelletto had made tearful confession as his greatest sin, and
	how he had hardly been able to make him conceive that God would
	pardon him; from which he took occasion to reprove his hearers;
	saying: <q direct="unspecified">And you, accursed of God, on the least pretext, blaspheme
	  God and His Mother, and all the celestial court.</q> 
	<milestone id="p01010086" />And much
	beside he told of his loyalty and purity; and, in short, so wrought
	upon the people by his words, to which they gave entire credence,
	that they all conceived a great veneration for Ser Ciappelletto, and
	at the close of the office came pressing forward with the utmost
	vehemence to kiss the feet and the hands of the corpse, from which
	they tore off the cerements, each thinking himself blessed to have
	but a scrap thereof in his possession; and so it was arranged that
	it should be kept there all day long, so as to be visible and accessible
	to all. 
	<milestone id="p01010087" />At nightfall it was honourably interred in a marble tomb
	in one of the chapels, where on the morrow, one by one, folk came
	and lit tapers and prayed and paid their vows, setting there the
	waxen images which they had dedicated. <milestone id="p01010088" />And the fame of Ciappelletto's
	holiness and the devotion to him grew in such measure that
	scarce any there was that in any adversity would vow aught to any
	saint but he, and they called him and still call him San Ciappelletto,
	affirming that many miracles have been and daily are wrought by
	God through him for such as devoutly crave his intercession.</p><div3 who="panfilo" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01010089" />So lived, so died Ser Cepperello da Prato, and came to be reputed
	a saint, as you have heard. Nor would I deny that it is possible that
	he is of the number of the blessed in the presence of God, seeing
	that, though his life was evil and depraved, yet he might in his last
	moments have made so complete an act of contrition that perchance
	God had mercy on him and received him into His kingdom. But,
	as this is hidden from us, I speak according to that which appears,
	and I say that he ought rather to be in the hands of the devil in hell
	than in Paradise. <milestone id="p01010090" />Which, if so it be, is a manifest token of the
	superabundance of the goodness of God to usward, inasmuch as He
	<pb n="33" />regards not our error but the sincerity of our faith, and hearkens
	unto us when, mistaking one who is at enmity with Him for a
	friend, we have recourse to him, as to one holy indeed, as our intercessor
	for His grace. <milestone id="p01010091" />Wherefore, that we of this gay company
	may by His grace be preserved safe and sound throughout this time
	of adversity, commend we ourselves in our need to Him, whose
	name we began by invoking, with lauds and reverent devotion and
	good confidence that we shall be heard.</p></div3><div3 who="author" type="commentary"><p><milestone id="p01010092" />And so he was silent.</p></div3></div2>