<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<epilogue who="author" id="epilogue"><pb n="400" /><head>The Author's Epilogue</head><p><milestone id="p11980001" />Most noble damsels, for whose solace I
	  addressed me to this long
	      and toilsome task, meseems that, aided by the Divine grace, the
	  bestowal whereof I impute to the efficacy of your pious prayers, and
	  in no wise to merits of mine, I have now brought this work to the
	  full and perfect consummation which in the outset thereof I promised
	  you. Wherefore, it but remains for me to render, first to God, and
	  then to you, my thanks, and so to give a rest to my pen and weary
	  hand. <milestone id="p11980002" />But this I purpose not to allow them, until, briefly, as to
	  questions tacitly mooted--for well assured I am that these stories
	  have no especial privilege above any others, nay, I forget not that at
	  the beginning of the Fourth Day I have made the same plain--I
	  shall have answered certain trifling objections that one of you, maybe,
	  or some other, might advance. <milestone id="p11980003" />Peradventure, then, some of you will
	  be found to say that I have used excessive license in the writing
	  of these stories, in that I have caused ladies at times to tell, and
	  oftentimes to list, matters that, whether to tell or to list, do not well
	  beseem virtuous women. The which I deny, for that there is none
	  of these stories so unseemly, but that it may without offence be told
	  by any one, if but seemly words be used; which rule, methinks, has
	  here been very well observed. <milestone id="p11980004" />But assume we that 'tis even so (for
	  with you I am not minded to engage in argument, witting that you
	  would vanquish me), then, I say that for answer why I have so done,
	  reasons many come very readily to hand. In the first place, if aught
	  of the kind in any of these stories there be, 'twas but such as was
	  demanded by the character of the stories, which let but any person
	  of sound judgment scan with the eye of reason, and 'twill be abundantly
	  manifest that, unless I had been minded to deform them, they
	  could not have been otherwise recounted. <milestone id="p11980005" />And if, perchance, they
	  do, after all, contain here and there a trifling indiscretion of speech,
	  such as might ill sort with one of your precious prudes, who weigh
	  <pb n="401" />words rather than deeds, and are more concerned to appear, than to
	  be, good, I say that so to write was as permissible to me, as 'tis to
	  men and women at large in their converse to make use of such terms
	      as hole, and pin, and mortar, and pestle, and
	  sausage, and polony, and
	  plenty more besides of a like sort. <milestone id="p11980006" />And therewithal privilege no
	  less should be allowed to my pen than to the pencil of the painter,
	  who without incurring any, or at least any just, censure, not only
	  will depict St. Michael smiting the serpent, or St. George the
	  dragon, with sword or lance at his discretion; but male he paints us
	      Christ, and female Eve, and His feet that for the salvation of our
	  race willed to die upon the cross he fastens thereto, now with one,
	  now with two nails.</p><p><milestone id="p11980007" />Moreover, 'tis patent to all that 'twas not in the Church, of
	  matters whereto pertaining 'tis meet we speak with all purity of
	  heart and seemliness of phrase, albeit among her histories there are
	  to be found not a few that will ill compare with my writings; nor
	  yet in the schools of the philosophers, where, as much as anywhere,
	  seemliness is demanded, nor in any place where clergy or philosophers
	  congregate, but in gardens, in pleasaunces, and among folk,
	  young indeed, but not so young as to be seducible by stories, and at
	  a time when, if so one might save one's life, the most sedate might
	  without disgrace walk abroad with his breeches for headgear, that
	  these stories were told. <milestone id="p11980008" />Which stories, such as they are, may, like
	  all things else, be baneful or profitable according to the quality
	  of the hearer. <milestone id="p11980009" />Who knows not that wine is, as Cinciglione and
	  Scolaio<note>Noted topers of the day.</note> and many another aver, an
	  excellent thing for the living
	  creature, and yet noxious to the fevered patient? Are we, for the
	  mischief it does to the fever-stricken, to say that 'tis a bad thing?
	  Who knows not that fire is most serviceable, nay, necessary, to
	  mortals? Are we to say that, because it burns houses and villages
	  and cities, it is a bad thing? <milestone id="p11980010" />Arms, in like manner, are the safeguard
	  of those that desire to live in peace, and also by them are men
	  not seldom maliciously slain, albeit the malice is not in them, but in
	  those that use them for a malicious purpose. <milestone id="p11980011" />Corrupt mind did never
	  yet understand any word in a wholesome sense; and as such a mind
	  has no profit of seemly words, so such as are scarce seemly may as
	  <pb n="402" />little avail to contaminate a healthy mind as mud the radiance of
	  the sun, or the deformities of earth the splendours of the heavens.
	  <milestone id="p11980012" />What books, what words, what letters, are more sacred, more excellent,
	  more venerable, than those of Holy Writ? And yet there
	  have been not a few that, perversely construing them, have brought
	  themselves and others to perdition. <milestone id="p11980013" />Everything is in itself good for
	  somewhat, and being put to a bad purpose, may work manifold mischief.
	  And so, I say, it is with my stories. <milestone id="p11980014" />If any man shall be
	  minded to draw from them matters of evil tendency or consequence,
	  they will not gainsay him, if, perchance, such matters there be in
	  them, nor will such matters fail to be found in them, if they be
	  wrested and distorted. Nor, if any shall seek profit and reward in
	  them, will they deny him the same; and censured or accounted as
	  less than profitable and seemly they can never be, if the times or the
	  persons when and by whom they are read be such as when they
	  were recounted. <milestone id="p11980015" />If any lady must needs say paternosters or make
	  cakes or tarts for her holy father, let her leave them alone; there is
	  none after whom they will run a begging to be read: howbeit, there
	  are little matters that even the beguines tell, ay, and do, now and
	  again.</p><p><milestone id="p11980016" />In like manner there will be some who will say that there are
	  stories here which 'twere better far had been omitted. Granted;
	  but 'twas neither in my power, nor did it behove me, to write any
	  but such stories as were narrated; wherefore, 'twas for those by
	  whom they were told to have a care that they were proper; in
	  which case they would have been no less so as I wrote them. <milestone id="p11980017" />But,
	  assuming that I not only wrote but invented the stories, as I did not,
	  I say that I should take no shame to myself that they were not all
	  proper; seeing that artist there is none to be found, save God, that
	  does all things well and perfectly. And Charlemagne, albeit he
	  created the Paladins, wist not how to make them in such numbers
	  as to form an army of them alone. <milestone id="p11980018" />It must needs be that in the
	  multitude of things there be found diversities of quality. No field
	  was ever so well tilled but that here and there nettle, or thistle, or
	  brier would be found in it amid the goodlier growths. Whereto I
	  may add that, having to address me to young and unlearned ladies,
	  as you for the most part are, I should have done foolishly, had I
	  gone about searching and swinking to find matters very exquisite,
	  <pb n="403" />and been sedulous to speak with great precision. 
	  <milestone id="p11980019" />However, whoso
	  goes a reading among these stories, let him pass over those that vex
	  him, and read those that please him. That none may be misled,
	  each bears on its brow the epitome of that which it hides within its
	  bosom.</p><p><milestone id="p11980020" />Again, I doubt not there will be such as will say that some of
	  the stories are too long. To whom, once more, I answer, that
	  whoso has aught else to do would be foolish to read them, albeit
	  they were short. And though, now that I approach the end of my
	  labours, 'tis long since I began to write, I am not, therefore, oblivious
	  that 'twas to none but leisured ladies that I made proffer of my
	  pains; nor can aught be long to him that reads but to pass the time,
	  so only he thereby accomplish his purpose. <milestone id="p11980021" />Succinctness were
	  rather to be desired by students, who are at pains not merely to pass,
	  but usefully to employ, their time, than by you, who have as much
	  time at your disposal as you spend not in amorous delights. Besides
	  which, as none of you goes either to Athens, or to Bologna, or to
	  Paris to study, 'tis meet that what is meant for you should be more
	  diffuse than what is to be read by those whose minds have been
	  refined by scholarly pursuits.</p><p><milestone id="p11980022" />Nor make I any doubt but there are yet others who will say that
	  the said stories are too full of jests and merry conceits, and that it ill
	  beseems a man of weight and gravity to have written on such wise.
	  To these I am bound to render, and do render, my thanks, for that,
	  prompted by well-meant zeal, they have so tender a regard to my
	  reputation. <milestone id="p11980023" />But to that, which they urge against me, I reply after
	  this sort: That I am of weight I acknowledge, having been often
	  weighed in my time; wherefore, in answer to the fair that have not
	  weighed me, I affirm that I am not of gravity; on the contrary I am
	  so light that I float on the surface of the water; and considering
	  that the sermons which the friars make, when they would chide folk
	  for their sins, are to-day, for the most part, full of jests and merry
	  conceits, and drolleries, I deemed that the like stuff would not ill
	  beseem my stories, written, as they were, to banish women's dumps.
	  <milestone id="p11980024" />However, if thereby they should laugh too much, they may be
	  readily cured thereof by the Lament of Jeremiah, the Passion of the
	  Saviour, or the Complaint of the Magdalen.</p><p><milestone id="p11980025" />And who shall question but that yet others there are who will
	  <pb n="404" />say that I have an evil tongue and venomous, because here and there
	  I tell the truth about the friars? <milestone id="p11980026" />Now for them that so say there
	  is forgiveness, for that 'tis not to be believed but that they have just
	  cause; seeing that the friars are good folk, and eschew hardship for
	  the love of God, and grind intermittently, and never blab; and, were
	  they not all a trifle malodorous, intercourse with them would be
	  much more agreeable. <milestone id="p11980027" />Nevertheless, I acknowledge that the things
	  of this world have no stability, but are ever undergoing change; and
	  this may have befallen my tongue, albeit, no great while ago, one of
	  my fair neighbours--for in what pertains to myself I trust not my
	  own judgment, but forgo it to the best of my power--told me 'twas
	  the goodliest and sweetest tongue in the world; and in sooth, when
	  this occurred, few of the said stories were yet to write; 
	  <milestone id="p11980028" />nor, for that
	  those who so tax me do it despitefully, am I minded to vouchsafe
	  them any further answer.</p><p><milestone id="p11980029" />So, then, be every lady at liberty to say and believe whatever she
	  may think fit: but 'tis now time for me to bring these remarks to a
	  close, with humble thanks to Him, by whose help and guidance I,
	  after so long travail, have been brought to the desired goal. And
	  may you, sweet my ladies, rest ever in His grace and peace; and
	  be not unmindful of me, if, peradventure, any of you may, in any
	  measure, have been profited by reading these stories.</p></epilogue>