<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<front><argument><p><milestone id="p99990001" />Beginneth here the book called Decameron, otherwise
	  Prince Galeotto, wherein are contained one hundred
	  novels told in ten days by seven ladies and three
	  young men.</p></argument><prologue who="author" id="proem"><head>PROEM.</head><p><milestone id="p99990002" />'Tis humane to have compassion on the afflicted; and as it
	  shews well in all, so it is especially demanded of those who have had
	  need of comfort and have found it in others: among whom, if any
	  had ever need thereof or found it precious or delectable, I may be
	  numbered; <milestone id="p99990003" />seeing that from my early youth even to the present I
	  was beyond measure aflame with a most aspiring and noble love<note>For
	    Fiammetta, i.e. Maria, natural daughter of Robert, King of
	    Naples.</note>
	  more perhaps than, were I to enlarge upon it, would seem to accord
	  with my lowly condition. Whereby, among people of discernment
	  to whose knowledge it had come, I had much praise and high
	  esteem, but nevertheless extreme discomfort and suffering, not indeed
	  by reason of cruelty on the part of the beloved lady, but through
	  superabundant ardour engendered in the soul by ill-bridled desire;
	  the which, as it allowed me no reasonable period of quiescence,
	  frequently occasioned me an inordinate distress. <milestone id="p99990004" />In which distress
	  so much relief was afforded me by the delectable discourse of a friend
	  and his commendable consolations, that I entertain a very solid
	  conviction that to them I owe it that I am not dead. <milestone id="p99990005" />But, as it
	  pleased Him, who, being infinite, has assigned by immutable law an
	  end to all things mundane, my love, beyond all other fervent, and
	  neither to be broken nor bent by any force of determination, or
	  counsel of prudence, or fear of manifest shame or ensuing danger,
	  <pb n="2" />did nevertheless in course of time abate of its own accord, in such
	  wise that it has now left nought of itself in my mind but that
	  pleasure which it is wont to afford to him who does not adventure
	  too far out in navigating its deep seas; so that, whereas it was used
	  to be grievous, now, all discomfort being done away, I find that
	  which remains to be delightful. <milestone id="p99990006" />But the cessation of the pain has
	  not banished the memory of the kind offices done me by those who
	  shared by sympathy the burden of my griefs; nor will it ever, I
	  believe, pass from me except by death. <milestone id="p99990007" />And as among the virtues
	  gratitude is in my judgment most especially to be commended,
	  and ingratitude in equal measure to be censured, therefore, that I
	  show myself not ungrateful, I have resolved, now that I may call
	  myself free, to endeavour, in return for what I have received, to
	  afford, so far as in me lies, some solace, if not to those who succoured
	  me, and who, perchance, by reason of their good sense or good
	  fortune, need it not, at least to such as may be apt to receive it.</p><p><milestone id="p99990008" />And though my support or comfort, so to say, may be of little
	  avail to the needy, nevertheless it seems to me meet to offer it most
	  readily where the need is most apparent, because it will there be
	  most serviceable and also most kindly received. <milestone id="p99990009" />Who will deny, that
	  it should be given, for all that it may be worth, to gentle ladies
	  much rather than to men? <milestone id="p99990010" />Within their soft bosoms, betwixt fear
	  and shame, they harbour secret fires of love, and how much of
	  strength concealment adds to those fires, they know who have proved
	  it. Moreover, restrained by the will, the caprice, the commandment
	  of fathers, mothers, brothers, and husbands, confined most part of
	  their time within the narrow compass of their chambers, they live,
	  so to say, a life of vacant ease, and, yearning and renouncing in the
	  same moment, meditate divers matters which cannot all be cheerful.
	  <milestone id="p99990011" />If thereby a melancholy bred of amorous desire make entrance into
	  their minds, it is like to tarry there to their sore distress, unless it be
	  dispelled by a change of ideas. Besides which they have much less
	  power to support such a weight than men. For, when men are
	  enamoured, their case is very different, as we may readily perceive.
	  <milestone id="p99990012" />They, if they are afflicted by a melancholy and heaviness of mood,
	  have many ways of relief and diversion; they may go where they
	  will, may hear and see many things, may hawk, hunt, fish, ride, play
	  or traffic. By which means all are able to compose their minds,
	  <pb n="3" />either in whole or in part, and repair the ravage wrought by the
	  dumpish mood, at least for some space of time; and shortly after, by
	  one way or another, either solace ensues, or the dumps become less
	  grievous. <milestone id="p99990013" />Wherefore, in some measure to compensate the injustice
	  of Fortune, which to those whose strength is least, as we see it to be
	  in the delicate frames of ladies, has been most niggard of support, I,
	  for the succour and diversion of such of them as love (for others
	  may find sufficient solace in the needle and the spindle and the reel),
	  do intend to recount one hundred Novels or Fables or Parables or
	  Stories, as we may please to call them, which were recounted in ten
	  days by an honourable company of seven ladies and three young men
	  in the time of the late mortal pestilence, as also some canzonets sung
	  by the said ladies for their delectation. <milestone id="p99990014" />In which pleasant novels
	  will be found some passages of love rudely crossed, with other
	  courses of events of which the issues are felicitous, in times as well
	  modern as ancient: from which stories the said ladies, who shall read
	  them, may derive both pleasure from the entertaining matters set
	  forth therein, and also good counsel, in that they may learn what to
	  shun, and likewise what to pursue. Which cannot, I believe, come
	  to pass, unless the dumps be banished by diversion of mind. <milestone id="p99990015" />And if
	  it so happen (as God grant it may) let them give thanks to Love,
	  who, liberating me from his fetters, has given me the power to
	  devote myself to their gratification.</p></prologue></front>